<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_urine_produced"><title>Tutor</title><question id="urine_produced_1"><body><p>When enough urine has been produced in the <input_ref input="A" /> it leaves the through the ureters and urine is then transported to the<input_ref input="B" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">ureters</choice><choice value="two">nephrons</choice><choice value="three">bladder</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">ureters</choice><choice value="two">nephrons</choice><choice value="three">bladder</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="identify_nephrons" /><skillref idref="identify_urine_production" /><response name="ureters" input="A" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect: Urine is produced in the nephrons, which are housed in each of the two kidneys. Once filtered, the blood exits through the renal vein and urine leaves each kidney through each ureter which is driven to the bladder. Through circular contraction urine is moved from the kidneys through the ureters, and into the bladder.</feedback></response><response name="nephrons" input="A" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct: Urine is produced in the nephrons, which are housed in each of the two kidneys. The kidneys are located toward the lower back. </feedback></response><response name="bladder" input="A" match="three" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect: Urine is produced in the nephrons, which are housed in each of the two kidneys. Once filtered, the blood exits through the renal vein and urine leaves each kidney through each ureter which is driven to the bladder</feedback></response><hint>Think in terms of what organ produces urine. </hint></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="identify_urinary_bladder" /><skillref idref="state_urine_transport" /><response name="kidneys" input="B" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect: Urine is produced by the nephrons which are in the kidneys. </feedback></response><response name="nephrons" input="B" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect: Urine is produced by the nephrons in the kidneys. </feedback></response><response name="bladder" input="B" match="three" score="10"><feedback>Correct: Urine is produced by the nephrons in the kidneys. Once filtered, the blood exits through the renal vein and urine leaves each kidney through each ureter which is driven to the bladder, where it is contained.</feedback></response><hint>Think in terms of where it is stored once it is produced.</hint></part></question></assessment>
