<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_high_gfr"><title>tutor</title><page><content><p>The average GFR is 125 milliliters (4 ounces) per minute, which adds up to nearly 140 liters (50 gallons) a day.</p></content><question id="q1"><body>What are the consequences of a GFR that is too high?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Waste products will accumulate in the renal tubules, ultimately leading to illness and death if untreated.</choice><choice value="B">There will be no consequences.</choice><choice value="C">Needed substances will rush through the renal tubules ultimately leading to illness and death if untreated.</choice><choice value="D">Needed substances will rush through the renal tubules and lost in urine.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="average_gfr_per_minute_day" /><skillref idref="consequences_gfr_high_low" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is not what happens of GFR is too high.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There will be a consequence.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Incorrect. A high GFR can be the result of high blood pressure not a low blood pressure. </feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. If the GFR is too high, needed substances will rush through the renal tubules too quickly to be completely absorbed, and they will be lost in urine.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What are the consequences of a GFR that is too low?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Waste products will accumulate in the plasma, ultimately leading to illness and death if untreated.</choice><choice value="B">There will be no consequences.</choice><choice value="C">Needed substances will rush through the renal tubules ultimately leading to illness and death if untreated.</choice><choice value="D">Un-needed substances will stay in the renal tubules.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="average_gfr_per_minute_day" /><skillref idref="consequences_gfr_high_low" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. A GFR that is too low will allow waste products to accumulate in the plasma, ultimately leading to illness and death if not corrected.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There will be a consequence.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is a made up consequence that combines the results of GFR that is too high and too low.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the GFR is too high, unneeded substances will not stay in the renal tubules. Rather, needed substances will rush through the renal tubules too quickly to be completely absorbed, and they will be lost in urine.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
