<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_process_urination"><title>Tutor</title><question id="micturition"><body><p>The process of urination is referred to as <input_ref input="A" />and urine is ultimately released through the <input_ref input="B" />. This body part connects the bladder to the outside of the body. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">micturition</choice><choice value="two">macturtion</choice><choice value="three">circular contraction</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">urethra</choice><choice value="two">sex organs</choice><choice value="three">kidneys</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="define_micturition" /><response name="micturition" input="A" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The process of urination is referred to as micturition.</feedback></response><response name="macturtion" input="A" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is a made up term that sounds similar to the correct term. </feedback></response><response name="circular_contraction" input="A" match="three" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Circular contraction occurs through the smooth muscles, otherwise known as parasitosis. This is how stored urine makes its’ way into the bladder.</feedback></response><hint>The word is derived from the latin word micturire, that describes the desire to urinate</hint></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="identify_urethra" /><response name="urethra" input="B" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct: The entire process of urination begins with blood carrying various wastes entering each of the two kidneys through the renal artery and ends when urine exits out of the body through the urethra. </feedback></response><response name="sex_organs" input="B" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect: The entire process of urination begins with blood carrying various wastes entering each of the two kidneys through the renal artery and ends when urine exits out of the body through the urethra. During the process, urine leaves each kidney through each ureter and is driven to the bladder.</feedback></response><response name="kidneys" input="B" match="three" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect: The entire process of urination begins with blood carrying various wastes entering each of the two kidneys through the renal artery and ends when urine exits out of the body through the urethra. </feedback></response><hint>The correct choice is based on location. Think about where each choice is located.</hint></part></question></assessment>
