<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_urine_formation"><title>tutor</title><page><content><p>To produce urine, nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions:</p></content><question id="glomerular_filtration"><body>One, glomerular filtration is</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">the first step in urine production where water and most of the solutes in blood plasma pass through into the renal tubule.</choice><choice value="B">a process where reabsorbed substances are returned to the blood as it travels along the peritubular capillaries and vasa recta.</choice><choice value="C">is the additional removal of substances from the blood in the peritubular capillary network or the vasa recta.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="glomerular_filtration_p1"><skillref idref="identify_glomerular_filtration" /><skillref idref="differentiate_major_processes_urine_formation" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Glomerular filtration is the first step in urine production where water and most of the solutes in blood plasma pass through into the renal tubule.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Tubular reabsorption is a process where reabsorbed substances are returned to the blood as it travels along the peritubular capillaries and vasa recta.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Secretion refers to the removal of additional substances from the blood after filtration in the renal corpuscle.</feedback></response></part></question></page><page><content><p>To produce urine, nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions:</p></content><question id="reabsorption"><body>Two, reabsorption is</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">when water and most of the solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of glomerular capillaries.</choice><choice value="B">when cells in the renal tubule and collecting duct collect substances (e.g., wastes, drugs, excess ions) from the filtrate as it flows through the tubule and duct.</choice><choice value="C">when cells of the tubule reabsorb almost all water and solutes from the filtrate as it flows through the renal tubule and collecting duct and return the fluid and solutes to the blood.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="reabsorption_p1"><skillref idref="identify_reabsorbtion" /><skillref idref="differentiate_major_processes_urine_formation" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Glomerular filtration is when water and most of the solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of glomerular capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Secretion is when cells in the renal tubule and collecting duct collect substances (e.g., wastes, drugs, excess ions) from the blood as it flows through the peritubular capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Reabsorption is when cells of the tubule reabsorb almost all water and solutes from the filtrate as it flows through the peritubular capillaries.</feedback></response></part></question></page><page><content><p>To produce urine, nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions:</p></content><question id="secretion"><body>Three, secretion occurs</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">when cells in the renal tubule and collecting duct remove additional substances from the blood as it flows through the peritubular capillaries or the vasa recta.</choice><choice value="B">upon the returning of substances to the bloodstream.</choice><choice value="C">when water and solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of glomerular capillaries, first into the glomerular capsule and then into the renal tubule.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="secretion_p1"><skillref idref="identify_secretion" /><skillref idref="differentiate_major_processes_urine_formation" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Secretion occurs when cells in the renal tubule and collecting duct remove additional substances from the blood as it flows through the peritubular capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Reabsorption is the returning of substances to the bloodstream.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Glomerular filtration is when water and solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of glomerular capillaries, first into the glomerular capsule and then into the renal tubule.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
