<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_countercurrent_mult_1"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The presence of ADH amplifies urea recycling, which, in turn, amplifies the osmotic gradient and enables the formation of more concentrated urine. This is otherwise known as:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">countercurrent exchange</choice><choice value="B">countercurrent multiplication</choice><choice value="C">countercurrent division</choice><choice value="D">osmolarity</choice></multiple_choice><part><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Two countercurrent mechanisms operate in the kidneys: countercurrent multiplication and countercurrent exchange. Countercurrent multiplication amplifies the osmotic gradient and enables the formation of more concentrated urine via the presence of ADH.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The presence of ADH amplifies urea recycling, which, in turn, amplifies the osmotic gradient and enables the formation of more concentrated urine. This is otherwise known as countercurrent multiplication.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The presence of ADH amplifies urea recycling, which, in turn, amplifies the osmotic gradient and enables the formation of more concentrated urine. This is otherwise known as countercurrent multiplication. There is no such thing as concurrent division.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osmolarity measures the concentration of a solution by osmoles of solutes per liter. The presence of ADH amplifies urea recycling, which, in turn, amplifies the osmotic gradient and enables the formation of more concentrated urine. This is otherwise known as countercurrent multiplication.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
