<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_fiber_org_digt"><title>Tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What is one of the advantages to having a convergent arrangement of muscle fibers?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">This arrangement allows the muscle fibers to shorten into a large bulge.</choice><choice value="B">This arrangement allows the muscle to expand and contract in a circular way</choice><choice value="C">This arrangement contains more muscle fibers and can produce more tension while only slightly pulling on their tendons.</choice><choice value="D">This arrangement of motor units the can be stimulated in different, smaller areas that can change the direction of the pull.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i2b341b03256f45be8a476860e21e55f1"><skillref idref="_u5_fiber_org_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u5_fiber_org_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The fibers would be in a parallel arrangement to cause this type of action.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The fibers would be in a circular arrangement for this type of motion.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The fibers would be arranged in a pennate or feather shape for this action.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The fibers would be arranged in a convergent attachment for this type of action.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What type of muscle arrangement allows you to whistle?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Parallel</choice><choice value="B">Sphincter</choice><choice value="C">Convergent</choice><choice value="D">Pennate</choice></multiple_choice><part id="a5a78410a5b44fb688479c1dc6d3d610"><skillref idref="_u5_fiber_org_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u5_fiber_org_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Parallel arrangement allows for movement like lifting your forearm.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Contraction of the sphincter muscle orbicularis oris allows you to pucker your lips to whistle.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Contraction of different parts of a convergent muscle allows changes in direction.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The feather shaped pennate fasicles do not pull their tendons very far.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
