<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="direction_systems_pool"><title>Introduction of Body Systems</title><multiple_choice id="_u1_quiz_20"><body>In the abdomen, which direction is the digestive system to the integumentary system?<input_ref input="qinput_0" /></body><input id="qinput_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="deep">deep</choice><choice value="super">superficial</choice><choice value="lat">lateral</choice><choice value="infer">inferior</choice></input><part id="qpart_6"><skillref idref="_u1_orientation_direction_SKILL" /><response input="qinput_0" match="deep" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The digestive system is closer to the center of the body; the integumentary system is superficial to the digestive system.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="super" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The digestive system is closer to the center of the body; the integumentary system is superficial to the digestive system.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="lat" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. You should be focusing on moving toward the inside of the body.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="infer" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The digestive system is inferior to some regions of the integumentary system, and superior to others. There is a more precise answer.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u1_quiz_21"><body>In the hands, which direction is the integumentary system to the muscular system?<input_ref input="qinput_0" /></body><input id="qinput_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="dist">distal</choice><choice value="super">superficial</choice><choice value="prox">proximal</choice><choice value="lat">lateral</choice></input><part id="qpart_7"><skillref idref="_u1_orientation_direction_SKILL" /><response input="qinput_0" match="dist" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. the hands are distal to the rest of the body, but this does not describe the location of the integumentary system in relation to the muscular system.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="super" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The skin, hair and nails of the integumentary system are on the surface of the body.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="prox" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The hands are distal to the rest of the body, not proximal. This question is about terms that describe depth of tissues, such as superficial, deep and intermediate.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="lat" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Lateral means toward the side. This question is about terms that describe depth of tissues, such as superficial, deep and intermediate.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u1_quiz_22"><body>In the hands, where is the muscular system in relation to the skeletal system and the integumentary system?<input_ref input="qinput_0" /></body><input id="qinput_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="inter">intermediate</choice><choice value="ant">anterior</choice><choice value="post">posterior</choice><choice value="lat">lateral</choice></input><part id="qpart_8"><response input="qinput_0" match="inter" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The muscles in the hands are intermediate to the bones and the skin.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="ant" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Anterior means toward the front. This question concerns terms that describe depth of tissues, such as superficial, deep and intermediate.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="post" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Posterior means toward the back. This question concerns terms that describe depth of tissues, such as superficial, deep and intermediate.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="lat" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Lateral means toward the side. This question concerns terms that describe depth of tissues, such as superficial, deep and intermediate.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u1_quiz_23"><body>Which direction is the brain from the heart?<input_ref input="qinput_0" /></body><input id="qinput_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="sup">superior</choice><choice value="ant">anterior</choice><choice value="post">posterior</choice><choice value="lat">lateral</choice></input><part id="qpart_9"><skillref idref="_u1_orientation_direction_SKILL" /><response input="qinput_0" match="sup" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Superior or cephalic means toward the head.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="ant" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Anterior means toward the front; the answer for this question is a term that means toward the head.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="post" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Posterior means toward the rear; the answer for this question is a term that means toward the head.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="lat" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Lateral means toward the side; the answer for this question is a term that means toward the head.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u1_quiz_24"><body>As the blood in the cardiovascular system travels from the heart through the upper abdomen to the feet, which direction does it go?<input_ref input="qinput_0" /></body><input id="qinput_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="inferior">inferior, then distal</choice><choice value="superior">superior, then proximal</choice><choice value="anterior">anterior, then lateral</choice><choice value="medial">medial, then superficial</choice></input><part id="qpart_10"><skillref idref="_u1_orientation_direction_SKILL" /><response input="qinput_0" match="inferior" score="10"><feedback>Correct. It travels inferior from the heart to the abdomen and leg and then distal through the leg away from the trunk.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="superior" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Superior and proximal to the heart does not describe travel to the abdomen or legs.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="anterior" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Anterior and lateral doesn’t describe travel through the abdomen to the legs;it could possibly describe travel into the hands.</feedback></response><response input="qinput_0" match="medial" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Medial means toward the center and superior means upward or toward the head.The blood travels down from the heart to the abdomen.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></pool>
