<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Sample XML file generated by XMLSPY v2004 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)-->
<!DOCTYPE feedback PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Feedback Activity 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_feedback_1_0.dtd">
<?xmlspysps http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_feedback_1_0.sps?>
<feedback id="DNA_structures_feedback">
	<title>About the Structures involved in Creating DNA and RNA</title>
  
	<description>
		<p>Evaluate how well you would perform on each learning objective below and then think of two questions about this lesson. Your questions can be for clarification of the
			material or further insight. Your self evaluation and questions may also shape the
			discussions in class.</p>
	</description>
	<questions>
	<likert_series>
	  <prompt>Selecting 1 means "I could do this not at all", selecting 3 means "I could do this while relying on the course material" and selecting 5 means "I could do this perfectly on an exam." </prompt>
      <likert_scale size="5" center="3">
        <label value="1">not at all</label>
	<label value="3">with support</label>
        <label value="5">on my own</label>
          </likert_scale>
      <item id="Bases_1" required="true">
        <prompt>Identify the difference between a purine and pyrimidine.</prompt>
          </item>
      <item required="true" id="BasePairing_1">
        <prompt>Identify correct base pairing between DNA and RNA bases.</prompt>
          </item>
	  <item required="true" id="BasePairing_2">
        <prompt>Correctly draw the hydrogen bonding between DNA and RNA bases.</prompt>
          </item>
	  <item required="true" id="BasePairing_3">
        <prompt>Describe why AT and AU base pairs are weaker than GC base pairs.</prompt>
          </item>
	  <item required="true" id="Hybridization_1">
        <prompt>Describe the criteria for determining the most stable structure between two DNA molecules, two RNA molecules, between a DNA and a RNA molecule.</prompt>
          </item>
	  <item required="true" id="Hybridization_2">
        <prompt>Describe the hydrogen bonding that exists between complimentary base pairs in DNA and RNA.</prompt>
          </item>
	</likert_series>
	  
		<open_response required="true" id="carbo_1">

		  <prompt>Think of two questions about this lesson. These can be for clarification of the
		    material or further insight. Your questions may also shape the
		    discussions in class. 
		    My Question 1</prompt>
		</open_response>
		<open_response id="carbo_2" required="false">
			<prompt>My Question 2</prompt>
		</open_response>
		
	</questions>
</feedback>
