<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m3_levels_org_02">
	<head>
		<title>Henry's Law</title>

		<!-- <objref idref="mechanisms_gas_exchange_lungs_tissue"/> -->
		<objref idref="state_henrys_law_relate_external_internal_respiration"/>
	</head>
	<body>


		<section>
			<title>Air</title>
			<body>
				<!--  <p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Relate quantities of oxygen in the air to
						availability in the body</em></p>-->
				<p>The four main gases in the atmosphere are nitrogen at 78.084%, oxygen at 20.946%,
					argon at 0.934%, and carbon dioxide at 0.039%. Other elements that account for
					less than 0.002% of the whole including neon, helium, krypton, hydrogen, nitrous
					oxide, carbon monoxide, xenon, ozone, nitrogen oxide, and trace amounts of
					ammonia. Water vapor ranges from 1 to 4 percent at sea level and 0.4% overall.
					The partial pressure of each of these elements can be found by multiplying the
					percentage of the particular gas by 1 atm or 760 mmHg, so the partial pressure
					of oxygen (PO<sub>2</sub>) is 760 x 0.20946, or 159.19 mmHg. The PCO<sub>2</sub>
					is 760 x 0.0039, or 3 mmHg.</p>


			</body>
		</section>
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<p>The partial pressure of oxygen is what determines how much oxygen is available in
					our lungs for transfer to the blood. Atmospheric pressure is 760 mmHg and the
					concentration of oxygen is 21% (21% is the same as a fraction of 0.21). Either a
					change in the amount of oxygen or a change in the atmospheric pressure can alter
					the partial pressure of oxygen (or the amount of oxygen available), but often it
					is the pressure that affects how much oxygen is available.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_partial_pressure" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

			</body>
		</section>



		<section>
			<title>How Gases Exchange</title>
			<body>


				<p>The respiratory system brings in oxygen and exchanges it for carbon dioxide.
					Oxygen makes up 21% of the air we breathe while carbon dioxide is found at very
					low levels (0.039%). The diffusion of gases across membranes follows the same
					principles as the diffusion of solutes in solution across membranes, basically
					molecules move down a gradient. The difference is that gases in solution are
					measured in terms of <term>partial pressure</term>. </p>
				<p>Partial pressure is the pressure that a given gas in a mixture contributes to the
					total pressure inside the container or in the atmosphere. The partial pressure
					is equal to the total pressure times the fraction of the gas. </p>
				<p>For example, at sea level, total atmospheric pressure is 760 mmHg. Because 21% of
					air is oxygen, the partial pressure of oxygen in atmospheric air at sea level is
					760 mmHg x 21% = 160 mmHg. At higher altitudes, where atmospheric pressure may
					only be 500 mmHg, the partial pressure of oxygen would be 500 mmHg x 21% = 105
					mmHg.</p>
				<p>When we inhale air all the major components of air are in gas form. However, the
					oxygen that enters our body must move from the air space in the lungs into the
					liquids found in our body such as blood plasma and cell cytoplasm.
					Alternatively, the carbon dioxide in the blood moves from the cell cytoplasm and
					the plasma into the air of the alveoli. To understand how the air-liquid interface
					affects the amount of oxygen or carbon dioxide found in the compartments of the
					body, we need to examine Henry’s law, which describes how gases dissolve in
					liquids based on their physical properties and the temperature of the liquid. </p>
				<p>Henry’s Law, explains that the amount of dissolved gas found in a liquid is
					proportionate to the gas phase partial pressure as well as the molecules
					solubility in a specific liquid. For example, considering partial pressures
					alone it would be expected that oxygen would readily diffuse from the aveoli
					because there is a high partial pressure gradient between alveoli and blood.
					However, oxygen has very low solubility in plasma, so even with the large
					gradient between the two very little of oxygen leaves the aveoli and dissolves
					directly into the plasma. Instead most of the dissolved oxygen found in the
					blood is attached to the hemoglobin molecules found inside the red blood cells.
					On the other hand carbon dioxide is very soluble in plasma (over 20 times more
					soluble than oxygen), so significant amounts can be found directly in dissolved
					form. Because of its high solubility, large amounts of carbon dioxide can move
					between air and liquid compartments even with small partial pressure
					gradients.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_oygen_co2_soluble" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				<p>We can be significantly affected by differences in the partial pressures of the
					air we are breathing. At high altitudes, the fraction of oxygen in the
					atmosphere is the same (21%), but the total atmospheric pressure is less (as
					shown earlier). This causes the partial pressure of the oxygen we breathe in to
					be significantly less than that at sea level, making it much harder to move
					oxygen from the air into our plasma. </p>

				<example title="scuba">
					<title>Decompression Sickness</title>
					<p>Scuba divers involved in deep dives breathe in air that is under very high
						pressure. At sea level very little nitrogen enters our plasma since it has a
						very low partial pressure. However, a large amount of nitrogen can
						move into the plasma (and consequently the other body and cell compartments)
						during underwater dives since the air in the tank is under higher pressure
						as well as the diver who experiences the pressure of the column of water on
						their body. When the diver ascends slowly, the scuba apparatus
						automatically lowers the total pressure on the air the diver is breathing.
						The partial pressure of the nitrogen in the tank becomes less than the
						partial pressure of the nitrogen inside the diver’s body. Consequently the
						nitrogen that had moved from the air in the tank into the blood and tissues will now move
						from the blood and tissues back into the alveoli and be removed when the diver exhales. </p>
					<p>But if the diver ascends too quickly, the gas, which has a very low
						solubility, comes out of solution and moves into the gas phase while still
						in the diver's body. The gas phase becomes manifest as bubbles trapped
						in the diver's tissues. The trapped bubbles can cause severe joint pains,
						dizziness, shortness of breath, extreme fatigue, paralysis, and possibly
						death. A hyperbaric (high pressure) chamber allows the diver to breathe air
						at an elevated partial pressure. The high partial pressure forces the nitrogen back into its dissolved
						liquid phase state. The barometric pressure of the chamber is then
						decreased very slowly to allow the nitrogen to be released slowly through
						the lungs.</p>

				</example>
				<p>Hyperbaric chambers can also be used to increase the partial pressure of oxygen
					and enhance its ability to enter our body through the respiratory system or
					through open wounds. Clinically high partial pressures of oxygen administered
					locally are used to treat people with regional infections such as bacterial
					gangrene infections sometimes found in the limbs of diabetics with poor blood
					circulation. Bacterial gangrene is an infection caused by anaerobic bacteria.
					These bacteria cannot survive in an oxygen-rich environment. The high partial
					pressures of oxygen found in the hyperbaric chamber can force more oxygen into
					the tissues infected by the bacteria. If the tissues in which the bacteria are
					living become too aerobic, the bacteria may die.</p>
				<image src="../webcontent/hyperbaric_chamber_blks_301m.jpg" height="400" width="400"
					alt="hyperbaric chamber">
					<caption>By Intermedichbo (<link
							href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Monoplace_chamber.JPG"
							>Hyperbaric Chamber</link>) <link
							href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" target="new"
							>CC-BY-3.0</link>
					</caption>
				</image>

				<!-- this is the wrong way to cite.  See above
				<p><cite>By  at sr.wikipedia [CC-BY-3.0-rs
						(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/rs/deed.en) or GFDL
						(http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html)], from Wikimedia Commons</cite></p>
-->
			</body>
		</section>



		<wb:inline idref="respiratory_partial_pressure_1" purpose="didigetthis"/>







	</body>
</workbook_page>
