<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m3_levels_org_01">
	<head>
		<title>Respiratory Levels of Organization</title>
		<objref idref="describe_four_respiratory_process"/>
	</head>
	<body>


		<p>Our bodies exchange oxygen for carbon dioxide at a number of different levels. The
			exchange of air from the outside environment into the lungs is driven by the mechanics
			of ventilation. At a molecular level oxygen binds to hemoglobin in the red blood cells
			in the capillaries of the lungs. Some of this oxygen displaces carbon dioxide that was
			transported from peripheral cells. The exchange of gases occurs in red blood cells
			(where hemoglobin is concentrated) at the interface of the circulatory system and
			respiratory system, called the respiratory membrane. Oxygen
			diffuses from the inhaled air in the lungs across the aveolar and capillary membranes
			and into the blood plasma. It then enters the red blood cells where it will be carried
			on hemoglobin molecules to the other tissues of the body. Gas exchange at the respiratory
			membrane is known as <term>external respiration</term>. Gas exchange at between the tissues and the
			blood is <term>internal respiration</term>. At the molecular level carbon
			dioxide created during cell metabolism diffuses across the cell membrane into the
			interstitial spaces and extracellular fluid. When it crosses the capillary and red blood
			cell membrane some carbon dioxide is picked up hemoglobin by molecules inside the red blood cell. Inside the cells of the
			body tissues, oxygen will be used during the process of aerobic <term>cellular
				respiration</term>. Cellular respiration is a process used by our cells to convert
			nutrients into energy. The process of aerobic cellular respiration requires oxygen and produces carbon dioxide as a
			waste product. </p>


		<!--  <image src="../webcontent/r_m1_1.png" height="350" width="500" alt="four respiratory processes"/>-->

		<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_1.png" width="550"
			alt="four respiratory processes">
			<caption>Four respiratory processes. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>

		<wb:inline idref="respiratory_gas_transport_exchange" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<p>To understand these system-level functions, you will be further exploring structures and
			processes occurring at all levels of organization. Some examples of major respiratory
			structures assigned to their structural level of organization of the respiratory system
			include:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><em style="italic">Chemical level</em> – oxygen, carbon dioxide, bicarbonate and
				hydrogen ions</li>
			<li><em style="italic">Macromolecular level</em> – hemoglobin, mucus, and surfactant</li>
			<li><em style="italic">Cellular level</em> – ciliated cells, goblet cells, alveolar
				cells, and macrophages</li>
			<li><em style="italic">Tissue level</em> – stratified to pseudostratified to simple
				squamous epithelium</li>
			<li><em style="italic">Organ level</em> – upper respiratory tract, bronchial tree and
				lungs</li>
			<li><em style="italic">Organ system level</em> - integration of organs for gas
				exchange</li>
		</ul>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
