<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m3_levels_org_03">
	<head>
		<title>Exchange of Oxygen and Carbon Dioxide </title>

		<objref idref="mechanisms_gas_exchange_lungs_tissue"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<!--  <p><term>With respect to external respiration:</term></p>
		<ul style="none">
			<li>a.Describe oxygen and carbon dioxide concentration gradients and net gas movements. </li>
			<li>b.Analyze how oxygen and carbon dioxide movements are affected by changes in partial
				pressure gradients (e.g., at high altitude), surface area, diffusion distance, and
				solubility and molecular weight of the gases. </li>

			 <li>NOT GOING TO COVER- c.Describe the mechanisms of ventilation-perfusion coupling and predict the effect
				that reduced alveolar ventilation has on pulmonary blood flow and the effect that
				reduced pulmonary blood flow has on bronchiole diameter and alveolar
				ventilation.</li> 
		</ul>
		<p><term>With respect to internal respiration:</term></p>

		 <p>Describe the four respiratory processes - ventilation, external respiration (gas exchange
			at lung), internal respiration (gas exchange at body tissues), and cellular
			respiration.</p>
		<ul style="none">
			<li>a.Describe oxygen and carbon dioxide concentration gradients and net gas
				movements.</li>
			<li>b.Explain the factors that maintain oxygen and carbon dioxide gradients between
				blood and tissue cells.</li>
		</ul>
		<p><em style="bold">END OF SUB OBJECTIVES</em></p>-->
		<section>
			<title>External Respiration</title>
			<body>

				<p>Air containing oxygen enters the alveoli by the process of ventilation (described
					in a later section). The partial pressure of oxygen in the alveoli is slightly
					lower than the partial pressure of oxygen found in the atmosphere. Air taken
					into the lungs (tidal volume minus the volume of the conduction zone) mixes with
					air that is already in the lungs (functional residual volume). ). Because gas
					exchange is constantly occurring (even between breaths, when we hold our breath,
					etc.), the air making up the functional residual volume has had some oxygen
					removed from it and some carbon dioxide added to it. When a new tidal volume of
					air is inhaled, the portion of this air that enters the alveoli mixes with the
					functional residual volume and effectively lowers the fraction of oxygen in this
					alveolar air.</p>

				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_gas_exchange" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

				<p>Inhaled air at sea level typically has a partial pressure of oxygen near 160
					mmHg. In the alveoli, the partial pressure of oxygen would vary with our
					ventilation pattern, but typically equilibrates at about 105 mmHg. It is the
					difference between alveolar oxygen partial pressure and the plasma oxygen
					partial pressure that drives external respiration across the alveolar membrane.
					Blood coming through the pulmonary arterial circulation is lower in oxygen, with
					a typical partial pressure of 40 mmHg. The differential concentration gradient
					for oxygen to move from the alveolar air into the capillary blood starts at
					about 65 mmHg (105 mmHg in the alveoli minus 40 mmHg in blood), providing enough
					of a difference in partial pressures for oxygen to diffuse from the aveoli into
					the capillary. Diffusion will occur along the length of the pulmonary capillary
					until the partial pressures come into equilibrium near 105 mmHg. </p>
				<example title="altitude_sickness">
					<title>Altitude Sickness</title>
					<p> Altitude sickness, also called acute mountain sickness, can strike people
						climbing to elevations above 8,000 feet (although it typically occurs only
						at altitudes much higher than this). At elevations high above sea level,
						there is the same percentage of oxygen (21%), but much less atmospheric
						pressure. This lowers the partial pressure of the oxygen being inhaled so
						less oxygen enters the body. If the body doesn’t adapt well, a person can
						experience altitude sickness ranging from mild to severe forms. Mild to
						moderate altitude sickness can cause nausea, vomiting, tachycardia,
						shortness of breath with exercise, or difficulty sleeping. Mild to moderate
						cases usually resolve themselves when the person descends to a lower
						altitude. However, severe cases are another matter. They can result in
						cyanosis, pulmonary congestion, confusion and stupor, a cough with or without
						blood, a gray or very pale complexion, the inability to walk a straight
						line, if able to walk at all, and shortness of breath when at rest. These
						cases require immediate evacuation to lower altitudes. Without treatment,
						severe altitude sickness may result in death due to pulmonary complications
						or brain swelling. The good news is that altitude sickness can be prevented.
						Individuals who climb to extremely high altitudes, like Mount Everest,
						should do so slowly to allow their bodies to become acclimated to the
						atmospheric differences.</p>
				</example>
				<p>The partial pressure of oxygen in the system circulation is slightly lower. As
					blood enters the left atrium of the heart, a small amount of the pulmonary blood
					mixes with the bronchial blood that has nourished the lung tissue, lowering the
					partial pressure so that the actual concentration of oxygen is about 100
					mmHg, which is a typical value measured in a sample of arterial blood.</p>
				<p>The functioning of the pressure gradient for carbon dioxide works in reverse of
					that for oxygen, with the carbon dioxide partial pressure being higher in the
					pulmonary arterial blood than in the alveoli. Even with a much smaller gradient
					for carbon dioxide than for oxygen, nearly as much carbon dioxide diffuses from
					the blood to the alveoli as oxygen diffuses from the alveoli to the blood
					because of the much higher solubility of carbon dioxide in the plasma.</p>
			</body>
		</section>


		<table rowstyle="alternating">
			<tr>
				<td><em style="bold">External respiration: pulmonary</em></td>
				<td align="center"><em style="bold">PO<sub>2</sub></em></td>
				<td align="center"><em style="bold">PCO<sub>2</sub></em></td>
			</tr>

			<tr>
				<td>Pulmonary arteries leading to capillaries</td>
				<td align="center">40</td>
				<td align="center">45</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Alveoli</td>
				<td align="center">105</td>
				<td align="center">40</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Pulmonary veins</td>
				<td align="center">100</td>
				<td align="center">40</td>
			</tr>

		</table>
		<!-- <image src="../webcontent/r_m1_3.jpg" height="300" width="500"
			alt="close up illustration of deoxgynated blood cells in external respiration process"/> -->

		<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_3.jpg" width="400"
			alt="close up illustration of deoxgynated blood cells in external respiration process">
			<caption>Deoxgynated blood cells. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>

		<section>
			<title>Internal Respiration </title>
			<body>

				<p>Internal respiration occurs between the blood and systemic tissues of the body.
					The systemic arteries carry essentially the same concentration of oxygen and
					carbon dioxide as the pulmonary veins. Oxygen is continually being used by the
					tissues, and the partial pressure of oxygen in active cells remains below 40
					mmHg. Oxygen circulating in the systemic arterial blood readily diffuses across
					the membranes of the blood vessels into the tissues, replenishing the supply of
					oxygen in the cells. The final concentration of oxygen and carbon dioxide in the
					systemic veins is essentially the same as it is in the pulmonary arteries. </p>

				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_internal_respiration" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<p>Just as the tissues are continually using up the oxygen, they are continually
					producing carbon dioxide. The partial pressure of carbon dioxide in tissues is
					always greater than 45 mmHg. This accounts for the diffusion of carbon dioxide
					into the systemic capillaries, raising the pressure to 45 mmHg. The systemic
					veins carry essentially the same concentration of oxygen and carbon dioxide as
					the pulmonary arteries.</p>

				<table rowstyle="alternating">

					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Internal respiration: tissues</em></td>
						<td align="center"><em style="bold">PO<sub>2</sub></em></td>
						<td align="center"><em style="bold">PCO<sub>2</sub></em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Systemic arteries leading to capillaries</td>
						<td align="center">100</td>
						<td align="center">40</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Metabolically active tissues</td>
						<td align="center">&lt; 40</td>
						<td align="center">&gt; 45</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Systemic veins</td>
						<td align="center">40</td>
						<td align="center">45</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</body>
		</section>

		<!--  	<image src="../webcontent/internal_respiration.jpg" height="300" width="500"
			alt="diagram illustrating circle of blood feeding o2 to cells and disposing of co2"/>-->

		<image src="../webcontent/internal_respiration.jpg" width="400"
			alt="diagram illustrating circle of blood feeding o2 to cells and disposing of co2">
			<caption>Oxgynated blood cells. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons
				Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>

		<!--  <p>Put image of Alveoli</p>-->

		<wb:inline idref="respiratory_internal_external_respiration" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
