<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m3_levels_org_wrapup_openfree">
	<head>
		<title>Respiratory Levels of Organization Summary</title>



	</head>
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Let’s summarize</title>
			
			<body>
				<p>The major function of the respiratory system is to obtain oxygen needed to
					convert nutrients to energy and to remove carbon dioxide that is a waste product
					of this reaction. In order to perform this function the respiratory system must
					have mechanisms for moving oxygen into the body from the atmosphere and a way to
					transport the oxygen to tissues throughout the entire body. The respiratory
					system must also transport carbon dioxide to the lungs to be expelled from the
					body. Additionally, the respiratory system plays a role in protecting the body
					from microorganisms and maintaining proper pH levels.</p>
				<p>The primary function of the respiratory system, the exchange of oxygen and carbon
					dioxide, occurs through several processes.</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Ventilation-moves air in and out of the lungs.</li>
				</ul>
				<ul>
					<li>External respiration exchanges oxygen and carbon dioxide between the air and
						the alveoli of the lungs.</li>
					<li>Internal respiration exchanges oxygen and carbon dioxide between the blood
						and tissues.</li>
					<li>Cellular respiration uses oxygen to release energy from nutrients.</li>
					<li>To understand how the respiratory system functions, it is studied on the
						chemical, macromolecular, cellular, tissue, organ and organ system
						levels.</li>
					<li>The role of partial pressure in the diffusion of gases in external and
						internal respiration <ul>
							<li>Henry’s law discuss the solubility of gasses in a liquid and helps
								explain why oxygen and carbon dioxide are transported
								differently</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>The macromolecule level related the structure of the macromolecules to
						its functions. <ul>
							<li>Mucus- immunoglobulin for immune function, glycosylate proteins for
								hydration</li>
							<li>Surfactant- phospholipids that disrupt the surface tension of water
								in the alveoli to prevent collapse.</li>
							<li>Hemoglobin- iron containing heme group to transport oxygen and carbon
								dioxide. <ul>
									<li>Transport of oxygen on hemoglobin- the benefit of a tight
										association and factors that will affect the affinity of
										hemoglobin for oxygen</li>
									<li>Transport of carbon dioxide as carbaminohemoglobin and
										bicarbonate as well as the role of carbonic anhydrase</li>
								</ul>
							</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<ul>
					<li>There are several important cell types that are found in different locations
						of the respiratory system. <ul>
							<li>Epithelial cell types located in the respiratory tree include goblet
								cells that secrete mucus, ciliated cells that sweep mucus into the
								pharynx and basal cells which can regenerate and produce new layers
								of cells.</li>
							<li>Macrophages located in the lungs will help to provide protection
								against pathogens.</li>
							<li>Epithelial cells in the alveoli are divided into simple squamous Type I cells that
								allow for diffusion and also secrete angiotensin-converting enzyme
								and the cuboidal Type II cells that secrete surfactant.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>In order to understand how the respiratory system functions, it is important to
					understand how the different organizational levels function both independently
					and together. Different portions of the respiratory system contain different
					cell types that all work together to allow for the diffusion of oxygen and
					carbon dioxide while providing protection from pathogens.</p>
				
			</body>
		</section>

		<!--	<section>
			
			<title><em style="bold">End Questions</em></title>
			
			<body>
				
				
				  <p>Before you do the quiz activity, please evaluate your understanding of the
					learning objectives for the Urinary Homeostasis and use the first
					My Response link below to ask any questions you might have about the material
					that you would like the instructor to address. Your questions can be for
					clarification of the material or further insight. Your self-evaluation will not
					be graded, but will be available for your instructor to read. Answering these
					questions may also shape the discussions in class. </p>
				
				<activity idref="_u12_m4_urinary_homeostasis_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/> 
				
			 	<p> If you do not feel ready for the quia, identify the objective(s) you need to
					review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t
					just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of
					questions that will be in the quiz.</p>
				<p>Quiz goes Here</p>
				
				 <activity idref="u2_m3_checkpoint" purpose="checkpoint"/>
				 
				<p> Now that you have finished the quiz, do you have any questions? Your instructor
					will be able to read the questions and comments that you submit. </p>
				 <activity idref="_u12_m4_urinary_homeostasis_feedback_post_quiz" purpose="myresponse"/> 
				
				
				
			</body>
			
		</section>-->
		



	</body>
</workbook_page>
