<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m3_levels_org_05">
	<head>
		<title>Transport of Oxygen</title>

		<objref idref="mechanisms_gas_transport_in_blood"/>
	</head>

	<body>



		<!-- <p>With respect to oxygen transport:</p>
		<ul style="none">
			<li>a.Describe the ways in which oxygen is transported in blood and discuss the relative
				importance of each to total oxygen transport. </li>
			<li>b.State the reversible chemical equation for oxygen binding to hemoglobin and
				predict how raising or lowering the partial pressure of oxygen will shift the
				equilibrium. </li>

		</ul>
		<p>With respect to the oxygen-hemoglobin saturation curve:</p>

		<ul style="none">
			<li>a.Interpret the curve at low and high partial pressures of oxygen. </li>
			<li>b.List factors that shift the curve down and to the right, and explain how this
				results in increased oxygen delivery to the tissues. </li>
			<li>c.List factors that shift the curve up and to the left, and explain how this
				facilitates oxygen binding to hemoglobin in the lungs.</li>

		</ul> -->
		<section>
			<title>Hemoglobin and Oxygen Association</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the structure and function of
						hemoglobin</em></p> -->
				<p>Adult humans require about 250 ml of new oxygen to enter the bloodstream per
					minute to support the internal respiration of their tissues while in a relaxed
					state. Since oxygen is poorly soluble in our plasma, we only deliver about 15 ml
					of oxygen per minute to our tissues in dissolved form (0.3 ml of dissolved
					oxygen per deciliter of blood times 50 deciliters (a unit that refers to 10 mls
					of a liquid) per minute of cardiac output. Therefore we become critically
					dependent on another mechanism to help deliver sufficient amounts of oxygen to
					where it is needed. That mechanism utilizes a protein, hemoglobin as a
					transporter molecule for either oxygen or carbon dioxide. Red blood cells
					contain high concentrations of hemoglobin.</p>

				<p>In order to be able to discuss the different macromolecules and the reactions
					they undergo, it is important to be familiar with the common chemical symbols
					that are used. </p>
				<p>Here are a few of symbols you will see:</p>
				<ul style="disc">
					<li>Deoxyhemoglobin (HHb) - A hemoglobin molecule that has been reduced and does
						not have a full complement of oxygen molecules attached to it.</li>
					<li>Oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) - A gas that is required for converting nutrients
						into cellular energy.</li>
					<li>Oxyhemoglobin (HbO<sub>2</sub>)- A hemoglobin
						molecule that has been oxidized and is bound to four oxygen molecules.</li>
					<li>Carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) - A gas that is released as a waste product
						during the breakdown of glucose to release energy. </li>
					<li>2,3-bisphosphoglycerate (BPG) - is a molecule found in red blood cells that
						can bind to hemoglobin and decrease its affinity for oxygen.</li>
					<li>Carbonic acid ( H<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> ) - is formed as an intermediate
						step in the transportation of carbon dioxide. Carbonic anhydrase is an
						enzyme that will speed up the formation of carbonic acid from water and
						carbon dioxide.</li>
					<li>Bicarbonate (HCO<sub>3</sub>−) - Carbonic acid can quickly convert to
						bicarbonate and a hydrogen ion. Bicarbonate plays a huge role in
						transporting carbon dioxide and maintaining blood pH. </li>
				</ul>

				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_oxygen_dissociation" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_chemical_equation_oxygen" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

				<!--  	<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_5.jpg" height="350" width="350"
					alt="oxygen partial pressure and percentage curve"/>-->

				<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_5.jpg" height="350" width="350"
					alt="oxygen partial pressure and percentage curve">
					<caption>Partial pressure. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
						Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
							href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
							>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
				</image>

				<p>On this curve, the x axis lists the PO<sub>2</sub> of the blood (whether it is in
					the lungs or other body tissues), and the y axis lists the percent saturation of
					the hemoglobin with oxygen. This graph has a sigmoidal ‘S’ shape, such that
					changes in partial pressures above 80 mmHg do not have a major effect on the
					percent of hemoglobin saturation. Since normal partial pressure in the lungs is
					over 100 mmHg, there are some safety factors that are important for people who
					travel to altitude or develop ventilation disorders to consider. As long as
					neither is too severe, hemoglobin will stay close to 100% saturated as long as
					the partial pressure in the alveoli can stay above 80 mmHg. Under normal
					conditions, hemoglobin ends up nearly 100% saturated in the lungs and then
					travels to the tissues. In the tissues, hemoglobin will have given up 25% of the
					oxygen it carries such that it is now 75% saturated (the relationship between
					oxygen levels and partial pressure is not linear because of the shape of the
					curve). If there is a higher demand for oxygen in metabolically active cells,
					more of the oxygen will diffuse into the tissues reducing hemoglobin saturation
					below 75%.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Hemoglobin and Oxygen Dissociation</title>
			<body>

				<!--  <p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe how oxygen is able to dissociate
						from hemoglobin and discuss the role that BPG and carbon dioxide
					play</em></p>-->
				<p>Tight binding of oxygen to hemoglobin allows us to transport oxygen throughout
					our cardiovascular system. At the same time hemoglobin cannot bind oxygen so
					tightly that oxygen cannot leave the hemoglobin when it the molecule encounters
					oxygen deprived tissues. Metabolically active tissues cause local environmental
					changes making it easier for oxygen to unload from hemoglobin in these tissues.
					These changes in rates of dissociation can be visualized by looking at the
						<term>oxygen-hemoglobin dissociation </term>under different conditions such
					as changing temperature, PCO<sub>2</sub>, pH, and the levels of
					2,3-bisphosphoglycerate (BPG). Increased cellular metabolism causes increases in
					temperature, BPG production and carbon dioxide levels. The increased carbon
					dioxide further causes a decrease pH. When this happens, oxygen more readily
					leaves hemoglobin molecules, and the oxygen-hemoglobin dissociation curve is
					shifted to the right. Regulation of oxygen delivery to cells is important since
					cells with a high metabolic rate need more oxygen to produce ATP.</p>

				<!--  	<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_6.jpg" height="350" width="350"
					alt="oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve"/>-->

				<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_6.jpg" height="350" width="350"
					alt="oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve">
					<caption>Dissociation curve. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
						Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
							href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
							>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
				</image>

				<p>Specifically, the oxygen-hemoglobin bond is weakened in the more acidic
					environment, and the oxygen leaves the heme more readily. The most commonly
					found acids that result in a locally lowered pH include lactic acid and carbonic
					acid. Lactic acid production results from situations where there is inadequate
					oxygen supply and cells have shifted to anaerobic metabolism of glucose for
					energy production. Carbonic acid is formed when carbon dioxide dissolves in
					water. Since carbon dioxide production is a byproduct of aerobic metabolism, it
					follows that very metabolically active cells will exhibit increased levels of
					carbon dioxide production. The chemical equation linking the increased carbon
					dioxide to a lowering of pH is CO<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O ↔
						H<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> ↔ H++HCO<sub>3</sub> which we will discuss
					later. </p>

				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_hemoglobin_oxygen_dis" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

				<p>Red bloods metabolize glucose in a variation of the standard glycolysis pathway.
					BPG is an intermediate compound made in red blood cells during glycolysis. When
					present in red blood cells, it attaches to the terminal amino acid groups of
					hemoglobin’s beta chains and decreases the affinity of hemoglobin for oxygen.
					BPG will increase in response to endocrine regulators including thyroxine,
					epinephrine, norepinephrine, and testosterone, and as part of the compensation
					that occurs at high altitudes and with some anemias.</p>


			</body>
		</section>

	</body>

</workbook_page>
