<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m3_levels_org_06">
	<head>
		<title>Transport of Carbon Dioxide </title>

		<objref idref="mechanisms_gas_transport_in_blood"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<!--  
		<p>With respect to carbon dioxide transport:</p>

		<ul style="none">
			<li>a.Describe the ways in which carbon dioxide is transported in blood and discuss the
				relative importance of each to total carbon dioxide transport. </li>
			<li>b.State the reversible chemical equation for the reaction of carbon dioxide and
				water to carbonic acid and then to hydrogen ion and bicarbonate ion. </li>

			<li>d.Explain how changing the partial pressure of carbon dioxide will affect the pH and
				the concentration bicarbonate ions in the plasma. </li>

			<li>f.State the reversible chemical equation for carbon dioxide binding to
				deoxyhemoglobin and predict how changing carbon dioxide concentrations will affect
				deoxyhemoglobin levels in the tissues and the lungs.</li>
			<li>g.Explain how each of the following relates to carbon dioxide transport: carbonic
				anhydrase, hydrogen ions binding to hemoglobin and plasma proteins, the chloride ion
				shift, and the oxygen- hemoglobin saturation level. </li>
		</ul>
		<p><em style="bold">END OF SUB OBJECTIVES</em></p>-->



		<section>
			<title>Forms of Carbon Dioxide</title>
			<body>

				<!-- 	<p> <em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Contrast how carbon dioxide is
						transported though blood when compared with oxygen</em></p> -->
				<p>Carbon dioxide is carried in the blood in three forms: dissolved, attached to
					hemoglobin, and converted to bicarbonate ions. Dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> accounts
					for 7–10 percent of the carbon dioxide carried in the blood. This is also the
					only form of carbon dioxide that diffuses from the tissues into the blood and
					from the blood into the alveoli for expulsion from the body. Here, we will
					examine in depth the transfer of carbon dioxide using hemoglobin or by the
					formation of bicarbonate.</p>

				<p><em style="bold">Carbaminohemoglobin and Bicarbonate</em></p>

				<!-- <p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Discuss the impact of carbon dioxide and
						carbonic acid on hemoglobin</em></p> -->
				<p>Carbon dioxide can bind to any protein and form a carbamate compound. The protein
					found in the highest concentration in red blood cells is hemoglobin, and 20–23
					percent of the CO<sub>2</sub> carried in the blood is bound to hemoglobin in the
					form of <term>carbaminohemoglobin</term>. In the capillaries of the systemic
					tissues, CO<sub>2</sub> molecules attach to the terminal amino acids of the
					alpha and beta chains of the hemoglobin molecule. Deoxygenated hemoglobin
					(hemoglobin with no or less than the maximal oxygen bound, abbreviated HHb),
					such as that found in metabolically active tissues, binds CO<sub>2</sub> easily.
					In the capillaries of the lungs, the elevated levels of oxygen found in alveoli
					force the carbon dioxide off the hemoglobin molecule and oxidize the protein,
					freeing up hydrogen ions. Although some carbon dioxide is transported as
					carbaminohemoglobin, the majority, about 70 percent, is dissolved in the blood
					as bicarbonate ions that arise from the reversible reactions discussed below. </p>
				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_carbon_dioxide_blood" purpose="didigetthis"/>

				<p>Carbon dioxide in the presence of water can be reversibly converted to carbonic
					acid. Carbonic acid is not very stable and readily dissociates into a hydrogen
					ion and a bicarbonate ion. In fact, this is why carbonated beverages are acidic.
					Carbon dioxide is added to the drink mixture under pressure and dissolves in the
					beverage. When the CO<sub>2</sub> has bubbled out of the beverage, it tastes
					flat because the acid is gone. The same thing happens in red blood cells, except
					that red blood cells contain an enzyme called <term>carbonic anhydrase</term>
					(CA), which is capable of facilitating one million reactions per second per
					enzyme molecule. Because of the enzyme, most of the CO<sub>2</sub> dissolved in
					the blood is quickly converted to carbonic acid which breaks down to form,
					hydrogen ions, and bicarbonate ions. </p>
				<p>The chemical reaction for this process is the following:</p>
				<p><formula>CO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup> (in the presence of CA) + H<sub>2</sub>O &#8646;
							H<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> &#8646; H++ HCO<sub>3</sub></formula>
				</p>
				<p>Where H<sub>2</sub>O is water, CA is carbonic anhydrase,
						H<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> is carbonic acid, H+ is a hydrogen ion, and
						HCO<sub>3</sub>- is a bicarbonate ion. The second part of the reaction,
					which produces the hydrogen and bicarbonate ions, does not have an enzyme, but
					depends on the dissociation of the weak acid. This series of reactions provides
					buffering for the blood.</p>

				<p>Carbon dioxide production occurs in many tissues, especially muscle. The carbon
					dioxide produced diffuses from the tissue of origin into a systemic capillary and
					dissolves in the plasma. A small amount of the carbon dioxide is transported
					this way. Most of the CO<sub>2</sub> that diffused into the plasma diffuses into
					a red blood cell and reacts with intracellular water molecules to produce
					hydrogen and bicarbonate ions. Remembering that the reactions are reversible, it
					makes sense that the direction of the reaction sequences will be driven by
					levels of accumulated products. The dissociation of carbonic acid is driven by
					the relative concentration of carbonic acid compared to the relative levels of
					bicarbonate(carbonic acid’s conjugate base). A build-up of bicarbonate in the
					RBCs would slow or halt the dissociation of carbonic acid. This build-up doesn’t
					usually happen because, RBCs have a membrane channel that allows bicarbonate to
					leave the RBC and enter the blood plasma. To maintain electric neutrality inside
					the RBC and in the plasma, every time a negative bicarbonate ion leaves the red
					blood cell it is exchanged for a negative chloride ion from the plasma. This
					exchange is called the <term>chloride shift</term>. The bicarbonate ion in the
					plasma becomes part of the blood’s buffering system, maintaining blood pH within
					a narrow range. Deviation from this range compromises organ function and can
					cause death. The hydrogen ion liberated from the conversion of CO<sub>2</sub> to
					bicarbonate binds to a a deoxygenated hemoglobin molecule causing it to become
					reduced. Deoxygenated hemoglobin easily picks up a molecule of CO<sub>2</sub>,
					creating carbaminohemoglobin. Hemoglobin is an important buffering agent for the
					hydrogen ions produced from the conversion of carbon dioxide to bicarbonate
					ions. If this buffering did not occur, the intracellular fluid of the red blood
					cell would become progressively more acidic, resulting in deterioration of cell
					functions. Some CO<sub>2</sub> from the tissues can be found as as bicarbonate
					ions and dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> in the plasma. The remainder of the carbon
					dioxide is attached to hemoglobin or it is still in the carbonic acid form and
					will stay in the red blood cells.</p>

				<!--  	<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_4.jpg" height="350" width="350" alt="graph of partial pressure for air,lungs, blood and tissues"/> -->

				<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_4.jpg" height="400" width="400"
					alt="graph of partial pressure for air,lungs, blood and tissues">
					<caption>Graph of partial pressure. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
						Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
							href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
							>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
				</image>

				<p>When the blood enters the pulmonary capillaries, gaseous carbon dioxide in the
					plasma diffuses into the alveoli. Some of the bicarbonate diffuses from the
					plasma into the red blood cells, and a chloride ion passes back into the plasma,
					reversing the chloride shift that occurred in the capillaries in the systemic tissues. The high partial
					pressure of oxygen in the alveoli causes the carbaminohemoglobin to dissociate
					into deoxyhemoglobin, a hydrogen ion, and a molecule of carbon dioxide. The
					released CO<sub>2</sub> is available for diffusion. The free hydrogen ion
					combines with a bicarbonate ion and reforms carbonic acid. The carbonic acid is
					converted back to carbon dioxide and water under the influence of carbonic
					anhydrase.</p>

			</body>
		</section>




	</body>
</workbook_page>
