<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u11_m3_levels_org_wrapup"><head><title>Respiratory Levels of Organization Review and Assessment</title></head><body><section id="dc032915d0ce47c7b4ab088ed3b90110"><title>Let’s Summarize</title><body><p id="f6c5b2ce65114309a0624363ebbc0027">The major function of the respiratory system is to obtain oxygen needed to convert nutrients to energy and to remove carbon dioxide that is a waste product of this reaction. In order to perform this function the respiratory system must have mechanisms for moving oxygen into the body from the atmosphere and a way to transport the oxygen to tissues throughout the entire body. The respiratory system must also transport carbon dioxide to the lungs to be expelled from the body. Additionally, the respiratory system plays a role in protecting the body from microorganisms and maintaining proper pH levels.</p><p id="d2c8d02009ab4556a6d5b09875875c05">The primary function of the respiratory system, the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide, occurs through several processes.</p><ul id="bac517aedebe4518bf9055b47cb8f47f"><li><p id="ac8b2fdd41d7b47709dba0df4eca8afe4">Ventilation-moves air in and out of the lungs.</p></li></ul><ul id="d1933dac172e47e2977b6af0ebc8a147"><li><p id="ab9bc0f669e0c4234892f13b83b54c1a5">External respiration exchanges oxygen and carbon dioxide between the air and the alveoli of the lungs.</p></li><li><p id="af220a16fc07d48c290eda41a3395a262">Internal respiration exchanges oxygen and carbon dioxide between the blood and tissues.</p></li><li><p id="ac39671cc352745b5b5e8aa1ab7daec1b">Cellular respiration uses oxygen to release energy from nutrients.</p></li><li><p id="afe6c4728363f4cc99f302f7d2a723a4a">To understand how the respiratory system functions, it is studied on the chemical, macromolecular, cellular, tissue, organ and organ system levels.</p></li><li><p id="aae30eb4353b340ecac8225555c564434">The role of partial pressure in the diffusion of gases in external and internal respiration </p><ul id="c88aff8fdad543e0bef9b248cbc58f24"><li><p id="af822d40c5b7343e2ae07f5dfa2bbc182">Henry’s law discuss the solubility of gasses in a liquid and helps explain why oxygen and carbon dioxide are transported differently</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="af748348087c14076916de2c0b98f8605">The macromolecule level related the structure of the macromolecules to its functions. </p><ul id="ed087b98275949128c5140bca49c9a8a"><li><p id="aa04bc805394f459ca70169afbb950183">Mucus- immunoglobulin for immune function, glycosylate proteins for hydration</p></li><li><p id="aef5aa7634eb1454e9d6f47f4887df3d7">Surfactant- phospholipids that disrupt the surface tension of water in the alveoli to prevent collapse.</p></li><li><p id="af9442b6cde6e41dd936d12fede94aad5">Hemoglobin- iron containing heme group to transport oxygen and carbon dioxide. </p><ul id="f9559a75d3444879a4a68394727f5bf1"><li><p id="aec03bb9b728a4ace9c3863262dc01cad">Transport of oxygen on hemoglobin- the benefit of a tight association and factors that will affect the affinity of hemoglobin for oxygen</p></li><li><p id="af982cb074d8f4a3ebcf938cb6d86c405">Transport of carbon dioxide as carbaminohemoglobin and bicarbonate as well as the role of carbonic anhydrase</p></li></ul></li></ul></li></ul><ul id="fc865641786e471c89f28433c7cb4f5c"><li><p id="ac6e94467593e46a1a0f8f83bb1f1d75b">There are several important cell types that are found in different locations of the respiratory system. </p><ul id="e70124dcfb464a49a3cc86593e8b34b3"><li><p id="aca17b436e6134d3e92aac12b49e69739">Epithelial cell types located in the respiratory tree include goblet cells that secrete mucus, ciliated cells that sweep mucus into the pharynx and basal cells which can regenerate and produce new layers of cells.</p></li><li><p id="ab3c21235956f493a816b474b4769143c">Macrophages located in the lungs will help to provide protection against pathogens.</p></li><li><p id="afcae16e1720f4ec6a08be4bab9ebafc2">Epithelial cells in the alveoli are divided into simple squamous Type I cells that allow for diffusion and also secrete angiotensin-converting enzyme and the cuboidal Type II cells that secrete surfactant.</p></li></ul></li></ul><p id="e4b2fb676d8445398496eddcf521182e">In order to understand how the respiratory system functions, it is important to understand how the different organizational levels function both independently and together. Different portions of the respiratory system contain different cell types that all work together to allow for the diffusion of oxygen and carbon dioxide while providing protection from pathogens.</p></body></section><section id="f2aeab45a3f2491aaeeb7131c32c5220"><title>Quiz</title><body><p id="a8feee0adfeb4524a89e23b925c95fa0">If you do not feel ready for the quiz, identify the objectives you need to review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of questions that will be in the quiz.</p><activity idref="respiratory_levels_org_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
