<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>

<assessment id="_u9_anemia-origin-DIGT">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
        <question id="u9_anemia-origin_1">
            <!--LO:identify_anemia_thalassemia_OBJ-->

              <body> Which type of anemia is not properly matched with its origin?</body>
            
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">Iron deficiency anemia:  Poor dietary intake of iron</choice>
                <choice value="B">Pernicious anemia:  Blood loss</choice>
                <choice value="C">Hemolytic anemia: Toxins or drugs</choice>
                <choice value="D">Sickle cell anemia:  Inherited disease most common among African Americans</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Iron deficiency anemia can be caused by poor dietary intake of iron or blood loss.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Pernicious anemia is the result of poor intestinal absorption of B12, not blood loss.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Hemolytic anemia can result from a genetic condition or from specific drugs and toxins.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Sickle cell anemia is a genetic condition that is most common in African Americans. 
                    </feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="u9_anemia-origin_2">
            <!--LO:identify_anemia_thalassemia_OBJ-->
     
            <body> Thalassemia is:</body>
            
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">The result of an iron deficiency in the diet.</choice>
                <choice value="B">A genetic disease that results in sickle shaped cells.</choice>
                <choice value="C">A genetic disease that affects the alpha or beta globin proteins.</choice>
                <choice value="D">A genetic disease that affects the heme portion of hemoglobulin</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect.  A dietary iron deficiency would result in Iron deficiency anemia.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect.  A genetic disease that causes sickling of the cells is Sickle Cell Anemia.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct.  This is a genetic disease where there is a mutation in either the alpha or beta globulin proteins.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect.  It is a genetic disease but it is not a mutation of the heme group.  It is a mutation in the alpha or beta globulin. 
                    </feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
