<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="ADP-ATP exchange" movieroot="">
    <step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_ADP-ATP/ADP-ATP.swf" menustep="Structure">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The mitochondrial ADP/ATP translocase (AAT) catalyses the exchange, across the inner membrane of the organelle, of cytosolic ADP for ATP, produced in the matrix by ATP-synthase. The AAT undergoes substantial conformational changes during transport. Down here diffrent models of the AAT  structure from diffrent views.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_ADP-ATP/mitochondria-intro.swf" menustep="ADP-ATP exchange">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; Proteins of the mitochondrial carrier family are embedded in this membrane, and each member of the family achieves the selective transport of a specific metabolite. Among these, the ADP/ATP carrier transports ADP into the mitochondrial matrix and exports ATP toward the cytosol after its synthesis. &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_ADP-ATP/mitochondria.swf" menustep="    mitrochondria">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The ADP/ATP carrier is imbedded in the inner membrane of the mitochondria where it transports ATP from the matrix to the inner membrane space while simultaneously transporting ADP from the inner membrane space to the matrix. Thus the protein is providing an exchange function.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_ADP-ATP/mitochondria-phase1.swf" menustep="    phase 1">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The dimer structure of the ADP/ATP carrier presents the structure of the molecule that accepts ADP into the closed cup conformation of the protein while the dimer pair in the open conformation binds ATP. Following binding each member of the dimer pair undergoes a conformational change that the releases the bound molecule on the opposite side of the membrane.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_ADP-ATP/mitochondria-phase2.swf" menustep="    phase 2">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; Having completed the first exchange reaction, the opposite member of the dimer pair is ready to undertake the transfer reaction. Again the cup structure binds the ADP while the open structure binds ATP. Conformational change then releases the ADP to the matrix and ATP to the inner membrane space.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
</TUTORIAL>
