<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Biological Membranes" movieroot="">
    <step stepURL="swfs/biological.swf" menustep=" Biological Membranes">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Biological membranes are dynamic structures composed of a diverse set of phospholipid molecules and proteins. In the case of eukaryotic organisms, they also contain the steroid cholesterol.
The phospholipid component of the biological membrane is responsibile for the key property of membranes, they act as an impermeable barrier towards most molecules. Molecules can only cross the membrane with the aid of proteins within the membrane.  
Therefore, membranes define the boundary of  cells as well intra-cellular organelles. &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mic.swf"  menustep=" Micelle Formation">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;When fatty acids or phospholipids are added to water they self-assemble into aggregates such that the charged or polar heads groups make contact with the water and the hydrophobic hydrocarbon tails are restricted to water-free areas. In the case of fatty acids and other detergent like molecules, they will orient at an air-water interface such that the non-polar tails project into the air. In addition, some fatty acids will enter the water and spontaneously form single shelled structures called micelles.
        &lt;br&gt;When you are ready to continue click the  "&lt;b&gt;Forward&lt;/b&gt;" button.
        When fatty acids or phospholipids are added to water they self-assemple into aggregates such that the charged
        or polar heads groups make contact with the water and the hydrophobic hydrocarbon tails are restricted to water-free areas. In the case of fatty acids and other detergent like molecules, they will orient at an air-ater interface such that the non-polar tails project into the air. In addition, some fatty acids will enter the water and spontaneously form single shelled structures called micelles.
        &lt;br&gt;When you are ready to continue click the  "&lt;b&gt;Forward&lt;/b&gt;" button.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/bilayerpho.swf"  menustep=" Bilayer Formation">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; When phospholipids are added to water, they will also orient at the air-water interface in the same way as fatty acids, with the polar/charged head groups in contact with the water and the non-polar acyl chains in the air.  An additional layer of phospholipids can be added to make a stable phospholipid bilayer with water on both sides of membrane.
        &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>   
   </step>
<step stepURL="swfs/bilayer.swf" menustep=" Bilayer Permeability">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; This diagram shows a lipid bilayer that is formed from two layers of phospholipids molecules. 
        The polar head-groups of the phospholipids are oriented towards of the aqueous solvent while the long non-polar hydrocarbon, or acil, chains are sequestred in the interior of the membrane. 
        Note that:
        i) The membrane is flexible and dynamic.
        ii) Water molecules, which are polar but uncharged, rarely cross the membrane. 
        iii) Ions, such as Na+, never cross the membrane. 
        &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>  
</step>
<step stepURL="swfs/mobility.swf"  menustep=" Bilayer Mobility">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; The proteins can move around the surface of the bilayer.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/asymetry.swf"  menustep=" Bilayer Asymetry">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; Describe Assymetry.&lt;/html&gt;</text> 
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/molecules.swf"  menustep=" Phospholypid Structure">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;    &lt;/html&gt;</text>
</step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/proteins.swf" menustep=" Membranes Proteins">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;    &lt;/html&gt;</text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/carrier.swf" textURL="text_carrier.swf" menustep="    Carrier Proteins">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;There are three main types of proteins that shuttle molecules across the membrane:
        &lt;b&gt;Uniport:&lt;/b&gt; transport a single molecule across the membrane.
        &lt;b&gt;Symport:&lt;/b&gt; transport two different molecules in the same direction.
        &lt;b&gt;Antiport:&lt;/b&gt; transport two different molecules in opposite directions.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/transporter.swf" menustep="    Sodium-Potassium Transporter">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;This is an example of an antiport transporter,  that uses the energy of ATP to transport 3 Na+ ions outside of the cell in exchange for the influx of 2 K+ ions into the cell.  The main features of the cycle are:
            1. Binding of 3 Na+ ions
            2. Phosphorylation of a carboxylic group by ATP,  this causes an allosteric change in the enzyme, allowing the Na+ to cross.
            3.  Two K+ bind to the external face of the transporter.
            4.  Dephosphorylation of the enzyme causes another allosteric change, bringing the K+ into the cell.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/extransporters.swf" menustep="    Other examples of Transporter">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Description needed&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
</step>
</TUTORIAL>