<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Phase Transition" movieroot="">
    
<step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_membnew/phasetransition.swf"  menustep="Phase Transition">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Phospholipids bilayers undergo a cooperative phase transition or melting that is similar to protein denaturation. The high degree of cooperativity is due to extensive interactions between the non-polar acyl chains in the center of the bilayer. The overall structure of the lipid bilayer is not changed by this transition. However, the disorder of the non-polar hydrocarbon chains increases dramatically after melting.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
<step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_membnew/saturated.swf"  menustep="  Saturated">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;At low temperatures the saturated acyl chains are able to pack close to each other as extended chains. This is very stable configuration because of the favorable van der Waals interactions between the chains. This causes the membrane to be solid-like below the melting temperature. As the temperature rises, clusters of phospholipids melt, followed by melting of the entire bilayer. At temperatures above the melting temperature the acyl-chains are disorder or fluid. 

The following shows the melting of a pure phosphatidylcholine membrane with myristic fatty acids (C14). &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
<step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_membnew/unsaturated.swf"  menustep="  Unsaturated">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;In an unsaturated bilayer the acyil chains have cis-double bonds that cause a sharp bend in the acyl chain. This impairs the packing of the acyl chains, reducing the van der Waals force between the chains. 

Consequently, the melting temperature of unsaturated bilayers is lower than that of a saturated bilayer. In addition, the transition occurs over a broader temperature range.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
<step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_membnew/cholsat.swf"  menustep="  Cholesterol + Saturated">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Cholesterol makes the lipid bilayer more fluid-like over a broad temperature range. 

Below the melting tempraure cholesterol disrupts the ability of the acyl chains to pack.
       
During the melting process cholesterol reduces the cooperativity of the melting, causing the transition to occur over  a very broad temperature range.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
<step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs_membnew/37.swf"  menustep="  37 Celsius">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;This chart demonstrates the relationships of the varius lipid bilayer components at 37° Celsius&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    
 </TUTORIAL>
