<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u0_m0_metacog_2_1"><head><title>Identifying Prior Knowledge and Misconceptions</title><objref idref="meta" /></head><body><p id="fac2f1e68c20485f90aa44ec0e57f332">It is crucial to remember, in this and in other courses, that it can be very useful to evaluate your existing knowledge base for misconceptions. When you examine things you think you know, whether they are inaccurate or not, you can better-identify gaps and inconsistencies in your knowledge. Once you successfully identify those gaps and inconsistencies, you can plan and apply methods to remedy any misconceptions you identified. Of course, if those inaccuracies persist, they can be harmful to your understanding of a concept. </p><p id="db0b1a57cf0049cc962da453ae8487af">Everyone will have some misconceptions and some useful pre-existing knowledge. As you work through the various learning activities within each module, it is important to remember they are primarily guiding your learning, not just scoring your performance. If you don’t know an answer, a hint may be all you need or it may help you realize you need to review the content again. The immediate feedback not only lets you know if you got an answer incorrect, but is intended to encourage your further exploration of the topic and review of the learning objective as you progress through the tasks. </p><p id="bb50a5d173c94ff98d77bd5a68c8502a">In this course, you will frequently be presented with “Fact / Myth Exploration” activities that help you assess your prior knowledge and potential misconceptions. In these activities, you will be presented with common conceptions and misconceptions about the human body, and provide you with opportunities to explore these ideas.</p><wb:inline idref="u0_factmyth_digt" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="f940548af1e243a2a7912ba0847fb1e8">Even when such an activity is not present, you can try to identify your own misconceptions. Whenever you pick an incorrect answer, ask yourself why. Sometimes it may be you didn’t know the information, but other times it may be that you have preconceptions that influenced the way you interpreted new information you are learning. Even if you get an answer correct, you can also check the hints and feedback for the other incorrect answers to make sure you really understand why it is incorrect and don’t have any related misconceptions. </p></body></workbook_page>
