<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u0_m0_metacog_1">
    <head>
        <title>How to Succeed in CC-OLI A&amp;P</title>
        <objref idref="meta"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p id="e65f7e007d1b4b89a2a4717ced6f82dc">A primary goal of the Open Learning Initiative is
            not only to teach the content within the disciplines of our courses, but also, through
            the manner in which these courses are presented, to support better learning. This course
            incorporates some of the foremost scientific research on learning, and attempts to guide
            you through the material in a thoughtful fashion, incorporating data gathered by the
            Open Learning Initiative from students just like you, learning this subject. Data from
            your own learning process and feedback will help us continue to make adjustments and
            improvements. This data provides insight into the structure of knowledge and knowledge
            construction, the role of activities and feedback in courses, and techniques for
            accelerating student learning and improving learning gains. </p>
        <section id="b8f31ec1ae0d456c947226831f9bc3a9">
            <title>Overall Course Structure</title>
            <body>
                <p id="fb8a4bc8b45044ad9f960e974fba3f0f">OLI Anatomy and Physiology is not your
                    typical course. Whether you are working through the course independently or
                    using it as a resource in a face-to-face or asynchronous course, our goal is for
                    you to work through the course materials online in the way that is most
                    efficient given your prior knowledge. </p>
                <p id="f2f574d1e7b04b2886ec3dc123201f29">While you may have more flexibility than
                    you do in a traditional course, you will also have more responsibility for your
                    own learning. You will need to: </p>
                <ul id="cfca68dcab8c4913aeb0ebcb58f97617">
                    <li><p id="ab44abd30b03c4793a5f71419e4aeecf8">Plan how to work through each
                            unit. </p></li>
                    <li><p id="abcf833d5e2b845b9963059089865d119">Determine how to use the various
                            features of the course to help you learn.</p></li>
                    <li><p id="aff96b81483894a7c92feda5b99c894b1">Decide when you need to seek
                            additional support.</p></li>
                </ul>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section id="bc992d005083420eb8612627a99394bb">
            <title>Completing This Course Efficiently and Effectively</title>
            <body>
                <p id="e795c8be6b134c0fa626777345c633e7">When starting an online course, most people
                    neglect planning, opting instead to jump in and begin working. While this might
                    seem efficient (after all, who wants to spend time planning when they could be
                    doing?), it can ultimately be inefficient. In fact, one of the characteristics
                    that distinguishes experts from novices is that experts spend far more time
                    planning their approach to a task and less time actually completing it; while
                    novices do the reverse - rushing through the planning stage and spending far
                    more time overall.</p>
                <p id="e3582b4eb51e4fa48c83a13ddbf74d68">In this course, we want to help you work as
                    efficiently and effectively as possible, given what you already know. Some of
                    you have already taken a course in this domain, and might already be familiar
                    with some of the terminology and concepts. Depending on how this course is being
                    used within a curriculum, you may not need to work through all of the activities
                    in the course; just enough to make sure that you&apos;ve &quot;got it.&quot; For
                    others, if this is your first exposure to the anatomy and physiology, you will
                    want to do more of the activities, since you are learning these concepts for the
                    first time. It may feel as if you are learning a new language, and in some ways
                    you are. You might start off feeling that you have to memorize a lot of new
                    structures and terms for anatomy. But as with any new language, over time and
                    with practice you will begin to understand the meanings of words and can focus
                    on their context rather than a single definition. There will be some specific
                    activities and useful study tools that can help you become comfortable
                    communicating and thinking in this language. As you master the language, you
                    will be better able to apply that understanding to the complex physiological
                    processes. This synthesis and integration of your growing knowledge base will be
                    presented in other activities and require use of other kinds of organizational
                    study tools. </p>
                <p id="f3f664fea8b144188e29751b971403e6">Improving your planning skills as you work
                    through the material in the course will help you to become a more strategic and
                    thoughtful learner and will enable you to more effectively plan your approach to
                    assignments, exams and projects in other courses.</p>
                <p id="e41641a6b26748d19cd8bebf99a80ac2">Research has shown that students who invest
                    in metacognitive activities improve their own learning. For this reason, the OLI
                    courses are designed with metacognition as a guide. In this module, you will be
                    introduced to the metacognitive cycle. </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section id="f235400e0e5640b9bd6eaa13084ac6bb">
            <title>Metacognition</title>
            <body>
                <p id="b2671483d6284c48b7a3adcae2bf9902">This idea of planning your approach to the
                    course before you start is called Metacognition. </p>
                <definition id="c7bac2d1660e43f59dba448c8286e5ff">
                    <term>Metacognition</term>
                    <meaning id="d3b43d3cf17942b59208b8469fe29fe6">
                        <material>
                            <p id="ba43e144a05d42d6b7dec76af9fc5f00">Metacognition, or “thinking
                                about thinking,” refers to your awareness of yourself as a learner
                                and your ability to regulate your own learning.</p>
                        </material>
                    </meaning>
                </definition>
                <p id="e7e9be35b1424b7288cd2afa10117320">Metacognition involves five distinct
                    skills:</p>
                <ol id="c214091b7598486ead42462f525a202b">
                    <li><p id="a5dc10824d824b38b44c822edc2be51a"><term>Assess</term> the task—Get a
                            handle on what is involved in completing a task (the steps or components
                            required for success) and any constraints (time, resources).</p></li>
                    <li><p id="dd4a3475e78a481ba33b5ece2e85aa0e"><term>Evaluate</term> your
                            strengths and weaknesses—Evaluate your own skills and knowledge in
                            relation to a task. </p></li>
                    <li><p id="d92ab05051594ebb84eb757459d26dd8"><term>Plan</term> an approach—Take
                            into account your assessment of the task and your evaluation of your own
                            strengths and weaknesses in order to devise an appropriate
                        plan.</p></li>
                    <li><p id="fed56a291a2c419c8aa0ac2fb6fecb14"><term>Apply</term> strategies and
                            monitor your performance—Continually monitor your progress as you are
                            working on a task, comparing where you are to the goal you want to
                            achieve.</p></li>
                    <li><p id="cf3e9e15d19c4c29a02dedd1d17ffcaf"><term>Reflect</term> and adjust if
                            needed—Look back on what worked and what didn&apos;t work so that you
                            can adjust your approach next time and, if needed, start the cycle
                            again.</p></li>
                </ol>
                <p id="e33ebe5cc97f453eb5dce4bc405690ff">These five skills are applied over and over
                    again in a cycle—within the same course as well as from one course to another.
                    Mouseover each skill in the picture below for a more explicit definition.</p>
                <iframe src="../webcontent/zipped-meta/oli-metacognitive.html" height="600" width="875" id="_i_3a"/>
                <p id="ca2879a2af9e4456afe6cccd8db8bb48">The following sections give you experience
                    in working through the metacognitive cycle as it applies to this anatomy and
                    physiology CC-OLI course. </p>
                <p id="f4c8196a7d404c498df28918c5d77bd3">You will learn how to:</p>
                <ol id="ba0d212323294f44af9293172c670d44">
                    <li><p id="ab2aa928a289d4d6aaa2f52e75e83a5c6">Use the Learning Objectives to
                            guide your focus as you move through explanatory content (text, images,
                            audio and animations) and complete the various activities and
                            assessments</p></li>
                    <li><p id="af82cf2373efe4802ba772f56b072bdf6">Evaluate existing knowledge and
                            possible misconceptions in regard to the learning objectives</p></li>
                    <li><p id="af1e3f1b1b03946e3a96c385d83c39557">Complete activities and
                            assessments successfully to indicate mastery of the objective</p></li>
                    <li><p id="af20cb79e71e0499ab67d5dfa66c722b9">Evaluate performance on activities
                            and assessments to monitor your achievement of the objective</p></li>
                    <li><p id="ac57bab750d1a4d6c82ec7c0950b64d70">Revise your study methods to
                            improve your performance on activities and assessments so that you
                            achieve the learning objective and thus meet the success criteria
                        </p></li>
                </ol>
                <p id="ad3348d785ed4c0a864818401e26265a">Engaging in the full cycle of metacognitive
                    processes as you move through this course will improve your understanding and
                    retention of the material.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
    <bib:file/>
</workbook_page>
