<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u0_m0_metacog_3"><head><title>Planning Your Approach</title><objref idref="meta" /></head><body><p id="a066d0d1751249568bcabbeeeadc791b">Once you take into account your assessment of the task and your evaluation of your own strengths and weaknesses, it is time to devise an appropriate plan. Planning your approach is an important step in your learning process, for reasons that research supports. In the book, How Learning Works, cognitive scientists discuss important differences between how novices and experts go about approaching a problem to solve (Ambrose, et. al., 2008). Experts spent significantly more time planning their approach to a problem before diving-in and solving it, which they did so much more quickly and accurately. Novices usually went straight to applying various solutions, fumbled around much longer, and usually not even getting to a correct solution. So, “...even though planning one’s approach to a task can increase the chances of success, students tend not to recognize the need for it.” (Ambrose et al., 2008, 380). For this reason, we will now help you explore a few strategies for moving through CC-OLI A&amp;P in an effective and successful fashion.</p><p id="d8e85b2648294d32b94177436fac6a68">The ideal way to achieve a given task is different for different individuals. Depending on your prior knowledge and skills, you may prefer to use tables to study, or images, or examples, or all of the above. </p><section id="c3ef8fdb919c4dd0a30c89a0914d0076"><title>Course Components</title><body><p id="ccf2cd9554594c9f877593fd154e8f0c">This course provides a number of components that are meant to help you through the material. By knowing what these components are and what they are designed to do, you can appropriately plan a course of action when you encounter a concept you are having difficulty understanding. </p><p id="bf84a6a2675d4d29b8e126c8cb6cc51a">One important part of learning is getting feedback. Getting a score on a quiz tells you if you mastered the material, but it is usually too late to make changes. In contrast, Learn By Doing and Did I Get This activities present formative feedback, which provides opportunities to “try out” your growing knowledge and get immediate feedback along the way. Because this is a valuable part of a metacognitive cycle, the two major question-type activities in this course provide just this sort of sequential feedback. Both are found throughout the course content, often after a major concept has been presented using text and other components. If you are already familiar with the topic, you can skim the text, but should be sure to complete all the activities. The Learn by Doing include hints as well as feedback for both correct and incorrect answers. Reading the hints and feedback for the incorrect answers, even if you did select the correct answer, will often provide information to help you better understand why the correct answer was correct or help you identify common misconceptions about the question. The Did I Get This activities also have feedback for correct and incorrect answers, but are designed more for self-assessment to be sure you are able to apply what you have been learning. </p><wb:inline idref="_u0_lbdtype_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="fc9a6ecd6e4d4c598f642e4b17535144">In addition to practicing and building understanding through active participation, our courses also include self-assessments. As mentioned above, you will encounter Did I Get This? activities which will ask questions to see if you have understood a specific concept. These, in addition to the end-of-module quizzes, generally appear after a concept has been explained and practiced in other activities. These are great additional practice and help you evaluate your knowledge and understanding gains. Each DIGT also gives you a chance to apply the metacognitive cycle by evaluating your learning progress and identifying what you can do next. </p><wb:inline idref="_u1_digttype_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><p id="eddcca9500564af4b76a978b0b9c70e5">Besides activities, a usual content page in this course contains expository text and other exploratory content - the information you are learning to be able to meet the course learning objectives and success criteria. There are several things you will encounter within the exploratory content that will help you to organize the material on a page, visually, and to help guide your learning. By knowing what these things are and how they can help, you will be able to strategize their uses effectively.</p><p id="ecfd087ae14b4018a08d78852fc8bdb7"><em style="italic">Explanatory Content</em>: This is the content of a page, including introduction of the basic structures learned in each chapter. It consists of short passages of text with information, examples, images, videos, and explanations. Sometimes the expository text is organized for you into tables - you can click on these tables to open them in a separate pop-up window, which can help when you are practicing in the activities. </p><p id="d7be96a16b1040c9aa42bf346f977c8d"><em style="italic">Vocabulary/Terms</em>: There are many important vocabulary terms introduced and used throughout the course, and they are presented in a variety of ways. If you mouse over some terms, an audio pronunciation is provided; for others, definitions in context will pop up if you hover over the word. Sometimes definitions of higher-level concepts are pointed-out in a specific way on the page; most important vocabulary words are highlighted in some way at least upon their first introduction and then again if used in another context. All of these ways are presented to help you gain familiarity with the language of anatomy and physiology. </p><p id="a73d0c55027b421982f5e12898968904"><em style="italic">Examples</em>: When a specific condition or event illustrates a concept in context, it will be noted as such. Detailed and in-depth examples provide opportunities to increase your knowledge about that particular topic, process, concept or even structure(s). </p><p id="fb25e961f4f543c1abea6edff7f91f72"><em style="italic">Images</em>: Images are critical in this course. Many times there is more detailed information in the images than even in the expository text. Like tables, images can be selected with a mouse-click to open them in a separate pop-up window, that gives you a larger view for closer study. </p><p id="ff8aedcb3baf4343b78e49c710f29e49"><em style="italic">Walkthrough Videos</em>: Videos are a great way to visually explore concepts, whether by walking you through a series of steps in a process and/or providing examples in different contexts. However, video is not always a complete replacement for expository text. It is important to recognize when popular media and online sources oversimplify complex information, so that misunderstandings are not generated. </p></body></section><section id="b7a5a222430b41d6b434fa6e93a57c47"><title>Strategies for Learning</title><body><p id="a07881ab1b4640aa9cc62479df7ad189">Along with strategizing specifically how you will apply the metacognitive cycle in your use of the various activities and course components, there are other useful strategies to employ toward your overall success in mastering the topic of anatomy and physiology: </p><ul id="e4d97963a1314818806a8ee09a7e22b5"><li><p id="bd0f17e7130e4c97acfeb5b58a74b8c4">Plan to complete all activities.</p><p id="dec9f322b45a49cabad87b4827092215">More practice is always a good strategy toward uncovering misconceptions, and remembering and understanding the material to be learned - we have filled the course with a variety of fun, exploratory activities so as to provide you with multiple opportunities to practice learning the material in different ways.</p></li><li><p id="adda3929d11d4d6ca64743748851d755">Analyze each task.</p><p id="c73ed06a40bb475fa58c29a9374a17d3">When presented with an activity or assessment in the course, it helps for you to be able to describe the cognitive level of the task, as well as describe the steps you can take to tackle it. Also recognize that different strategies are better for certain tasks. For example, eliminating possible answer choices first is a good strategy to employ when answering a multiple choice question. </p></li><li><p id="acd02158403d4169b81a5a33d5e01570">Use the Big Ideas, Vital Functions, and Themes provided in this course as ways to organize your expanding knowledge. </p><p id="e5959eb115e84553b4ce6db8e5b1c9fc">“Experts&apos; knowledge is not simply a list of facts and formulas that are relevant to their domain; instead, their knowledge is organized around core concepts or “big ideas” that guide their thinking about their domains.”</p></li><li><p id="ab6e986c71b954936a1025ef97f2f20fd">Make your own graphic representations (e.g. concept maps, flow charts, semantic webs) of the knowledge you acquire. </p></li><li><p id="ba13bb020dee4fe99ff5b35ec7e5a87b">Frequently self-question and think aloud. </p><p id="f0cc89c2312b4f47842c7a2cfeda3238">You should ask yourself regularly what you might already know about a topic you encounter in the course. Think about ways you might have dealt with that information before, or how you solved a similar problem. </p></li><li><p id="a89e05290c2a40dc9aac7d9b13bfc6e2">Employ mnemonics.</p><p id="cc603e8ad2f249cbadbaff07889b8300">Mnemonics are frequently employed in settings where a large amount of material and vocabulary needs to be memorized and recalled, such as in the medical professions. Your instructor will most likely give you many established mnemonics, such as learning to remember “spare TIRE” for abdominal muscles: Transverse abdominus, internal oblique, rectus abdominus, external oblique. Creating your own where necessary is also a great strategy.</p></li><li><p id="abdeef44cbce4472baefb6518ae538ad3">Summarize and explain concepts in your own words to someone else. You can start to use this strategy by rephrasing objectives, and then continue with any concepts presented on the pages of this course. By performing this practice, you are rehearsing many of the steps in the metacognitive process all at once. </p></li></ul></body></section></body></workbook_page>
