<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u0_m0_metacog_4"><head><title>Doing the Work and Monitoring Performance</title><objref idref="meta" /></head><body><p id="e43d828195ea4daa92573224347292ba">After assessing the task at hand, evaluating your strengths and weakness, and applying the selected strategies in a mindful way to hopefully increase your learning and retention, the next thing to do is to monitor your performance so that you know if the strategies are working and that you are increasing your learning. While practice and multiple learning modes are important, just studying longer will not ensure you are learning the material. You have to find a way to test yourself so you know what you have mastered and what you still need to work on more. Try using some of the same learning strategies, but this time do it without your notes. </p><example id="c73b6df0e96e4537b338d8c825b50ae6"><title>Learning Strategy </title><p id="b766d605b88c4cb29659526fd63ce918">Make a graphic organizer or table of information from memory and you will quickly see which parts you haven’t learned just yet. Then go back to your notes to check your answers for correctness and completeness, and try new strategies to learn the parts you couldn’t complete by memory. If using flash cards, separate them into two piles as you review: ones you got correct and ones you didn’t. Put the ones you got correct away for a day or two, then see if you can still get them correct when you put them back into the mix with the other cards you continued to study.</p></example><p id="cbf3d3892a99490982a697fc8c60b5b6">An important feature of this course is that the majority of activities within the course content are meant to be a safe place for practicing the concepts you are just learning. You may keep trying them until you answer correctly, and they do not report a grade to the gradebook. As you work carefully through the activities, take advantage of all hints and feedback. Also, see if you can use the hints to write different questions to make each of the incorrect answers now the correct choice. If you have a study group, ask these in your meetings or trade questions with another student. Go back and review the Learn by Doing and Did I Get This questions several days after you have completed that module and moved on to the next module. This will help check your retention and you may discover new linkages to the things you have learned since you first did that earlier module. </p><p id="db786cbe8c1d4527873c16330b252597">The learning dashboard link below each activity will present the following information: </p><image id="c221a37821a145fbbd52cb783d66b54b" src="../webcontent/learningdashboard.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="510" width="700"><caption><p id="acfe7879ee1fd48e3a58b833b5226ab40">Caption: student view of learning dashboard, which 1) includes a count of students in your class who have worked on the activity, 2) presents the average score on the activity, and 3) shows the actual activity with the correct answer and the distribution of student responses, indicated.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f4c11b520e8c489aa3fe68ec01ddafcd">This will let you know how your classmates have performed on this question, and examine the misconceptions of yourself and others.</p><p id="b5546b3e8f354df9a6731bbf1b95de3c">Another tool provided in this course that allows you to monitor your progress is the student gradebook. As you see below, the percentage of activities you have completed for each of the modules is indicated with a bar graph -- here, the gray indicates that Module 17 does not have any inlines. As you can see, the Unit assessment and feedback are given their own columns in the gradebook; in fact, these titles are links that can be followed to complete the activities. </p><image id="e6d617634db8420b9473366ed14f5b3e" src="../webcontent/student_gradebook.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ab00f6faf3358483bb858ec08ade196f5">The student view of the OLI gradebook, with progress indicated on inline activities in blue and gray indicating modules without any inlines. </p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a303a10c071e49fab827421238489c25">In the online course, you can access the “Quizzes” through the links on the syllabus page, at the end of each module, or in the gradebook. When you click on a link to the quiz, it will open in a new window, so as you take the quiz, you can also go back within the course to review some information. </p></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
