<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u0_m01_metacog_00"><head><title>Community College-Open Learning Initiative (CC-OLI) Project</title></head><body><p id="a29e74f2f41d4435be667341eaac4f85">Built with funding provided by the <link href="http://www.gatesfoundation.org" target="new" internal="false">Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation</link>, The <link href="http://www.hewlett.org/" target="new" internal="false">William and Flora Hewlett Foundation</link>, and the <link href="http://www.luminafoundation.org/" target="new" internal="false">Lumina Foundation</link>, the <link href="http://oli.cmu.edu/get-to-know-oli/get-involved/current-collaborators-partners/" target="new" internal="false">CC-OLI project</link> brought together teams of community college faculty content experts, learning scientists, human-computer interaction experts, and software engineers to make best use of multidisciplinary knowledge for designing effective learning environments. We also partnered with <link href="http://www.wordsandnumbers.com/" target="new" internal="false">Words &amp; Numbers</link>, through <link href="http://cnx.org/" target="new" internal="false">Connexions<sup>®</sup></link> for some of the content for this course. </p><p id="ed81feb86ac946ee9e7cf42ef3eb6555">The course is centered on the learning outcomes developed by the Human Anatomy &amp; Physiology Society (HAPS) Curriculum and Instruction Committee, and can be used independently by students or by faculty as a course supplement. The project attempts to meet the needs at the learner, instructor, and institutional levels by providing the student with individualized learning support, the faculty with customized teaching support, and the community college with assessment support.</p><p id="bce3b9cad945442ea0b2381fdca77d98">Aside from providing continuous practice opportunities to the students, the assessments and activities throughout the course are used to collect real-time, interaction-level data about how and what students are learning and use this data to drive positive feedback loops to students, instructors, course design teams, institutions, and learning science researchers.</p></body></workbook_page>
