<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_factmyth_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>All bones are completely formed by age 21.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u5_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The xiphoid process of your sternum doesn’t completely form until your 40s.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The xiphoid process of your sternum doesn’t completely form until your 40s.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>There really is a bone known as your “funny bone”</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u5_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There is a bone in your arm called a humerus (not humerous). The sensation of hitting your “funny bone” occurs when you hit your ulnar nerve, which is close to the skin near your elbow.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. There is a bone in your arm called a humerus (not humerous). The sensation of hitting your “funny bone” occurs when you hit your ulnar nerve, which is close to the skin near your elbow.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Only older people get osteoporosis.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="_u5_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteoporosis is a disease which results in weak, porous bones. This disease can strike at any age, especially in women if their estrogen levels decrease. Estrogen is a lipid hormone and if a female’s body fat drops too low this can result in less estrogen and weaker bones.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osteoporosis is a disease which results in weak, porous bones. This disease can strike at any age, especially in women if their estrogen levels decrease. Estrogen is a lipid hormone and if a female’s body fat drops too low this can result in less estrogen and weaker bones.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body>Bones tissue is stagnant and not very active.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="_u5_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Bone tissue is constantly being remodeled. Bone is broken down and resynthesized. Approximately 20% of a young adult’s skeleton is completely remodeled every year.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Bone tissue is constantly being remodeled. Bone is broken down and resynthesized. Approximately 20% of a young adult’s skeleton is completely remodeled every year.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q5"><body>There are bones in the human body that are floating bones and not attached to any other bones.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="_u5_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hyoid bone is in the neck and is not attached to any other bones. It is attached to the larynx via ligaments.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The hyoid bone is in the neck and is not attached to any other bones. It is attached to the larynx via ligaments.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q6"><body>A baby has more bones than an adult.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q6_p1"><skillref idref="_u5_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. When a baby is born, many bones are still cartilage and have not fused together. A baby is born with approximately 305 bones while an adult has 206.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. When a baby is born, many bones are still cartilage and have not fused together. A baby is born with approximately 305 bones while an adult has 206.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
