<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u3_m01_sampling1">
<head>
<title>Sampling (1 of 2)</title>
    <objref idref="identify_sampling_method"/>
    <objref idref="evaluate_reliability_of_results"/>
</head>
<body>
  
    <p>As mentioned in the introduction to this section, we will begin with the first stage of data
            production<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133540-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133537-0400" content=" - "?>sampling.
            Our discussion will be framed around the following examples:</p>
<example><title>#1</title>

<p>Suppose you want to determine the musical preferences of all students at your university, based on a sample of students. Here are some examples of the many possible ways to pursue this problem.</p>
<p>
                 Post a music-lovers' survey on a university
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133649-0400"?>I<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133648-0400" content="i"?>Internet
                bulletin board, asking students to vote for their favorite type of music.</p>
<p>This is an example of a <em>volunteer sample</em>, where individuals have selected themselves to
                be included. Such a sample is almost guaranteed to be <em>biased</em>. In general,
                volunteer samples tend to be comprised of individuals who have a particularly strong
                opinion about an issue<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133746-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133747-0400" content="("?>and are
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133814-0400"?>looking<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133811-0400" content="just waiting"?>
                for an opportunity to voice
                it<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133753-0400" content="....)"?>.
                Whether the variable's values obtained from such a sample are over- or under-stated,
                and to what extent, cannot be determined. As a result, data obtained from a
                voluntary response sample is quite useless when you think about the "Big
                Picture<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T133853-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>"
                since the sampled individuals only provide information about themselves, and we
                    <em>cannot generalize to any larger group at all. </em>
</p>
</example>
                
                <pullout type="note">
<p>
<em>Comment</em>: It should be mentioned that in some cases volunteer samples are the only ethical way to obtain a sample.  In medical studies, for example, in which new treatments are tested, subjects must choose to participate by signing a consent form that highlights the potential risks and benefits.  As we will discuss in the next module, a volunteer sample is not so problematic in a study conducted for the purpose of comparing several treatments.</p>
                               </pullout>

 <example><title>#2</title>
<p> Stand outside the Student Union, across from the Fine Arts Building, and ask students passing by to respond to your question about musical preference.</p>
<p>This is an example of a <em>convenience sample</em>, where individuals happen to be at the right
                time and place to suit the schedule of the researcher. Depending on what variable is
                being studied, it may be that a convenience sample provides a fairly representative
                group. However, there are often subtle reasons why the sample's results are
                    <em>biased</em>. In this case, the proximity to the Fine Arts Building might
                result in a disproportionate number of students favoring classical music. A
                convenience sample may
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T134144-0400"?>also
                <?oxy_insert_end?>be susceptible to bias because certain types of individuals are
                more likely to be selected than others. In the extreme, some convenience samples are
                designed in such a way that certain individuals have no chance at all of being
                selected, as in the next example.</p></example>
                
 <example><title>#3</title>
<p>
 Ask your professors for email rosters of all the students in your classes. Randomly sample some addresses, and email those students with your question about musical preference.</p>
<p>Here is a case where the <em>sampling
                    frame<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135026-0400" content="-"?></em><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135029-0400" content="--"?><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135036-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?>list
                of potential individuals to be
                sampled<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135043-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135041-0400" content="---"?>does
                not match the population of interest. The population of interest consists of all
                students at the university, whereas the sampling frame consists of only your
                classmates. There may be <em>bias</em> arising because of this discrepancy. For
                example, students with similar majors will tend to take the same classes as you, and
                their musical preferences may also be somewhat different from those of the general
                population of students. It is always best to have the sampling frame match the
                population as closely as possible.</p></example>
                
  <example>    <title>#4</title>          
<p>
 Obtain a student directory with email addresses of all the university's students, and send the music poll to every 50th name on the list. </p>
<p>This is called <em>systematic sampling</em>. It may not be subject to any clear bias, but it would not be as safe as taking a random sample. </p>
<p>If individuals are sampled completely at random, and without replacement, then each group of a
                given size is just as likely to be selected as all the other groups of that size.
                This is called a <em>simple random sample (SRS)</em>. In contrast, a systematic
                sample would not allow for sibling students to be selected, because of having the
                same last name. In a simple random sample, sibling students would have just as much
                of a chance of both being selected as any other pair of students. Therefore, there
                may be subtle sources of bias in using
                <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135255-0400" content="such "?>a
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135258-0400"?>systematic
                <?oxy_insert_end?>sampling plan.</p></example>

<example><title>#5</title>
<p>
Obtain a student directory with email addresses of <em>all </em>the university's students, and send your music poll to a <em>simple random sample</em> of students. As long as all of the students respond, then the sample is <em>not subject to any bias</em>, and should succeed in being representative of the population of interest. </p>
<p>But what if only 40% of those selected email you back with their vote?</p>
<p>The results of this poll would not necessarily be representative of the
                                                  population<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135338-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                                                  because of
                                                  <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135345-0400"?>the
                                                  potential problems associated with
                                                  <?oxy_insert_end?><em>volunteer response</em>.
                                                  Since individuals are not compelled to respond,
                                                  often a relatively small subset take the trouble
                                                  to participate. Volunteer response is not as
                                                  problematic as a volunteer sample (presented in
                                                  <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135533-0400"?>example
                                                  <?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135530-0400" content="("?>1<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T135531-0400" content=")"?>
                                                  above), but there is still a danger that those who
                                                  do respond are different from those who don't,
                                                  with respect to the variable of interest. An
                                                  improvement would be to follow up with a second
                                                  email, asking politely for students' cooperation.
                                                  This may boost the response rate, resulting in a
                                                  sample that is fairly representative of the entire
                                                  population of interest, and it may be the best
                                                  that you can do, under the circumstances.
                                                  <em><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T140045-0400" content=" "?>Non<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101102T160012-0400" content="-"?>response</em>
                                                  is still an issue, but at least you have managed
                                                  to reduce its impact on your results.</p>
</example>
</body>
</workbook_page>
