<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_11">
    <head>
        <title>The Pituitary Gland and Hypothalamus</title>
        <objref idref="endo_pit_hypo"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <!-- INSERT SLIDE 7. ACCORDING TO GOOGLE DOC, THIS SLIDE BELONGS ABOVE THE TITLE. I DON'T KNOW HOW TO CODE IT THAT WAY. -hrt -->
        <image src="../webcontent/E_M1_7.jpg" alt="Diagram of glands in the Endocrine System"
            width="400" style="block"/>

        <p>The pituitary-hypothalamus axis links the nervous system with the endocrine system. The
                <term>hypothalamus</term> is a region of the brain that is located inferior to the
            thalamus. It coordinates signals from internal organs and other regions of the brain and
            regulates a response from the endocrine system via the pituitary. The hypothalamus
            secretes both <term>releasing hormones</term> that stimulate the anterior pituitary to
            secrete a hormone and <term>inhibiting hormones</term> that inhibit the release of a
            hormone from the anterior pituitary.</p>
        <p>The <term>pituitary gland</term> is a pea-sized gland located at the base of the brain
            attached to the hypothalamus via a stalk called the <term>infundibulum</term>. The
            pituitary gland is primarily regulated by nerve impulses or hormones released by
            neurosecretory cells of the hypothalamus. The pituitary, in turn, releases hormones that
            either have a direct effect on target cells or regulate hormone production by other
            endocrine glands. Those hormones that control the release of another hormone from an
            endocrine gland are called <term>tropic hormones</term>. The pituitary has two distinct
            regions: the anterior pituitary, and the posterior pituitary. The anterior pituitary
            secretes seven different peptide or protein hormones: growth hormone(GH), prolactin
            (PRL), thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), adrenocorticotropic hormone (ATCH),
            follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH), luteinizing hormone (LH), and melanocyte stimulating
            hormone (MSH). The posterior pituitary is an extension of the brain and releases
            hormones produced by the hypothalamus. The posterior pituitary releases antidiuretic
            hormone (ADH) (also known as vasopressin) and oxytocin. The pituitary looks like one
            gland because the anterior and posterior pituitary do not have externally visible
            distinctions, but from a cell and tissue perspective, they are really two different and
            distinct organs. </p>

        <!--   <image src="../webcontent/E_M1_8b.jpg" alt="detail of pineal gland" id="pineal1"/>-->
        <wb:inline idref="endo_pit_hypo_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
