<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_07">
    <head>
        <title>Hormone Receptors</title>
        <objref idref="endo_hormone_recep"/>
        <objref idref="endo_recep_loc"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Hormones mediate changes in cells by binding to specific <term>receptors</term>;
            individual hormones have their own unique receptor or class of receptors. A cell that
            has a receptor for a specific hormone is called a target cell. A hormone can, therefore
            circulate throughout the body, contacting many different cell types, but affecting only
            those cells that possess the specific receptor. A receptor is a protein (cell membrane
            or intracellular) that binds specifically to a particular hormone. Receptors for a
            specific hormone may be found in or on many different target cells, or may be limited to
            a small number of specialized cells.</p>
        <example>
            <p>Thyroid hormones act on almost all cells of the body, stimulating metabolic activity
                throughout the body. However, thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) acts only on the
                endocrine cells of the thyroid gland. Cells can have many receptors for the same
                hormone, but may also possess receptors for many different types of hormones.
                Follical stimulating hormone (FSH), which is produced by the anterior pituitary
                gland in the brain and circulates throughout the body, primarily impacts
                reproductive tissues in men and women, and these tissues also have receptors for
                thyroid hormones.</p>
        </example>
        <p>The number of receptors that respond to a hormone determine the cell’s potential
            sensitivity to that hormone and the resulting cellular response. The number of receptors
            that respond to a hormone can change, resulting in increased or decreased cell
            sensitivity. Since alcohol (ethanol) inhibits glutamate receptor channels, people with
            high alcohol levels show higher number of glutamate receptors in a classic example of
            <term>up-regulation</term> that makes the cells more sensitive to the hormone to try to maintain the
            normal level of response to glutamate (homeostasis). The number of cell surface
            receptors can also decrease in response to rising hormone levels, called
                <term>down-regulation</term>, leading to reduced cellular response to the hormone.
            Thus, the action of a hormone can be regulated either by the amount of hormone in
            circulation or by the number of receptors (either inside the cell or on the cell
            surface) available at that time for that hormone.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Receptor location</title>
            <body>
                <p>Hormones bind to receptors and cause changes in cellular function. Receptors
                    can be found either inside the cell (<term>intracellular receptors</term>) or on
                    the cell’s surface (<term>plasma membrane receptors</term>). Knowing the
                    location of a specific receptor provides important information about the
                    mechanism that specific hormone uses to affect cell physiology.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_LOO_location_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_hormone_recep_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
