<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_05">
    <head>
        <title>Control of Hormone Production</title>
        <objref idref="endo_hormone_loops"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Hormone production can be regulated by <activity_link idref="_u3_m1_feedback_02" target="new"
                >positive</activity_link> and <activity_link idref="_u3_m1_feedback_03"
                 target="new">negative</activity_link> feedback pathways. In positive feedback systems, the
            release of a hormone leads to an action that stimulates release of more of the same
            hormone. </p>
        <example>
            <title>Positive Feedback Loop in the Endocrine System</title>
            <p>Oxytocin released by the pituitary gland prior to childbirth stimulates contraction
                of the uterus and increases pressure on the cervix. The increased pressure signals
                the pituitary to release even more oxytocin, which increases force of contractions,
                leading to even more cervical pressure. This amplification cycle continues until
                childbirth is complete.</p>
        </example>
        <p> In a hormonal negative feedback loop, when a stimulus causes the release of a hormone
            (Hormone A), the hormone binds to the target cell receptor, causing the necessary
            metabolic change toward homeostasis. In a negative loop, the effect of this metabolic
            change is to counter the stimulus that caused the release of Hormone A. Once the cause
            of the stimulus returns to normal range, the production of that hormone stops and plasma
            level of that hormone returns to the normal (pre-stimulus) level. In this way, the
            concentration of most hormones in blood is maintained within a narrow range.</p>
        <example>
            <title>Negative Feedback Loop in the Endocrine System</title>
            <p>The hypothalamus monitors the plasma level of thyroid hormones, among others. When
                the level drops, the hypothalamus stimulates the anterior pituitary to release a
                hormone (Thyroid Stimulating Hormone, or Thyrotropin) that stimulates the thyroid to
                release thyroid hormones. Increased levels of the thyroid hormones in the blood then
                feed back to the hypothalamus and anterior pituitary to inhibit further stimulation
                of the thyroid gland. Other homeostatic imbalances, such as low body temperature,
                can also stimulate the hypothalamus to stimulate the anterior pituitary to release
                thyrotropin. Thyroid hormones play an important role in metabolic heat production
                via ATP production.</p>
        </example>

        <wb:inline idref="endo_LOO_hormones_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_LOO_regulation_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_hormone_loops_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
