<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_09">
    <head>
        <title>Plasma Membrane Hormone Receptors</title>
        <objref idref="endo_intracellular_recep"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Most peptide and amino acid hormones are polar and therefore cannot diffuse through the
            plasma membrane of cells. So, they bind to <term>plasma membrane hormone
                receptors</term> on the outer surface of the plasma membrane. Unlike steroid
            hormones, polar hormones also alter intracellular processes and can also affect the
            target cell’s transcription. Since they cannot enter the cell and act directly on any
            DNA-binding proteins, they exert their transcriptional effects through intermediate
            molecules called second messengers as described below. Catecholamines (amine class) and
            polar eicosanoids (lipid-derived class) also bind to cell-surface hormone receptors.</p>
        <p>Binding of these hormones to a cell membrane surface receptor results in activation of a
            signaling pathway that triggers a cascade of intracellular activity and specific effects
            associated with the hormone. Most hormones that bind at the surface receptor remain
            outside the target cell. Some hormones are taken into the cell by endocytosis to
            initiate the intracellular biochemical response from within vesicles. The hormone that
            initiates the signaling pathway, the first messenger, activates a second messenger
            within the cell.</p>
        <example>
            <p>Glucagon is produced when blood sugar drops. The glucagon binds to its receptor on
                target liver cells and stimulates two different metabolic reactions inside the cell.
                The liver cells will be stimulated to break down stored glycogen to glucose and to
                synthesize new glucose from some amino acids. As a result, glucose is released into
                the blood and blood sugar returns to normal.</p>
        </example>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_intracellular_recep_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <!-- THIS IMAGE IS MISSING INSERT SLIDE 5 -->
        <!--   <p><em style="highlight">[slide 5]</em></p>
        <image src="../../../_u6_muscular/webcontent/image.jpg" alt="this is a placeholder"/>-->
    </body>
</workbook_page>
