<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u10_m1_LOO_18"><head><title>Adrenal Cortex</title><objref idref="endo_adrenal_cortex" /></head><body><p id="d970b1f20af441b3b03346542b59c6ea">The <term>adrenal cortex</term> is the outer layer of the adrenal gland and is made up of layers of epithelial cells and associated capillary networks. These layers form three distinct regions that secrete different steroid hormones: the outer zona glomerulosa produces mineralocorticoids (influence salt and water balance), the middle zona fasciculata produces glucocorticoids (impact metabolism and inflammation), and the inner zona reticularis produces androgens (regulate catabolism and sexual characteristics).</p><p id="c25876f014be49429a3382e902763ba1">The main mineralocorticoid is aldosterone, which regulates the concentration of ions in urine, sweat, and saliva. Aldosterone release from the adrenal cortex can be triggered by a number of things including decrease in blood concentrations of sodium ions, blood volume, or blood pressure, or an increase in blood potassium levels.</p><p id="b3d3c7d0c8904341977d0dc8aba4ef61">The three main glucocorticoids are cortisol, corticosterone, and cortisone. The glucocorticoids stimulate the synthesis of glucose from non-glycogen sources, and they promote the release of fatty acids from adipose tissue. These hormones increase blood glucose levels to maintain levels within a normal range between meals. They are secreted in response to ACTH, and levels are regulated by negative feedback. </p><p id="f99fd2c0247e491c89d84ed036a4b549">Androgens are a class of hormones and that affect sexual characteristics. Testosterone is associated with male sexual characteristics, while progesterone and estrogen are associated with female reproductive function; androstenedione is an intermediate molecule in the synthetic pathways of these and many of the steroid hormones.</p><example id="ac38816bf9fd45e7add292be6764f4fc"><p id="b565c276357d496dbe7e8ac3eff8711c">In situations where the gonads are not functioning the progesterone made in the adrenal glands does influence sexual characteristics. One of the reasons why post-menopausal women develop more male characteristics is that the progesterone their adrenal makes gets converted to testosterone. </p></example><image id="c69df1a0f6234dcd8890024d6e9a6671" src="../webcontent/E_M1_14a.jpg" alt="detail of adrenal cortex" style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="endo_adrenal_cortex_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
