<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_21">
    <head>
        <title>The Pancreas</title>
        <objref idref="endo_pancreas"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The <term>pancreas</term> is an elongated organ that plays a central role in energy
            metabolism, storage, and utilization of glucose (carbohydrate). It is located slightly
            dorsal to the stomach and between the stomach and the small intestine. The tapered
            distal end lies in contact with the spleen, while the ducts from broader proximal end
            enter the duodenum at gastro-duodenal junction. The pancreas contains both exocrine
            cells that excrete digestive enzymes and endocrine cells that release hormones.
            Approximately 99 percent of pancreatic cells are exocrine cells that are arranged around
            ducts in clusters called acini (singular is acinus).</p>
        <p> The endocrine cells of the pancreas form clusters called pancreatic islets or the
                <term>islets of Langerhans</term> (islets are small islands) with associated blood
            capillaries. The pancreatic islets contain two major cell types: <term>alpha
                cells</term>, which constitute 20 percent of the total mass of the islets and
            produce the hormone glucagon, and <term>beta cells</term>, which constitute 75 percent
            of the total mass of the islets and produce the hormone insulin. These hormones regulate
            blood glucose levels. Alpha cells release glucagon as blood glucose levels decline below
            the set point. When blood glucose levels rise, alpha cells stop secreting glucagon, and
            beta cells then release insulin. When blood glucose levels drop below the set point
            (which does not happen under normal conditions), beta cells stop secreting insulin.</p>
        <p> Pancreatic cells also contain two minor populations of cells: delta cells, which
            constitute 4 percent of the total mass of the islets and secrete somatostatin, and F (or
            PP) cells, which constitute 1 percent of the total mass of the islets and secrete
            pancreatic polypeptide. They have specific paracrine regulator effects in the pancreas.
            Pancreatic polypeptide is secreted after a high protein meal or fasting and inhibits
            pancreatic exocrine secretion and stimulates gastric juice secretion (opposite effect of
            cholecystokinin, CCK, of the small intestine). It also stimulates both alpha and beta
            cells.</p>
        <!-- INSERT SLIDE 16 -->
        <!--<p><em style="highlight">[slide 16]</em></p>-->
        <image src="../webcontent/E_M1_15.jpg" width="450"/>
        
        
       <section purpose="learnbydoing">
           <title/>
           <body>
               <image src="../webcontent/endo_homeo_2a.png"/>
           <image src="../webcontent/endo_homeo_2b.png"/>
           <wb:inline idref="endo_pancreas_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
           </body>
       </section>
        <composite_activity purpose="didigetthis">
            <wb:inline idref="endo_pancreas_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <wb:inline idref="endo_pancreas_tt_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        </composite_activity>
        <!--  <!-\- INSERT LINK TO DIGESTIVE SYSTEM: PANCREAS. -\->
        <p><em style="highlight">INSERT LINK TO DIGESTIVE SYSTEM: PANCREAS.</em></p>-->
    </body>
</workbook_page>
