<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_19">
    <head>
        <title>Adrenal Medulla</title>
        <objref idref="endo_adrenal_medulla"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The <term>adrenal medulla</term> is the inner layer of the adrenal glands and contains
                <term>chromaffin cells</term>, which are large, irregularly shaped cells that are
            closely associated with blood vessels. These cells are innervated by autonomic
            (involuntary) nerve fibers from the central nervous system, which allows for quick
            hormone release.</p>
        <p> Chromaffin cells of the adrenal medulla produce epinephrine (adrenaline) and
            norepinephrine (noradrenaline). Epinephrine is the primary adrenal medulla hormone
            accounting for 75–80 percent of its secretions. Epinephrine and norepinephrine increase
            heart rate, breathing rate, cardiac muscle contractions, and blood glucose levels. They
            also accelerate the breakdown of glucose in skeletal muscles and stored fats in adipose
            tissue.</p>
        <p> Both are stored in vesicles or granules in the adrenal medulla, very similar to the way
            posterior pituitary cells store the neurosecretory hormones from hypothalamus for
            release. The release of epinephrine and norepinephrine into the blood is stimulated by
            neural impulses from the sympathetic nervous system. These neural impulses originate
            from the hypothalamus in response to stress to prepare the body for the fight-or-flight
            response.</p>
        <!--<image src="../webcontent/E_M1_15.jpg" style="block"
            alt="detailed view of adrenal medulla with cell details"/>-->
        <section>
            <title>Blood Supply to the Adrenal Glands</title>
            <body>
                <p>The adrenal glands have a large blood supply. They
                    receive arterial blood from the renal arteries, the phrenic arteries, and
                    suprarenal arteries from the aorta. Arterial blood enters the adrenal glands at
                    the adrenal cortex and drains into venules in the adrenal medulla. The
                    suprarenal vein of the right adrenal gland drains into the inferior vena cava,
                    and the suprarenal vein of the left adrenal gland drains into the left renal
                    vein.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_adrenal_cortex_medulla_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
