<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_08">
    <head>
        <title>Intracellular Hormone Receptors</title>
        <objref idref="endo_intracellular_recep"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Steroid hormones are lipophilic and need transport proteins in the blood. Once released
            from their transport protein, the non-polar hormone is able to diffuse across the plasma
            membrane of cells. Recall that the lipid bilayer of the plasma membrane of cells uses
            amphiphilic phospholipids to compartmentalize the cytoplasm of a cell. When a steroid
            hormone crosses the plasma membrane of a target cell, it binds to an <term>intracellular
                hormone receptor</term> in the cytoplasm, on intracellular membrane system (ER) or,
            within the nucleus of the cell. The receptor/hormone complex can then bind to a specific
            site on DNA and act as a transcription regulator to increase or decrease the synthesis
            of particular mRNA molecules coded by these specific genes. This, in turn, alters mRNA
            production, which determines the amount of corresponding protein that is synthesized.
            The steroid hormone regulates specific cell processes. The rate of transcription and
            protein synthesis is directly proportional to the amount of hormone forming
            receptor/hormone complexes; so if the hormone production increases, so does the
            physiological effect in the body.</p>
        <p>The thyroid hormones, T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub>, also use plasma transport proteins
            and intracellular DNA-binding receptors. There are, however, some important
            physiological differences with the steroid hormone mechanism. The target cells have
            membrane transport proteins that transport the thyroid hormones into the cell. The
            Thyroid hormone receptor is found bound to a transcription repressor protein on the DNA.
            The binding of the hormone with the receptor-repressor complex to form the
            receptor/hormone complex causes the repressor protein to dissociate, and a transctiption
            activator protein becomes associated with the receptor. This, in turn, initiates
            transcription.</p>

        <!--<p><em style="highlight">[slide 4]</em></p>
        <image src="../../../_u6_muscular/webcontent/image.jpg" alt="this is a placeholder"/>-->
    </body>
</workbook_page>
