<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_16">
    <head>
        <title>Parathyroid Glands</title>
        <objref idref="endo_parathyroid"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The four <term>parathyroid glands</term> are each the size of a grain of rice and are
            usually located on the posterior surface of the thyroid gland. The exact location and
            number of parathyroid glands can vary from person to person. The parathyroid glands are
            named for their proximity to the thyroid gland (para- means next to), often seeming to
            be part of the same gland; however, their cells are distinct from those of the thyroid
            gland.</p>

        <image src="../webcontent/E_M1_12.jpg" alt="detail of parathyroid glands" width="550">
            <caption>Note that this image is on a different anatomical plane than the previous image
                of the thyroid.</caption>
        </image>

        <p>Each parathyroid gland is covered by connective tissue and contains many secretory cells
            called <term>chief cells</term>, which synthesize and secrete parathyroid hormone (PTH).
            Another type of cell, oxyphil cells, can be distinguished histologically in the
            parathyroid but they are not clearly understood. They appear to increase during renal
            failure, but their function is still a subject of clinical research.</p>
        <p>PTH is synthesized as a pro-peptide that is cleaved into an active hormone, which is
            vital in maintaining blood calcium levels. Calcium is required for nerve impulse
            transmission, for muscle contractions and for many cellular processes--including signal
            transduction. Therefore, plasma calcium concentrations must be maintained within a
            narrow normal range of 9–10 mg/dL. PTH functions by increasing blood calcium
            concentrations when calcium ion levels fall below normal. Calcium ions bind to specific
            receptors on the chief cell and inhibit release of PTH; when the plasma calcium level
            falls, PTH secretion is stimulated. PTH stimulates reabsorption of calcium from filtrate
            during urine formation, increased absorption in the intestines from digested products
            and increased activity of osteoclasts to release calcium (and phosphate) from bone
            matrix into the plasma. There is some evidence that it may also indirectly inhibit
            osteoblast activity.</p>
        <p>A parathyroid adenoma is a benign tumor of the parathyroid gland that can cause an
            overproduction of PTH leading to hyperparathyroidism. Hyperparathyroidism results in
            hypercalcemia, which can lead to kidney stones. Additionally, increased rate of bone
            resorption due to higher osteoclast activity due to this condition may also lead to
            osteoporosis. Usually only one of the four parathyroid glands is affected and can be
            surgically removed without any adverse effects. However, removal of all the parathyroid
            glands will cause an imbalance in blood calcium levels resulting in death.</p>
        <!-- INSERT SLIDE 12 -->



        <section purpose="learnbydoing">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <image src="../webcontent/endo_homeo_1a.png" width="400"/>
                <image src="../webcontent/endo_homeo_1b.png" width="400"/>

                <wb:inline idref="endo_parathyroid_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            </body>

        </section>



        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_parathyroid_tt_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <!--<wb:inline idref="endo_parathyroid_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
