<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_10">
    <head>
        <title>G-protein-coupled Receptors</title>
        <objref idref="endo_g_prot_recep"/>
        <objref idref="endo_recep_loc"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>G-proteins are a class of trans-membrane cell surface proteins that can be activated by
            hormones or ions and other chemicals for cell signaling. G-proteins remain inactive
            unless a hormone is bound to its cell surface receptor. Inactive G-proteins are bound to
            GDP on its cytoplasmic side. When a hormone binds to the cell surface receptor the bound
            GDP is replaced by GTP.</p>
        <p>Activated G-proteins can have different functions depending on the hormone receptor: it
            can open a membrane protein channel; it can release a small molecule; or it can activate
            a membrane-bound enzyme. There is a large variety of G-protein-induced effects. For
            example, G-protein-linked ion channels can stimulate movements of ions across the
            membranes. There are specific channels for potassium, sodium, calcium or chloride.</p>
        <p>For G-protein activated membrane-bound enzymes, there are large numbers of activated
            enzymes. One of the membrane bound enzymes that the G-Protein coupled receptor (GPCR)
            activates upon binding to a hormone molecule is the adenylate cyclase. This enzyme
            catalyzes the conversion of ATP to cyclic AMP (cAMP). which, in turn, activates a class
            of enzymes called protein kinases. These kinases transfer a phosphate group from ATP to
            a substrate molecule in a process called phosphorylation. The phosphorylation of a
            substrate molecule changes its shape, thereby activating it. This chain of reactions,
            where hormone binding to the GPCR leads to the appearance of cAMP in the cytoplasm as
            the second messenger which, in turn, leads to the activation of protein kinase is an
            example of a “reaction cascade.” In this case, since a signal from the exterior of the
            cell is transferred to the interior via the formation of a “second messenger,” the
            process is called “signal transduction cascade." Other second messengers that can be
            involved as a result of hormone binding to a cell membrane receptor include cyclic GMP
            (derived from guanosine
            triphosphate<!-- NOTE: THIS MOLECULE NAME HAS A BROKEN LINK ASSOCIATED WITH IT IN
                THE GOOGLE DOC-->),
            tyrosine kinases, inositol phospholipids, and even calcium ions. Cellular responses to
            hormone binding of a cell membrane receptor include altering membrane permeability,
            activating metabolic pathways, stimulating synthesis of proteins and enzymes, and
            hormone release.</p>
        <p>The binding of a hormone at a single cell membrane receptor causes the activation of many
            G-proteins, which can catalyze many reactions simultaneously. Thus, the effect of a
            peptide hormone is amplified as the signaling cascade progresses. A small amount of
            hormone can trigger the formation of a large amount of cellular product. To stop hormone
            activity, the cascading chemical reaction is interrupted; for example cAMP is
            deactivated by the cytoplasmic enzyme <term>phosphodiesterase (PDE)</term>. PDE is
            always present in the cell, and it breaks down cAMP spontaneously, preventing
            overproduction of cellular products. The specific response of a cell to a
            lipid-insoluble hormone depends on the type of receptors that are present on the cell
            membrane and the substrate molecules present in the cell cytoplasm.
            <!--I am concerned about
            this section on G protein interactions. It really only presents one G protein mediated
            response. cAMP amplification. G protein activation can also result in activation of the
            phospholipase C system or directly opening a membrane channel. If you only present one
            way G proteins responds, students will get it fixed in there heads that G protein
            activation results only in cAMP amplification. I am not sure you can present the main
            lipophobic hormone receptor response only. G proteins bind to all kinds of receptors.At
            the very least have a pop up box that explains other G protein response mechanisms. --></p>
        <!-- IMAGE HAS NOT BEEN PROVIDED: INSERT SLIDE 6 -->
        <!--  <p><em style="highlight">[slide 6]</em></p>
        <image src="../../../_u6_muscular/webcontent/image.jpg" alt="this is a placeholder"/>-->
        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_g_prot_recep_digt"/>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_recep_loc_digt"/>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
