<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_15">
    <head>
        <title>Synthesis of Thyroid Hormones</title>
        <objref idref="endo_production_comp"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Unlike most endocrine glands, the thyroid gland stores large amounts of some of the
            hormones it synthesizes. Thyroglobulin is produced and secreted by follicle cells into
            the lumen of follicles as a colloid. There it undergoes post-translational modification
            to produce functioning thyroid hormones. Iodide molecules are added to the thyroglobulin
            precursor to produce the hormones thyroxine and triiodothyronine. Thyroxine is also
            known as T<sub>4</sub> because it contains four atoms of iodine, and triiodothyronine is
            also known as T<sub>3</sub> because it contains three atoms of iodine. In developed
            countries, the iodide required for hormone synthesis is obtained primarily from iodized
            salt. However, seafood and plants grown in iodine rich soil at lower elevations also
            provide the required iodide. Since iodine as a molecule is quite volatile, the food
            grown in higher elevations (lower atmospheric pressure) lacks sufficient iodine. Iodide
            ions are actively transported into the follicular lumen from the capillaries by follicle
            cells. Follicle cells are stimulated to release stored T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub>
            from the lumen into the blood capillaries by thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH), which is
            produced by the anterior pituitary.
            <!--[LINK back to earlier activity with homeostatic feedback
            analysis for T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub>]-->
            Follicle cells also begin synthesizing more T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub> in response
            to TSH stimulation.</p>

        <!-- <!-\- INSERT SLIDE 11 -\->
            <p><em style="highlight">[slide 11]</em></p>-->
        <image src="../webcontent/E_M1_11a.jpg" alt="molecular diagram: thyroxine"/>
        <p>A third hormone, calcitonin, is produced by parafollicular cells, or C cells of the
            thyroid. Calcitonin release is not controlled by TSH, but instead is released when
            calcium ion concentrations in the blood rise. Calcium ions bind to specific receptor on
            the C cell and stimulate release of calcitonin. Calcitonin acts primarily in children to
            lower blood calcium levels when levels get too high. Calcitonin causes decreased tubular
            reabsorption of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the kidneys, leading to calcium loss in urine. It
            inhibits bone resorption activity of osteoclasts and calcium absorption in intestine to
            also reduce plasma calcium levels. It is also suspected to have an indirect effect
            stimulating osteoblast activity and development. However, in adult humans it appears to
            play only a minor role in calcium homeostasis because abnormalities in calcitonin
            production do not appear to be associated with specific plasma calcium imbalances.
            Research has implicated its role during times of high calcium demands, such as pregnancy
            and lactation.</p>


        <!-- <!-\- INSERT HOMEOSTASIS LOOP LEARNING ACTIVITY -\->
            <p><activity_link idref="homeostasis_looO$">Return to the homeostasis unit for further
            details.</activity_link></p>
            
            <p><em style="highlight">homeostasis loop learning activity</em></p>-->
        <wb:inline idref="endo_thyroid_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_production_comp_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
