<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_14">
    <head>
        <title>Thyroid Gland</title>
        <objref idref="endo_thyroid"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The <term>thyroid gland</term> possesses two lobes that are connected by the isthmus. It
            is located in the neck, just below the larynx with the isthmus in front of and lobes
            lateral to the trachea. It has a dark red color due to its extensive vasculature. When
            the thyroid increases in size due to dysfunction, it can be felt under the skin of the
            neck. The main function of the thyroid gland is the synthesis and storage of thyroid
            hormones that are involved in maintaining metabolic homeostasis.</p>
        <p>The thyroid gland is made up of many spherical thyroid follicles, which are lined with
            simple cuboidal epithelium. These follicles contain a viscous fluid called
                <term>colloid</term> that stores the glycoprotein <term>thyroglobulin</term>, the
            precursor to the two thyroid hormones. Thyroglobulin is not normally released into
            circulation unless the thyroid gland is damaged due to disease or injury. Other
            endocrine cells, called parafollicular cells, are located between adjacent follicles and
            produce a different hormone, calcitonin, that is involved in blood calcium
            homeostasis.</p>

        <image src="../webcontent/E_M1_10.jpg" alt="location and detail of thyroid gland"
            width="450" style="block"/>
        
        <!--<wb:inline idref="endo_thyroid_tt_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
        <wb:inline idref="endo_thyroid_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
