<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_20">
    <head>
        <title>Pineal Gland</title>
        <objref idref="endo_pineal"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The <term>pineal gland</term> is located between the cerebral hemispheres of the brain.
            It is attached to the roof of the third ventricle in the diencephalon. The pineal gland
            consists of secretory cells, called <term>pinealocytes</term>, that secrete the hormone
            melatonin. <term>Melatonin</term> is derived from serotonin (a neuropeptide) and is
            regulated in response to the light and dark of the environment (the diurnal cycle).
            Photons, packets of light, are detected by the retinas of the eyes, which initiate a
            nerve impulse that is detected by the pineal gland. This mechanism is similar to the
            process in the posterior pituitary or adrenal medulla. The pineal gland synthesizes the
            highest levels of melatonin during the night, when light levels are the lowest, and the
            increased blood concentrations of melatonin makes us sleepy. Blood concentrations of
            melatonin are lowest during the day, when light exposure inhibits the synthesis of the
            hormone.</p>
        <p> The target cells of melatonin are located in the <term>suprachiasmatic nucleus
                (SCN)</term> of the brain. The SCN functions as a biological clock that regulates
            physiological processes such as the sleep-wake cycle, appetite, and body temperature.
            Melatonin is thought to inhibit the release of gonadotropins from the anterior
            pituitary, which affect the onset of puberty.</p>
        <p> Higher melatonin levels at night make us sleepy, and a disruption in melatonin synthesis
            can disrupt the sleep cycle. Travel across several time zones can result in disruptions
            to the sleep cycle, or jet lag. This is due to the change in the dark-light cycle that
            the body is accustomed to, and it can take several days for melatonin synthesis to adapt
            to the change. Melatonin supplements are available to treat jet lag as well as other
            sleep disorders; however, their efficacy has not been conclusively established.</p>
        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_pineal_tt_digt"/>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_pineal_digt"/>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
