<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m1_LOO_24">
    <head>
        <title>Organs with Secondary Endocrine Function</title>
        <objref idref="endo_secondary"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <!--    <!-\- INSERT SLIDE 17 -\->
        <p><em style="highlight">[slide 17]</em></p>
        <image src="../../../_u6_muscular/webcontent/image.jpg" alt="this is a placeholder"/>-->
        <p>There are several organs whose primary functions are non-endocrine but that also possess
            endocrine functions. These include the heart, gastrointestinal tract, kidneys, adipose
            tissue, skin, and thymus.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Heart and Cardiovascular System</title>
            <body>
                <p>The heart possesses specialized cardiac muscle cells, which are endocrine cells
                    in the walls of the atria. These cells respond to increased blood volume by
                    releasing the hormone <term>atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP)</term>. Natrium is
                    the name for sodium in many languages and is the reason that Na is the chemical
                    symbol for sodium. High blood volume causes the cells to be stretched, opening
                    stretch-activated membrane channels, resulting in hormone release. ANP acts on
                    the kidneys to reduce the reabsorption of Na<sup>+</sup>, causing Na<sup>+</sup>
                    and water to be excreted in the urine. ANP also reduces the amounts of renin
                    released by the kidneys and aldosterone released by the adrenal cortex, further
                    preventing the retention of water. In this way, ANP reduces the concentration of
                        Na<sup>+</sup> in the blood and causes a reduction in blood volume and blood
                    pressure. Another natriuretic hormone, BNP (misnamed brain natriuretic because
                    it was first isolated from pig brains) from the heart ventricle, enhances the
                    effect of ANP.</p>
                <p>Endothelial cells lining the cardiovascular system also have an endocrine
                    function. They produce paracrine <term>endothelin</term>, a vasodilator and
                    stimulator of ANP secretion, and <term>nitric oxide (NO)</term>, a vasodilator
                    and inhibitor of ANP secretion.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Digestive System</title>
            <body>
                <p>The digestive system produces several hormones that aid in digestive and
                    metabolic homeostasis. Endocrine cells are located in the mucosa of the GI tract
                    throughout the stomach and small intestine. Hormone secretion is controlled by
                    receptors monitoring the chemical content of the digestive lumen. Some of the
                    hormones produced include <term>gastrin</term> (from stomach),
                        <term>secretin</term>, and <term>cholecystokinin CCK</term> (from small
                    intestine) that act on the GI tract and accessory organs such as the pancreas,
                    gallbladder, and liver. They trigger the release of digestive juices that help
                    to break down and digest food in the GI tract. The GI tract also produces the
                    hormones <term>glucose-dependent insulinotropic peptide (GIP)</term> (from
                    stomach) and <term>glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1)</term> (from small
                    intestine). These hormones are secreted in response to glucose in the intestinal
                    lumen. GIP and GLP-1 target cells are beta cells in the pancreas, which are
                    stimulated to release insulin and alpha cells that are inhibited from releasing
                    glucagon. The stomach also produces <term>ghrelin</term> that mediates hunger,
                    stimulating appetite and growth hormone release. </p>
                <p>The liver, as an accessory organ of the digestive system, also has an endocrine
                    function in production of <term>insulin-like growth factor (IGFs)</term> and
                        <term>thrombopoietin (THPO)</term>. IGFs work with growth hormone to
                    regulate cell metabolism while THPO triggers the formation of platelets in the
                    blood. The liver also produces prohormones (angiotensinogen and calcidiol,
                    vitamin D) and plasma proteins that transport many of the hormones.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Kidneys and Urinary System</title>
            <body>
                <p>The adrenal glands associated with the kidneys are major endocrine glands, and
                    the kidneys themselves also possess endocrine functions. <term>Renin</term> (<em
                        style="italic">'renal'</em> generally describes aspects of the kidney) is
                    released in response to decreased blood volume or pressure and is part of the
                    renin-angiotensin system that is responsible for the formation of angiotensin II
                    and ultimately leads to the release of aldosterone. Both angiotensin II and
                    aldosterone then causes the retention of Na<sup>+</sup> and water, raising blood
                    volume. The kidneys also release the steroid hormone <term>calcitriol</term>,
                    which is the biologically active form of vitamin D that aids in the absorption
                    of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <term>Erythropoietin (EPO)</term> is a protein hormone that
                    triggers the formation of red blood cells in the bone marrow. EPO is released in
                    response to low oxygen levels. Because red blood cells are oxygen carriers,
                    increased production results in greater oxygen delivery throughout the body. The
                    banned substance EPO had been used by athletes at one point to improve
                    performance, as greater oxygen delivery to muscle cells allows for greater
                    endurance. Because red blood cells increase the viscosity of blood, artificially
                    high levels can cause severe health risks.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adipose Tissue</title>
            <body>
                <p>Adipose tissue is a connective tissue found throughout the body. It produces the
                    hormone leptin (Greek “leptos” means “thin”) in response to food intake.
                        <term>Leptin</term> binds to neuropeptide Y in the CNS neurons,
                    producing a feeling of satiety after eating, thus affecting appetite and
                    reducing the urge for further eating. Note that it has the opposite effect of
                    ghrelin secretion from the stomach, but when leptin levels drop, the brain
                    detects a state of starvation and the feeling of hunger increases. These two
                    hormones are the subject of much research related to obesity. </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Skin</title>
            <body>
                <p>Skin produces <term>cholecalciferol</term>, which is an inactive hormone form of
                    vitamin D3. It is formed when cholesterol molecules in the skin, in the form of
                    7-dehydrocholesterol, are exposed to ultraviolet radiation. Cholecalciferol then
                    enters the bloodstream and is modified in the liver to form calcifediol.
                    Calcifediol is then modified in the kidneys to form calcitriol, which is the
                    active form of vitamin D<sub>3</sub>. Vitamin D plays an important role in bone
                    formation.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Bone</title>
            <body>
                <p>Bones not only respond to hormones to maintain blood calcium homeostasis, but
                    recent research shows they also have an endocrine function. Osteocytes have been
                    found to produce two hormones (<term>fibroblast growth factor 23</term> and
                        <term>osteocalcin</term>) that act on kidney, pancreas and other body
                    tissues influencing Vitamin D and glucose homeostasis.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Thymus</title>
            <body>
                <p>The <term>thymus</term> is an organ that is found behind the sternum and is most
                    prominent in infants, becoming smaller in size through adulthood, replaced by
                    adipose tissue that continues to produce angiogenic factors. The thymus is part
                    of the immune system, with a role in maturation and immunocompetence of
                    T-lymphocytes. The thymus also produces a group of hormones called
                        <term>thymosins</term>, because they were first discovered from the thymus,
                    but now are understood to be produced by many different tissues in the body.
                    They appear to have an anti-inflammatory effect and stimulate tissue repair.
                    Thymosin is also involved in neuroplasticity, and they may have clinical
                    implications in the treatment of cardiovascular, infectious and autoimmune
                    diseases as well as cancer.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_secondary_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
