<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE objectives PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Learning Objectives 2.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_learning_objectives_2_0.dtd"><objectives id="lo_nervous"><title>Nervous System Learning Objectives</title><objective id="describe_nervous_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the major functions of the Nervous System.</objective><objective id="classify_cns_pns_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Classify the organs that are part of the nervous system as belonging to the central nervous system (CNS) or the peripheral nervous system (PNS).</objective><objective id="describe_neuron_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Within a neuron, identify the soma, axon and dendrite and describe the main function of each region.</objective><objective id="neuron_anatomy_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify neurons based on anatomical features: unipolar, bipolar, multipolar and anaxonic and based on functional properties: sensory, motor, interneuron.</objective><objective id="glial_types_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">List the four types of CNS glial cells and describe their function.</objective><objective id="list_glial_cells_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">List the two types of PNS glial cells and describe their function. Describe the anatomical relationship between the glial cells and the PNS.</objective><objective id="compare_axons_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Compare the structure of myelinated vs. unmyelinated axons. Distinguish between white matter and gray matter.</objective><objective id="describe_voltage_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the transmembrane potential or voltage across the cell membrane and how it is measured.</objective><objective id="ion_concentration_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Contrast the relative concentrations of ions in body solutions inside and outside of a cell (sodium, potassium, calcium and chloride ions).</objective><objective id="explain_resting_potential_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain how four factors determine a neuron’s resting membrane potential.</objective><objective id="explain_electrical_response_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain how a local electrical response in a neuron membrane is caused by stimulation.</objective><objective id="interpret_voltage_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Interpret a graph showing the voltage vs. time relationship of an action potential. </objective><objective id="explain_action_potential_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain action potential.</objective><objective id="discuss_action_potential_LO">Discuss the underlying changes in membrane permeability that occur during the action potential.</objective><objective id="explain_refractory_LO">Explain refractory period and the consequences of the absolute and relative refractory periods on firing frequency.</objective><objective id="explain_all_actionpot_LO">Explain all-or-none with relation to the action potential.</objective><objective id="synapse_cells_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify the presynaptic and postsynaptic cells at a synapse.</objective><objective id="explain_synapses_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain synaptic transmission in terms of the structural and functional features of electrical and chemical synapses.</objective><objective id="synapses_LO">Distinguish between structural features and functional features of electrical and chemical synapses.</objective><objective id="synapse_events_LO">Describe the events of synaptic transmission in proper chronological order.</objective><objective id="explain_ion_flux_LO">Explain how ion flux across the postsynaptic membrane can lead to excitation or inhibition.</objective><objective id="explain_neurotransmitters_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain how a single neurotransmitter may have different effects at different postsynaptic cells.</objective><objective id="define_epsp_LO">Define excitatory postsynaptic potential (EPSP) and inhibitory postsynaptic potential (IPSP) and interpret graphs of voltage vs. time (local potential).</objective><objective id="explain_synapse_potential_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain temporal and spatial summation of synaptic potentials and discuss how action potentials differ from synaptic potentials.</objective><objective id="describe_neuro_function_LO">Describe how excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmitter(s) are able to function together.</objective><objective id="identify_neuro_classes_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify the four classes of neurotransmitters and identify the most common excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmitters.</objective><objective id="classify_receptors_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Classify receptors based on structure, location relative to the stimulus, and types of signals they transduce.</objective><objective id="explain_receptors_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain the distribution of receptors involved in providing information for our general (somesthetic) senses.</objective><objective id="describe_receptor_modality_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the types of information (modality) detected by the receptors associated with the somesthetic senses and the phenomenon of adaptation.</objective><objective id="explain_adaptation_LO">Explain the phenomenon of adaptation.</objective><objective id="describe_pain_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain pain function, nociceptor distribution, and distinguish the fiber types that carry their signals.</objective><objective id="define_nociceptors_LO">Define nociceptors, describe their distribution and provide examples of the types of stimuli that they transduce.</objective><objective id="compare_pain_fibers_LO">Compare and contrast the two main fiber types that carry pain signals (information from nociceptors).</objective><objective id="list_pain_categories_LO">List and briefly describe the 3 categories of pain.</objective><objective id="define_pain_characteristics_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe pain in terms of hyperalgesia, analgesia, and receptive field.</objective><objective id="define_hyperalgesia_LO">Define hyperalgesia and explain the basis of hyperalgesia development.</objective><objective id="define_analgesia_LO">Define analgesia and list processes that can be targeted to induce analgesia.</objective><objective id="define_receptive_field_LO">Define receptive field.</objective><objective id="define_dermatome_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Define dermatome and explain how dermatomes can be used in neurological exams for diagnosing nerve damage.</objective><objective id="define_reflex_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe reflexes, reflex repsonses, and distinguish types of reflexes.</objective><objective id="reflex_pairs_LO">Distinguish between each of the following pairs of reflexes: intrinsic (inborn) reflexes vs. learned reflexes, somatic vs. visceral reflexes, monosynaptic vs. polysynaptic reflexes, and ipsilateral vs. contralateral reflexes.</objective><objective id="eye_functions_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify and describe the functions of the accessory eye structures, the tunics, and the optical components of the eye.</objective><objective id="eye_muscles_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify the muscles that help to coordinate eye movement.</objective><objective id="eye_structures_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the structures and functions of the eye.</objective><objective id="eye_light_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain how the path of light through the eye causes vision.</objective><objective id="eye_lightpath_LO">Trace the path of light as it passes through the eye to the retina.</objective><objective id="explain_eye_image_LO">Explain how the optical system of the eye creates an image on the retina.</objective><objective id="eye_visionchanges_LO">Relate changes in the anatomy of the eye to changes in vision.</objective><objective id="describe_eye_retina_LO">Describe the structure of the retina and the cells that compose it.</objective><objective id="compare_eye_rodscones_LO">Compare and contrast the function of rods and cones in vision.</objective><objective id="describe_eye_photoreceptors_LO">Describe how light activates photoreceptors</objective><objective id="explain_light_adaption_LO">Explain the process of light and dark adaptation.</objective><objective id="eye_retina_nervepath_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Trace the path of nerve impulses from the retina to various parts of the brain.</objective><objective id="identify_ear_structures_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify the hearing structures of the outer, middle and inner ear and describe their functions.</objective><objective id="describe_ear_glands_LO">Describe the functions of the ceruminous glands.</objective><objective id="describe_auditory_tube_LO">Describe the role of the auditory tube in drainage and equalization of pressure in the middle ear.</objective><objective id="describe_ear_sound_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe how the various structures of the ear conduct and transduce sound.</objective><objective id="describe_sound_waves_LO">Describe how sound waves are transmitted through the inner ear and transduced into neuronal signals.</objective><objective id="explain_ear_pitch_LO">Explain how the structures of the ear enable differentiation of pitch (frequency) and loudness of sounds.</objective><objective id="describe_ear_impulses_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the ear to various parts of the brain.</objective><objective id="distinguish_equilibrium_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Distinguish between static and dynamic equilibrium, describe the structures involved, and their functions.</objective><objective id="describe_ear_maculae_LO">Describe the structure of the maculae and their function in static and dynamic equilibrium.</objective><objective id="describe_ear_crista_LO">Describe the structure of the crista ampullaris and explain its function in dynamic equilibrium.</objective><objective id="describe_ear_nervepath_LO">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the vestibular organ to various parts of the brain.</objective><objective id="explain_taste_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain the gustation and describe the structures involved.</objective><objective id="identify_tastebuds_LO">Identify the location and structure of taste buds.</objective><objective id="explain_tastechems_LO">Explain how dissolved chemicals activate gustatory receptors.</objective><objective id="describe_taste_LO">Describe the five primary taste sensations.</objective><objective id="describe_taste_nerves_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the gustatory receptors to various parts of the brain.</objective><objective id="identify_olfactory_LO">Identify the location of olfactory receptors.</objective><objective id="explain_odor_receptors_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain how odorants activate olfactory receptors.</objective><objective id="describe_olfactory_nerves_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the olfactory receptors to various parts of the brain.</objective><objective id="predict_olfactory_dysfunction_LO">Predict factors or situations affecting the olfactory system that could disrupt its function.</objective><objective id="predict_olfactory_impact_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Predict the types of problems that would occur in the body if the olfactory system was not functioning normally.</objective><objective id="autonomic_nervous_intro_LO">Identify the autonomic nervous system and describe it&apos;s basic functions.</objective><objective id="compare_somatic_autonomic_systems_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Compare the somatic and autonomic nervous systems.</objective><objective id="explain_autonomic_motor_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain the role of the autonomic nervous system as a motor division of the nervous system.</objective><objective id="explain_homeostatic_balance_LO">Explain the importance of homeostatic balance between the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems.</objective><objective id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Contrast the anatomy of the parasympathetic and sympathetic systems.</objective><objective id="describe_local_para_sympa_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the local organization of each of the sympathetic and parasympathetic systems, including the pattern of innervation of target glands, organs, and tissues.</objective><objective id="describe_local_sympathetic_LO">Describe the local organization of the sympathetic nervous system.</objective><objective id="describe_local_parasympathetic_LO">Describe the local organization of the parasympathetic nervous system.</objective><objective id="describe_pattern_innervation_LO">Describe the pattern of innervation of target glands, organs, and tissues for the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems.</objective><objective id="describe_para_symp_effects_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe major parasympathetic and sympathetic physiological effects on target organs.</objective><objective id="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify the neurotransmitters released by preganglionic and postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems and describe their effects.</objective><objective id="explain_sympathetic_activation_LO">Explain how norepinephrine and epinephrine mediate widespread sympathetic system activation throughout the body.</objective><objective id="explain_role_homeostasis_LO">Explain the role of the autonomic nervous system in maintaining homeostasis.</objective><objective id="describe_effectors_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe examples of specific effectors dually innervated by the autonomic nervous system and explain how each branch influences function in a given effector.</objective><objective id="name_exclusive_effectors_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Name examples of effectors innervated either by only the sympathetic branch or by only the parasympathetic branch of the autonomic nervous system and explain how that branch by itself influences function in a given effector.</objective><objective id="explain_sympathetic_innervation_LO">Explain how sympathetic innervation of blood vessels is dependent on neurotransmitter receptor subtypes.</objective><objective id="describe_brain_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the basic (overall) structure of the human brain.</objective><objective id="explain_csf_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Explain the roles of CSF, ventricles, and the blood brain barrier.</objective><objective id="correlate_hindbrain_functions_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Correlate hindbrain and midbrain regions to their major function(s).</objective><objective id="correlate_forebrain_functions_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Correlate forebrain regions to their major functions(s).</objective><objective id="identify_brainregions_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify the location of major brain regions.</objective><objective id="cranialnerve_functions_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Assign function(s) to each of the cranial nerves.</objective><objective id="spinal_gross_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Describe the gross anatomy of the spinal cord and spinal nerves and specify their location relative to the anatomy of the vertebral column.</objective><objective id="spinal_gray_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Contrast the relative position of gray matter and white matter in the spinal cord with the corresponding arrangement of gray and white matter in the brain.</objective><objective id="spinal_anat_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Compare and contrast the anatomical features of the spinal cord in the cervical, thoracic and lumbar regions.</objective><objective id="spinal_general_LO">Provide a general description of a spinal tract, including the general location of these tracts in the spinal cord, common structures that the tracts communicate between , the types of information carried in these tracts.</objective><objective id="spinal_structures_LO" high_mastery="2.5" min_practice="2" medium_mastery="1.5" low_opportunity="false">Identify how spinal structures relate to each other: tract, root, ganglion, nerve, ramus, plexus.</objective><objective id="spinal_plexus_LO">Identify the 4 spinal plexuses and list an example of a nerve that emerges from each plexus.</objective><objective_skills idref="classify_cns_pns_LO"><skillref idref="classify_cns_pns_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="classify_receptors_LO"><skillref idref="classify_receptors_structure_SKILL" /><skillref idref="classify_receptors_location_SKILL" /><skillref idref="classify_receptors_signals_SKILL" /><skillref idref="classify_receptors_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="compare_axons_LO"><skillref idref="compare_axon_structure_SKILL" /><skillref idref="compare_axons_whvsgr_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="compare_somatic_autonomic_systems_LO"><skillref idref="explain_autonomic_motor_SKILL" /><skillref idref="compare_somatic_autonomic_systems_SKILL" /><skillref idref="autonomic_nervous_function_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LO"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_SKILL" /><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_sympathetic_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="correlate_forebrain_functions_LO"><skillref idref="correlate_forebrain_thalamus_SKILL" /><skillref idref="correlate_forebrain_hypothalamus_SKILL" /><skillref idref="identify_brainregions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="correlate_forebrain_functions_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="correlate_hindbrain_functions_LO"><skillref idref="correlate_hindbrain_med_obl_SKILL" /><skillref idref="correlate_hindbrain_pons_SKILL" /><skillref idref="correlate_hindbrain_cereb_SKILL" /><skillref idref="correlate_hindbrain_midbrain_SKILL" /><skillref idref="identify_brainregions_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="cranialnerve_functions_LO"><skillref idref="cranialnerve_functions_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="define_dermatome_LO"><skillref idref="define_dermatome_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="define_pain_characteristics_LO"><skillref idref="define_hyperalgesia_SKILL" /><skillref idref="define_analgesia_SKILL" /><skillref idref="define_receptive_field_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="define_reflex_LO"><skillref idref="define_reflex_SKILL" /><skillref idref="reflex_pairs_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_brain_LO"><skillref idref="describe_brain_SKILL" /><skillref idref="identify_brainregions_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_ear_impulses_LO"><skillref idref="describe_spiral_impulses_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_vestibular_impulses_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_ear_sound_LO"><skillref idref="describe_ear_sound_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_sound_waves_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_ear_pitch_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_effectors_LO"><skillref idref="describe_effectors_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_local_para_sympa_LO"><skillref idref="describe_local_sympathetic_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_local_parasympathetic_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_parasymp_innervation_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_sympath_innervation_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_nervous_LO"><skillref idref="describe_nervous_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_neuron_LO"><skillref idref="describe_axon_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_soma_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_dendrite_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_olfactory_nerves_LO"><skillref idref="describe_olfactory_nerves_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_pain_LO"><skillref idref="describe_pain_SKILL" /><skillref idref="define_nociceptors_SKILL" /><skillref idref="compare_pain_fibers_SKILL" /><skillref idref="list_pain_categories_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_para_symp_effects_LO"><skillref idref="describe_para_symp_effects_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_receptor_modality_LO"><skillref idref="describe_receptor_modality_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_adaptation_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_taste_nerves_LO"><skillref idref="describe_taste_nerves_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="describe_voltage_LO"><skillref idref="describe_voltage_SKILL" /><skillref idref="measure_voltage_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="distinguish_equilibrium_LO"><skillref idref="distinguish_equilibrium_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_ear_maculae_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_ear_crista_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_action_potential_LO"><skillref idref="discuss_action_potential_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_refractory_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_all_actionpot_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_autonomic_motor_LO"><skillref idref="autonomic_nervous_function_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_autonomic_motor_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_csf_LO"><skillref idref="describe_csf_SKILL" /><skillref idref="sequence_ventricles_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_b-b_barrier_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_electrical_response_LO"><skillref idref="explain_electrical_response_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_neurotransmitters_LO"><skillref idref="explain_neurotransmitters_excite_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_neurotransmitters_fast_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_odor_receptors_LO"><skillref idref="explain_odor_receptors_SKILL" /><skillref idref="identify_olfactory_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_receptors_LO"><skillref idref="explain_receptors_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_resting_potential_LO"><skillref idref="explain_respot_concengrad_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_respot_selectperm_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_respot_electricattract_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_respot_nakpump_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_synapse_potential_LO"><skillref idref="define_epsp_SKILL" /><skillref idref="define_graph_epsp_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_synapse_potential_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_neuro_function_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_synapses_LO"><skillref idref="synapse_cells_SKILL" /><skillref idref="synapses_SKILL" /><skillref idref="synapse_events_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_ion_flux_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="explain_taste_LO"><skillref idref="identify_tastebuds_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_tastechems_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_taste_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="eye_functions_LO"><skillref idref="eye_functions_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="eye_light_LO"><skillref idref="eye_lightpath_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_eye_image_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_eye_photoreceptors_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_light_adaption_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="eye_muscles_LO"><skillref idref="eye_muscles_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="eye_retina_nervepath_LO"><skillref idref="eye_retina_nervepath_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="eye_structures_LO"><skillref idref="explain_eye_image_SKILL" /><skillref idref="eye_visionchanges_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_eye_retina_SKILL" /><skillref idref="compare_eye_rodscones_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="glial_types_LO"><skillref idref="glial_types_SKILL" /><skillref idref="glial_types_function_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="identify_brainregions_LO"><skillref idref="identify_brainregions_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="identify_ear_structures_LO"><skillref idref="identify_ear_structures_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_ear_glands_SKILL" /><skillref idref="describe_auditory_tube_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="identify_neuro_classes_LO"><skillref idref="identify_neuro_classes_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LO"><skillref idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="interpret_voltage_LO"><skillref idref="interpret_voltage_SKILL" /><skillref idref="interpret_voltage_terms_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="ion_concentration_LO"><skillref idref="ion_concentration_inside_SKILL" /><skillref idref="ion_concentration_outside_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="list_glial_cells_LO"><skillref idref="list_glial_cells_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="name_exclusive_effectors_LO"><skillref idref="name_exclusive_effectors_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="neuron_anatomy_LO"><skillref idref="neuron_anatomy_SKILL" /><skillref idref="neuron_function_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="predict_olfactory_impact_LO"><skillref idref="predict_olfactory_impact_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="spinal_anat_LO"><skillref idref="spinal_anat_region_SKILL" /><skillref idref="spinal_anat_cross_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="spinal_gray_LO"><skillref idref="distinguish_white-gray_brain-spinal_SKILL" /><skillref idref="spinal_gray_SKILL" /><skillref idref="compare_axons_whvsgr_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="spinal_gross_LO"><skillref idref="spinal_gross_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="spinal_structures_LO"><skillref idref="spinal_tracts_SKILL" /><skillref idref="spinal_structures_SKILL" /><skillref idref="spinal_plexus_SKILL" /></objective_skills><objective_skills idref="synapse_cells_LO"><skillref idref="synapse_cells_SKILL" /></objective_skills></objectives>
