<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="nerv_loo_review"><head><title>Nervous Levels of Organization Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="abc3691606e21463e9d7231d5bd107f7a">Neurons are considered the simplest functional unit of nervous tissue. The soma (cell body) is the region of the neuron that integrates all the incoming information from the dendrites. On one side of the soma are short, tapering processes called dendrites (Greek, dendreon – tree). Most neurons have many, highly branched dendrites, although they may have as few as one. Dendrites receive information from other neurons and transfer it to the cell body. The soma is similar to the dendrites in that it can also receive inputs from other neurons. The incoming information is coded as electrical signals that are integrated to determine what, if any, response is required. If the incoming signal is large enough, it travels to the process on the other side of the soma called the axon. The axon functions like a cable, relaying electrical signals away from the cell body towards other neurons or cells (e.g. muscles, glands). The axon may travel to its target as a single fiber, but some axons form branches called collaterals, so that they can interact with not just one, but many target cells.</p><p id="ae6ee13d75d9640afb6226a0d1981251f">
Neurons are classified according to 2 different characteristics: their morphology (anatomical or structural features) and their function. Sensory (afferent) neurons are specialized for detection of sensory information (e.g. light, pressure, vibration, temperature, chemicals, etc.). They transduce physical and chemical stimuli into electrical signals and transfer this information from the periphery towards the central nervous system for processing. Interneurons (association neurons) are located entirely within the central nervous system (with the dendrites, soma and axons of the cell all residing within the CNS). Interneurons are also referred to as association neurons, in part because they are sandwiched between sensory and motor neurons where they integrate and distribute sensory information and coordinate motor output. Motor (efferent) neurons carry impulses or motor commands away from the central nervous system to effectors/target organs (e.g. muscles and glands). Most motor neurons have dendrites and cell bodies in the CNS and axons that exit the CNS to form peripheral nerves that travel to effectors (targets). Most neurons are surrounded by glial cells (neuroglia), the other cell type found in the nervous tissue. Glial cells are the supportive cells of the nervous system and are 10 times more numerous than neurons.</p><p id="dfed208682d4427f82641fbe9c1281ec">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this module. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="afd1a52814754d0c9ac1d9096c92df35"><li><p id="adc4ac0ac76df428785f773d82e142b9b">Classify the organs that are part of the nervous system as belonging to the central nervous system (CNS) or the peripheral nervous system (PNS).</p></li><li><p id="affe37c2228064d14b5e1c9f8f16aec24">Within a neuron, identify the soma, axon and dendrite and describe the main function of each region.</p></li><li><p id="acd92eba2b3564e82bec7355b7160d009">Identify neurons based on anatomical features: unipolar, bipolar, multipolar and anaxonic and based on functional properties: sensory, motor, interneuron.</p></li><li><p id="ae21047d459db404fb66804cebcec9150">List the four types of CNS glial cells and describe their function.</p></li><li><p id="ab7963be0b8d245e8b0dc3a47f712078e">List the two types of PNS glial cells and describe their function. Describe the anatomical relationship between the glial cells and the PNS.</p></li><li><p id="aff30bb4490594d26b912d52522fbd569">Compare the structure of myelinated vs. unmyelinated axons. Distinguish between white matter and gray matter.</p></li><li><p id="aaad3cb8732b04dc1afa84af30c3ab770">Describe the transmembrane potential or voltage across the cell membrane and how it is measured.</p></li><li><p id="ad88c6a5d8d3941ac9649d8849bcaa77f">Contrast the relative concentrations of ions in body solutions inside and outside of a cell (sodium, potassium, calcium and chloride ions).</p></li><li><p id="ab8e1e7af8f2e469d8fba93ac79374d36">Explain how four factors determine a neuron’s resting membrane potential.</p></li><li><p id="aa48c8009c8ab4a409e33287fa7a40518">Explain how a local electrical response in a neuron membrane is caused by stimulation.</p></li><li><p id="adaf58dc4e1bb4169acb7897bca3a347f">Interpret a graph showing the voltage vs. time relationship of an action potential.</p></li><li><p id="aaa9f5d68366a425e826d2e80c8f5a40b">Explain action potential.</p></li><li><p id="aed94dd5a96214e0bb1a10b84e41f3613">Identify the presynaptic and postsynaptic cells at a synapse.</p></li><li><p id="aaf9b45064c0c4fc188e0a2d3d01a3f4d">Explain synaptic transmission in terms of the structural and functional features of electrical and chemical synapses.</p></li><li><p id="af8ca1c61cb8a484f895d043f80e56675">Explain how a single neurotransmitter may have different effects at different postsynaptic cells.</p></li><li><p id="ac3f5a6f6189d4e0ab6059fbd517e880e">Explain temporal and spatial summation of synaptic potentials and discuss how action potentials differ from synaptic potentials.</p></li><li><p id="ab7aafb0323ea4f0c9725a140eddb3711">Identify the four classes of neurotransmitters and identify the most common excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmitters.</p></li><li><p id="aaddf6382976647b9873cd0b9398b3206">Explain the role of the autonomic nervous system as a motor division of the nervous system.</p></li><li><p id="afaa1a4e0497241d5ba35a4361b719228">Compare the somatic and autonomic nervous systems.</p></li><li><p id="aa3c3d2871c344d1b992df642dd6b433e">Contrast the anatomy of the parasympathetic and sympathetic systems.</p></li><li><p id="ac07c38dc81c04343b2f692dfcbb52d5a">Describe the local organization of each of the sympathetic and parasympathetic systems, including the pattern of innervation of target glands, organs, and tissues.</p></li><li><p id="aef786bd5975243e5a78f5fad6edee3ab">Describe major parasympathetic and sympathetic physiological effects on target organs.</p></li><li><p id="add12d868b23947879f3c3116953f4052">Identify the neurotransmitters released by preganglionic and postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems and describe their effects.</p></li><li><p id="ad03aab8e9d864b3a91959a8ec01fb08e">Describe examples of specific effectors dually innervated by the autonomic nervous system and explain how each branch influences function in a given effector.</p></li><li><p id="aa162f1fcc72d4161b4548d67091ddf74">Name examples of effectors innervated either by only the sympathetic branch or by only the parasympathetic branch of the autonomic nervous system and explain how that branch by itself influences function in a given effector.</p></li></ul><activity idref="nerv_loo_exam" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
