<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="nerv_sensory_review"><head><title>Nervous System: Sensory Functions Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="acb100a84079472ea0b94d185af32acf">Stimuli in the environment activate specialized receptors in the peripheral nervous system. The classification of receptors into types can be based on three different criteria: structure of the receptors, location of the receptors relative to the stimuli they sense, and by the types of stimuli to which they respond. Regardless of type, the function of these receptors is to transduce a stimulus from one form of energy (chemical, physical, etc.) into a change in the cell membrane potential that may or may not create an action potential. Collectively, the receptors and associated neurons that sense and process information related to our somesthetic senses are called the somatosensory system. Make sure you understand the different categories of receptors within this system.</p><p id="eb0247d0000d42cd88ae4797e088c9ea">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="dda5bcc06d7a42d1bdc44bc6f654b0de"><li><p id="abc75f0b998854bdaa0d453e8935feda6">Classify receptors based on structure, location relative to the stimulus, and types of signals they transduce.</p></li><li><p id="acf754646e45f4c2f8e14a5a2fb09c4ae">Explain the distribution of receptors involved in providing information for our general (somesthetic) senses.</p></li><li><p id="abb0b2bb0699a408891d5a3b2d7cbeafb">Describe the types of information (modality) detected by the receptors associated with the somesthetic senses and the phenomenon of adaptation.</p></li><li><p id="abce6dfca976f47e19f3e2ce04f4f2fcf">Explain pain function, nociceptor distribution, and distinguish the fiber types that carry their signals.</p></li><li><p id="ab77b92865d744fd08d768219d75f091a">Describe pain in terms of hyperalgesia, analgesia, and receptive field.</p></li><li><p id="af6cbbdedbb6b48c1b4f1f42f88b20f61">Define dermatome and explain how dermatomes can be used in neurological exams for diagnosing nerve damage.</p></li><li><p id="ac9b74829b1d24f5f8e3a1c4406c19882">Describe reflexes, reflex repsonses, and distinguish types of reflexes.</p></li><li><p id="aa5155a8abaa648faa2090ef91b7d5f7d">Identify and describe the functions of the accessory eye structures, the tunics, and the optical components of the eye.</p></li><li><p id="ab0cfdf447bd648c3ac99d0d7433e9ea9">Identify the muscles that help to coordinate eye movement.</p></li><li><p id="ab975cf0d99da48f1be765f73b1473b90">Describe the structures and functions of the eye.</p></li><li><p id="ad34c31786069458696015cd638e209d0">Explain how the path of light through the eye causes vision.</p></li><li><p id="acab3cf3afae14a369f44f4d679c95c7d">Trace the path of nerve impulses from the retina to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="adbc17b436119498db914d2698d9d3a52">Identify the hearing structures of the outer, middle and inner ear and describe their functions.</p></li><li><p id="abfb9e1ce8dc24255a448fbdfab8c511b">Describe how the various structures of the ear conduct and transduce sound.</p></li><li><p id="adadf859201b846538bd7bd39ec96afe4">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the ear to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="ac8828337403e4d6bbfeceaf6dc31c3c2">Distinguish between static and dynamic equilibrium, describe the structures involved, and their functions.</p></li><li><p id="adbe4eddd915a40c19f9e819a92babd79">Explain the gustation and describe the structures involved.</p></li><li><p id="ac96919c8449f4bc2b21e4ef5b99fe00c">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the gustatory receptors to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="ae4ccd11611e64172b7a555af89a786cc">Explain how odorants activate olfactory receptors.</p></li><li><p id="ab070b15a70d64bd8aec766e0ed2ed7ad">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the olfactory receptors to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="ae51ea27259ec409c95558b03a62a6202">Predict the types of problems that would occur in the body if the olfactory system was not functioning normally.</p></li></ul><activity idref="nerv_sensory_exam" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
