<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u14_m1_review"><head><title>Nervous System Structures and Functions Review and Assessment (UNUSED, can be archived/deleted)</title></head><body><p id="acce5255ad74490a84427249e0a872f8">The inside of the brain is characterized by regions of gray matter and white matter. The gray matter is mostly cell bodies, dendrites, and synapses and forms a cortex over the cerebrum and cerebellum, and also forms some nuclei deeper in the cerebrum. White matter is myelinated axons forming tracts. Like the spinal cord, the brain is covered and partially protected by connective tissue meninges. From outermost (bordering the skull bones) to the innermost (adjacent to the nervous tissue) they are the dura mater, arachnoid mater, and pia mater. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) is a clear, colorless liquid that bathes the external surfaces of the brain. CSF functions in cushioning and supporting the brain by buoyance, and in chemical stability of the brain, by transporting nutrients and wastes respectively. Make sure you understand the different brain regions and their functions.</p><p id="d782a406907442c0b86bf72635cff7b8">The spinal cord is a central nervous system structure that extends inferiorly from the brain stem and into the lower back. Throughout its length, it is enclosed within the spinal column, with the cord passing through the vertebral foramen of the vertebrae. Make sure you know the various spinal tracts, their locations and their functions.</p><activity idref="nerv_componenets" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
