<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u14_m2_review"><head><title>Nervous System Levels of Organization Review and Assessment (unused, can be archived/deleted)</title></head><body><p id="ccfe2e0d03dd40aa8516385344573867">Neurons are considered the simplest functional unit of nervous tissue. The soma (cell body) is the region of the neuron that integrates all the incoming information from the dendrites. On one side of the soma are short, tapering processes called dendrites (Greek, dendreon – tree). Most neurons have many, highly branched dendrites, although they may have as few as one. Dendrites receive information from other neurons and transfer it to the cell body. The soma is similar to the dendrites in that it can also receive inputs from other neurons. The incoming information is coded as electrical signals that are integrated to determine what, if any, response is required. If the incoming signal is large enough, it travels to the process on the other side of the soma called the axon. The axon functions like a cable, relaying electrical signals away from the cell body towards other neurons or cells (e.g. muscles, glands). The axon may travel to its target as a single fiber, but some axons form branches called collaterals, so that they can interact with not just one, but many target cells.</p><p id="a46efad509b049819fea6cdf5b06a03a">Neurons are classified according to 2 different characteristics: their morphology (anatomical or structural features) and their function. Sensory (afferent) neurons are specialized for detection of sensory information (e.g. light, pressure, vibration, temperature, chemicals, etc.). They transduce physical and chemical stimuli into electrical signals and transfer this information from the periphery towards the central nervous system for processing. Interneurons (association neurons) are located entirely within the central nervous system (with the dendrites, soma and axons of the cell all residing within the CNS). Interneurons are also referred to as association neurons, in part because they are sandwiched between sensory and motor neurons where they integrate and distribute sensory information and coordinate motor output. Motor (efferent) neurons carry impulses or motor commands away from the central nervous system to effectors/target organs (e.g. muscles and glands). Most motor neurons have dendrites and cell bodies in the CNS and axons that exit the CNS to form peripheral nerves that travel to effectors (targets). Most neurons are surrounded by glial cells (neuroglia), the other cell type found in the nervous tissue. Glial cells are the supportive cells of the nervous system and are 10 times more numerous than neurons.</p><activity idref="nerv_loo_exam" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
