<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_m03_bridge_intro">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>In the previous module, we introduced probability as way to mathematically describe
            uncertainty. We saw that the probability of an event is estimated by the relative
            frequency with which an event occurs in a long series of trials. </p>
        <p>In this module, we will shift our investigation to describing the probabilities of
                <em>all possible outcomes</em>, instead of the probability of just one outcome. </p>
        <p>We can think of all the possible outcomes as variable values to which we are assigning
            probabilities. The variable values, together with the assigned probabilities, make up a
                <em>probability distribution</em>. Here is an example of a probability distribution. </p>
        <example>
            <p>Consider the variable “blood type.” This is a categorical variable with variable values
                A, B, AB, or O. Using relative frequencies from large samples of randomly chosen
                individuals, we can estimate the probability of choosing a person with a given blood
                type. Using relative frequencies, the Stanford University's Blood Center
                (bloodcenter.stanford.edu), gives the probabilities of human blood types in the United
                States as follows: </p>
            <image src="../webcontent/image017.png" alt="Here are the probabilities given in
&quot;Blood Type: Probability&quot; format:
            O: 0.45;
            A: 0.41;
            B: 0.10;
            AB: 0.04;"/>
            <p>This table is an example of a probability distribution. Each variable value is assigned a
                probability.  </p>
        </example>
        
        <p>Probability distributions for categorical variables, like in the example above, will not
            be investigated in this module. Instead, the focus of this module will be on probability
            distributions for <em>quantitative variables</em>, because such distributions will be
            used in statistical inference. Examples of such variables are “number of times a college
            student changes major” or “weight of a student.” </p>
        <p>When the outcomes are quantitative, we call the variable a <term>random variable</term>.
            In this module, we discuss the probability distributions of <term>Discrete Random
                Variables</term> and <term>Continuous Random Variables</term>. Discrete random
            variables have values that can be listed and often can be counted. Continuous random
            variables can take any value in an interval and are often measurements. For example, the
            variable “number of times a college student changes major” is a discrete random
            variable. The (exact) weight of a person is a continuous random variable. </p>
        <p>Comment: The word “random” here means that the outcomes are uncertain in the short run
            but have a regular distribution or predictable pattern in the long run. In statistics,
            we reserve the term “random variable” for quantitative variables. This can be a bit
            confusing, since categorical variables can also describe random outcomes. </p>
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_bridgeintro_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <p>Now we will investigate the probability distributions for
            discrete random variables.</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
