<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>

<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_m03_bridge3">
    <head>
        <title>Random Variables (3 of 3)</title>
        <objref idref="use_probability_distributions"/>
        <objref idref="describe_models_shape_center_spread"/>
    </head>
    <body>
       


        <example>
            <p>Let’s return to the example of estimating the percentage of U.S. adults who favor the
                death penalty. If we collect a random sample of U.S. adults, we are uncertain how
                well the sample really estimates the true percentage of the population supporting
                the death penalty. We are uncertain because we don’t know how much variation there
                will be in random samples. </p>
            <p>Reputable polling organizations will state a probability with their results.
                Frequently, they report a probability of 0.95 that an estimate from their sample
                will come within 3 percentage points of the true population value. We will learn
                more about this later. For now, let’s focus on creating a probability model using
                random samples to determine the probability of different sample outcomes. </p>
            <p>Let’s look at the possible results from a sample of 10 people and define X as the
                number in the sample who support the death penalty. (Of course, reputable polling
                organizations will collect a much larger sample. For purposes of illustration, we
                will work with a small sample size of 10.) </p>
            <p>To create a probability model, we need to repeat this random sampling many, many
                times. We will use a computer to simulate this process by taking 5,000 samples of 10
                people at a time from a hypothetical population. Note that in order to run this
                simulation, we have to make an assumption about the average number of supporters we
                will see over the long run. For this example, we assumed that the average was 6.2. </p>
            <p>Here are the results of our 5,000 samples. We will use the relative frequency to
                assign a probability to each outcome. </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image011.png" alt="There are two rows in this table,
labeled &quot;X = # supporting in sample of 10&quot; and &quot;P(X) = Relative Frequency = (Sample
Count)/5000.&quot; We will present the data in this table by column, in &quot;X: P(X)&quot; format:
            0: 0;
            1: 0.001;
            2: 0.007;
            3: 0.031;
            4: 0.092;
            5: 0.181;
            6: 0.255;
            7: 0.227;
            8: 0.142;
            9: 0.053;
            10: 0.009;"/>
            <p>According to this probability model, is it likely that we will collect a random
                sample in which 3 or fewer support the death penalty? </p>
            <p>P(3 or fewer) = P(X=0) + P(X=1) + P(X=2) + P(X=3) = 0 + 0.001 + 0.007 + 0.031 =
                0.039, so it is unlikely that we would get a random sample of 10 people in which 3
                or fewer support the death penalty. </p>
            <p>Here you see the probability distribution as a histogram. Using technology, we find
                that the mean is 6.21 and the standard deviation is 1.53. The shape is approximately
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101120T161511-0500" comment="consider removing underscores from graphic below"?>normal.<?oxy_comment_end?>
            </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image012.png" alt="A histogram of the data
in the above table. The vertical axis is labeled &quot;Relative Frequency of sample_count,&quot;
and the horizontal axis is labeled &quot;sample_count.&quot; Here is the description of the histogram,
going from left to right across the horizontal axis: The histogram is in a normal shape, so it grows
from 0 to a peak at x = 6 (with Frequency of 0.255). From there, it decays back to zero."/>
            <p>What is the probability that a sample will give results that fall within one standard
                deviation of the mean of 6.21? </p>
            <p>Samples with 5, 6, or 7 people (out of 10) supporting the death penalty fall within
                one standard deviation of the mean. </p>
            <p>P(sample has 5, 6, or 7 supporters) = P(X=5) + P(X=6) + P(X=7) = 0.181 + 0.255 +
                0.227 = 0.663. </p>
            <p>So there is a 66.3% probability that a sample gives results within one standard
                deviation of the overall mean of 6.21. Notice that this is very close to the
                probability of 0.68 predicted by the Standard Deviation Rule for normal
                distributions that we discussed in the unit on Exploratory Data Analysis. </p>
        </example>
       
            <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_bridge3_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>In each of the examples we have discussed in this module we were able to list the
                    outcomes. When we can list the outcomes, it is easy to use a table to list the
                    probability for each outcome. In the next module we will look at examples in
                    which outcomes can be any number in an interval, so it will be impossible to
                    list the outcomes and corresponding probabilities. </p>
                <p>As we’ll see, when any number in an interval can be an outcome, we assign
                    probabilities using areas under the curve defined by the probability model. We
                    will extend the previous example to just give you a “taste” of how this might
                    work before we move into a more in-depth treatment in the next module. </p>
                <p>In this histogram, the width of each bar is 1, so the area of each bar has the
                    same numerical value as the height (area = height * width = height * 1). So in
                    the histogram, the area of the shaded bars can also be used to find
                    probabilities. For example, the shaded area is also 0.663. </p>
                <p>We have also graphed a normal curve on top of the histogram. You can see the area
                    under the curve closely approximates the area in the bars. When we use area to
                    represent probability, we will not worry about the vertical scale. But we will
                    make sure that the total area under the curve is 1, so that the area is a
                    mathematically correct probability
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101120T161537-0500" comment="consider removing underscores from graphic below"?>model.<?oxy_comment_end?>
                </p>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image013.png" alt="The same histogram as the
previous one. The bars for sample_count = 5, 6, and 7 have been shaded red. In addition, a normal curve
has been drawn on top, and for almost every bar on the histogram the curve goes through the flat top of
the bar, showing that it closely approximates the area in the bar."/>
                <p>In the next module, we will develop in more depth the idea of using the area
                    under a curve as a probability model. This idea is used when outcomes can be any
                    number in an interval, or when the area gives a good approximation of the
                    discrete probabilities for listed outcomes. </p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
