<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_m03_bridge1">
    <head>
        <title>Random Variables (1 of 3)</title>
        <objref idref="use_probability_distributions"/>
    </head>
    <body>
      
        <section>
            <title>Probability Distribution for Discrete Random Variables</title>
            <body>
                <p>In this section, we will work with probability distributions for discrete random
                    variables. Here is an example: </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <example>
            <p>Consider the random variable “The number of times a student changes major.” </p>
            <p>(For convenience, it is common practice to say: Let X be the random variable “The
                number of changes in major,” or “X = number of changes in major” so that from this
                point we can simply refer to X, with the understanding of what it represents.). </p>
            <p>Here is the probability distribution of (or, a probability model for) the random
                variable X: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image001.png" alt="Here is the distribution data
given in &quot;X=# changes in major: Probability for that #&quot;:
             0: 0.135;
             1: 0.271;
             2: 0.271;
             3: 0.180;
             4: 0.090;
             5: 0.036;
             6: 0.012;
             7: 0.003;
             8: 0.002;"/>
            <p><em style="italic">Here is what this tells us: </em>
            </p>
            <p>For a randomly selected student, we cannot predict how many times he or she will
                change majors, but there is a predictable pattern described by the probability
                distribution (or model) above. So this is a random variable, for which we are
                assuming the values range from 0 to 8. (In reality, a negligible proportion of
                students change majors more than 8 times.) The table provides a way to assign
                probabilities to outcomes. Note that if you add up the probabilities of all possible
                outcomes (0.135 + 0.271 + … + 0.002) we get exactly 1, which is not surprising
                (since one of the possible outcomes 0, 1, … 8 will occur for sure). </p>
            <p>Another way to represent the probability distribution of a random variable is a
                probability
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101120T110140-0500" comment="Consider changing the bottom line on the graphic below to say &quot;Number of Changes in Major&quot;

(Not a big travesty to leave as is if it&apos;s too much trouble to change it)."?>histogram<?oxy_comment_end?>. </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image015.png" alt="A histogram, in which the
vertical axis is titled &quot;Probability&quot; and the Horizontal axis is labeled &quot;Number
of Major Changes.&quot; Moving from left to right across the horizontal axis, the values increase to
the mode (peak) at x=1 and x=2, then slowly decay to near zero. This histogram represents the
same data as the table above."/>
            <p>The horizontal axis accounts for the range of all possible values of the random
                variable (in our case, 0-8), and the vertical axis represents the probabilities of
                those values. </p>
            <p>The heights of the bars add to 1, which is not surprising since the heights represent
                probabilities.</p>
        </example>
        <p>Let’s summarize the features of a probability distribution (also called a probability
            model): </p>
        <ul>
            <li>The outcomes described by the model are <em>random</em>. This means that individual
                outcomes are uncertain, but there is a regular, predictable distribution of outcomes
                in a large number of repetitions. </li>
            <li>The model provides a way of assigning probabilities to all possible outcomes. </li>
            <li>The probability of each possible outcome can be viewed as the relative frequency of
                the outcome in a large number of repetitions, so like any other probability, it can
                be any value between 0 and 1. </li>
            <li>The sum of the probabilities of all possible outcomes must be 1. </li>
        </ul>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>At this point you must be asking yourself, "How do we generate a probability
                    distribution of a (discrete) random variable?" </p>
                <p>Probability distributions can be generated empirically through repeated trials.
                    We record the relative frequency of each outcome then look at the distribution
                    of the relative frequencies for all possible outcomes. We can also use a
                    mathematical model to represent a probability distribution. In this case, we
                    make assumptions about how outcomes will be distributed. In other words, we use
                    a mathematical formula to describe the predicted relative frequencies for all
                    possible outcomes. </p>
                <p>At any case, the focus of this module is not on how to generate a probability
                    distribution, but rather on how to gain useful information from a given
                    distribution. </p>
                <p>Let’s return to the example and do exactly that. </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <example>
            <p>Recall the probability distribution of the random variable X = number of changes in
                major: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image001.png" alt="Here is the distribution data
given in &quot;X=# changes in major: Probability P(X=# changes in major)&quot;:
                0: 0.135;
                1: 0.271;
                2: 0.271;
                3: 0.180;
                4: 0.090;
                5: 0.036;
                6: 0.012;
                7: 0.003;
                8: 0.002;"/>
            <p>Let’s see what kinds of probability questions we can answer using it. </p>
            <p>(a) What is the probability that a college student will change majors at most once? </p>
            <p>The phrase “at most once” means either the student never changed majors (X = 0) or
                the student changed majors once (X = 1). Therefore, to find this probability, we
                need to add up the probabilities that are highlighted in the table: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image001highlighted.png" alt="The same table as above, except
that the cells representing P(X=0) = 0.135 and P(X=1) = 0.271 have been highlighted."/>
            <p>So, </p>
            <p>P(a college student changes majors at most once) = P(X=0) + P(X=1) = 0.135 + 0.271 =
                0.406 </p>
            <p>So the probability that a randomly selected college student will change majors at
                most once is about 0.406. We can also say that about 40.6% of the time, a randomly
                selected college student will change majors at most once. </p>
            <p>(b) John’s parents are concerned that he has decided to change his major for the
                second time. John claims that he is not unusual. What is the probability that a
                randomly selected college student will change his major as often as or more often
                than John? </p>
            <p>To answer the question about John, we need know the probability that a randomly
                selected student will change his major 2 or more times. We need to add together the
                probabilities shaded in the table. </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image002.png" alt="The probabilities shaded are P(X=2) =
0.271,
            P(X=3) = 0.180;
            P(X=4) = 0.090;
            P(X=5) = 0.036;
            P(X=6) = 0.012;
            P(X=7) = 0.003;
            P(X=8) = 0.002;
            P(X=9) = 0.000;"/>
            <p>P(change major 2 or more times) = P(X=2) + P(X=3) + … + P(X=8) = 0.594 </p>
            <p>Here is another way to figure this out. We can use the idea that all of the
                probabilities together make up 100% of the possibilities. So if we add up all the
                probabilities in the table we should get 1. Now if we figure out the probability
                that someone changes majors 0 or 1 times, we can just subtract this from 1 to find
                the probability that someone changes majors 2 or more times. </p>
            <p>P(change major 2 or more times) = 1– [P(X=0) + P(X=1)] = 1 – [0.135 + 0.271] = 0.594 </p>
            <p>Do you think John has given a convincing argument that he is not unusual? Yes! 59% of
                the time, a college student will change majors as often as or more often than John
                did. Stating this same result in terms of probability, we might say, “There is a 59%
                probability that a randomly selected college student will change majors 2 or more
                times while in college.” </p>
            <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_bridge1_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_bridge1_tutor2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <p>We found that changing a major 2 or more times is not very unusual, since it happens
                about 59% of the time. So … </p>
            <p>(c) How often would John need to change his major to be considered unusual? </p>
            <p>One way to answer this question is to just a make a judgment call about what we might
                consider “unusual” based on the table. For example, we might notice that the
                probability that a student will change majors 5 or more times is about 5%. </p>
            <table rowstyle="plain">
                <tr>
                    <td>P(change majors 5 or more times)</td>
                    <td>= P(X=5) + P(X=6) + P(X=7) + P(X=8) </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td/>
                    <td>= 0.036 + 0.012 + 0.003 + 0.002 = 0.053</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p>An event that occurs only 5% of the time is pretty unusual. </p>
        </example>
        <p>Are there other ways to more definitively determine what might be considered unusual?
            Well, we might use a measure of center, such as the mean, to determine a “typical”
            number of times that students change majors. Values that are two standard deviations
            above the mean could be used to identify unusual behavior. We will come back to this
            question after we have developed an understanding of mean and standard deviation for a
            probability distribution. </p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
