<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="Brain_1"><head><title>Overview of the Brain</title><objref idref="describe_brain_LO" /></head><body><p id="caf171b3339d4999ba90f203366651a0">The large brain of humans is perhaps the most important evolutionary advance for the species. At the minimum, it is the characteristic most of us consider the distinguishing characteristic of a human. This module outlines the structural and functional relationships of the human brain.</p><image id="f830e8fae4ca4418957f3d25130ac37e" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_63.jpg" alt="Superior view of the brain, pointing out the Frontal lobe, Central sulcus, Parietal lobe, Occipital lobe, and Longitudinal fissure" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="b77a53dc1531430787b787ba781fedff">Superior view of the brain. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="ffaab95a256b4cc3b47720a910f2f0e7" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_64.jpg" alt="Lateral view of the brain, pointing out the Temporal lobe, Central sulcus, Gyri, Cerebellum, and Cerebrum" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="c4e38dc5a954468b9ff08fb50114f9b7">Lateral view of the brain. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a284cc8141264e5aabdb93dc8055c9bf">The dominant portion of the human brain is the cerebrum. It is the large upper part of the brain, distinguished by the <term>gyri</term> (folds) and <term>sulci</term> (folds) of the surface. The cerebrum is clearly split into left and right <term>hemispheres</term>; the split is the deep <term>longitudinal fissure</term>. The cerebrum sits atop and around the <term>midbrain</term>, which leads into the <term>brainstem</term>. Situated essentially behind the midbrain and under the cerebrum is the distinctive <term>cerebellum</term>.</p><p id="facc8635af7a463f86d1fdedd035145c">The inside of the brain is characterized by regions of <term>gray matter</term> and <term>white matter</term>. The gray matter is mostly cell bodies, dendrites, and synapses and forms a cortex over the cerebrum and cerebellum, and also forms some nuclei deeper in the cerebrum. White matter is myelinated axons forming tracts. (These definitions and components of gray and white matter are similar to the ones for the spinal cord, although their arrangement will be different as you will discover later in this unit.)</p><p id="e60f021ff30c4f64bb2ddee4a1e1df5e">The cerebral white matter tracts are classified as</p><ul id="b56196098df448569800659afae3a096"><li><p id="ae6bb1a4fb5ca4b358fa23714e7ae581c">Projection tracts - from higher to lower, from cerebrum to brainstem and spinal cord</p></li><li><p id="aefdd1baf36e541fcb314c2f71d3fe2be">Commissural - across hemispheres</p></li><li><p id="ad3ca203d9cbb4150865859e904fa8842">Association - within same hemisphere</p></li></ul><p id="d48238fe26a542efa3304a6960fefe3f">The gray matter of the cerebral cortex includes:</p><ul id="bff17e3119664680b680f440997284ec"><li><p id="afb329bd4da014555abd7f87508fcf40b">Stellate cells - receive sensory input and process information locally</p></li><li><p id="aec156b0f67ae470988f02f44797f08d1">Pyramidal cells - extend to other parts of the CNS</p></li><li><p id="af59fda2c5ae3487caff6b80d0cb820eb">Neocortex - 6 layered tissue of recent evolutionary origin</p></li></ul><wb:inline idref="describe_brain_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
