<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="Brain_5">
	<head>
		<title>Brain Regions</title>
		<objref idref="identify_brainregions_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Higher brain functions are ones generally assigned to regions in the forebrain. 
			Most of these locations were discovered by studying people who had lesions in 
			these regions, and as a result, were defective in one of these functions.</p>

		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_83.jpg"
			alt="Cerebral lateralization: assignment of some specific tasks to each hemisphere.">
			<caption>Cerebral lateralization: assignment of some specific tasks to each hemisphere.
				This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United
				States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->

		<p>For most functions, there is a localization between the left and right hemispheres,
			called <term>cerebral lateralization</term>. The left hemisphere generally is stronger
			in motor, mathematical, and language skills, while the right hemisphere generally
			emphasizes spatial and tactile skills. The two hemispheres are connected by the
				<term>corpus callosum</term>.</p>
		<p><term>Cognition</term> is awareness perception, thinking, knowledge, and memory. Its most
			basic definition is the integration of sensory and motor systems. The cerebral lobes
			contain most of the regions associated with cognition. An important memory forming
			center is the hippocampus.</p>
		<p><term>Emotion</term> is deeper feeling, resulting from memory and learned behavior. Many
			emotions are rooted in the hypothalamus and amygdala.</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_84.jpg"
			alt="Location of the motor (precentral gyrus) and sensory (postcentral gyrus).">
			<caption>Location of the motor (precentral gyrus) and sensory (postcentral gyrus).<!-- This
				work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States
					(<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).--></caption>
		</image>

	<!--	<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_85.jpg" alt="Orientation of the sensory cortex.">
			<caption>Orientation of the sensory cortex. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->

		<p><term>Sensation</term> is the perception of one of the senses. Here, we will simply point
			out the importance of the <term>post-central gyrus</term> for the interpretation of
				<term>general senses</term>. General senses are ones from widely distributed
			receptors, such as touch, pressure, temperature, pain. These pathways end at the
			post-central gyrus, or sensory cortex. The cortex exhibits <term>somatotophy</term>:
			point by point correspondence of body locations to brain locations. The point by point 
			correspondence gives more area of the cortex to regions that are well innervated with 
			sensory receptors, such as fingers, and face; meanwhile regions that do not have large
			sensory innervation have correspondingly smaller areas on the sensory cortex.</p>

		<p>The <activity_link idref="NervousSensory_Reflexes_1" target="new">special
				senses</activity_link> are interpreted in their own specialized cortical regions,
			and are discussed in another section of this course.</p>

		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_86.jpg" alt="Orientation of the motor cortex.">
			<caption>Orientation of the motor cortex. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->

		<p>Motor control refers to the initiation and proper coordination of the movement of a
			muscle. For a skeletal muscle, the intent to contract a skeletal muscle begins in motor
			association area (frontal lobe). The signal is then sent to the <term>precental
				gyrus</term> or <term>primary motor area</term>, which is the origin of the upper
			motor neuron. The precentral gyrus also exhibits somatotophy. Body areas, such as lips
			and fingers, which have fine motor control, have a large area dedicated on the primary
			motor cortex while areas that do not have fine control have a correspondingly smaller
			area.</p>
		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_87.jpg" alt="Locations of major language centers.">
			<caption>Locations of major language centers. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->
		<p>Language includes abilities such as reading, writing, speaking, and comprehending words.
			At least two major areas are involved in the recognition and formation of language.
				<term>Wernicke’s area</term>, within the parietal and temporal lobes, is involved in
			the recognition of language. <term>Broca’s area</term> is involved in the formation of
			words.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="identify_brainregions_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="identify_brainregions_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
