<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="Brain_2"><head><title>Meninges, Cerebrospinal Fluid and Blood Supply</title><objref idref="explain_csf_LO" /></head><body><p id="eacbe7205eb1411eb99503ecf1475d90">Like the spinal cord, the brain is covered and partially protected by connective tissue
<term>meninges</term>. From outermost (bordering the skull bones) to the
innermost (adjacent to the nervous tissue) they are the <term>dura
mater</term>, <term>arachnoid mater</term>, and <term>pia mater</term>.
The dura mater folds into two layers, a periosteal layer fused to the skull bones, and a
meningeal layer. In some areas, these layers are separated by a dural sinus, a space
used to collect blood. Some areas may also contain a <term>subarachnoid space</term>
or a <term>subdural space</term>.</p><image id="afad557c89534206b2525e14ec9bf11f" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_67.jpg" alt="Cross-section of top of the head; Meninges." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af11ddd34418f4593b7f83f6be8925e6e">Meninges. </p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d2087a7f9e4c4f2287722152cee74be3"><term>Cerebrospinal fluid</term> (CSF) is a clear, colorless liquid that bathes
the external surfaces of the brain. It is constantly produced, flows through the network
of <term>ventricles</term>, and is reabsorbed. CSF functions in cushioning and supporting 
the brain by buoyance, and in chemical stability of the brain, by transporting nutrients 
and wastes respectively.</p><wb:inline idref="describe_brain_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="b65ddf0735b441feb0c756ac766abc0d">The ependymal cells lining the ventricles produce the CSF. Then the CSF flows throughout
the brain in the ventricles. Each cerebral hemisphere contains a <term>lateral ventricle</term>. Each lateral ventricle drains through an <term>interventricular foramen</term> into the <term>third ventricle</term>. The
third ventricle sits in the midbrain region. The CSF then flows into the <term>cerebral aqueduct</term> to the <term>fourth ventricle</term>.
Before being reabsorbed, the CSF enters one of two <term>lateral apertures</term>
or a <term>median aperture</term>, and then fills the subarachnoid space.
Reabsorption of CSF occurs there by the <term>arachoid villi</term> and enters
the venous blood. </p><image id="e4d2b3caeb3546dd852eaff57d8651a4" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_69.jpg" alt="View of the brain showing CSF flow through the ventricles." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="adaee8bca6e9244069ba1db5cfd228692">CSF flow through the ventricles. </p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b136404c0a074062b297a4347c6de247">The <term>choriod plexus </term>is the network of blood vessels and ependymal
cells on surface of the ventricles. The ependymal cells of this choroid plexus secrete
the CSF. Overall the close proximity of ependymal cells and blood vessels create a <term>blood-brain barrier</term> (BBB). The brain
requires large amounts of oxygen and glucose but other items in blood may harm it, hence
the barrier. At the capillaries there is a BBB of tight endothelial cells and basement
membrane; at the choriod plexus the blood-CSF barrier due to tight junctions between ependymal
cells</p><p id="cf528bdb3138403bbd2fb83449bf0b46">Next, the main structural areas of the brain will be surveyed with some of their major
functions. We will go in general order of most primitive brain region to most
evolutionary advanced region, or, in other words, from basic functions to more advanced
functions.</p><wb:inline idref="explain_csf_lbd_assessment" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/explain_csf_lbd_layout.xml</param></wb:inline><wb:inline idref="explain_csf_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
