<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="spinal_cord_3a">
	<head>
		<title>Spinal Cord Communication</title>
		<!--<objref idref="spinal_general"/>-->
		<objref idref="spinal_structures_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The spinal cord acts as a conduit for information traveling up and down its length. But
			because most of this information has to either exit the spinal cord to send signals to
			peripheral tissues (<term>efferent transmission</term>), or information from peripheral tissues needs
			to be carried into the spinal cord (<term>afferent transmission</term>), there must be appropriate
			structures for these types of transmission to occur. It is the 31 pairs of spinal nerves
			and their related structures that provide the pathways for this interaction.</p>
		
		<p>Sensory and motor fibers enter and exit the cord via <term>rootlets</term> that arise from both the
			posterior and anterior aspects of the cord. Anterior rootlets carry motor
			information out of the spinal cord (i.e. they contain efferent fibers) while the
			posterior rootlets carry sensory information into the spinal cord (i.e. they contain
			afferent fibers). Several posterior rootlets merge together to form the posterior root,
			while several anterior rootlets similarly converge to form the anterior root.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_95.jpg"
			alt="Rootlets and the passing of information to and from the spinal cord.">
			<caption>Rootlets and the passing of information to and from the spinal cord. <!--This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).--></caption>
		</image>
		<p>Along the posterior root is a <term>ganglion</term>, where cell bodies of many of the
			sensory neurons are found. These are unipolar neurons, such that their dendrites extend
			out to the peripheral tissues, and their axons project into the dorsal horn of the
			spinal cord, where they synapse. These unipolar peripheral neurons are considered first
			order neurons in the sensory pathway, while the neurons they synapse with in the
			posterior horn are considered the second order neurons of the sensory pathway. It is the axons of these second order neurons that make up the various ascending white matter tracts.</p>
		
		
		<p>The anterior root does not contain a ganglion. This is because motor control is typically
			a two neuron pathway. It starts with an upper motor neuron, whose cell body is in the
			cerebral cortex or gray matter of the brainstem. This neuron projects its axon via a descending white
			matter tract to a point in the spinal cord where it synapses in the ventral horn with a
			lower motor neuron. The cell body of the lower motor neuron is in the gray matter of the
			spinal cord, and it projects its axon out one of the anterior rootlets and through the
			anterior root. Ganglia are only found where neuron cell bodies are outside the CNS.</p>
		<p>Distal to the posterior root ganglion, the fibers of the anterior and posterior root
			merge together and pass through the dura to become the spinal nerve. Because the spinal
			nerves contain both sensory and motor fibers, they are considered a <term>mixed nerve</term>, as
			opposed to either a sensory or motor nerve.</p>
		<p>Just distal to the intervertebral foramen of the spinal column, the spinal nerve branches
			into <term>rami</term> (singular: <term>ramus</term>). In general, the posterior ramus communicates
			with structures posterior to the cord, while the anterior ramus communicates with
			structures anterior to the cord. In spinal nerves T1-L2, the anterior ramus gives rise
			to a communicating ramus that communicates with the sympathetic ganglia in the region. The sympathetic motor pathway involves two motor neurons, so this ganglion houses the second motor neuron’s cell body. 
			In various regions of the body, the anterior rami from several spinal nerves join
			together and then branch again, in a complex network of nerves called a <term>plexus</term>.</p>
		
		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_X1.jpg"
			alt="Rami and their communication functions.">
			<caption>Rami and their communication functions. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->
		<wb:inline idref="spinal_tracts_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<!--<p>&lt;!-\- IMAGE CAPTION: Figure 5: We would also need to label rootlets on the upper
			portion of this figure.-\-/&gt;</p>-->
		<!--<p>&lt;!-\- IMAGE CAPTION: Figure 6: NO CAPTION PROVIDED.-\-/&gt;</p>-->
		
		<wb:inline idref="spinal_structures_sc1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="spinal_structures_digt" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
