<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="spinal_cord_1">
	<head>
		<title>Overview of the Spinal Cord</title>
		<objref idref="spinal_gross_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The nervous system is critical to many of our homeostatic feedback loops. In most of
			these loops, the structures of the nervous system make up more than one component, and
			carry out more than one function in these loops. For example, specialized nerve endings
			often act as sensors (<term>receptors</term>), information is carried along nerves and/or <term>tracts</term> of
			the spinal cord, integration occurs within the CNS, and spinal cord tracts and nerves
			carry the responding information back out to the effectors. The spinal cord is a nervous
			system structure dedicated to relaying information from the periphery to the brain and
			back, as well as carrying out certain levels of integration, such as those found in many
			reflexes. The structure of the spinal cord aids it in carrying out these relaying and
			integrative functions.</p>
	
		<p>The spinal cord is a central nervous system structure that extends inferiorly from the
			brain stem and into the lower back. Throughout its length, it is enclosed within the
			<term>spinal column</term>, with the cord passing through the <term>vertebral foramen</term> of the <term>vertebrae</term>. In
			an adult, the spinal cord itself terminates at a point called the <term>medullary cone</term>, at approximately the level of the first <term>lumbar</term> vertebrae (L1). Below the
			medullary cone, the <term>vertebral canal</term> contains a bundle of nerve roots called the <term>cauda
			equina</term>.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_91.jpg"
			alt="Spinal cord detail.">
			<caption>Spinal cord. <!--This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).--></caption>
		</image>
		<p>This figure shows other important features of the spinal cord, many of them related to the
			spinal cord's function of relaying information. Starting between the base of the skull
			and the first <term>cervical</term> vertebrae, and continuing into the <term>sacral
				region</term> of the spinal column, a pair of spinal nerves extend from the spinal
			cord (although information is transmitted in both directions on sensory and motor
			neurons within these mixed nerves). All but the first <term>spinal nerve</term> (C1)
			pass through the <term>intervertebral foramen</term> of the spinal cord, whereas spinal
			nerve C1 passes between the occipital bone and vertebrae C1. In all there are 31 pairs of
			spinal nerves that carry information to and from the spinal cord and the periphery of
			the body. Note that not all of the spinal nerves arise from the cord at the level of the
			vertebrae between which they pass. This is most obvious when considering those spinal
			nerves arising in the lower lumbar and sacral regions. The nerve roots for these nerves
			arise from the spinal cord at, or near, the medullary cone, which you will recall is
			near the L1 vertebrae. These roots are contained within the cauda equina until passing
			out of the spinal column. Because the spinal nerve roots don’t always originate at the
			level of the vertebrae that they pass through, the segments of the spinal cord are named
			for the spinal nerve to which they give rise. For example, segment S2 of the spinal cord
			would be located near the T12 vertebrae.</p>
		<p>Because the spinal cord terminates near vertebrae L1, and there is a lot of body tissue that
			needs to be innervated below this level, there are a significant number of nerves
			arising from the lower aspect of the spinal cord. This leads to an area of increased
			spinal cord thickness in the <term>lumbosacral regions</term> of the spinal cord
			(corresponding to a region associated with the inferior thoracic vertebrae) called the
				<term>lumbar enlargement</term>. There is a corresponding <term>cervical
				enlargement</term> in the cervical segments that give rise to nerves innervating the
			upper limbs.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="spinal_gross_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body><wb:inline idref="spinal_gross_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="spinal_gross_sc" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline></body>
		</section>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
