<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m1_intro_01">
	<head>
		<title>Introduction to the Urinary System</title>

		<objref idref="urinary_major_functions"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Major Functions of the Urinary System</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the major functions of the urinary system</p>-->
				<p>Usually, when we think of the urinary system, we think about getting rid of waste
					products in our urine. The urinary system, however, involves more than just
					waste removal. The urinary system plays many important roles in
					the maintenance of homeostasis. This means this system helps to regulate the
					internal conditions of the whole body. For instance, if the body is dehydrated, the body will
					function to conserve the liquid. Consequently, the body does not produce large
					volumes of urine. Much of this proper maintenance of homeostasis is a function
					of the kidneys. </p>
				<p>The roles of the urinary system include detoxifying harmful substances (or
					toxins), maintaining water levels, maintaining appropriate levels of some
					vitamins and minerals, maintaining acid-base and electrolyte balances, and
					interacting with the circulatory system to help regulate blood pressure and red
					blood cell count. In a three-way interaction with both the respiratory and the
					circulatory systems, the urinary system helps stabilize blood oxygen and carbon
					dioxide levels. </p>
				<p>The final outcome of the above functions of the urinary system is excretion.
					Excretion is the removal of wastes generated by the normal processes of cell
					metabolism in the body. Such metabolic wastes include urea, uric acid,
					creatinine, creatine, bilirubin, and ammonia. The metabolic wastes originate in
					the cells throughout the body and are moved into the blood. If allowed to
					accumulate, these wastes would be toxic to the body. All of the organs of the
					urinary system are involved in the removal of these metabolic wastes by
					contributing to the process of excretion. Other body systems that are also
					involved in excretion are the respiratory system, integumentary system (the
					skin), and the digestive system. Excretion and elimination are two similar
					processes. Excretion specifically referes to the removal of the waste products
					of metabolism from the body. Elimination is the explulsion of undigested or
					unmetabolized waste products from the body. </p>

				<section purpose="didigetthis">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_function_urinary_sys" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_function_urinary_sys_1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
					</body>
				</section>




				<section>
					<title>Let's Summarize</title>
					<body>

						<p>The major functions of the urinary system include:</p>
						<ul>
							<li><em style="bold">Excretion of waste products</em> such as urea, uric
								acid, creatinine, bilirubin, and ammonia.</li>
							<li><em style="bold">Maintenance of homeostasis</em>, or the ability for
								the urinary system to regulate its internal conditions.</li>
							<li><em style="bold">Detoxifying harmful substances</em> in the
								body</li>
							<li><em style="bold">Maintenance of proper water levels</em>, vitamin
								and mineral levels, and acid-base and electrolyte levels</li>
							<li>Interaction with the respiratory and the circulatory systems, to <em
									style="bold">help stabilize blood oxygen and carbon dioxide
									levels</em>.</li>
						</ul>

					</body>
				</section>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
