<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="distributions_conc">
	<head>
		<title>Wrap-Up (Distributions)</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>You have now completed the module on examining distributions, which is the first of two modules
			within the EDA unit. You've seen how, by using graphs and numbers, we can bring to light
			all the information that is stored in the data about the variable of interest. Another
			important point is that graphs and numbers are powerful only when accompanied by their
			interpretation in the context of the problem. You are now ready to practice your
			knowledge by going through your first StatTutor exercise, and then doing a quick
			checkpoint activity. </p>
		<p>One of the first few screens in StatTutor will have a link to download the dataset for this
			StatTutor exercise. When you click that link, a pop-up window will appear asking if you
			want to open or save the file. Make sure you click "Save," which will allow you to save
			the file to your hard drive. Then find the downloaded file and double-click it to open
			it if you're using R, StatCrunch, Minitab, or Excel, or transfer it to your calculator if you're
			using the TI Calculator.</p>
		
		
		 	<!--<activity idref="survey" purpose="lab"/>-->
		<activity idref="ctat2_m1_stattutor" purpose="lab"/>
		
		

		<section>
			<title>End of Section Questions</title>
			<body>
				<p>Before you do the checkpoint activity, please evaluate your understanding of the
					learning objectives for the Examining Distributions module and use the first
						<em>My Response</em> link below to ask any questions you might have about
					the material that you would like the instructor to address. Your questions can
					be for clarification of the material or further insight. Your self-evaluation
					and questions may also shape the discussions in class.</p>
				<p>Your response will not be graded, but will be available for your instructor to
					read. Answering these questions may also shape the discussions in class.</p>
				<activity idref="distributions_conc_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Checkpoint</title>
			<body>
				<p>This checkpoint will test your understanding of the material you have learned in this module.</p>
				<p>
					
						
				</p>
				<activity idref="_u2_m1_checkpoint2_pool" purpose="checkpoint"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<p>After you complete the checkpoint, if additional questions arise that you would like to discuss
			in class, please click on the <em>My Response</em> link below and submit the additional
			questions.</p>
		<activity idref="distributions_conc_feedback_post_quiz" purpose="myresponse"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
