<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
  xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
  id="spread5">
  <head>
    <title>Measures of Spread (5 of 5)</title>
    <objref idref="summarize_quantitiative_distribution"/>
    <objref idref="relate_center_and_spread"/>
    
  </head>
  <body>
    
   
    <section>
      <title>Understanding Outliers</title>
      <body>
        <p>We just practiced one way to 'flag' possible outliers. Why is it important to identify
          possible outliers, and how should they be dealt with? The answers to these questions
          depend on the reasons for the outlying values. Here are several possibilities: </p>
        <ol>
          <li><p>Even though it is an extreme value, if an outlier can be understood to have been
            produced by <em>essentially the same sort of physical or biological process</em> as the
            rest of the data, and if such extreme values are expected to <em>eventually occur
              again</em>, then such an outlier indicates something important and interesting about
            the process you're investigating, and it <em>should be kept</em> in the data.</p> </li>
          <li><p>If an outlier can be explained to have been produced under fundamentally
              <em>different</em> conditions from the rest of the data (or by a fundamentally
            different process), such an outlier <em>can be removed</em> from the data if your goal
            is to investigate only the process that produced the rest of the data.</p> </li>
          <li><p>An outlier might indicate a <em>mistake</em> in the data (like a typo, or a measuring
            error), in which case it <em>should be corrected if possible or else removed</em> from
            the data before calculating summary statistics or making inferences from the data (and
            the reason for the mistake should be investigated). </p></li>
        </ol>



        <p> <em>Here are examples of each of these types of outliers:</em></p>

        <ol>
          <li><p>The following histogram displays the magnitude of 460 earthquakes in California, occurring in the
              year 2000, between August 28 and September 9: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/spread21.gif" alt="A histogram titled &quot;California Earthquakes,
Aug 28,2000 - Sep 9,2000&quot;. The histogram is skewed-right. Frequency on the Y-axis ranges from 0 to 90, and on the
X-axis is Magnitude in Richter units, from 0 to 5.4 . As we go from left to right across the X-axis, the frequency
increases to the mode at x=1.2, y=90, then it decreases to 0 after x=3.6. However, beyond 4.8, we see a small bar
representing a frequency of 1."/>
            <p><em>Identifying the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>On the very far right edge of the display (beyond 4.8), we see a low bar; this
              represents one earthquake (because the bar has height of 1) that was much more severe
              than the others in the data. </p>
            <p><em>Understanding the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>In this case, the outlier represents a much stronger earthquake, which is relatively
              rarer than the smaller quakes that happen more frequently in California. </p>
            <p><em>How to handle the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>For many purposes, the relatively severe quakes represented by the outlier might be
              the most important (because, for instance, that sort of quake has the potential to do
              more damage to people and infrastructure). The smaller-magnitude quakes might not do
              any damage, or even be felt at all. So, for many purposes it could be important to
              keep this outlier in the data. </p>
          </li>
          <li><p>The following histogram displays the monthly percent return on the stock of Phillip
              Morris (a large tobacco company) from July 1990 to May 1997: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/spread22.gif" alt="A histogram titled &quot;Phillip Morris
Monthly Stock Return, July 1990 - May 1997. On the Y-axis is Frequency, from 0 to 30. On the X-axis is Monthy
Stock Return in percent. It ranges from -30 to 20. The histogram is skewed-left. At the very left, between at
the interval x=(-30, -25), a bar indicating frequency of 1 appears. Then, we see no bar until x=-15, where there is
a bar of frequency 5. As we continue moving right along the x-axis, frequency increases to the mode of 30 at
the interval x=(0,5), and then decreases, until reaching a frequency of 5 at the interval x=(15,20).">
            <cite>as described by statisticians David Moore and George McCabe, and available online</cite></image>
            <p><em>Identifying the outlier:</em> </p>
            <p>On the display, we see a low bar far to the left of the others; this represents one
              month’s return (because the bar has height of 1), where the value of Phillip Morris
              stock was unusually low. </p>
            <p><em>Understanding the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>The explanation for this particular outlier is that, in the early 1990s, there were
              highly-publicized federal hearings being conducted regarding the addictiveness of
              smoking, and there was growing public sentiment against the tobacco companies. The
              unusually low monthly value in the Phillip Morris dataset was due to public pressure
              against smoking, which negatively affected the company’s stock for that particular
              month. </p>
            <p><em>How to handle the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>In this case, the outlier was due to unusual conditions during one particular month
              that aren’t expected to be repeated, and that were fundamentally different from the
              conditions that produced the values in all the other months. So in this case, it would
              be reasonable to remove the outlier, if we wanted to characterize the ‘typical’
              monthly return on Phillip Morris stock. </p>
          </li>
          <li><p>When archaeologists dig up objects such as pieces of ancient pottery, chemical analysis can be
              performed on the artifacts. The chemical content of pottery can vary depending on the
              type of clay as well as the particular manufacturing technique. The following
              histogram displays the results of one such actual chemical analysis, performed on 48
              ancient Roman pottery artifacts from archaeological sites in Britain: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/spread23.gif" alt="A histogram titled &quot;Manganous Oxide
Content in a sample of Ancient Roman Pottery&quot;. The X-axis is labeled &quot;number of pottery shards&quot;,
and ranges from 0 to 20. The Y-axis is labeled &quot;manganous oxide [MnO] content&quot; and ranges from 0.0 to
0.4 . The histogram is skewed-right. Here are the bars: x=0.0,y=10; x=0.05,y=13; x=0.1,y=18; x=0.15,y=5;
x=0.20,y=1; x=0.4,y=1. Note that there are no shards for x=0.25 to x=0.35">
              <cite>As appeared in Tubb, et al. (1980). “The analysis of Romano-British pottery by
                atomic absorption spectrophotometry.” <em style="italic">Archaeometry</em>, vol. 22,
                reprinted in <em style="italic">Statistics in Archaeology</em> by Michael Baxter, p.
                21.</cite>
            </image>
            
            <p><em>Identifying the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>On the display, we see a low bar far to the right of the others; this represents one
              piece of pottery (because the bar has a height of 1), which has a suspiciously high
              manganous oxide value. </p>
            <p><em>Understanding the outlier:</em> </p>
            <p>Based on comparison with other pieces of pottery found at the same site, and based on
              expert understanding of the typical content of this particular compound, it was
              concluded that the unusually high value was most likely a typo that was made when the
              data were published in the original 1980 paper (it was typed as “.394” but it was
              probably meant to be “.094”). </p>
            <p><em>How to handle the outlier: </em></p>
            <p>In this case, since the outlier was judged to be a mistake, it should be removed from
              the data before further analysis. In fact, removing the outlier is useful not only
              because it’s a mistake, but also because doing so reveals important structure that was
              otherwise hidden. This feature is evident on the next display: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/spread24.gif" alt="A histogram titled &quot;
Histogram without the outlier&quot; The Y-axis is labeled &quot;number of pottery shards&quot;, and
it ranges from 0 to 12. The X-axis is labeled &quot;manganous oxide [MnO] content&quot; and ranges
from 0.00 to about 0.18. Going from left to right along the X-axis reveals that at x=0, there is a
frequency of 10. Then, there are no bars until x=0.4 . From here the bars increase in height until
x=0.08, where the frequency is 12. Then the bars begin to decrease."/>
            <p>When the outlier is removed, the display is re-scaled so that now we can see the set
              of 10 pottery pieces that had almost no manganous oxide. These 10 pieces might have
              been made with a different potting technique, so identifying them as different from
              the rest is historically useful. This feature was only evident after the outlier was
              removed. </p>
          </li>
        </ol>














      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Let's Summarize</title>
      <body>
        <ul>
          <li><p>The range covered by the data is the most intuitive measure of spread and is exactly
            the distance between the smallest data point (min) and the largest one (Max).</p></li>
          <li><p>Another measure of spread is the inter-quartile range (IQR), which is the range
            covered by the middle 50% of the data.</p></li>
          <li><p>IQR = Q3 - Q1, the difference between the third and first quartiles. The first
            quartile (Q1) is the value such that one quarter (25%) of the data points fall below
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101019T120511-0400" comment="I added phrases to match wording used previously in text. OK?"?>it<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101019T120419-0400"?>,
            or the median of the bottom half of the data<?oxy_insert_end?>. The third quartile is
            the value such that three quarters (75%) of the data points fall below
            it<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101019T120433-0400"?>, or the median
            of the top half of the data<?oxy_insert_end?>.<?oxy_comment_end?></p></li>
          <li><p>The IQR should be used as a measure of spread of a distribution only when the median
            is used as a measure of center.</p></li>
          <li><p>The IQR can be used to detect outliers using the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101019T121135-0400" comment="OK to add a reminder of how this works here?

"?>1.5(IQR) criterion.<?oxy_comment_end?>
            <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101019T121137-0400"?>Outliers are
            observations that fall below Q1 - 1.5(IQR) or above Q3 +
            1.5(IQR).<?oxy_insert_end?></p></li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </body>
</workbook_page>
