<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="binomial_param_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_binomial_param" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO: binomial_param -->
        <body>
            <p>Colorblindness is any abnormality of the color vision system that causes a person to
                see colors differently than most people, or to have difficulty distinguishing among
                certain colors (www.visionrx.com). </p>
            <p>Colorblindness is gender-based, while the majority of sufferers being males. </p>
            <p>Roughly 8% of white males have some form of colorblindness, while the incidence among
                white females is only 1%. A random sample of 20 white males and 40 white females was
                chosen.</p>
            <p>Let <em style="bold">X</em> be the number of males (out of the 20) who are
                colorblind.</p>
            <p>Let <em style="bold">Y</em> be the number of females (out of the 40) who are
                colorblind.</p>
            <p>Let <em style="bold">Z</em> be the total number of colorblind individuals in the
                sample (males and females together).</p>
            <p>Which of the following is true about the random variables X, Y, and Z? Check all that
                apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">X is binomial with n = 20 and p = .08. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Y is binomial with n = 40 and p = .01. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Z is not binomial. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that <em style="bold">X</em> represents the
                    number of colorblind males out of a random sample of 20 → <em style="bold">X</em> is binomial with n = 20 and p = 0.08. However, there is at least one
                    other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that <em style="bold">Y</em> represents the
                    number of colorblind females out of a random sample of 40 → <em style="bold">Y</em> is binomial with n = 40 and p = 0.01. However, there is at least one
                    other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that <em style="bold">Z</em> represents the
                    total number of colorblind people out of the total sample of 60. <em style="bold">Z</em> is not binomial, since the probability of "success"
                    (being colorblind) is not the same for all 60 people (0.08 for the 20 males and
                    0.01 for the 40 females). However, there is at least one other true
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that <em style="bold">X</em> represents the
                    number of colorblind males out of a random sample of 20 → <em style="bold">X</em> is binomial with n = 20 and p = 0.08. Also, you are correct that <em style="bold">Y</em> represents the number of colorblind females out of a
                    random sample of 40 → <em style="bold">Y</em> is binomial with n = 40 and p =
                    0.01. However, there is at least one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that <em style="bold">X</em> represents the
                    number of colorblind males out of a random sample of 20 → <em style="bold">X</em> is binomial with n = 20 and p = 0.08. Also, you are correct that <em style="bold">Z</em> represents the total number of colorblind people out of
                    the total sample of 60. <em style="bold">Z</em> is not binomial, since the
                    probability of "success" (being colorblind) is not the same for all 60 people
                    (0.08 for the 20 males and 0.01 for the 40 females). However, there is at least
                    one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that <em style="bold">Y</em> represents the
                    number of colorblind females out of a random sample of 40 → <em style="bold">Y</em> is binomial with n = 40 and p = 0.01. Also, you are correct that <em style="bold">Z</em> represents the total number of colorblind people out of
                    the total sample of 60. <em style="bold">Z</em> is not binomial, since the
                    probability of "success" (being colorblind) is not the same for all 60 people
                    (0.08 for the 20 males and 0.01 for the 40 females). However, there is at least
                    one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. <em style="bold">X</em> represents the number of colorblind males
                    out of a random sample of 20 → <em style="bold">X</em> is binomial with n = 20
                    and p = 0.08. <em style="bold">Y</em> represents the number of colorblind
                    females out of a random sample of 40 → <em style="italic">Y</em> is also
                    binomial with n = 40 and p = 0.01. <em style="bold">Z</em> represents the total
                    number of colorblind people out of the total sample of 60. <em style="bold">Z</em> is not binomial, since the probability of "success" (being color
                    blind) is not the same for all 60 people (0.08 for the 20 males and 0.01 for the
                    40 females).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_binomial_param" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO: binomial_param -->
        <body>
            <p>Blood type AB is the rarest blood type, occurring in only 4% of the population in the
                United States. In Australia, only 1.5% of the population has blood type AB. Suppose
                a random sample of 50 U.S. residents and 40 Australians is obtained. Consider the
                random variables described below:</p>
            <p>X: the number of US residents (out of 50) with blood type AB.</p>
            <p>Y: the number of Australians (out of 40) with blood type AB.</p>
            <p>Z: the total number of individuals (out of 90) with blood type AB.</p>
            <p>Which of the following is true about the random variables X, Y, and Z? Check all that
                apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">X is a binomial random variable with n = 50 and p = 0.04</choice>
            <choice value="B">Y is a binomial random variable with n = 40 and p = 0.015</choice>
            <choice value="C">Z is a binomial random variable with n = 90 and p = 0.055</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that X is a binomial random variable. However
                    there is at least one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that Y is a binomial random variable. However
                    there is at least one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Z is not a binomial random variable because the probability of
                    type AB blood is not the same for all individuals in the sample.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. X and Y are binomial random variables and Z is not binomial
                    because the probability of type AB blood is not the same for all individuals in
                    the sample.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that X is a binomial random variable. However Z
                    is not a binomial random variable because the probability of type AB blood is
                    not the same for all individuals in the sample.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that Y is a binomial random variable. However Z
                    is not a binomial random variable because the probability of type AB blood is
                    not the same for all individuals in the sample.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that X and Y are binomial random variables.
                    However Z is not a binomial random variable because the probability of type AB
                    blood is not the same for all individuals in the sample.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
