<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="discrete_vs_continuous_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_discrete_vs_continuous" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>Consider the following statements about a particular traditional class of statistics
                students at State U related to discrete and continuous variables. Which of the
                following is a true statement? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">The number of students in the class is a discrete variable.</choice>
            <choice value="B">The average age of the students in the class is a continuous
                variable.</choice>
            <choice value="C">The room number of the class is a continuous variable
                variable.</choice>
            <choice value="D">The average weight of the students is a discrete variable.</choice>
            <choice value="E">A student's GPA is a continuous variable.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable. However there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable. However there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="2">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a
                    continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable. Also,
                    there is at least one correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="2">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The average weight of the students in the class is a continuous
                    variable not a discrete variable. Also, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that a student's GPA is a continuous variable.
                    However there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that the average age of the students in the class is a
                    continuous variable. However, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable, but the room number of the class is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em>
                    variable. Additionally, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable, but the average weight of the students in the class is a
                    continuous variable <em style="italic">not</em> a discrete variable.
                    Additionally, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,E" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However,
                    there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable, but the room number of the class is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable. Also, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable, but the average weight of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable <em style="italic">not</em> a discrete variable.
                    Also, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,E" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable and that a student's GPA is a continuous
                    variable. However, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a
                    continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the
                    average weight of the students in the class is a continuous variable not a
                    discrete variable. Also, there is at least one correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,E" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that a student's GPA is a continuous variable,
                    but the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous
                    variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable. Also, there is at
                    least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D,E" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that a student's GPA is a continuous variable,
                    but the average weight of the students in the class is a continuous variable <em style="italic">not</em> a discrete variable. Also, there is at least one
                    other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that the average age of the students in the class is a
                    continuous variable. However, the room number of the class is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em>
                    variable. Also, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that the average age of the students in the class is a
                    continuous variable. However the average weight of the students in the class is
                    a continuous variable not a discrete variable. Also, there is at least one other
                    correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,E" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The number of students in the class is a discrete variable, the
                    average age of the students in the class is a continuous variable, and a
                    student's GPA is a continuous variable. The number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the average weight of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable not a discrete variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="2">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable however the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em>
                    variable and the average weight of the students in the class is a continuous
                    variable not a discrete variable. Also, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,E" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However,
                    the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable
                    it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable. Also, there is at least
                    one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D,E" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However,
                    the average weight of the students in the class is a continuous variable not a
                    discrete variable. Also, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="2">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable. However, the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the average weight of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable not a discrete variable. Also, there is at least
                    one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,E" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable and that a student's GPA is a continuous
                    variable. However the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a
                    continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable. Also,
                    there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D,E" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable and that a student's GPA is a continuous
                    variable. However, the average weight of the students in the class is a
                    continuous variable not a discrete variable. Also, there is at least one other
                    correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D,E" score="2">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that a student's GPA is a continuous variable.
                    However, the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous
                    variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the average
                    weight of the students in the class is a continuous variable not a discrete
                    variable. Also, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and that the average age of the students in the class is a
                    continuous variable. However, the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em>
                    variable and the average weight of the students in the class is a continuous
                    variable not a discrete variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,E" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable, the average age of the students in the class is a continuous
                    variable, and a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However, the number of
                    the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D,E" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable, the average age of the students in the class is a continuous
                    variable, and a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However, the average
                    weight of the students in the class is a continuous variable not a discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D,E" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable and a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However, the
                    number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it
                    is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the average weight of the
                    students in the class is a continuous variable not a discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D,E" score="4">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the average age of the students in the
                    class is a continuous variable and a student's GPA is a continuous variable.
                    However, the number of the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous
                    variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the average
                    weight of the students in the class is a continuous variable not a discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D,E" score="6">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number of students in the class is a
                    discrete variable, the average age of the students in the class is a continuous
                    variable, and a student's GPA is a continuous variable. However, the number of
                    the classroom is <em style="italic">not</em> a continuous variable it is a <em style="italic">categorical</em> variable and the average weight of the
                    students in the class is a continuous variable not a discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_discrete_vs_continuous" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>Joe went to watch the Quakes play baseball at Epicenter stadium in Rancho Cucamonga.
                While he enjoyed the game, he also purchased some food. Consider whether some of the
                things he saw or did at the game that involve discrete or continuous variables.
                Which of the following is a true statement? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">The batting average of Joe’s favorite player is a continuous
                variable.</choice>
            <choice value="B">The number of hot dogs that Joe bought is a discrete
                variable.</choice>
            <choice value="C">The number of strikeouts in the game is a continuous
                variable.</choice>
            <choice value="D">The Quakes standings in the league is a discrete variable.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable.
                    However, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a
                    discrete variable. However, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete variable not a
                    continuous one. Also, there is at least one correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the team’s ranking in the league is a
                    discrete variable. However there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable
                    and that the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a discrete variable.However,
                    there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable
                    however, the number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete variable not a
                    continuous one. Also, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable
                    and that the team’s ranking in the league is a discrete variable. However, there
                    is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a
                    discrete variable. However, the number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete
                    variable not a continuous one. Also, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a
                    discrete variable and that the team’s ranking in the league is a discrete
                    variable. However, there is at least one other correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the team’s ranking in the league is a
                    discrete variable However, the number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete
                    variable not a continuous one. Also, there is at least one other correct
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable
                    and that the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a discrete variable. However,
                    the number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete variable not a continuous
                    one.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Batting average is a continuous variable, the number hot dogs
                    purchased by Joe is a discrete variable, and the team’s ranking in the league is
                    a discrete variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable,
                    and that the team’s ranking in the league is a discrete variable. However, the
                    number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete variable not a continuous
                    one.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a
                    discrete variable and that the team’s ranking in the league is a discrete
                    variable. However, the number of strikeouts in a game is a discrete variable not
                    a continuous one.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that batting average is a continuous variable,
                    the number hot dogs purchased by Joe is a discrete variable, and the team’s
                    ranking in the league is a discrete variable. However, the number of strikeouts
                    in a game is a discrete variable not a continuous one.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one correct statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_discrete_vs_continuous" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following variables is discrete? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Shoe size</choice>
            <choice value="B">Waist measurement</choice>
            <choice value="C">Foot length</choice>
            <choice value="D">Dress size</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that shoe size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, there is at least
                    one other discrete variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Waist measurement is a <em style="italic">continuous</em>
                    variable in that it is measured and can take any value in an
                    interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Foot length is a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in
                    that it is measured and can take any value in an interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that dress size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, there is at least
                    one other discrete variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that shoe size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, waist measurement is
                    a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in that it is measured and can take
                    any value in an interval. Additionally, there is at least one other discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that shoe size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, foot length is a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in that it is measured and can take
                    any value in an interval. Additionally, there is at least one other discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Shoe size and dress size are discrete variables in that they are
                    countable and have a list of distinct values.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Waist measurement and foot length are <em style="italic">continuous</em> variables in that they are measured and can take any value
                    in an interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that dress size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, waist measurement is
                    a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in that it is measured and can take
                    any value in an interval. Additionally, there is at least one other discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that dress size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, foot length is a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in that it is measured and can take
                    any value in an interval. Additionally, there is at least one other discrete
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that shoe size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, waist measurement
                    and foot length are <em style="italic">continuous</em> variables in that they are
                    measured and can take any value in an interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that shoe size and dress size are discrete
                    variables in that they are countable and have a list of distinct values.
                    However, waist measurement is a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in
                    that it is measured and can take any value in an interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>You are correct that shoe size and dress size are discrete
                    variables in that they are countable and have a list of distinct values. However, foot length is a <em style="italic">continuous</em> variable in that it is measured and can take any value in an interval.<!--[added feedback 9/25 ~carol]--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that dress size is a discrete variable in that
                    it is countable and has a list of distinct values. However, waist measurement
                    and foot length are <em style="italic">continuous</em> variables in that they are
                    measured and can take any value in an interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that shoe size and dress size are discrete
                    variables in that they are countable and have a list of distinct values.
                    However, waist measurement and foot length are <em style="italic">continuous</em>
                    variables in that they are measured and can take any value in an
                    interval.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one discrete variable.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_discrete_vs_continuous">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following is a characteristic of a discrete random variable?</p>
            <!-- question choices unclear -->
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">It is something you measure.</choice>
            <choice value="B">It is something you count.</choice>
            <choice value="C">It is something you both measure and count.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Measured data is continuous and therefore NOT countable.
                    Discrete data is countable. A <em style="italic">continuous</em> random variable
                    is something you measure.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Discrete data is countable. A <em style="italic">discrete</em>
                    random variable is something you count.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Measured data is continuous and therefore NOT countable.
                    Discrete data is countable. A <em style="italic">discrete</em> random variable
                    is something you count. However, a <em style="italic">continuous</em> random
                    variable is something you measure.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q5_discrete_vs_continuous">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following is a discrete data random variable?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">A person's height each birthday</choice>
            <choice value="B">The volume of water in a swimming pool each day</choice>
            <choice value="C">Cars finished in a factory each day</choice>
            <choice value="D">A person's weight on each year</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A person’s height is measured and therefore is a continuous data
                    random variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Volume is measured and therefore is a continuous data random
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Number of cars is countable and therefore is a discrete data random
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A person’s weight is measured and therefore is a continuous data
                    random variable.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q6_discrete_vs_continuous">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>Daily rainfall is an example of what type of data random variable?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Discrete</choice>
            <choice value="B">Continuous</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Rainfall is measured and therefore is a continuous data random
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Rainfall is measured and therefore is a continuous data random
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q7_discrete_vs_continuous">
        <!-- LO: discrete_vs_continuous -->
        <body>
            <p>The number of times that a hiker walks over 8 miles each day is what type of
                data random variable?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Discrete</choice>
            <choice value="B">Continuous</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The number of times that a hiker walks is countable and therefore
                    is a discrete data random variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The number of times that a hiker walks is countable and
                    therefore is a discrete data random variable.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
