<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_digestive_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Which function of the digestive system would be LEAST directly affected by the lack of CCK?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">digestion of food into chemical building blocks</choice><choice value="B">absorption of building blocks into the body</choice><choice value="C">elimination of residual indigestible materials</choice><choice value="D">regulation among different organs of the digestive system</choice></multiple_choice><part id="fa8626337c8e4ed89e3cae85ce05bd2b"><skillref idref="describe_digestive_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This will directly limit the proper release of the digestive secretions from the accessory organs and make digestion within the tract less efficient.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the material in the lumen is not being digested fully into the form that can be absorbed, the absorption will be less efficient.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Material in the digestive lumen can still be moved for elimination; however, with the improper digestion and absorption, now some material that should have been digested and absorbed will be included with the residual material, possibly leading to symptoms such as diarrhea.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This hormone plays an important role in coordinating the functions among the different parts of the system.</feedback></response><hint>All these functions will be affected, but one of them will continue despite the lack of CCK and may even be enhanced in a way that leads to some of the symptoms this person could experience related to the digestive system.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
