<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="digest_cells_LBD"><title>Digestive Cells</title><page><question id="digest_cells_A"><body><p>Now apply what you have learned about histology of the digestive system and enzymes. Select the correct cells for each blank to complete these paragraphs comparing the histology and function among the different parts of the digestive system:</p><p>To help physically protect cells lining the lumen of the intestines, cup-shaped cells called <input_ref input="i1" /> secrete a thick mucus. This mucus is different from the bicarbonate-rich alkaline mucus, produced by cells of the stomach called<input_ref input="i2" />, that also protects the lining from the acidic gastric juice in the lumen.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i1" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1a">goblet cell</choice><choice value="v1b">paneth cell</choice><choice value="v1c">gastric neck cell</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i2" shuffle="false"><choice value="v2a">chief cell</choice><choice value="v2b">gastric neck cell</choice><choice value="v2c">G cell</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i7d91ae236fd4400fa4ff5b83248562b8"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i1" match="v1a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These can also be found producing mucus in other places in the body, such as the respiratory system.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are found in the small intestine and protect, but not by producing mucus.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are found in the stomach and their mucus is different.</feedback></response><hint targets="i1">This type of cell, in the intestine, has a name based on a drinking cup with a stem or foot.</hint></part><part id="faeb45319545425b864be1bc440de316"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i2" match="v2a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are found in the stomach, but produce enzymes, not mucus.</feedback></response><response input="i2" match="v2b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These mucous cells are specialized and different from the goblet cells found elsewhere.</feedback></response><response input="i2" match="v2c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are found in the stomach, but produce a hormone, not mucus.</feedback></response><hint targets="i2">This one, in the stomach, is named for its location close to the top or “head” of the gastric pit.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="digest_cells_B"><body><p>Digestive enzymes are produced both by cells lining the lumen and by accessory organ cells that have ducts leading into the lumen. The <input_ref input="i3" />cells lining the gastric pits secrete both gastric lipase and pepsinogen. While not an enzyme, hydrochloric acid secreted by the <input_ref input="i4" /> cells of the gastric pit activates pepsinogen into pepsin for protein digestion and activates salivary and gastric lipase for lipid digestion. Lining the lumen of the small intestine, the <input_ref input="i5" /> cells with microvilli not only absorb but also produce several surface enzymes for digestion and enterokinase for activation of trypsinogen into trypsin for protein digestion. Ducts carry pancreatic juice with a mixture of enzymes for all four organic compounds from the exocrine <input_ref input="i6" /> cells of the pancreas. While not an enzyme, ducts also carry exocrine secretion of bile produced by<input_ref input="i7" /> of the liver; once in the digestive lumen, the bile emulsifies lipids to facilitate the activity of lipases.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i3" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">chief</choice><choice value="v3b">parietal</choice><choice value="v3c">brush-border </choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i4" shuffle="false"><choice value="v4a">acini</choice><choice value="v4b">parietal</choice><choice value="v4c">brush-border</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i5" shuffle="false"><choice value="v5a">acini</choice><choice value="v5b">paneth</choice><choice value="v5c">brush-border </choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i6" shuffle="false"><choice value="v6a">acini</choice><choice value="v6b">hepatocyte</choice><choice value="v6c">iset</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i7" shuffle="false"><choice value="v7a">paneth</choice><choice value="v7b">hepatocyte</choice><choice value="v7c">brush-border</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i6ab3bf26371d49d2acb733f3bb8838e1"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i3" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. This exocrine cell of the stomach secretes two kinds of enzymes.</feedback></response><response input="i3" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This stomach cell secretes something that activates enzymes and denatures protein, but is not an enzyme.</feedback></response><response input="i3" match="v3c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This cell is found in the small intestine, not the stomach.</feedback></response><hint targets="i3">This type of cell, in the stomach, produces a major enzyme so its name reflects it primary role. </hint></part><part id="i4e8986209e8f4aa683068d6e29333824"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i4" match="v4a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the pancreas, not the stomach.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="v4b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. In addition to hydrochloric acid, this cell also secretes intrinsic factor into the stomach lumen.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="v4c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the small intestine, not the stomach.</feedback></response><hint targets="i4">This type of cell, in stomach and in the intestine, is associated with the wall of the lumen. </hint><hint targets="i4">This type of cell, in stomach, derives from Latin “paries” for wall.</hint></part><part id="i93178c87fff94703bf056bb221f62533"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i5" match="v5a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the pancreas, not the stomach.</feedback></response><response input="i5" match="v5b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are found in the small intestine, but don’t have microvilli and don’t produce enzymes.</feedback></response><response input="i5" match="v5c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The microvilli of the cell surface look “fuzzy” under the microscope, giving these cells their name.</feedback></response><hint targets="i5">The name of this type of cell derives from Old French “bordeaure” for outer edge.</hint></part><part id="f5e5ca8a7dc84b5eb6f2f87298e79a31"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i6" match="v6a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These cells produce enzymes and secrete bicarbonate ions that make up pancreatic juice.</feedback></response><response input="i6" match="v6b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the liver, not the pancreas.</feedback></response><response input="i6" match="v6c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are endocrine “duct-less” cells found in the pancreas, producing hormones not enzymes.</feedback></response><hint targets="i6">The cells in the pancreas create a many-lobed gland, thus the name derived from Latin “acinus” for berry, such as raspberry.</hint></part><part id="i95556d1bfed14fa9b8f57bc35418f9d7"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i7" match="v7a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the small intestine glands, not the liver.</feedback></response><response input="i7" match="v7b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These cells secrete bile with bile salts for lipid emulsification into small ducts in the liver.</feedback></response><response input="i7" match="v7c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the small intestine, not the stomach.</feedback></response><hint targets="i7">The bile producing cells are named based on the Greek “hepar” for liver.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="digest_cells_C"><body><p>Other cells associated with the digestive system perform important immune functions, since the gastrointestinal lumen is a possible pathway for food-borne or water-borne microorganisms. In the glands associated with the small intestine lumen are phagocytotic cells called <input_ref input="i8" />. They can also secrete lysozyme to kill a variety of foreign microorganism in the lumen with the digested food. If any do get absorbed, they will be carried in the blood to the liver by the hepatic portal system. There in the sinusoidal capillaries of the liver, <input_ref input="i9" /> cells will also phagocytize any of these foreign microorganisms absorbed by the small intestine. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i8" shuffle="false"><choice value="v8a">paneth</choice><choice value="v8b">hepatocyte</choice><choice value="v8c">alpha cells</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i9" shuffle="false"><choice value="v9a">beta</choice><choice value="v9b">hepatocyte</choice><choice value="v9c">kupffer</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i63503e2de9a0497489c824f284d0e76e"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i8" match="v8a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These cells can do phagocytosis and also secrete lysozyme into small intestine lumen.</feedback></response><response input="i8" match="v8b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the liver, not the small intestine.</feedback></response><response input="i8" match="v8c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are endocrine cells of the pancreas, producing glucagon.</feedback></response><hint>This type of cell was named after the person who first discovered it in the late 1800’2 and early 1900’s, an Austrian physiologist.</hint></part><part id="i1c97e81c99de44329f57c59daf0fa825"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i9" match="v9a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are endocrine cells of the pancreas, producing insulin.</feedback></response><response input="i9" match="v9b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are the metabolically active liver cells that make up the tissue of the liver, not found in the blood sinuses of the liver.</feedback></response><response input="i9" match="v9c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These cells in the liver sinuses can do phagocytosis and can start a specific immune response for your body to produce antibodies.</feedback></response><hint>This type of cell was named after the person who first discovered it in the late 1800’2 and early 1900’s, a German anatomist.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="digest_cells_D"><body><p>Another group of cells throughout the gastrointestinal tract are endocrine cells, producing hormones, not enzymes. These hormones are absorbed into the blood, not secreted into the lumen like the enzymes. They are transported through the body in blood and regulate the metabolic activity of only those body cells that have receptors for those specific hormones. These endocrine cells of the gastrointestinal tract include <input_ref input="i10" /> cells of the stomach producing gastrin and a variety of <input_ref input="i11" /> cells (CCK, K, and S) of the small intestine produce secretin, CCK and GIP hormones regulating various digestive functions. Special groups of <input_ref input="i12" /> cells in the pancreas (alpha, beta, delta and PP) also produce hormones regulating metabolism of some of the absorbed digestive products. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i10" shuffle="false"><choice value="v10a">G</choice><choice value="v10b">enteroendocrine</choice><choice value="v10c">islet</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i11" shuffle="false"><choice value="v11a">G</choice><choice value="v11b">enteroendocrine</choice><choice value="v11c">islet</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i12" shuffle="false"><choice value="v12a">hepatocyte</choice><choice value="v12b">acini</choice><choice value="v12c">islet</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i64db0d1d41294d81acfdd97baa0d5201"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i10" match="v10a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These stomach endocrine cells secrete the hormone gastrin to facilitate release of gastric juice.</feedback></response><response input="i10" match="v10b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the small intestine, not the stomach.</feedback></response><response input="i10" match="v10c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the pancreas, not the stomach.</feedback></response><hint>This endocrine cell could be named based on the first letter of the hormone it produces or its location in the stomach from the Greek “gaster” for stomach.</hint></part><part id="i4ea628e0940a48c5bf2a4e93a4134785"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i11" match="v11a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the stomach, not the small intestine.</feedback></response><response input="i11" match="v11b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These cells are found in the stomach, not the small intestine.</feedback></response><response input="i11" match="v11c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the pancreas, not the stomach.</feedback></response><hint>This endocrine cell includes the root from Greek for intestine, “entero”.</hint></part><part id="i4d9b39a415724a00966911bb54d8b0a8"><skillref idref="GIcell_specialization_SKILL" /><response input="i12" match="v12a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells are found in the liver, not the pancreas.</feedback></response><response input="i12" match="v12b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are exocrine cells of the pancreas, not endocrine.</feedback></response><response input="i12" match="v12c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These endocrine cells, including alpha and beta cells, produce several hormones that regulate carbohydrate metabolism after it has been absorbed by the small intestine.</feedback></response><hint>The name of this endocrine cell comes from the formation of a small island of cells within different tissue of the pancreas.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
