<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="digest_intro_lbd1"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Based on our modern day understanding of the digestive system anatomy and physiology, this system would best be classified in which of the vital function categories?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Provide structure, support, protection and movement</choice><choice value="B">Exchange with the environment</choice><choice value="C">Transport fluids and material throughout the body</choice><choice value="D">Regulate and control processes</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i6f9be864b8064f41878f5dfb6b1360c7"><skillref idref="_u1_Explain_vital_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Think about this vital function more as the whole organism in its environment; this is not its best category choice for digestive system, even though all organs have a “structure”, there are structures associated with the digestive system specifically for protection because it is another pathway for pathogens to enter the body, and food is moved through the lumen.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Because the GI tube is technically “external”, the secretion of substances for digestion into the lumen and absorption of nutrients and water from the lumen is an exchange with our environment.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This happens to the material that is absorbed by the digestive system cells, but it is a function of the circulatory or lymphatic systems.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While there is a portion of the nervous system that is specifically associated with the digestive system, called the enteric nervous system, it is still considered to be part of the nervous system and so would not be considered a major function of the digestive system.</feedback></response><hint>In theory, all systems are interrelated and contribute in some way to each vital function, but one is the best classification based on major function of the system for the organism as a whole in its environment.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
