<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="digest_intro_c_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>There are two different kinds of secretions associated with the digestive system that need to be understood to avoid confusion when describing how the digestive system functions. Which one of these secretions will be involved in control of digestion through the blood?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>endocrine</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>exocrine</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="digest_cell_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The various endocrine hormones secreted and transported in the blood will coordinate the movement of food through the GI tract as well as the secretion of exocrine substances into the lumen.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These substances, such as enzymes, are secreted into the GI tract lumen and not into the blood.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What two body systems regulate and control the proper function of the digestive system?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">endocrine and lymphatic systems</choice><choice value="B">nervous and cardiovascular system</choice><choice value="C">nervous and endocrine systems</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="digest_nervous_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The lymphatic system helps protect from any pathogens that might enter through the digestive system but doesn’t regulate the digestive system function.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The cardiovascular system does transports but doesn’t produce chemicals that control the digestive system function.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both of these systems produce chemical messengers to coordinate proper system function and homeostasis.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p>All the secretion and absorption functions of digestive system need to be understood as happening at what level of organization?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>the cell and cell membrane</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>tissues</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>organs</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="digest_loo_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This is the level where substances are moved between the “external environment” of the GI lumen and internal body fluids.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an important structural level to study because they make up the different organs of the digestive system, but most physiology happens at a different level.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an important structural level to study because the different organs of the system function together, but most physiology happens at a different level.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body>What structure-function concept is important at all levels of organization for very efficient absorption in the digestive system?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">accessory organ secretions</choice><choice value="B">increased surface area</choice><choice value="C">hormonal control of digestion</choice><choice value="D">enzyme digestion of food</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="describe_digestive_SKILL" /><skillref idref="digest_loo_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This will directly enhance digestion necessary before absorption can occur, but not the process of absorption.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The various structural features that increase the surface area exposed to the substances in the GI tract will enhance the amount of absorption that can occur while the food passes through the tube.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This will coordinate digestion and movement of material through the GI tract, but not the process of absorption.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This will directly enhance digestion necessary before absorption can occur, but not the process of absorption.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
