<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="digest_carbo_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Generally, monosaccharides that are not processed in the digestive system can cause what dietary condition?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">diarrhea</choice><choice value="B">consitpation</choice><choice value="C">altered color of stool</choice><choice value="D">increased amounts of polysaccharides</choice></multiple_choice><part id="dff8d82a96f34f7da6dad85e8e079c4f"><skillref idref="digest_carbo_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Sugars in the large intestine increase water content of the stool, causing diarrhea.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sugars in the large intestine <em style="italic">increase</em> water content of the stool causing diarrhea. Decrease in water content causes constipation. </feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There are numerous digestive issues that alter the color of stool, but sugar content is not one.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Humans do not produce polysaccharides from monosaccharides in the digestive system.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Why can’t there be a single brush-border enzyme to break down the three common disaccharides?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Bacterial enzymes are required to break down lactose.</choice><choice value="B">Enzymes are substrate specific.</choice><choice value="C">a-dextrins are too small to be broken down by these enzymes.</choice><choice value="D">There is only one enzyme to break down disaccharides, the other brush-border enzymes break down starch.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i9b701d6b2e084931b02e2ab46b358f21"><skillref idref="digest_carbo_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the brush-border enzyme for lactose is missing, bacteria will break down these molecules for energy and cause conditions such as diarrhea.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Each enzyme can only catalyze a specific reaction, so each disaccharide would need a different enzyme.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A-dextrin is actually a short chain of glucose that is converted to glucose by a brush-border enzyme.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Starch is broken down by amylase which is not a brush-border enzyme.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
