<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="digest_bp_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><content><p>As you study this body system, you will be learning at the knowledge and understanding level as well as developing reasoning proficiency.</p><p>Knowledge and understanding requires students recall previously-learned information and show their understanding of that material, while reasoning proficiency requires students use those facts to find relationships between parts of the whole (application and analysis), combine ideas to form a new whole (synthesis), and/or make decisions based on the information (evaluation). For each of the following sample learning objectives associated with this organ system unit, assess the skills you will most likely be applying:</p></content><question id="q1"><body><p>Identify organs of the digestive system based on position and structure; identify the general function of each.</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">knowledge and understanding</choice><choice value="B">reasoning proficiency</choice></multiple_choice><part id="d520ea86fc6b4a7a81c78d555f21d173"><skillref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This includes identifying anatomical parts by image or description and basic functions.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While you need to be able to identify structures and functions on new images or by new descriptions, this is not involving analysis of the basic information.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p>Explain how mechanical and chemical digestion work together to produce absorbable nutrients.</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">knowledge and understanding</choice><choice value="B">reasoning proficiency</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i06bfd06ec592453eacdd2045145786cc"><skillref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While you need to know the structures involved, this requires you to go beyond facts to application of that information.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This requires you apply what you have learned about the structures and physiological processes and explain how they work together.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p>Trace the pathway of the bolus from mouth to stomach, identifying major structures and describing their role in facilitating the process of deglutition (swallowing).</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">knowledge and understanding</choice><choice value="B">reasoning proficiency</choice></multiple_choice><part id="c16e57d4af9a456681e7861178dd3502"><skillref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This sequencing activity is a bit more involved than just randomly identifying parts, but is still a basic level of recall of information you have learned.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While this seems more than recall because you have to put them in correct order, it is still just recalling the facts you have learned.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p>Distinguish between exocrine and endocrine function of the digestive system cells and relate this to their role in the overall process of digestion.</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">knowledge and understanding</choice><choice value="B">reasoning proficiency</choice></multiple_choice><part id="c46513cdf1404d52a01ae7bd52933d99"><skillref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While you have to know examples of endocrine and exocrine secretions, that alone will now sufficiently address this learning objective.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. While you have to give specific examples you have learned, you will be differentiating and synthesizing this information to explain how they function within the system.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q5"><body><p>Identify the location and functions of specific cells in different parts of the digestive system.</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">knowledge and understanding</choice><choice value="B">reasoning proficiency</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i63ca88e9286a492fa7c92c86c60ed890"><skillref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This objective involves cells in different parts of the system, but is still just using what you have learned about their basic anatomy and physiology.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While this information could help you with a more involved learning objective such as the previous one, this is still just learning facts associated with specific parts of the digestive system.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q6"><body><p>Provide examples of how the digestive system relates to other body systems to maintain homeostasis.</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">knowledge and understanding</choice><choice value="B">reasoning proficiency</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i1a52a0e472534bb892e805e1332a8109"><skillref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While you have to know the basic functions of the digestive, that alone will not sufficiently address this learning objective.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. You will have to interpret not only what you learned about this system but other systems to make predictions and justify your example of how they work together to maintain homeostasis in the body.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
