<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="enzy_secretions1_la"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="enzyme_secretions1"><body>Which of these enzymes is produced and secreted into one section of the GI tract, but not active until it reaches another section?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Salivary Amylase</choice><choice value="B">Pancreatic Amylase</choice><choice value="C">Lingual Lipase</choice><choice value="D">Gastric Lipase</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i4083e8f72c3a4dde9a5c79c2da2a4e17"><skillref idref="digest_secretions_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is active in the mouth and inactivated by the stomach pH.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is secreted and active in the small intestine.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Saliva is maintained at low acidity and this enzyme needs to be activated by the acidic contents of the stomach.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is secreted and active in the stomach lumen</feedback></response><hint>This is produced and secreted in a low acidity (high pH) area, but is active only at high acidity (low pH).</hint></part></question><question id="enzyme_secretions2"><body><p>Which chemical is produced and secreted into the GI tract to help buffer and maintain high pH for proper enzyme activity?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Mucus</choice><choice value="B">Bicarbonate Ions</choice><choice value="C">Bile Salts</choice><choice value="D">Intrinsic Factor</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i2ccc624dc05d4209b5e0c811492704f4"><skillref idref="digest_secretions_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Mucus forms a mucosal barrier that protects the tissues from stomach acid, but it doesn’t buffer the pH of the stomach contents.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Bicarbonate ions in both saliva and pancreatic juice help maintain a slightly alkaline pH for the many enzymes that don’t function at low pH.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Bile salts emulsify lipids but don’t affect the pH of the GI tract contents.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Intrinsic Factor is produced in the stomach and assists proper absorption of vitamin B 12 in the small intestine, but doesn’t affect the pH.</feedback></response><hint>This is produced and secreted in both saliva and pancreatic juice.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
