<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="GI_layers1_la"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Which two layers of the GI tract include nerve plexus and endings (varicosities) of the autonomic nervous system?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">mucosa and serosa</choice><choice value="B">mucosa and submucosa</choice><choice value="C">submucosa and muscularis</choice><choice value="D">muscularis and serosa</choice></multiple_choice><part id="a851147108c747c9aa52855657c9ff5b"><skillref idref="wall_layers_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The serosa supports major nerves and blood vessels, but doesn’t include the nerve plexus ending (varicosities) and neither does the mucosa layer.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The submucosa has a nerve plexus, but the mucosa does not.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The submucosal plexus controls the movement of muscularis mucosa for moving mucosa structures such as villi and glands, and the myenteric plexus controls the movement of the circular and longitudinal muscle for peristalsis.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The muscularis has a nerve plexus, but the serosa does not.</feedback></response><hint>These nerves would control contraction of smooth muscle tissue.</hint><hint>The first GI nerve plexus is named for the layer it is found in, under the layer with the thin smooth muscle that produces small, localized movement of the mucosa. The name of the second GI nerve plexus is derived from Greek “myos” for muscle and Greek “enteron” for intestine, because it is found in the layer with and controls the major muscle layers that perform peristalsis.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which two layers are made up of epithelial cells?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">mucosa and serosa</choice><choice value="B">mucosa and submucosa</choice><choice value="C">submucosa and muscularis</choice><choice value="D">muscularis and serosa</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i4b9a4937530b45d681af08701ddbe038"><skillref idref="wall_layers_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The innermost layer of mucosa and outermost layer of serosa are both epithelial tissues.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The submucosa is made of areolar connective tissue.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The submucosa is made of areolar connective tissue while the muscularis is made of smooth muscle.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The muscularis is made of smooth muscle.</feedback></response><hint>One is non-keratinized stratified or simple columnar epithelium with some glandular cells and other is simple squamous epithelium.</hint><hint>Remember epithelial cells will be on inner lumen or outer surface of organs.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Which structure would separate and define the change of the outer layer of the GI tract from adventitia to serous mesothelium?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">visceral peritoneum</choice><choice value="B">parietal peritoneum</choice><choice value="C">diaphragm</choice><choice value="D">greater omentum</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i26223c5eb72d4103b2769f603f55ca3d"><skillref idref="wall_layers_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the serous membrane covering the surface of abdominal organs.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the serous membrane lining the abdominal wall.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The esophagus superior to the diaphragm does not have a serous membrane on its outer surface, passing through the esophageal hiatus from the thoracic cavity to the abdominal cavity.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is one of the serous membrane folds in the abdominal cavity.</feedback></response><hint>The serous membranes would cover most of the abdominal organs within that cavity, but the esophagus passing through the mediastinum of the thoracic cavity is not passing within either the pericardial or pleural serous cavities.</hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body>Some organs of the GI tract are not within the peritoneal cavity even though they are in the abdominopelvic cavity, located between the parietal peritoneum and posterior wall of the abdomen. These include parts of the esophagus, pancreas, duodenum, colon, and rectum. What term would be used to describe their location?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">suprarenal</choice><choice value="B">infraspinatus</choice><choice value="C">extracellular</choice><choice value="D">retroperitoneal</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i62ebd7c6358e4e50b1f6f7a2b7a8459e"><skillref idref="wall_layers_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This mean above the kidney, as in the adrenal glands</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would mean below the spine, as in the scapula fossa</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be outside the cell, such as matrix of connective tissue</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. These parts would only have parietal peritoneum on their anterior surface; the kidneys are also retroperitoneal with cushion of adipose tissue outside the peritoneal cavity protection.</feedback></response><hint>Think of a term that means “backwards” or “in the past”.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
