<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="HCI_cells_lbd2"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>In addition to the causes of gastric ulcers discussed earlier, Zollinger-Ellison syndrome associated with a cancerous tumor in the pancreas or first part of small intestine also causes ulcers in the stomach and small intestine. This tumor increases the release of a hormone from cells in the pancreas or small intestine. What is this hormone that can increase the acidity of the stomach and thus stimulate formation of gastric and small intestine ulcers in this situation?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">gastrin</choice><choice value="B">pepsin</choice><choice value="C">lipase</choice><choice value="D">intrinsic factor</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i4e63259734ab4e6689835cc6d0a1d22d"><skillref idref="digest_cell_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This hormone will stimulate the secretion of acid in the gastric juice and can lead to the breakdown of the protective mucosal barrier discussed earlier.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an enzyme activated in the acidic lumen, not a hormone travelling in the blood.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an enzyme produced by chief cells for lipid digestion in the lumen.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is a chemical that binds to vitamin B12 in the small intestine to allow its absorption, not a hormone travelling in the blood.</feedback></response><hint>This is the same hormone produced by enteroendocrine cells in the stomach to increase the release of hydrochloric acid by parietal cells. It is also produced in the pancreas and small intestine, but the effect of the hormone is the same no matter its source.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
