<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<!--Created by OLI Author v2.0-->
<assessment id="smintest_regions">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
       <content><p>Match the small intestine section to the characteristic: </p></content>
        <question id="q1">
            
            <!--LO:smintest_regions_LO-->
            <body><p>Shortest and least mobile, with input from stomach, liver and pancreas</p></body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A">duodenum</choice>
                <choice value="B">jejunum</choice>
                <choice value="C">ileum</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Food enters through pyloric sphincter, while bile and pancreatic juice enters through hepatopancreatic sphincter.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. This is the middle, mobile section with no accessory gland ducts.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. This is the last, mobile section with no accessory gland ducts.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>This section receives food from the stomach through the pyloric sphincter.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        
        
        <question id="q2">
            
            <!--LO:smintest_regions_LO-->
            <body><p>Longest for increased transit time with continued digestion and absorption of most of the organic compounds</p></body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A">duodenum</choice>
                <choice value="B">jejunum</choice>
                <choice value="C">ileum</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Inorrect. this is shortest of three sections.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. In addition to length, the plicae circulares, villi, and microvilli also increase surface area for efficient absorption while chyme is in the small intestine.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. While absorption of remaining nutrients does occur, much of that has typically already happened before chyme reaches this last section.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>This is the middle section, between the other two.</hint>
            </part>
        
        </question>
        
        <question id="q3">
            
            <!--LO:smintest_regions_LO-->
            <body><p>Location of specialized glands for secretion of bicarbonate-rich mucus</p></body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A">duodenum</choice>
                <choice value="B">jejunum</choice>
                <choice value="C">ileum</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. This secretion helps neutralize the acidic chyme entering from stomach.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The glands here secrete typical mucus for lubrication and protection.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The glands here secrete typical mucus for lubrication and protection.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>This would need to be in the section receiving the acidic material directly from the stomach.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        
        <question id="q4">
            
            <!--LO:smintest_regions_LO-->
            <body><p>Location of most Peyer’s patches for immune response to bacteria that might enter from large intestine</p></body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A">duodenum</choice>
                <choice value="B">jejunum</choice>
                <choice value="C">ileum</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. This section receives the acidic chyme from stomach that helps destroy bacteria.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Although they are found here, this section is a distance from the large intestine.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. This section connects to the large intestine at the ileocecal sphincter.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>This would need to be in the last section, connecting to the large intestine through the ileocecal sphincter. </hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        
    </page>
</assessment>