<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Protein Synthesis" movieroot="">
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/structure.swf" menustep="tRNA Structures">
          <text>&lt;html&gt; The biosynthesis of proteins involves translation of the information contained in the mRNA into a polypeptide sequence. Each triplet of bases in the mRNA encodes one amino acid.  The translation is accomplished by the ribosome with the use of specialized RNA molecules called transfer RNA, or tRNA.  The tRNA molecules bind to the mRNA and deliver the correct amino acid to the growing polypeptide chain. 
        
        During this tutorial you will learn about the structure of tRNA molecules, how the correct amino acid become associated with each tRNA, and how the tRNAs act in concert with the Ribosome to synthesize a polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/primary.swf" menustep="   Primary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The primary structure of a tRNA is a linear polymer of ribonucleic acid containing approximately 70 nucleotide bases.  The 3' end of the tRNA contains the nucleotide sequence CCA, which is shown in black. The last base of this sequence will be joined to an amino acid during charging of the tRNA. If you hit the play button the tRNA will fold from its primary structure to its secondary structure, the traditional cloverleaf shape. Note the anticodon loop in the lower part of the diagram. This part of the rRNA binds to one codon in the mRNA.  &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/secondary.swf" menustep="   Secondary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The secondary structure of the tRNA is stabilized by hydrogen bonds between the anti-parallel strands as well as base stacking interactions, forming short helices of type A RNA that are similar in structure to the double helix in DNA.   By pressing the play button, you can see how the tRNA folds from its secondary structure into a complex tertiary structure. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>      
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/tertiary.swf" menustep="   Tertiary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The biosynthesis of proteins involves translation of the information contained in the mRNA into a polypeptide sequence. Each triplet of bases in the mRNA encodes one amino acid.  The translation is accomplished by the ribosome with the use of specialized RNA molecules called transfer RNA, or tRNA.  The tRNA molecules bind to the mRNA and deliver the correct amino acid to the growing polypeptide chain. 
        
        During this tutorial you will learn about the structure of tRNA molecules, how the correct amino acid become associated with each tRNA, and how the tRNAs act in concert with the Ribosome to synthesize a polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/charging.swf.swf" menustep="Charging tRNAs">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The correct charging of tRNAs by the 20 aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (aa-RS) is essential to the cell because once it is attached to a tRNA, an amino acid will be incorporated into protein strictly on the basis of the codon-anticodon interaction at the ribosome.
        
        This animation shows: 
        1. the basic steps of Met charging; and 
            2. how the tRNAIle synthetase achieves an error frequency &lt;1/10,000 even though the charging and hydrolysis steps are only about 99% accurate. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/charging_met.swf" menustep="   Met-tRNA with Met">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; In this reaction the correct amino acid is joined to the 3' CAA sequence of the tRNA. This is a two-step reaction that is catalized by the enzyme aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase:
        In the &lt;b&gt;first step&lt;/b&gt;, the amino acid is activated by attachment of the adenosine monophoswphate to the carboxy-terminus of the amino acid.
        In the &lt;b&gt;second step&lt;/b&gt;, the amino acid is transferred to the 3'-OH group of the tRNA and the charged tRNA is released into solution. Although the anticodon loop on the tRNA is used in decoding the mRNA, it is not used to select the specific tRNA that will be attached to a specific amino acid.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>        
<step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/ribo1.swf" menustep="Ribosome Structure">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The ribosome is an enormous particle composed of both ribosomal RNA (rRNA) molecules as well as many different proteins.  The ribosome normally exists as separate 30s and 50s subunits, however during translation both of these subunits  become associated to form a 70s particle. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/ribo2.swf" menustep="   3 Sites">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; There are three sites on the 70S ribosome that bind tRNAs:
            A: The amino-acyl site binds tRNA charged with the next amino acid that is to be added to the growing chain. This site also contains the growing peptide at one point in the elongation cycle.
            P: The peptidyl site contains a tRNA with the growing peptide chain attached to it.
            E: The exit site briefly holds the uncharged tRNA before it is released from the ribosome.  &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>   
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/polypeptide.swf" menustep="Building a Polypeptide">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The actual synthesis of a polypeptide involves three distinct phases:
            &lt;b&gt;Initiation:&lt;/b&gt; The mRNA, f-Met charged tRNA, and the 30s subunit form a initiation complex.  This complex then recruits the 50s subunit to form the 70s particle.
            &lt;b&gt;Elongation:&lt;/b&gt; Additional amino acids are added to the growing polypeptide chain.
            &lt;b&gt;Termination:&lt;/b&gt; The presence of stop codon in the mRNA signals termination of the process and release of the completed polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/initiation1.swf" menustep="   Initiation 1">
        <text>The initiation factors, IF-1 and IF-3, after helping to dissociate the 70S ribosome following polypeptide chain termination, remain on the 30S subunit.
            The actual order of assembly is uncertain. We show the mRNA binding the 30s subunit, followed by addition of the fMet-tRNA
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/initiation2.swf" menustep="   Initiation 2">
        <text>Initiation factor IF-2, with bound GTP, forms a complex with fMet-tRNAfMet and binds to the 30S subunit. This completes the formation of the "30S initiation complex".
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/initiation3.swf" menustep="   Initiation 3">
        <text>Before the 50S subunit joins this complex, IF-3 dissociates.  When the 50S subunit binds, GTP is hydrolyzed to GDP and IF-1 and IF-2 dissociate (leaving the "70S initiation complex" ready to bind the second aminoacyl-tRNA).
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/elongation1.swf" menustep="   Elongation 1">
        <text>The elongation factors, EF-Tu and EF-Ts, combine with GTP to form an EF-Tu-GTP complex with dissociation of EF-Ts. The EF-Tu-GTP complex binds aminoacyl-tRNA and brings it to the vacated A-site on the ribosome. GTP is hydrolyzed; EF-Tu-GDP dissociates; and EF-Ts combines with EF-Tu to begin another cycle.
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/elongation2.swf" menustep="   Elongation 2">
        <text>With peptidyl-tRNA in the P site and aminoacyl-tRNA in the A site, peptidyl transfer occurs without any additional energy input, e.g. ATP or GTP hydrolysis.
            After this process, the nascent peptide chain is  found in the A-site.
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/elongation3.swf" menustep="   Elongation 3">
        <text>Translocation requires the action  of the EF-G-GTP complex. It binds between the two ribosomal subunits in the vicinity of the A site. During translocation, GTP is hydrolyzed; EF-G, GDP, and P dissociate. The newly-formed peptidyl-tRNA has moved to the P-site. The uncharged tRNA has moved to the E-site, from which it quickly dissociates.
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/elongation4.swf" menustep="   Elongation 4">
        <text>This process continues until the stop signal is reached.  The addition of each amino acid requires the hydrolysis of two GTP molecules, one for loading of the charged tRNA and one for translocation, or moving, of the ribosome.
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/termination1.swf" menustep="   Termination 1">
        <text>A protein called the release factor binds to the stop codon on the mRNA.</text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="ProteinSynthesis/swfs/termination2.swf" menustep="   Termination 2">
        <text>The release factor allows water to hydrolyze the bond between the finished peptide and the last tRNA molecule.  Then the entire complex disassociates, releasing the completed peptide.</text>
    </step>
</TUTORIAL>
