<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="a7a2804fb0864eb2b6c94b0d28b3f09a"><head><title>Nervous System Unit Review</title></head><body><p id="d1a13c90c1424c17ae85f9141f7fb73d">Consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives.</p><ul id="cd4219bee0b942eab49c6a24e95b17e3"><li><p id="aa0f1c45f307c487a91faa58fdda26641">Describe the major functions of the Nervous System.</p></li><li><p id="ab0bb67af02b541cebe86d2c0dfd3b4a4">Describe the basic (overall) structure of the human brain.</p></li><li><p id="aec3af47e6c954be7a52276b889c76878">Explain the roles of CSF, ventricles, and the blood brain barrier.</p></li><li><p id="afcafd52163e742879123187d3ed7c9ec">Correlate hindbrain and midbrain regions to their major function(s).</p></li><li><p id="abe5ab0d82225442c9d8935289c233cb1">Correlate forebrain regions to their major functions(s).</p></li><li><p id="ab2579b3bdb704ff7b35875734baf47a9">Identify the location of major brain regions.</p></li><li><p id="af782a11c46074e359fc7888af6a0d256">Assign function(s) to each of the cranial nerves.</p></li><li><p id="aad58c99d64ef4fc4be70a3854c33a62e">Describe the gross anatomy of the spinal cord and spinal nerves and specify their location relative to the anatomy of the vertebral column.</p></li><li><p id="ae1d65158d60849f7b5970f1a2701f5d0">Contrast the relative position of gray matter and white matter in the spinal cord with the corresponding arrangement of gray and white matter in the brain.</p></li><li><p id="ae46b9b3bf4944b72b948b460e3cd6360">Compare and contrast the anatomical features of the spinal cord in the cervical, thoracic and lumbar regions.</p></li><li><p id="aa45cd9947fa54504af0f3a2526c6f858">Identify how spinal structures relate to each other: tract, root, ganglion, nerve, ramus, plexus.</p></li><li><p id="aa3f4ee3f431b45f0855152f97d3e2bf9">Classify the organs that are part of the nervous system as belonging to the central nervous system (CNS) or the peripheral nervous system (PNS).</p></li><li><p id="ab7abe44f069a45428907d6be3482f3b2">Within a neuron, identify the soma, axon and dendrite and describe the main function of each region.</p></li><li><p id="ab51ed234317b43b9a570191592b7bc85">Identify neurons based on anatomical features: unipolar, bipolar, multipolar and anaxonic and based on functional properties: sensory, motor, interneuron.</p></li><li><p id="aefdd4c195f5f405fb92fe57a1a7bb6ec">List the four types of CNS glial cells and describe their function.</p></li><li><p id="afa5ed28dc118445cb1fe37b144769e07">List the two types of PNS glial cells and describe their function. Describe the anatomical relationship between the glial cells and the PNS.</p></li><li><p id="aca48c0d2fd8f4758a71ba95b6d1417b9">Compare the structure of myelinated vs. unmyelinated axons. Distinguish between white matter and gray matter.</p></li><li><p id="aa7662e4c2ca94277b4d8a3891b36f62d">Describe the transmembrane potential or voltage across the cell membrane and how it is measured.</p></li><li><p id="afd940c1a77af43739e7d548b29b9f890">Contrast the relative concentrations of ions in body solutions inside and outside of a cell (sodium, potassium, calcium and chloride ions).</p></li><li><p id="af3fac50075f04177aaa01df29863fd86">Explain how four factors determine a neuron’s resting membrane potential.</p></li><li><p id="ab565dca8bbcc45bbac233762b79af25a">Explain how a local electrical response in a neuron membrane is caused by stimulation.</p></li><li><p id="af7e49d7cb838452ea8be7bbc412a58a1">Interpret a graph showing the voltage vs. time relationship of an action potential. </p></li><li><p id="aaba167366b124ed9a82776accf07b728">Explain action potential.</p></li><li><p id="ad7398b83e30c42b4907f35d80b1566ff">Identify the presynaptic and postsynaptic cells at a synapse.</p></li><li><p id="ad8b7a9805e2f40c5b0d7e4567759f602">Explain synaptic transmission in terms of the structural and functional features of electrical and chemical synapses.</p></li><li><p id="acb2935f4caa1441b855c80c4d9132618">Explain how a single neurotransmitter may have different effects at different postsynaptic cells.</p></li><li><p id="adbf59349bbe24502a7c90b7bb36cc037">Explain temporal and spatial summation of synaptic potentials and discuss how action potentials differ from synaptic potentials.</p></li><li><p id="ab9f8f20b6cb74b9b8fff6a428f489049">Identify the four classes of neurotransmitters and identify the most common excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmitters.</p></li><li><p id="aea73673d6c7243f8a6ec5f56c646c6f4">Explain the role of the autonomic nervous system as a motor division of the nervous system.</p></li><li><p id="af834d2edd49e4f9eb967c011e8c0cc66">Compare the somatic and autonomic nervous systems.</p></li><li><p id="ac0c9cd7c605847678982bc44380e014b">Contrast the anatomy of the parasympathetic and sympathetic systems.</p></li><li><p id="ae0705f26b6b044c7bbdf1bead9b222b8">Describe the local organization of each of the sympathetic and parasympathetic systems, including the pattern of innervation of target glands, organs, and tissues.</p></li><li><p id="ad99f1f2997294e32a949f6526b44b6a7">Describe major parasympathetic and sympathetic physiological effects on target organs.</p></li><li><p id="ae72c6e803ff74547b9f0d78b26b34808">Identify the neurotransmitters released by preganglionic and postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems and describe their effects.</p></li><li><p id="aedcfef972b184fc493111e5a8b302fde">Describe examples of specific effectors dually innervated by the autonomic nervous system and explain how each branch influences function in a given effector.</p></li><li><p id="ae2ece9ab488340f4a31a31c2f8759231">Name examples of effectors innervated either by only the sympathetic branch or by only the parasympathetic branch of the autonomic nervous system and explain how that branch by itself influences function in a given effector.</p></li><li><p id="ab50aaf8c6f2b4a09bc43fc36ed833030">Classify receptors based on structure, location relative to the stimulus, and types of signals they transduce.</p></li><li><p id="aa2deba77788c402a875fa9c87a921072">Explain the distribution of receptors involved in providing information for our general (somesthetic) senses.</p></li><li><p id="af5438dd6f3b94ea6a62339ae366cf93b">Describe the types of information (modality) detected by the receptors associated with the somesthetic senses and the phenomenon of adaptation.</p></li><li><p id="abc355559a6a641e387f5cfd338204259">Explain pain function, nociceptor distribution, and distinguish the fiber types that carry their signals.</p></li><li><p id="aebca1e483af6419184f8316fda3564db">Describe pain in terms of hyperalgesia, analgesia, and receptive field.</p></li><li><p id="ab0683cda394b4272a8bf33e30fb1db68">Define dermatome and explain how dermatomes can be used in neurological exams for diagnosing nerve damage.</p></li><li><p id="adf7fff1280b546c8a9b1b1420856c81f">Describe reflexes, reflex repsonses, and distinguish types of reflexes.</p></li><li><p id="afe8c4c81605b4b8099e540122a058bad">Identify and describe the functions of the accessory eye structures, the tunics, and the optical components of the eye.</p></li><li><p id="ad6244b0aeb08452da05a7e3bcf224d05">Identify the muscles that help to coordinate eye movement.</p></li><li><p id="af911bb097a7d4e34a075d229852bb0de">Describe the structures and functions of the eye.</p></li><li><p id="abdf9eea835ef41bba842a28bc88c293c">Explain how the path of light through the eye causes vision.</p></li><li><p id="afc5a18ba81f44fb9b89552cf84837f72">Trace the path of nerve impulses from the retina to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="aab4e48288d92447092f1c7cfa6cee7ee">Identify the hearing structures of the outer, middle and inner ear and describe their functions.</p></li><li><p id="ad9c7b081743340399b29546fd3923fb6">Describe how the various structures of the ear conduct and transduce sound.</p></li><li><p id="ad7047f19e4734c7ba2b200bb95b39b31">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the ear to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="ae861ae4252eb462ebd3d2541fa0e7fb7">Distinguish between static and dynamic equilibrium, describe the structures involved, and their functions.</p></li><li><p id="ac9f100e46a604876ae46d4345bd8aec0">Explain the gustation and describe the structures involved.</p></li><li><p id="afb3d26c82be24f08b9eef5ee3580fd2b">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the gustatory receptors to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="ab8c258bc36e04fb790bbc7adf80bfa96">Explain how odorants activate olfactory receptors.</p></li><li><p id="ae5c03215d37c47c5bb392516ad5c9167">Describe the path of nerve impulses from the olfactory receptors to various parts of the brain.</p></li><li><p id="aefc5053e3604480083b79999c7e2d5bb">Predict the types of problems that would occur in the body if the olfactory system was not functioning normally.</p></li></ul><activity idref="c38c052fae474cc9b368fcb7628639f9" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
