<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="a9fb638975ae49d89b2400a66f5d38bf"><head><title>Cardiovasular System Unit Review and Assessment</title></head><body><p id="d1a13c90c1424c17ae85f9141f7fb73d">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="cd4219bee0b942eab49c6a24e95b17e3"><li><p id="aa0f1c45f307c487a91faa58fdda26641">Explain how the cardiovascular system performs the function of moving material through the body.</p></li><li><p id="ab0bb67af02b541cebe86d2c0dfd3b4a4">Identify major diseases associated with the cardiovascular system and their causes.</p></li><li><p id="aec3af47e6c954be7a52276b889c76878">Describe the conduction system of the heart, including the role of the autonomic nervous system in regulating aspects of cardiac conduction.</p></li><li><p id="afcafd52163e742879123187d3ed7c9ec">Identify the waveforms in a normal ECG and relate them to the activity of the conduction system of the heart.</p></li><li><p id="abe5ab0d82225442c9d8935289c233cb1">Describe the cardiac cycle and all of its phases.</p></li><li><p id="ab2579b3bdb704ff7b35875734baf47a9">Identify the relationship between cardiac output (CO), heart rate (HR), and stroke volume (SV) and predict how changes in HR and SV affect CO.</p></li><li><p id="af782a11c46074e359fc7888af6a0d256">Define blood pressure (BP) and describe factors that influence blood pressure. Relate blood pressure to mean arterial pressure (MAP) and how MAP is calculated.</p></li><li><p id="aad58c99d64ef4fc4be70a3854c33a62e">Describe the different modes of transport that molecules may take during capillary exchange. Define Starling&apos;s Law of the Capillaries and use it to determine the relative rate and direction of fluid exchange in the capillaries. Relate imbalances in capillary exchange to edema.</p></li><li><p id="ae1d65158d60849f7b5970f1a2701f5d0">Define venous return and describe how skeletal muscles and the respiratory pump help maintain venous return.</p></li><li><p id="ae46b9b3bf4944b72b948b460e3cd6360">Contrast the vasculature of the systemic and pulmonary circuits.</p></li><li><p id="aa45cd9947fa54504af0f3a2526c6f858">Describe the overall composition of plasma, including the major types of plasma proteins, their functions, and where in the body they are produced.</p></li><li><p id="aa3f4ee3f431b45f0855152f97d3e2bf9">Describe the phases of hemostasis.</p></li><li><p id="ab7abe44f069a45428907d6be3482f3b2">Identify the microscopic features of erythrocytes (red blood cells), the five types of leukocytes (white blood cells), and thrombocytes (platelets).</p></li><li><p id="ab51ed234317b43b9a570191592b7bc85">Identify the function of red blood cells and describe the life cycle of red blood cells, including how and where iron and heme are recycled, as well as the resulting breakdown products.</p></li><li><p id="aefdd4c195f5f405fb92fe57a1a7bb6ec">Describe the functions for each of the five major types of leukocytes as well as the two major subtypes of lymphocytes (T and B).</p></li><li><p id="afa5ed28dc118445cb1fe37b144769e07">Describe the structure and function of platelets.</p></li><li><p id="aca48c0d2fd8f4758a71ba95b6d1417b9">Describe the basic process of hematopoiesis, where it occurs, and the significance of the pluripotent stem cell (hemocytoblast) in the process.</p></li><li><p id="aa7662e4c2ca94277b4d8a3891b36f62d">Identify the types of cells associated with blood vessels and relate them to the different properties of blood vessels.</p></li><li><p id="afd940c1a77af43739e7d548b29b9f890">Describe the features of blood that give it the characteristics of a connective tissue.</p></li><li><p id="af3fac50075f04177aaa01df29863fd86">Identify the three kinds of cells that make up the myocardium and describe the role of each in the physiology of muscle contraction.</p></li><li><p id="ab565dca8bbcc45bbac233762b79af25a">Describe the properties of the vessel wall layers (tunica interna, media, externa) and associate each with the function of different vessel types.</p></li><li><p id="af7e49d7cb838452ea8be7bbc412a58a1">Describe the anatomical structures of the heart and major blood vessels entering and leaving the heart. Relate the features of these structures to blood flow into, out of, and through the heart.</p></li><li><p id="aaba167366b124ed9a82776accf07b728">Describe the anatomy of the aorta and its major branches and relate it with their functions.</p></li><li><p id="ad7398b83e30c42b4907f35d80b1566ff">Describe the anatomical structure of the arteries in the body and relate it with their function.</p></li><li><p id="ad8b7a9805e2f40c5b0d7e4567759f602">Describe the structure and function of arterioles, metarterioles, capillaries, and venules.</p></li><li><p id="acb2935f4caa1441b855c80c4d9132618">Describe the anatomical structure of the veins in the body and relate it with their function.</p></li><li><p id="adbf59349bbe24502a7c90b7bb36cc037">Describe common changes of the circulatory system related to aging.</p></li><li><p id="ab9f8f20b6cb74b9b8fff6a428f489049">Describe factors that could disrupt homeostasis of the cardiovascular system and predict the types of homeostatic imbalances that would occur.</p></li><li><p id="aea73673d6c7243f8a6ec5f56c646c6f4">Explain how the cardiovascular system relates to other body systems to maintain homeostasis through autoregulation.</p></li><li><p id="af834d2edd49e4f9eb967c011e8c0cc66">Describe the determinants of blood flow to an organ or tissue.</p></li><li><p id="ac0c9cd7c605847678982bc44380e014b">Identify unique characteristics of blood flow to the liver, the kidney, and the hypothalamus/pituitary system.</p></li><li><p id="ae0705f26b6b044c7bbdf1bead9b222b8">Explain the role of the sympathetic nervous system in regulation of cardiac output.</p></li><li><p id="ad99f1f2997294e32a949f6526b44b6a7">Identify the hormones involved in regulating blood volume flow and blood pressure and the role they play in these processes.</p></li></ul><activity idref="_u9_cardio_unit_quiz" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="_u9_m5_integration_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
