<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bc3ef329f7e142e7870c29c53206c4c6"><head><title>Lymphatic System Unit Review</title></head><body><p id="d1a13c90c1424c17ae85f9141f7fb73d">Consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives.</p><ul id="cd4219bee0b942eab49c6a24e95b17e3"><li><p id="aa0f1c45f307c487a91faa58fdda26641">Explore some common misconceptions about the lymphatic system. </p></li><li><p id="ab0bb67af02b541cebe86d2c0dfd3b4a4">Explore connections between the Big Ideas of Anatomy &amp; Physiology and the Lymphatic System and Immunity.</p></li><li><p id="aec3af47e6c954be7a52276b889c76878">Recognize Big Ideas seen in the workings of individual components of the Lymphatic System and Immunity.</p></li><li><p id="afcafd52163e742879123187d3ed7c9ec">Describe the lymphatic system: list the major organs and structures, describe the major functions, and use anatomical planes and directional terms to identify organs and their relationships to each other.</p></li><li><p id="abe5ab0d82225442c9d8935289c233cb1">Describe the major functions of the lymphatic system. Define immunity.</p></li><li><p id="ab2579b3bdb704ff7b35875734baf47a9">Compare and contrast interstitial fluid and lymph. </p></li><li><p id="af782a11c46074e359fc7888af6a0d256">Compare and contrast lymphatic vessels and blood vessels in terms of structure and function. Describe the mechanisms of lymph formation and circulation. Describe the path of lymph circulation.</p></li><li><p id="aad58c99d64ef4fc4be70a3854c33a62e">Identify dysfunction associated with the lymphatic circulation.</p></li><li><p id="ae1d65158d60849f7b5970f1a2701f5d0">Describe early events in the history of immunology in relation to current understanding of immunity.</p></li><li><p id="ae46b9b3bf4944b72b948b460e3cd6360">Identify major diseases associated with the lymphatic system and their causes.</p></li><li><p id="aa45cd9947fa54504af0f3a2526c6f858">Integrate the levels of organization in the lymphatic system and their functional interconnections.</p></li><li><p id="aa3f4ee3f431b45f0855152f97d3e2bf9">Describe the basic structure and function of chemical molecules of the lymphatic system and correlate it to the overall functions of lymphatic system.</p></li><li><p id="ab7abe44f069a45428907d6be3482f3b2">Explain how interferons, complement and tranferrins function as antimicrobial chemicals.</p></li><li><p id="ab51ed234317b43b9a570191592b7bc85">Describe how histamine, kinins, prostaglandins, leukotrienes and complement contribute to flammation.</p></li><li><p id="aefdd4c195f5f405fb92fe57a1a7bb6ec">Define and describe location of pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) and their receptors (PRRs). </p></li><li><p id="afa5ed28dc118445cb1fe37b144769e07">Define and describe location of antigens and antigen receptors. Discuss the source of antigen receptor diversity. </p></li><li><p id="aca48c0d2fd8f4758a71ba95b6d1417b9">Define and describe location of major histocompatibility complex (MHC). </p></li><li><p id="aa7662e4c2ca94277b4d8a3891b36f62d">Describe antibody structure, list the five classes of antibodies and functional features that distinguish each class.</p></li><li><p id="afd940c1a77af43739e7d548b29b9f890">Define and describe the functional role of the important cytokines participating in the immune response.</p></li><li><p id="af3fac50075f04177aaa01df29863fd86">Define and describe the roles of various types of white blood cells in the innate and adaptive immune response and correlate them to the overall functions of the lymphatic system.</p></li><li><p id="ab565dca8bbcc45bbac233762b79af25a">Name the cells of the innate immune response and correlate their function to the overall functions of the innate immune response.</p></li><li><p id="af7e49d7cb838452ea8be7bbc412a58a1">Name the cells of the adaptive immune response and correlate their function to the overall functions of the adaptive immune response.</p></li><li><p id="aaba167366b124ed9a82776accf07b728">Compare and contrast interstitial fluid and lymph. Describe the basic structure and cellular composition of lymphatic tissues and correlate them to the overall functions of the lymphatic system.</p></li><li><p id="ad7398b83e30c42b4907f35d80b1566ff">Identify the lymphatic organs and correlate them to the overall functions of the of the lymphatic system. Identify and describe the gross anatomical and microscopic anatomy of each organ. Describe the location and function of each organ.</p></li><li><p id="ad8b7a9805e2f40c5b0d7e4567759f602">Compare and contrast innate defenses with adaptive defenses. Analyze ways in which the innate and adaptive immunity cooperate to enhance the overall resistance to disease.</p></li><li><p id="acb2935f4caa1441b855c80c4d9132618">Describe the types of defensive mechanisms of innate immunity such as barriers, phagocytosis, inflammation and fever.</p></li><li><p id="adbf59349bbe24502a7c90b7bb36cc037">Name the barriers and describe their anatomic, chemical and microbiological mechanisms of defense.</p></li><li><p id="ab9f8f20b6cb74b9b8fff6a428f489049">Describe the origin and roles of various white blood cells in innate immunity. </p></li><li><p id="aea73673d6c7243f8a6ec5f56c646c6f4">Describe the steps involved in phagocytosis and give examples of phagocytic cells in the body. Describe the mechanisms of inflammation initiation. Summarize the cells and chemicals involved in the inflammatory process. List and explain the cause of the four cardinal signs of inflammation. Explain the benefits of inflammation. </p></li><li><p id="af834d2edd49e4f9eb967c011e8c0cc66">Describe the steps involved in phagocytosis and give examples of phagocytic cells in the body. </p></li><li><p id="ac0c9cd7c605847678982bc44380e014b">Describe the mechanisms of inflammation initiation. Summarize the cells and chemicals involved in the inflammatory process. List and explain the cause of the four cardinal signs of inflammation. Explain the benefits of inflammation. </p></li><li><p id="ae0705f26b6b044c7bbdf1bead9b222b8">Explain how the kinin-kallikrein and complement systems aid in the inflammatory response. Describe the mechanism and benefits of fever and the role of pyrogens. </p></li><li><p id="ad99f1f2997294e32a949f6526b44b6a7">Distinguish between innate and adaptive immunity. Distinguish the various types of lymphocytes including helper T cells, cytotoxic T cells, B cells, plasma cells and memory cells. Distinguish between humoral and cell-mediated immunity. Describe the immunological memory response. </p></li><li><p id="adb7cacd5bd1f4c31b1312b06e731e709">Explain the role of antigen-presenting cells (APCs). Distinguish and describe the processing of exogenous and endogenous antigens and provide examples of APCs. </p></li><li><p id="ad53ad0efbdf54edcbf0335ff9936afe9">Define immunocompetence (maturity) and self tolerance and distinguish between naïve and activated immune cells. Compare and contrast mechanisms of antigen challenge and the clonal selection processes and defense mechanisms.</p></li><li><p id="afb498da8390d47ca940fd5630808bb72">Provide specific examples to demonstrate how the lymphatic system responds to maintain homeostasis in the body, particularly related to the diseases presented in the introduction. </p></li><li><p id="afa2f6776e5534e40b0b2e3bd3ee28ddf">Explore the condition and symptoms of B-Cell Chronic Leukemia using concepts and vocabulary from the Lymphatic System unit.</p></li><li><p id="ada2d71d2665549efbdee4da6ee396e75">Describe the basic process of hematopoiesis, where it occurs, and the significance of the pluripotent stem cell (hemocytoblast) in the process.</p></li><li><p id="aa7ddd5b9bbe649e99eb18282d042c498">Explain how the lymphatic system relates to other body systems to maintain homeostasis.</p></li></ul><activity idref="b5bd0deee04f420492252190978bc1a7" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
