<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e3dad49a0e5d44d19d9c27260be46db2"><head><title>Respiratory System Unit Review and Assessment</title></head><body><p id="d1a13c90c1424c17ae85f9141f7fb73d">Consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives.</p><ul id="cd4219bee0b942eab49c6a24e95b17e3"><li><p id="aa0f1c45f307c487a91faa58fdda26641">Describe major functions and processes of the respiratory system.</p></li><li><p id="aaa5f42d2f2724e7283fe774de169c718">Identify and describe gross &amp; microscopic anatomy of the respiratory tract and related organs.</p></li><li><p id="af86863fe66ca433bab7f5c4db0a29efa">Describe the structure and function of the the respiratory conducting zone and respiratory zone.</p></li><li><p id="aef07ae29d7b7450d8453c9f8566d46d2">Describe the mechanisms of pulmonary ventilation.</p></li><li><p id="ab857ad6ac67643d3b98301557b673c8c">Define, identify, and determine values for the respiratory volumes (IRV, TV, ERV, and RV) and the respiratory capacities (IC, FRC, VC, and TLC).</p></li><li><p id="ae11f50a8629d45cc835dea5f9876a3e3">Describe the four respiratory processes - ventilation, external respiration (gas exchange at lung), internal respiration (gas exchange at body tissues), and cellular respiration.</p></li><li><p id="af91def5b18e94ed4bc35d06c3088d8ea">State Henry’s Law, and relate it to the events of external and internal respiration and to the amounts of oxygen and carbon dioxide dissolved in plasma.</p></li><li><p id="aebb0a7e7827842dfbbab28ab5f7abdca">Describe and analyze the mechanisms of gas exchange in the lungs &amp; tissues.</p></li><li><p id="aea37a86c2fce4971bbcea5a8fd18fc29">Describe how the structure of these macromolecules allow the structures of the respiratory system to perform their functions.</p></li><li><p id="afe1903e443a246f4bd7784fe13b17a64">Explain the mechanisms of gas transport in the blood.</p></li><li><p id="acfeae9ef82b84e64a9a12e41e34e489a">Describe the changes in epithelial and connective tissue seen in various portions of the air passageways and relate these changes to function.</p></li><li><p id="ad088865a1f1749aba2d245c0e002ff16">Explain and analyze respiratory homeostatic mechanisms.</p></li></ul><activity idref="a5ac55cafe0f4d61954f7f779c79cf24" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
