<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="Google_Doc_Markup_Rules_1">
	<head>
		<title>Google Doc Markup Rules</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>This document will explain how to markup a Google Doc so that the document can be translated to OLI XML.</p>
		<p>The first heading on the page will be used as the page title. So for example, if this document were to get translated, the page title would be "Google Doc Markup Rules".</p>
		<p>Enter regular text in paragraphs as you normally would when writing a document, using the "Normal Paragraph Text" style from the "Styles" pull-down menu above.</p>
		<p>You can use <em style="bold">bold</em> and <em style="italic">italics</em>. To denote a <term>key term</term>, use a font color other than black. It is also possible to mark up variables by using a fixed width font - just set the font face to Courier New.</p>
		<p>Images can be inserted in the document by choosing "Insert -&gt; Image":</p>
		<image src="../webcontent/Google_Doc_Markup_Rules/image1.jpeg"></image>
		<p>Similarly, figures can be inserted by choosing "Insert -&gt; Drawing". Google Docs has a nice drawing editor that you can use to create figures.</p>
		<image src="../webcontent/Google_Doc_Markup_Rules/image2.png"></image>
		<section>
			<title>Section Title</title>
			<body>
				<p>To start a section, enter the section title and then style it as "Heading" text (any size is ok) from the "Styles" pull-down menu above.</p>
				<p>To end a section, use a horizontal line (choose "Insert -&gt; Horizontal line") like this:</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<p>For tables, choose "Table -&gt; Insert Table". Assigning a background color to a table cell indicates that it is a table header. Cell alignment is supported, as shown in the table below. Google Docs does not support row and column spanning.</p>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<th></th>
				<th>Column Header 1</th>
				<th>Column Header 2</th>
				<th>Column Header 3</th>
				<th>Column Header 4</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<th>Row Header 1</th>
				<td>Left</td>
				<td>Center</td>
				<td>Right</td>
				<td></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<th>Row Header 2</th>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
			</tr>
		</table>
		<p>Ordered and unordered lists are supported - just use the appropriate buttons on the Google Doc toolbar above.</p>
		<ol>
			<li>Item 1</li>
			<li>Item 2</li>
			<li>Item 3</li>
		</ol>
		<ul>
			<li>Item 1</li>
			<li>Item 2</li>
			<li>Item 3</li>
		</ul>
		<example>
			<title>Translation and Rotation</title>
			<p>An example is styled similar to a section. It starts with header text containing the word "Example:", and is followed by the example title. You can also create definitions, figures, and quotations with this method.</p>
			<p>To end an example, use a horizontal line ("Insert -&gt; Horizontal line").</p>
		</example>
		<p>To start a new page, insert a page break ("Insert -&gt; Page break").</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>