<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="kidney_stones">
 <head>
  <title>Disorders of the Kidneys: Kidney Stones</title>
 </head>

 <body>

  
  
  <p>Kidney stones are one of the most painful urinary system disorders. Also called
   calculi ("little stones"), kidney stones are not a new disorder. Scientists have
   discovered them in 7,000-year-old Egyptian mummies. Kidney stones are formed
   when the uric acid salts, magnesium, or calcium in urine crystallize. Certain
   types of kidney stones run in families and appear to have a hereditary
   component. Some substances in foods may also contribute to the incidence of
   kidney stones. Most calculi are small enough to pass through the urinary tract
   and be eliminated with urine. Stones larger than five millimeters in diameter,
   however, can prevent urine from draining. The backed-up urine exerts increasing
   pressure in the kidney, causing extreme pain in the back and side near the
   kidney or in the lower abdomen. Kidney stones can also contribute to
   dehydration. Each year, about 2.4 million Americans seek treatment for kidney
   stones. They are more common in people with a family history of calculi, or who
   have urine retention or frequent bacterial urinary tract infections. The most
   commonly used treatment for kidney stones is a procedure called extracorporeal
   shock wave lithotripsy. Shock waves created outside the body pass through the
   skin and body tissues and break down the stones into small particles that can be
   eliminated in the urine. In severe cases, endoscopic or open surgery may be
   required to remove the stones.</p>
 </body>



</workbook_page>
