<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="renal_ptosis">
 <head>
  <title>Disorders of the Kidneys: Renal Ptosis</title>
 </head>

 <body>

  <p>The kidneys are secured in place by a capsule of fat. People who lose a lot of weight in
   a short period of time can also lose some of the fat that surrounds their kidneys. Very
   thin people may not have enough fat around their kidneys to hold them in their normal
   position. In either case, one or both kidneys may drop down into the pelvis when a
   person stands up, a condition called <em style="bold">renal ptosis</em> (<em
    style="italic">ptosis</em>: "to fall"). Congenital physical abnormalities may also
   predispose individuals to renal ptosis, which may occur after physical trauma. This is a
   common condition, especially in females. Also called <em style="bold">nephroptosis
   </em>or <em style="bold">floating kidney</em>, renal ptosis can create a kink in the
   ureter, preventing the drainage of urine. Urine can then back up into the kidney,
   creating pressure that may damage renal tissue. Even when urine flow is not obstructed,
   renal ptosis can cause considerable pain, as well as vomiting. Diagnosis is
   controversial but may be confirmed by a patient experiencing relief from abdominal pain
   upon lying in a supine position and/or by imaging tests. Treatment for severely
   symptomatic patients usually involves a surgical procedure called <em style="bold"
    >nephropexy</em>. This procedure affixes the kidney to the retroperitoneal tissue,
   closer to its usual position, and may be done laparoscopically.</p>
 </body>



</workbook_page>
