<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="urinary_track_infections">
 <head>
  <title>Disorders of the Kidneys: Urinary Tract Infections</title>
 </head>

 <body>

  
  <p>Urinary tract infections (UTIs) are the most common type of bacterial infection.
   Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are shorter than those of
   men. Moreover, the urethra's external opening in women is closer to the anus
   than it is in men. Over 50 percent of women will have a UTI at some point during
   their lifetime. Fecal bacteria such as <em style="italic">Escherichia coli</em>
   (<em style="italic">E. coli</em>) can easily travel up the urethra. This is
   why women should never wipe the anus in a forward direction after defecation.
   However, most UTIs in women occur as a result of sexual activity. During
   intercourse, bacteria from the external genital area and the vagina can be
   pushed up the short urethra toward the bladder. The use of spermicides actually
   increases the risk of UTIs, because spermicides kill bacteria that would
   otherwise help destroy infectious fecal bacteria in the vagina. Drinking plenty
   of water and urinating immediately after sexual activity can help prevent UTIs
   by flushing bacteria out of the urethra. Infection of the urethra (<em
    style="bold">urethritis</em>) can easily spread to the urinary bladder (<em
     style="bold">cystitis</em>) and sometimes to the kidneys (<em style="bold"
      >pyelitis </em>or <em style="bold">pyelonephritis</em>). Symptoms of a UTI
   include pain during urination (<em style="bold">dysuria</em>), frequent
   urination or an urgent need to urinate, cloudiness or blood in the urine (<em
    style="bold">hematuria</em>), urine with a strong odor, nausea, and fever.
   Fortunately, most UTIs respond to antibiotics. Analgesics may also be prescribed
   to reduce discomfort. Unfortunately, having a UTI increases the chances of
   having subsequent UTIs. UTIs are also common in infants, particularly in
   uncircumcised male infants.</p>
 </body>



</workbook_page>
