<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Biological Membranes" movieroot="unit2/">
    <step stepURL="swfs/biological.swf" menustep="Biological Membranes">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Biological membranes are dynamic structures composed of a diverse set of phospholipid molecules and proteins. In the case of eukaryotic organisms, they also contain the steroid cholesterol. The phospholipid component of the biological membrane is responsibile for the key property of membranes, they act as an impermeable barrier towards most molecules. Many molecules can only cross the membrane with the aid of proteins within the membrane.  Therefore, membranes define the boundary of cells as well intra-cellular organelles.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;red&gt;Click the play button to advance through the next scenes.&lt;/red&gt; &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mic.swf"  menustep="   Micelle Formation ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;When fatty acids or phospholipids are added to water they self-assemble into aggregates such that the charged or polar heads groups make contact with the water and the hydrophobic hydrocarbon tails are restricted to water-free areas. In the case of fatty acids and other detergent like molecules, they will orient at an air-water interface such that the non-polar tails project into the air. In addition, some fatty acids will enter the water and spontaneously form single shelled structures called micelles.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;red&gt;Click the play button to advance through the scenes.&lt;/red&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/bilayerpho.swf"  menustep="   Bilayer Formation ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; When phospholipids are added to water, they will also orient at the air-water interface in the same way as fatty acids, with the polar/charged head groups in contact with the water and the non-polar acyl chains in the air.  An additional layer of phospholipids can be added to make a stable phospholipid bilayer with water on both sides of membrane.
        &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>   
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/liposome.swf"  menustep="   Liposome Formation ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; When this solution is shaken, the phospholipids that are immersed in the water will form a LIPOSOME. They orient the hydrophilic "heads" of the molecules to water and shield the hydrophobic "tails" from water.
	&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>   
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/permiability_05.swf" menustep="   Bilayer Permeability ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; This diagram shows a lipid bilayer that is formed from two layers of phospholipids molecules.The polar head-groups of the phospholipids are oriented towards of the aqueous solvent while the long non-polar hydrocarbon, or acil, chains are sequestred in the interior of the membrane. 
        Note that:
        i) The membrane is flexible and dynamic.
        ii) Water molecules, which are polar but uncharged, can cross the membrane. 
        iii) Ions, such as Na+, never cross the membrane. &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>   </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/proteinMobility.swf"  menustep="   Bilayer Mobility ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; The proteins can move around the surface of the bilayer.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
</step>
<!--<step stepURL="structure.swf"  menustep="   Phospholypid  Structure ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; Describe &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
</step>-->
    <step stepURL="swfs/phospholipids.swf"  menustep=" Phospholipids" popupname="    Phospholipids">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;&lt;red&gt;Use the PLAY button to advance through the scenes of this animation.&lt;/red&gt;&lt;/html&gt;
     </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/bilayers.swf"  menustep=" Bilayers" popupname="   Bilayers">
     <text>&lt;html&gt;.&lt;/html&gt;
     </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/phase.swf"  menustep="&nbsp;Phase Transition ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; Phospholipids bilayers undergo a cooperative phase transition or melting that is similar to protein denaturation. The high degree of cooperativity is due to extensive interactions between the non-polar acyl chains in the center of the bilayer. The overall structure of the lipid bilayer is not changed by this transition. However, the disorder of the non-polar hydrocarbon chains increases dramatically after melting.
    &lt;/html&gt;
        </text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/saturated.swf"  menustep="   Saturated ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;At low temperatures the saturated acyl chains are able to pack close to each other as extended chains. This is very stable configuration because of the favorable van der Waals interactions between the chains. This causes the membrane to be solid-like below the melting temperature. As the temperature rises, clusters of phospholipids melt, followed by melting of the entire bilayer. At temperatures above the melting temperature the acyl-chains are disorder or fluid. 
&lt;br&gt;The following shows the melting of a pure phosphatidylcholine membrane with myristic fatty acids (C14).&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/unsaturated.swf"  menustep="   Unsaturated ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;In an unsaturated bilayer the acyil chains have cis-double bonds that cause a sharp bend in the acyl chain. This impairs the packing of the acyl chains, reducing the van der Waals force between the chains. Consequently, the melting temperature of unsaturated bilayers is lower than that of a saturated bilayer. In addition, the transition occurs over a broader temperature range.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/cholesterol.swf" menustep="   Cholesterol Saturated ">   
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Cholesterol makes the lipid bilayer more fluid-like over a broad temperature range. Below the melting tempraure cholesterol disrupts the ability of the acyl chains to pack. During the melting process cholesterol reduces the cooperativity of the melting, causing the transition to occur over  a very broad temperature range.</text> </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/thirtysevendegrees.swf" menustep="   Thirty Seven Degrees ">   
        <text>&lt;html&gt;At 37 degrees, body temperature, the membrane contructed of mainly unsaturated phospholipids will have melted more and provide greater fluidity.&lt;/html&gt;</text> </step>   
    <step stepURL="swfs/proteins.swf" menustep=" Membranes Proteins ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Membranes rely upon their embedded proteins to transport nutrients,messages and other molecures through the membrane.&lt;/html&gt;</text> </step>
	
    <step stepURL="swfs/carrier.swf" textURL="text_carrier.swf" menustep="   Carrier Proteins ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;There are three main types of proteins that shuttle molecules across the membrane:
        &lt;b&gt;Uniport:&lt;/b&gt; transport a single molecule across the membrane.
        &lt;b&gt;Symport:&lt;/b&gt; transport two different molecules in the same direction.
        &lt;b&gt;Antiport:&lt;/b&gt; transport two different molecules in opposite directions.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/transporter.swf" menustep="   Sodium-Potassium Transporter ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;This is an example of an antiport transporter,  that uses the energy of ATP to transport 3 Na+ ions outside of the cell in exchange for the influx of 2 K+ ions into the cell.  The main features of the cycle are:
            1. Binding of 3 Na+ ions
            2. Phosphorylation of a carboxylic group by ATP,  this causes an allosteric change in the enzyme, allowing the Na+ to cross.
            3.  Two K+ bind to the external face of the transporter.
            4.  Dephosphorylation of the enzyme causes another allosteric change, bringing the K+ into the cell.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text> 
    </step>
    <step stepURL="signaling/intro.swf" textURL="text_intro.swf" menustep=" Signaling (Introduction) ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;This animation illustrates how binding of a ligand to its receptor ultimately leads to the production of high levels of cAMP, an important second messenger in the signal transduction pathway.  This process is mediated by a protein called G-Protein.  G-protein is inactive when bound to GDP, but becomes
        activated by the receptor induced exchange of GDP for GTP.  Many ligand-receptor complexes utilize this method of signal transduction.  The epinephrine receptor is an important example of such a G-coupled receptor.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="signaling/one.swf" textURL="text_one.swf" menustep="   Ligand binding ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The ligand forms a specific complex with its receptor.  The binding of ligand to the receptor causes an allosteric change in the structure of the receptor on the other side of the membrane, inside the cell. This allosteric change produces a binding site for the G-protein/GDP complex.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="signaling/two.swf" textURL="text_two.swf" menustep="   Ligand + R + G complex ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The G-protein/GDP complex binds to the intra-celluar part of the receptor-ligand complex.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="signaling/three.swf" textURL="text_three.swf" menustep="   GTP/GDP exchange  ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The interaction of the G-protein/GDP complex with the receptor causes a conformational change in the G-protein/GDP complex. This change results in the exchange of GTP for GDP. The G-protein/GTP complex is the active form of the G-protein.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="signaling/four.swf" textURL="text_four.swf" menustep="   Dissociation ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The active G-protein/GTP complex dissociates from the receptor and is now competent to bind to Adenylate cyclase, the enzyme that converts ATP to cAMP.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="signaling/eight.swf" textURL="text_eight.swf" menustep="   Ligand dissociation ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The ligand-receptor complex is still competent to activate G-protein/GDP by exchanging the bound GDP with GTP.  The signaling process does not terminate until the ligand leaves the receptor, causing the receptor to return to its original state.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
   <!-- <step stepURL="extransporters.swf" menustep="&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Other examples of Transporter ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Description needed - or delete&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
</step>-->
</TUTORIAL>