<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="cardio-lab_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Cardiovascular System Review Lab</title><page id="b59913f5375741f2ae2e6b31b628c59d"><short_answer id="q1" grading="automatic"><body><p id="c955c8f55bfe4bee8e74f2b02299ab69">Why is it a good idea to perform a range of tests for cardiovascular issues even if you identify the cause right away? <input_ref input="cardio-lab-quiz-sc1" /></p></body><part id="d7e63f5e476e4782aea1d9b187614519"><response match="*" score="1" input="cardio-lab-quiz-sc1"><feedback><p id="fe2bc742b31d4f9ab2c6fb0f3e55d0fc">Cardiovascular issues, such as tachycardia, can be complicated greatly by other cardiovascular dysfunction. For example, atherosclerosis combined with rapid cardiac output could result in vascular insufficiency. </p></feedback></response></part></short_answer><multiple_choice id="q2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa74ae35fb480497bbb178bfc7b643606">Which of the following hormones can regulate blood pressure?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="fc1d2e11f210446c97a49afeb1e4d280" labels="false"><choice value="a">epinephrine</choice><choice value="b">growth hormone</choice><choice value="c">somatostatin</choice><choice value="d">parathyroid hormone</choice></input><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="list_local_hormonal_neuronal_factors_peripheral_resist_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_role_sympathetic_reg_bp_vol_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback><p id="aa6a0aecf5ab642d195c6fab7b5115d14">Correct. Also known as adrenaline, epinephrine can either raise or lower blood pressure by changing vascular resistance.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe710546bc064f969fc6f1acc83012ce">Incorrect. Growth hormone functions to stimulate growth, as well as cell reproduction and regeneration. It does not affect blood pressure. </p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae121e9b9323a4105955fbae23c403bdf">Incorrect. Somatostatin is an inhibitory hormone that can regulate the release of growth hormone and thyroid stimulating hormone. It does not affect blood pressure. </p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback><p id="aec8cf875b0bc4ff89d4ea501fe1dc745">Incorrect. PTH increases blood calcium levels, but does not directly affect blood pressure.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="ae6581eac1ab74ae8af387613d9986011">This hormone can regulate blood pressure via changes in blood vessel diameter. </p></hint></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q3" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="adc25e2ff84b64a56adb2d561b9eeaf6f">Where are the majority of hormones that regulate blood pressure released from?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d9124b23048d430ca52772342011ce79" labels="false"><choice value="a">adrenal glands</choice><choice value="b">pancreas</choice><choice value="c">thyroid gland</choice><choice value="d">pineal gland</choice></input><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="list_local_hormonal_neuronal_factors_peripheral_resist_SKILL" /><skillref idref="explain_role_sympathetic_reg_bp_vol_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback><p id="af7d04cdf4e26438fa067b6fb0da15c1b">Correct. The adrenal glands secrete stress hormones such as epinephrine and aldosterone that are responsible for regulating blood pressure.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="aca63a38dc7274152bb59edbe95147bd8">Incorrect. Hormones released by the pancreas include insulin and glucagon, which do not directly affect blood pressure. </p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="adc343558ad534ba5a335a1ddd3f2767c">Incorrect. The thyroid gland controls the body&apos;s use of energy, in addition to controlling how sensitive the body is to other hormones. However, it does not directly affect blood pressure.</p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback><p id="afce783f07fad43daa1d2fb5ed95074fd">Incorrect. The pineal gland releases the hormone melatonin, but does not directly affect blood pressure. </p></feedback></response><hint><p id="acaafc4160631493f92c4e5c3677af9a2">Consider the root of the colloquial term for epinephrine, adrenaline. </p></hint></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q4" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="a4c68cec0b3d40b39edd8e808713b638">All of the following are risk factors for myocardial infarction (heart attack) <em style="italic">except</em>:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ecb76c824d0e4d92841905d8198d20de" labels="false"><choice value="a">smoking</choice><choice value="b">diabetes</choice><choice value="c">lack of physical activity</choice><choice value="d">gastroesophageal reflux disease</choice></input><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="identify_major_diseases_cardio_SKILL" /><skillref idref="identify_vessel_based_disrupt_homeostasis_SKILL" /><skillref idref="identify_blood_based_disrupt_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa202bfb0d74547b79bc93e298fa9c076">Incorrect. Smoking can increase blood pressure, blood clotting, and can damage blood vessels. </p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="afaab421c88e64d588d6ac69a0a75da1c">Incorrect. The high blood glucose levels associated with diabetes can lead to deposits of fatty materials inside blood vessel walls. This can result in clogging and impede blood flow to the heart. </p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac96eefe2e6504e59bb97d7bc94595243">Incorrect. Staying physically active helps regulate weight, blood pressure, blood lipid/glucose levels, and health of blood vessels, and subsequently decreases the risk of myocardial infarction. </p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="1"><feedback><p id="adaab10f232f7488abdffc67c2a469ce0">Correct. While GERD, also known as heartburn, can have similar symptoms to a heart attack, it is not a risk factor for myocardial infarction.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="ac45412757ec848c5a841a0251787b7a0">Most risk factors for heart attacks can result in unhealthy changes in blood pressure, fat content, or damage to blood vessels.</p></hint></part></multiple_choice><short_answer id="q5_sc" grading="automatic"><body><p id="abee4056501549c9ac5b1d0798e46fc8">How does the nervous system control heart rate? <input_ref input="q5_sc2" /></p></body><part id="dfd775cbfcc8476ab2d93b7859ab6330"><response match="*" score="1" input="q5_sc2"><feedback><p id="f2cc369433ef42b4a26773e3fdd942a3">The autonomic nervous system of the brain controls the body’s visceral functions, such as heart rate. The sympathetic and parasympathetic systems often act opposite to each other to maintain homeostasis. Stimulation of the sympathetic system can increase the rate of heart contractions, while stimulation by the parasympathetic system can decrease their rate.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="af9ca9936747c4e49b22b398ff146fb06">Most visceral functions, or those that operate at a level below consciousness, are controlled by the autonomic nervous system.</p></hint></part></short_answer><short_answer id="q6_sc" grading="automatic"><body><p id="b418ee7a333646999809b5ae54aa6022">If a patient has symptoms of dizziness related to changes in blood pressure, would you expect a higher or lower blood pressure? <input_ref input="q6_sc2" /></p></body><part id="d2783fbfa7f749aeb7a659adaa93c23a"><response match="*" score="1" input="q6_sc2"><feedback><p id="c3672679fea34826a5a49c2ae60e5eb3">A patient who complains of dizziness most likely has low blood pressure, also known as hypotension. Low blood pressure results in a deficiency in the amount of oxygen-rich blood that is supplied to the brain. If left untreated, it can result in heart problems, as well as neurological and endocrine disorders. </p></feedback></response><hint><p id="aee6598919cf34e39a816f434f0a1aa45">Normal blood pressure is essential to supplying the body with oxygen-rich blood.</p></hint></part></short_answer></page></assessment>
