<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u5_endUnit"><head><title>Skeletal System Unit Review and Assessment</title></head><body><p id="ec2244d616534c2cb497f3f2fdd73795">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="afa546f806414044ae504d761eb8adad"><li><p id="acae78b40ca3340b598530cfc42339d71">List several conditions that lead to decreased or altered function of the skeletal system.</p></li><li><p id="ac4c09909566d410ab2e05b83b4746d5b">Describe the anatomical components of the skeletal system that contribute to the functions of structure and support.</p></li><li><p id="ac823ef8a12ea451a819b671718909fac">Describe bone anatomy in terms of axial and appendicular skeletons. List bones from both functional groups and compare functions based on group. </p></li><li><p id="afea5fa99c1c848ab94097d787ff80211">Integrate the functions of the different skeletal system components to the system functions.</p></li><li><p id="aa620d3fdd5c24e1292c990123f8885cd">Describe different types of bone as classified by microscopic structure and as classified by shape. Compare intramembranous and endochondral (intracartilaginous) bone formation.</p></li><li><p id="ab4599cbf09ad424892a72a2015b3514a">Describe the functional classification of articulations, based on degree of movement allowed—synarthrotic, amphiarthrotic, and diarthrotic—and provide examples of each type.</p></li><li><p id="ad0ea98fcff22496793b9f8e87f6162da">Integrate the levels of organization in the skeletal system and their interconnections.</p></li><li><p id="aa3f027e6652f43d0ad45821ec16fd9cf">List the molecules relevant to the skeletal system, both inorganic and organic, and describe their function in the skeletal system.</p></li><li><p id="ad5d1a3aad7e8457d9d331a0518dc91cc">List the cell types and extracellular matrix components in the skeletal system and describe their function. Compare the structure and function of extracellular matrix components, and describe how cells alter the extracellular matrix.</p></li><li><p id="acdbaf31ffabd4a72b1ac2ae4a61a26c4">Visually identify microscopic and macroscopic bone structures and identify what influence cells had on the structures.</p></li><li><p id="ab082c28d84a4423e9c8d36fa2c3aa246">Provide specific examples to demonstrate how the skeletal system and articulations respond to maintain homeostasis in the body.</p></li><li><p id="af69bdd9c03c74fea9b491ef238a54bcd">Explain the hormonal regulation of skeletal growth, and the implications for bone and circulating calcium levels.</p></li><li><p id="aca1b8bf5aef54eb69b8a31de3d7b64c9">Describe the cellular and extracellular matrix reorganization that occurs in response to stress (force) on bones.</p></li><li><p id="aee21035f090744559c1165b7b94fa146">Describe the passive and active responses that occur in cartilage when stress (force) on the tissue changes.</p></li><li><p id="ae431057eb2594a43af33661b64cb1328">Discuss ways in which other body systems integrate with the skeletal system.</p></li></ul><activity idref="_u5_skeletal_unit_quiz" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="_u5_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
