<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>

<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u4_m03_random_variables1">
<head>
<title>Random Variables (1 of 2)</title>
    <objref idref="distinguish_discrete_continuous"/>
</head>
<body>
   
<p>In the previous two modules we've learned principles and tools that help us find probabilities of
            events in general. Now that we've become proficient at doing that, we<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085313-0500"?>'ll<?oxy_insert_end?>
            <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085317-0500" content="move on to "?>talk
            about random variables. Just like any other variable, random variables can take on
            multiple values. What differentiates random variables from other variables is that the
            values for these variables are determined by a random trial, random sample, or
            simulation. The probabilities for the values can be determined by theoretical or
            observational means. Such probabilities play a vital role in the theory behind
            statistical inference, our ultimate goal in this course.</p>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>
<p>We first discussed variables in the Exploratory Data Analysis portion of the course. A variable
                    is a characteristic of an individual. We also made an important distinction
                    between <em>categorical variables</em>, whose values are groups or categories
                    (and
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085426-0500" content="place "?>an
                    individual
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085431-0500"?>can be
                    placed <?oxy_insert_end?>into one of them), and <em>quantitative variables</em>,
                    which have numerical values for which arithmetic operations make sense. In the
                    previous two modules, we focused mostly on events which arise when there is a
                    categorical variable in the background: blood type, pierced ears
                    (yes<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085512-0500"?>/<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085509-0500" content=" or "?>no),
                    gender, on time delivery (yes/no), side effect (yes/no), etc. Now we will begin
                    to consider quantitative variables that arise when a random experiment is
                    performed. We will need to define this new type of variable.</p>
</body>
</section>
<!--:WARNING: The syntax of the definition element has changed.-->
<!--Please verify that the translated output below is correct.-->
<definition>
<term>random variable</term>
<meaning>
<material><p>A <em>random variable</em> assigns a unique numerical value to the outcome of a random experiment.</p>
</material></meaning>
</definition>
    <p>A random variable can be thought of as a function that associates exactly one of the possible numerical outcomes
     to each trial of a random experiment.  However, that number can be the same for many of the trials.</p>
<p>Before we go any further, here are some simple examples:</p>
<example><title>Theoretical</title>

<p>Consider the random experiment of
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085628-0500"?>flipp<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085626-0500" content="toss"?>ing
                a coin twice. The sample space of possible outcomes is S = { HH, HT, TH, TT }.</p>
<p>Now, let's <em>define the variable X to be the number of tails</em> that the random experiment will produce.</p>
    <ul style="none"><li>If the outcome is HH, we have no tails, so the value for X is 0.</li>
        <li>If the outcome is HT, we got one tail, so the value for X is 1.</li>
        <li>If the outcome is TH, we again got one tail, so the value for X is 1.</li>
        <li>Lastly, if the outcome is TT, we got two tails, so the value for X is 2.</li></ul>
    <p>As the definition suggests, X is a quantitative variable
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085734-0500"?>that<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085733-0500" content="which"?>
                takes the possible values of 0, 1, or 2.</p>
    <p>It is random
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085749-0500"?>because<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085752-0500" content="since"?>
                we do not know which of the three values the variable will eventually take. We can
                ask questions like:</p>
<ul><li><p>What is the probability that X will be 2? In other words, what is the probability of getting
                        <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085836-0500"?>2<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085834-0500" content="two"?>
                        tails?</p></li>
<li><p>What is the probability that X will be at least 1? In other words, what is the probability of
                        getting at least
                        <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085842-0500"?>1<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085840-0500" content="one"?>
                        tail?</p></li>
</ul>
<p>As you can see, random variables are not really a new thing, but just a different
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085857-0500"?>way to look at
                the same
                problem<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085854-0500" content="angle"?>.</p>
</example>
    <p>Note that if we had tossed a coin three times, the possible values for the number of tails
            would be 0, 1, 2, or 3. In general, if we toss a coin "n" times, the possible number of
            tails would be 0, 1, 2, 3,
            .<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085942-0500" content=" "?>.<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T085944-0500" content=" "?>.
            , <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090002-0500"?>or
            <?oxy_insert_end?>n.</p>

    <example>
            <title>Observational</title>
            <p>Consider getting data from a random sample on the number of ears in which a person
                wears one or more earrings.</p>
            <p>We <em>define the variable X to be the number of ears</em>
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090029-0500"?>i<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090028-0500" content="o"?>n
                which a randomly selected person wears an earring.</p>
            <p>If the selected person does not wear any earrings, then X = 0.</p>
            <p>If the selected person wears earrings in either the left or the right ear, then X =
                1.</p>
            <p>If the selected person wears earrings in both ears, then X = 2.</p>
            <p>As the definition suggests, X is a quantitative variable which takes the possible
                values of 0, 1, or 2. We can ask questions like: </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>What is the probability that a randomly selected person will have earrings in
                        both ears?</p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>What is the probability that a randomly selected person will not be wearing
                        any earrings in either ear?</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </example>
    <pullout type="note"><p>We identified the first example as
                    <em><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090300-0500"?>t<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090300-0500" content="T"?>heoretical</em>
                and the second as
                    <em><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090304-0500"?>o<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090303-0500" content="O"?>bservational</em>.
                Let's discuss the distinction.</p>
    <p>To answer probability questions about a theoretical
                situation<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090133-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                we only need the principles of probability. However, if we have an observational
                situation, the only way to answer probability questions is to use the relative
                frequency we obtain from a random sample.</p></pullout>
    <p>Here is a different type of example:</p>
    <example><title>Lightweight Boxer</title>
<p>Assume we choose a lightweight male boxer at random and record his exact weight. According to the boxing rules, a lightweight male boxer must weigh between 130 and 135 pounds, so the sample space here is S = { All the numbers in the interval 130-135 }. (Note that we can't list all the possible outcomes here.)</p>
<p>We'll <em>define X to be the weight of the boxer</em> (again, as the definition suggests, X is a
                quantitative
                variable<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090340-0500" content=","?>
                whose value is the result of our random experiment). Here X can take any value
                between 130 and 135. We can ask questions like:</p>
<ul><li><p>What is the probability that X will be more than 132? In other words, what is the probability that the boxer will weigh more than 132 pounds?</p></li>
<li><p>What is the probability that X will be between 131 and 133? In other words, what is the probability that the boxer weighs between 131 and 133 pounds?</p></li></ul>
</example>


<p>What is the difference between the random variables in these examples?  Let's see:</p>
<ul><li><p>They all arise from a random experiment (tossing a coin twice, choosing a person at random, choosing a lightweight boxer at random).</p></li>
<li><p>They are all quantitative (number of tails, number of ears, weight).</p></li></ul>
<p>Where they differ is in the type of possible values they can take: In the first two examples, X
            has three distinct possible values: 0, 1, and 2. You can list them. In contrast, in the
            third example, X takes any value in the interval
            <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090448-0500" content="["?>130-135<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090451-0500" content="]"?>,
            and thus the possible values of X cover an infinite range of possibilities, and cannot
            be listed.</p>
<p>A random variable like the one in the first two examples, whose possible values are a list of distinct values, is called a <em>discrete random variable</em>.  
    A random variable like the one in the third example, that can take any value in an interval, is called a <em>continuous random variable</em>.</p>
<p>Just as the distinction between
            <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090523-0500" content="a "?>categorical
            and quantitative variables was important in
            E<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090528-0500"?>xploratory
            <?oxy_insert_end?>D<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090531-0500"?>ata
            <?oxy_insert_end?>A<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090534-0500"?>nalysis<?oxy_insert_end?>,
            the distinction between
            <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101121T090543-0500" content="these "?>discrete
            and continuous random variables is important here, as each one gets a different
            treatment when it comes to calculating probabilities and other quantities of
            interest.</p>


</body>
</workbook_page>
