<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_m03_normal_random_variables8">
    <head>
        <title>Applications (2 of 2)</title>
        <objref idref="find_probabilities_of_normal_distribution"/>
    </head>
    <body>
       
        <p>The previous examples all followed the same general form: given values of a normal random
            variable, you were asked to find an associated probability. The two basic steps in the
            solution process were to</p>
        <ol style="decimal">
            <li>
                <p> standardize to Z; and</p></li>
            <li><p>find associated probabilities inside the normal table. </p></li>
        </ol>
        <p>The next example will be a different type of problem: given a certain probability, you
            will be asked to find the associated value of the normal random variable. The solution
            process will go more or less in reverse order from what it was in the previous
            examples.</p>
        <example>
            <title>Foot Length Revisited</title>

            <p>Again, foot length of a randomly chosen adult male is a normal random variable with a
                mean of 11 and standard deviation of 1.5. </p>
            <ol style="lower-alpha">
                <li><p> The probability is .04 that a randomly chosen adult male foot length will be
                        less than how many inches?</p>
                    <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image167.gif" alt="A normal probability
distribution curve for which the horizontal axis is foot length. An area of .04 size has been shaded,
starting as far left as possible and ending at a vertical line, which crosses the horizontal axis at
an unknown value. The probability is .04 that a randomly chosen foot length is less than this unknown
value."/>
                    <p>According to the normal table, a probability of .04 below (actually .0401) is
                        associated with z = -1.75.</p>
                    <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image168.gif" alt="A normal probability
distribution curve, for which the horizontal axis is in z-score units. A z-score of -1.75 has been
marked, and to the left of it under the curve is an area of .04 ."/>
                    <p>In other words, the probability is .04 that a normal variable takes a value
                        lower than 1.75 standard deviations below its mean. For adult male foot
                        lengths, this would be 11 - 1.75(1.5) = 8.375. The probability is .04 that
                        an adult male foot length would be less than 8.375 inches.</p>
                    <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image169.gif" alt="A normal probability
distribution curve, for which the horizontal axis is in foot length. 8.375 has been marked on the
horizontal axis, with an area of .04 to the left of it under the curve. 8.375 is marked at the same
place as the z-score in the previous curve."/></li>
                <li><p> The probability is .10 that an adult male foot will be longer than how many
                        inches? Caution is needed here because of the word "longer." Once again, we
                        must remind ourselves that the table only shows the probability of a normal
                        variable taking a value <em>lower than</em> a certain number of standard
                        deviations below or above its mean. Adjustments must be made for problems
                        that involve probabilities besides "lower than" or "less than." As usual, we
                        have a choice of invoking either symmetry or the fact that the total area
                        under the normal curve is 1. Students should examine both methods and decide
                        which they prefer to use for their own purposes.</p>
                    <p>
                        <em>Method 1:</em> According to the table, a probability of .10
                            <em>below</em> is associated with a z value of -1.28. By symmetry, it
                        follows that a probability of .10 <em>above</em> has z = +1.28. We seek the
                        foot length that is 1.28 standard deviations above its mean: 11 + 1.28(1.5)
                        = 12.92, or just under 13 inches.</p>
                    <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image170.gif" alt="A normal
probability distribution curve with a horizontal axis in z-score units. To the left of
Z=-1.28 under the curve is a shaded area of .10 . By symmetry, to the right of Z=1.28
under the curve is an area of .10 ."/>
                    <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image171.gif" alt="A normal
probability distribution curve with a horizontal axis for foot length. We see on the axis
X=12.92 marked, and to the right, under the curve, is an area of .10 ."/>
                    <p>
                        <em>Method 2</em>: If the probability is .10 that a foot will be longer than
                        the value we seek, then the probability is .90 that a foot will be shorter
                        than that same value, since the probabilities must sum to 1.</p>
                    <p>According to the table, a probability of .90 below is associated with a z
                        value of +1.28. Again, we seek the foot length that is 1.28 standard
                        deviations above its mean, or 12.92 inches.</p>
                    <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image172.gif" alt="A normal
probability distribution curve with a horizontal axis in z-score units. Marked on the axis
is Z=1.28, and to the left is an area of .90 . To the right is an area of .10 ."/></li>
            </ol>
        </example>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>
                    <em><?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T124629-0500" comment="remove bold -- no emphasis needed"?>Part
                        (a) in the above example<?oxy_comment_end?></em> could have been re-phrased
                    as:</p>
                <p>".04 is the proportion of all adult male foot lengths that are below what
                    value?", which takes the perspective of thinking about the probability as a
                    proportion of occurrences in the long-run. As originally stated, it focuses on
                    the chance of a randomly chosen individual having a normal value in a given
                    interval.</p>
                <example>
                    <title>Money Spent for Lunch</title>

                    <p>A study reported that the amount of money spent each week for lunch by a
                        worker in a particular city is a normal random variable with a mean of $35
                        and a standard deviation of $5. </p>
                    <ol style="lower-alpha">
                        <li>
                            <p> The probability is .97 that a worker will spend less than how much
                                money in a week on lunch? </p>
                            <p>The z associated with a probability of .9700 below is +1.88. The
                                amount that is 1.88 standard deviations above the mean is 35 +
                                1.88(5) = 44.4, or $44.40.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p> There is a 30% chance of spending more than how much for lunches in
                                a week?</p>
                            <p>The z associated with a probability of .30 above is +.52. The amount
                                is 35 + .52(5) = 37.6, or $37.60.</p></li>
                    </ol>
                </example>
                <p> </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>Another way of expressing <em>Example (part a.)</em> above would be to ask, "What
                    is the 97th percentile for the amount (X) spent by workers in a week for their
                    lunch?" Many normal variables, such as heights, weights, or exam scores, are
                    often expressed in terms of percentiles.</p>
                <example>

                    <p>The height X (in inches) of a randomly chosen woman is a normal random
                        variable with a mean of 65 and a standard deviation of 2.5. What is the
                        height of a woman who is in the 80th percentile? A probability of .7995 in
                        the table corresponds to z = +.84. Her height is 65 + .84(2.5) = 67.1
                        inches.</p>
                </example>
                <p>By now we have had practice in solving normal probability problems in both
                    directions: those where a normal value is given and we are asked to report a
                    probability, and those where a probability is given and we are asked to report a
                    normal value. Strategies for solving such problems are outlined below:</p>
                <p> </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Steps in Solving Two Types of Normal Problems</title>
            <body>
                <p> </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <ol style="decimal">
            <li><p> Given a normal value x, solve for probability:</p>
                <ol style="lower-alpha">
                    <li><p> Standardize: calculate <m:math display = 'block'>
                        <m:mrow>
                            <m:mi>z</m:mi>
                            <m:mo>=</m:mo>
                            <m:mfrac>
                                <m:mrow>
                                    <m:mi>x</m:mi>
                                    <m:mo>&minus;</m:mo>
                                    <m:mi>&mu;</m:mi>
                                </m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>&sigma;</m:mi>
                            </m:mfrac>
                        </m:mrow>
                    </m:math>
                        <!-- <image style="block"
                                src="../webcontent/image130.gif"/> --></p></li>
                    <li><p> Locate z in the margins of the normal table (ones and tenths for the
                            row, hundredths for the column). Find the corresponding probability
                            (given to four decimal places) of a normal random variable taking a
                            value below z inside the table. (Adjust if the problem involves
                            something other than a "less-than" probability, by invoking either
                            symmetry or the fact that the total area under the normal curve is
                            1.)</p></li>
                </ol>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p> Given a probability, solve for normal value x:</p>
                <ol style="lower-alpha">
                    <li><p> (Adjust if the problem involves something other than a "less-than"
                            probability, by invoking either symmetry or the fact that the total area
                            under the normal curve is 1.) Locate the probability (given to four
                            decimal places) inside the normal table. Find the corresponding z value
                            in the margins (row for ones and tenths, column for
                        hundredths).</p></li>
                    <li><p> "Unstandardize": calculate <m:math display = 'scroll'>
                        <m:mrow>
                            <m:mi>x</m:mi>
                            <m:mo>=</m:mo>
                            <m:mi>&mu;</m:mi>
                            <m:mo>+</m:mo>
                            <m:mi>z</m:mi>
                            <m:mo>&lowast;</m:mo>
                            <m:mi>&sigma;</m:mi>
                        </m:mrow>
                    </m:math>.
                         </p></li>
                </ol></li>
        </ol>
        <p/>
        <!--<activity idref="_u4_m3_lbd9" purpose="learnbydoing"/>-->
        <p>This next activity is a continuation of the previous one, and will give you guided
            practice in solving word problems involving the normal distribution. In particular,
            we'll solve problems like the ones you just solved, in which you are given a probability
            and you are asked to find the normal value associated with it.</p>
        <!-- <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_normal8_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>-->
       <section purpose="learnbydoing">
           <title></title>
           <body><p>Recall the example from the last activity:</p>
               <p>According to the College Board website, the scores on the math part of the SAT (SAT-M) in
                   a certain year had a mean of 507 and standard deviation of 111. Assume that SAT scores
                   follow a normal distribution.</p>
               <p>One of the criteria for admission to a certain engineering school is an SAT-M score in
                   the top 2% of scores. How does this translate to an actual SAT-M score? In other words,
                   how high must a student score on the SAT-M in order for his application to be
                   considered? A different way to ask the same question is "What is the 98th percentile of
                   the SAT-M distribution?"</p>
               <p>Let’s work through this problem in a step-by-step manner....</p>
               <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_normal8_tutor2" purpose="learnbydoing"/></body>
       </section>
       
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>In the days before computer software could easily provide high degrees of
                    precision if desired, limitations in the precision of the normal table were
                    offset by the process of interpolating. For example, if z were found to be
                    1.783, students were sometimes required to calculate the probability that was
                    three tenths of the distance between the probability for 1.78 and that for 1.79.
                    Such calculations are now considered obsolete. For most purposes, it is fine
                    simply to make do with the closest table value provided.</p>
                <p>So far, we've seen how to find probabilities associated with a normal random
                    variable using a table.</p>
                <p>The following activity will teach you how the same can be done using statistical
                    software.</p>
                <activity idref="_u4_m3_lbd10" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
                <p> </p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
