<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="one_cat_var3lbd">
    <head>
        <title>One Categorical Variable</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>The same survey that asked 1,200 U.S. college students about their body perception also
            asked the following question: </p>
        <p>"With whom do you find it easiest to make friends?" (opposite sex, same sex or no
            difference). </p>
        <!--<p>In this activity we will use the collected data to: </p>
        <ul>
            <li> learn how to tally our data into a table of counts and
                percents. </li>
            <li> learn how to produce a pie-chart. </li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>To create a table of counts and percents: </p>
        <ul>
            <li> Choose: Statistics → Table of Counts and Percents</li>
            <li> Choose the 'Friends' Variable</li>
            <li> Under "Display", check "Counts" and "Percents".</li>
            <li> Click OK.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>To create a pie-chart of the data: </p>
        <ul>
            <li> Choose: Graph → Pie Chart.</li>
            <li> Choose the "Friends" variable.</li>
            
            <li> Click OK.</li>
        </ul>
        
        <flash src="../../../webcontent/flash/StatRex.swf" width="800"
            height="400"/>-->
        <p>In this activity we will use the collected data to </p>
        <ul>
            <li>Learn how to tally our data into a table of counts and percentages. </li>
            <li>Learn how to produce a pie chart. </li>
        </ul>
        <pullout>
            <alternatives group="statistics.package">
                <default><pref:value preference="statistics.package"/></default>
                <alternative value="r">
                    <title>R Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open R with the dataset preloaded, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/r/friends.RData" target="self">here</link> and
                        choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Then find the
                        downloaded file and double-click it to open it in R. </p>
                    <p>The data have been loaded into the data frame <code>friends</code>. Enter the
                        command <code>friends</code> to see the data.</p>
                    <p>You can scroll up and down to see how 1,200 men and women answered the
                        question: "With whom do you find it easiest to make friends?"</p>
                    <p>Notice that the column title in the data frame <code>friends</code> is
                            <code>Friends</code>. The column title <code>Friends</code> is the
                        variable name, while the data frame name is <code>friends</code>. The subtle
                        difference is the capital F in the column title. R is sensitive to
                        capitalization so R identifies <code>friends</code> and <code>Friends</code>
                        as two different things. To extract a specific variable from a data frame
                        there are many methods, the simplest method is to use the $ to identify the
                        desired variable (column title) within the data frame, or
                            <code>friends$Friends</code>.</p>
                    <p>Obviously the raw data is not very useful so we will summarize it using a
                        table. To get a summary table of the data, copy and paste the next commands
                        into R (and press Enter if necessary to execute the command):</p>
                    <code>t = table(friends$Friends);t</code>

                    <p><em>Note:</em> Using R—When you assign a value to a variable, R will not
                        display the value unless you ask for the display by executing the variable
                        name as a command in the console.</p>

                    <p>The same method is used below when the summary table for <code>Friends</code>
                        is converted to percentages and assigned to the variable percent. Executing
                        the variable name to see its contents may seem like an unnecessary extra
                        step, but the convention allows you to assign a large amount of data to a
                        variable and not fill your screen with the result (which could be millions
                        of numbers) unless you really want to see it.</p>
                    <p>To see the proportion of the total in each category, copy and paste the
                        command:</p>
                    <p><code>prop = prop.table(t);prop</code></p>


                    <p>To see the percentage of the total in each category, copy and paste the
                        command:</p>
                    <code>percent=prop.table(t)*100;percent</code>

                    <p>Finally, copy and paste the next command to create a pie chart of your
                        data:</p>
                    <code>pie(t)</code>
                    <p>The following alternate version of the pie chart command will produce a chart
                        with more informative labels:</p>
                    <p>First we will modify our <em style="bold">percent</em> table so that each
                        value is rounded to one decimal place.</p>
                    <code>pf = round(percent,1);pf</code>

                    <p>Next we will create a label that will include the category name and the
                        percent as the labels for each section of the pie chart. R defaults to
                        alphabetical order for tables and graphic creation so if you create your own
                        labels list the names accordingly.</p>
                    <code>lbl = paste(c("No difference","Opposite sex","Same
                        sex"),pf,"%",sep="");lbl</code>

                    <p>Finally, create the pie chart with the new label added:</p>
                    <code>pie(t,label=lbl)</code>
                </alternative>
                <alternative value="StatCrunch">
                    <title>StatCrunch Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open this file in StatCrunch, you must first right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/excel/friends.xls" target="self">here</link>
                        and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Next,
                        click <link href="http://www.statcrunch.com/" target="new">here</link> to
                        open StatCrunch in a separate window, and log in using your username and
                        password.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Click on the link “Open StatCrunch” at the top of the My StatCrunch
                            page.</li>
                        <li>To open the dataset, choose <code>Data → Load → From file → on my
                                computer</code>.</li>
                        <li>Select "Browse" or “Choose File” (depending on which browser you're
                            using), and select the dataset you downloaded.</li>
                        <li>Scroll to the bottom of the page and click on “Load File.”</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To ask StatCrunch for a table of counts and percentages:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose <code>Stat → Tables → Frequency</code>.</li>
                        <li>In the Frequency Table window, select the column Friends.</li>
                        <li>Press Compute! (The information will appear in a pop-up window.)</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To ask StatCrunch for a pie chart of the data:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose <code>Graph → Pie Chart → with data</code>.</li>
                        <li>In the Pie Chart With Data window, select column Friends.</li>
                        <li>Press Compute! (Pie chart will appear in a pop-up window.)</li>
                    </ul>
                    <!--<ul>
                        <li>Click on the link "Open StatCrunch" at the top of the My StatCrunch
                            page. </li>
                        <li>To open the data set select the "My computer" link under Load a data set
                            from box on the left side of the page.</li>
                        <li>Select the "Browse" or "Choose File" (depending on which browser you're
                            using and select the data set you downloaded.</li>
                        <li>Scroll to the bottom of the page and click on "Load File."</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To ask StatCrunch for a table of counts and percents:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li> Choose: Stat → Tables → Frequency.</li>
                        <li> In Frequency Table window select the column: Friends.</li>
                        <li> Press Calculate (The information will appear in a pop-up window).</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To ask StatCrunch for a pie chart of the data:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li> Choose: Graphics → Pie Chart → with data</li>
                        <li> In Pie Chart window select column: Friends.</li>
                        <li> Press Create Graph! (Pie chart will appear in a pop-up window).</li>
                    </ul>-->
                </alternative>
                <alternative value="minitab">
                    <title>Minitab Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open Minitab with the data in the worksheet, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/minitab/friends.mtw" target="self">here</link>
                        and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Then find
                        the downloaded file and double-click it to open it in Minitab. Note: you
                        will likely see a dialog box appear that says "A copy of the content of this
                        file will be added to the current project"&#8212;just click OK.</p>
                    <p>To ask Minitab for a table of counts and percentages: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose: Stat → Tables → Tally Individual Variables.</li>
                        <li>Under "Variables" type friends (or double-click on this variable in the
                            left panel).</li>
                        <li>Under "Display," check "Counts" and "Percents."</li>
                        <li>Click OK (The information will appear in the session (upper)
                            window).</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To ask Minitab for a pie chart of the data: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose: Graph → Pie Chart.</li>
                        <li>Under "Categorical variables," type "Friends" (or double-click on this
                            variable in the left panel).</li>
                        <li>Click on "Labels," choose the "Slice Labels" tab on top, and check
                            "Frequency" and "Percent."</li>
                        <li>Click OK twice. A separate window with the pie chart will show up.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>
                <alternative value="excel">
                    <title>Excel 2013 and 2016 Instructions</title>

                    <p>To open the dataset, click <link href="../../../webcontent/excel/friends.xls"
                            target="self">here</link> to download the file to your computer. Then
                        find the downloaded file and double-click it to open it in Excel. When Excel
                        opens you may have to enable editing. </p>

                    <p>To ask Excel for a table of counts and percentages: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Click on the cell with the variable label <em>Friends</em>.</li>
                        <li>Click on the arrow under <em>PivotTable</em> in the <em>Tables</em>
                            group in the <em>Insert</em> tab, and choose <em>Pivot Table</em> from
                            the drop-down menu.</li>
                        <li>Click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                        <li>Excel will create a new worksheet with a blank table. We have to tell
                            Excel how to construct the table:</li>
                        <li>You should see a window titled <em>PivotTable Field List</em> with a
                            single item that is our "Friends" variable. </li>
                        <li>Check the box next to <em>Friends</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now drag the <em>Friends</em> item to the table where it says <em>Drop
                                Value Fields Here</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>You should now have a table that shows the number of each type of data
                        entry&#8212;"No difference," "Opposite sex," and "Same sex,"&#8212;and a
                        grand total. This is the count of each of these entries. To see the percents
                        for each entry, we can ask Excel to show percents instead of counts:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Right-click on any of the cells containing the counts and choose
                                <em>Value Field Settings</em> from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li>Click the tab that says <em>Show values as</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now use the drop-down menu labeled <em>Show data as:</em> to select
                                <em>% of total</em> and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To produce a pie chart of the data using Excel: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li> First, if your table is showing percents, you need to change it back to
                            counts:</li>
                        <li>Right-click on any of the cells containing the percents and choose
                                <em>Value Field Settings</em> from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li>Click the tab that says <em>Show values as</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now use the drop-down menu labeled <em>Show values as: </em> to select
                                <em>No Calculation</em> and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                        <li> Now click on one of the cells in your table and then click the
                                <em>PivotChart</em> button in the <em>Tools</em> group on the
                                <em>Analyze (PivotTable Tools)</em> tab.</li>
                        <li> In the <em>Insert Chart</em> window that appears, choose the first pie
                            chart option and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                        <li>To label the sections of the pie, right click the pie and choose
                                <em>Format Data Labels</em> (version 2013) or <em>Add Data Labels
                            </em> (version 2016) from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li>To see percentages as well as absolute values, right-click the pie and
                            choose Format Data Labels from the pop-up menu. On the menu that appears
                            to the right, check the box next to <em>Percentage</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>
                <!--   <alternative value="excel2003">
                    <title>Excel 2003 Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open Excel with the data in the worksheet, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/excel/friends.xls" target="self">here</link>
                        and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Then find
                        the downloaded file and double-click it to open it in Excel.</p>
                    <p>To ask Excel for a table of counts and percentages: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li> Click on the cell with the variable label <em>Friends</em>.</li>
                        <li> Choose: <em>Data → Pivot Table and Pivot Chart Report</em>.</li>
                        <li> Click <em>Finish</em>.</li>
                        <li> Excel will create a new worksheet with a blank table. We have to tell
                            Excel how to construct the table:</li>
                        <li>You should see a window titled <em>PivotTable Field List</em> with a
                            single item that is our "Friends" variable. </li>
                        <li>Drag the <em>Friends</em> item to the table where it says <em>Drop
                                Column Fields Here</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now go back to the PivotTable Field List and drag the <em>Friends</em>
                            item to the table where it says <em>Drop Data Items Here</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>You should now have a table that shows the number of each type of data
                        entry&#8212;"No difference," "Opposite sex," and "Same sex,"&#8212;and a
                        grand total. This is the count of each of these entries. To see the percents
                        for each entry, we can ask Excel to show percents instead of counts:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Right-click on any of the cells containing the counts and choose
                                <em>Field Settings</em> from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li>Click the button that says <em>Options</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now use the drop-down menu labeled <em>Show data as:</em> to select
                                <em>% of row</em> and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To produce a pie chart of the data using Excel: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li> First, if your table is showing percents, you need to change it back to
                            counts:</li>
                        <li>Right-click on any of the cells containing the percents and choose
                                <em>Field Settings</em> from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li>Now use the drop-down menu labeled <em>Show data as:</em> to select
                                <em>Normal</em> and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                        <li> Now right-click one of the cells in your table and choose
                                <em>PivotChart</em> from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li> Excel will create a new chart with a bar graph. We want to change this
                            to a pie chart:</li>
                        <li>Right-click somewhere in the graph
                                <em style="italic">outside of the bar</em>.</li>
                        <li>Choose <em>Chart Type</em> from the pop-up menu.</li>
                        <li>Now select <em>Pie</em> from the <em>Chart type</em> list on the left
                            and then click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                        <li>To complete the pie chart, drag the <em>Friends</em> item from the
                                <em>PivotTable Field List</em> to the legend where it says <em>Drop
                                Category Fields Here</em>. Note: if you don't see the legend, the
                            PivotTable Field list window may be covering it.</li>
                        <li>To label the sections of the pie, right click one of the sections of the
                            pie and choose <em>Format Data Series</em> from the pop-up menu, select
                            the tab marked <em>Data Labels</em>, and then check the boxes next to
                                <em>Value</em> and <em>Percentage</em> and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>-->
                <alternative value="ti">
                    <title>TI Instructions</title>
                    <p><em>Important Note!</em> TI 83/84 calculators do not have the built-in
                        capability to create a table of counts and percentages or to construct a pie
                        chart. Thus, for this activity, we suggest trying one of the other
                        technologies available in OLI Statistics. <link
                            href="http://cran.r-project.org/">R</link> is an excellent statistical
                        package that is free to download and that is available for both Windows and
                        Mac OS X.</p>
                    <p>If you want to continue with the TI Calculator, you can produce a table of
                        counts and percentages by hand using your TI to help. You can download an
                        app that will allow you to construct a pie chart. </p>
                    <p>To open a group of lists with the survey data loaded, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/ti/friends.8xg" target="self">here</link> and
                        choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Then find the
                        downloaded file and send it to your calculator. For instructions on how to
                        connect your calculator to your computer and transfer a file, click
                            <activity_link idref="ti_instructions" target="new"
                        >here</activity_link>.</p>
                    <p>Since the dataset is too large (n=1,200) to store in one list, the 1,200
                        values are split into two lists.</p>
                    <p>The friends data should now be loaded in L1 and L2, and is coded as follows:
                        0=no difference, 1=opposite sex, 2=same sex.</p>
                    <p>You can produce a table of counts or percents by hand using your TI to
                        help.</p>
                    <p><em>Table of Counts and Percentages </em>
                    </p>
                    <p>First, sort the lists (L1 and L2) that contain the coded data for the
                        categorical variable in ascending order:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">STAT/EDIT/2:SortA(</code>
                        </li>
                        <li>You should see: <image style="inline"
                                src="../../webcontent/image503.jpg"/></li>
                        <li>Before pressing <code style="inline">ENTER</code>, choose the list that
                            you want to sort: <ul>
                                <li>To access one of the built-in lists (L1-L6), press <code
                                        style="inline">2ND</code> and then the number of the list.
                                    For example, to access L1, you would press <code style="inline"
                                        >2ND/1</code>.</li>
                                <li>To access a non-built-in list, use the <code style="inline"
                                        >LIST</code> menu (<code style="inline">2ND/STAT</code>).
                                    Press <code style="inline">LIST/NAMES</code> to choose the
                                    appropriate list.</li>
                            </ul></li>
                        <li>Press the right parenthesis, then <code style="inline">ENTER</code>. </li>
                        <li>You should see: <image style="inline"
                                src="../../webcontent/image504.jpg"/></li>
                        <li>Check out the sorted list by choosing <code style="inline"
                                >STAT/EDIT/1:Edit</code>. </li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Count the number of values for each category. </p>
                    <p> The page <activity_link target="new" idref="one_cat_var1">One Categorical
                            Variable (1 of 3)</activity_link> describes how to create a table with
                        counts and percentages. </p>
                    <p><em>PieChart</em></p>
                    <p>While the TI Calculator does not have the built-in capability to create a pie
                        chart, you can download an app for your calculator that will do this. It is
                        called CellSheet App and is a free download from the <link
                            href="http://education.ti.com/educationportal/sites/US/productDetail/us_cellsheet_83_84.html"
                            target="new">TI website</link>. Note that some TI calculators have the
                        CellSheet App preloaded&#8212;choose <code style="inline">APPS</code> on
                        your TI to see if CellSheet App is already loaded on your calculator.</p>

                    <p>The TI website also includes <link target="new"
                            href="http://education.ti.com/educationportal/sites/US/nonProductSingle/download.html"
                            >instructions for downloading apps to your TI</link> and an <link
                            target="new"
                            href="http://education.ti.com/educationportal/activityexchange/download_file.jsp?cid=US&amp;fileurl=Math%2FProbabilityStatistics%2F2974%2F2-02_goodtofair_MT_TG_FINAL.pdf"
                            >example exercise</link> that shows how to construct a pie chart.</p>
                    <p>Once you have CellSheet App installed, use it to create a pie chart on the
                        TI:</p>
                    <ul>

                        <li>Press <code style="inline">APPS</code>.</li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">Cellsheet</code>.</li>
                        <li>Press any key twice to get to the spreadsheet screen. </li>
                        <li>Press <code style="inline">GRAPH</code> to access the CellSheet
                            menu.</li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">1:File</code></li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">3:New</code></li>
                        <li>Name the spreadsheet and press <code style="inline">ENTER</code>.</li>
                        <li>Press <code style="inline">ENTER</code> again.</li>
                        <li>Now enter the labels for the pie chart in row 1, starting in column A. <ul>
                                <li>Use the arrow keys to position the cursor in A1.</li>

                                <li>Choose <code style="inline">A-LOCK (2ND/ALPHA)</code></li>
                                <li>Press
                                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101015T165246-0400" comment="does &quot; have its own key, or are you saying you have to press shift (or the TI equivalent, if there is one) and the + key? (just checking)"?>"
                                    (found over the + key)<?oxy_comment_end?>, then continue
                                    pressing the letters for a name for the first category. Press
                                        <code style="inline">ENTER</code> when finished.</li>
                                <li>Your cursor should be in A2.</li>
                                <li>Enter the percentage for the first category.</li>
                                <li>Repeat for each category of the categorical variable.</li>
                                <li>You should see: <image style="inline"
                                        src="../../webcontent/image505.jpg"/></li>
                            </ul></li>
                        <li>Choose the <code style="inline">Menu</code> by pressing <code
                                style="inline">GRAPH</code>.</li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">4: Charts</code>.</li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">7:Pie</code></li>
                        <li>You should see: <image style="inline"
                                src="../../webcontent/image506.jpg"/></li>
                        <li>For Categories: enter the range for the category labels, ex. A1:C1 <ul>

                                <li>Press <code style="inline">ALPHA/MATH</code> for the A, then
                                    press the number 1.</li>
                                <li>Press <code style="inline">ALPHA/.</code> for the : (press ALPHA
                                    and a decimal point to get a colon)</li>
                                <li>Press <code style="inline">ALPHA/APPS</code> for the C, then
                                    press the number 1.</li>
                                <li>Press <code style="inline">ENTER</code> or the down arrow to
                                    move to the next line.</li>
                            </ul></li>
                        <li>For Series: enter the range of the percentages of each category, or
                                <code style="inline">A2:C2</code></li>
                        <li>Choose Percent by highlighting <code style="inline">Percent</code> and
                            pressing <code style="inline">ENTER</code>.</li>
                        <li>Enter a <code style="inline">Title:</code>. Alpha-lock is automatically
                            on, so press up to 10 letters for a title.</li>
                        <li>You should see: <image style="inline"
                                src="../../webcontent/image507.jpg"/></li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">DRAW</code> and press <code style="inline"
                                >ENTER</code>.</li>
                        <li>Choose <code style="inline">TRACE</code> and use arrows to investigate
                            the different categories for the pie chart.</li>
                        <li>Note: you can enter counts instead of percentages if you prefer.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>
            </alternatives>
        </pullout>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>Note that the pie chart visually provides all the information that is in the
                    table.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m1_onecatvar3_lbd_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m1_onecatvar3_lbd_tutor2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
