<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_15">
	<head>
		<title>Functional Epithelial Tissue Structures</title>
		<objref idref="digest_histology_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<section>
			<title>Plicae</title>
			<body>
				<p>On the organ scale, sheets of epithelial cells organize themselves into <em
						style="bold">plicae circulares</em>, which are permanent, ridges or folks
					inside the small intestine. These folds increase surface area for a given length
					of small intestine, which allows increased absorption. The function of most of
					the structures inside the small intestine is to increase surface area for
					absorption.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Villi</title>
			<body>
				<p><em style="bold">Villi </em>are small (0.5-1 mm long) finger-like projections on
					the lumen surface of absorptive epithelial cells of the small intestine. There
					are about 20 to 40 villi per square millimeter, increasing the surface area of
					the epithelium tremendously. The increase in surface area allows for a more
					rapid and efficient rate of absorption when digestive material is present in the
					lumen of the small intestine. In the core of each villus is a blood capillary
					network and a lymphatic capillary called a <em style="bold">lacteal</em>, so
					absorbed material can access the bloodstream for transport throughout the body.
					Lacteals are needed for fat absorption since emulsified fats are often too big
					to passively enter capillaries.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Microvilli </title>
			<body>
				<p><em style="bold">Microvilli </em>are small (1 µm) cylindrical extensions of the
					plasma member of the mucosa's absorptive cells. The combined microvilli give the
					mucosal surface a "fuzzy" appearance, which is called the <em style="bold">brush
						border</em>. The plasma membranes of the microvilli include <em style="bold"
						>brush-border enzymes </em>that finish digesting carbohydrates and proteins.
					There are an estimated 200 million microvilli per square millimeter of small
					intestine, greatly expanding the surface area of the plasma membrane and thus
					greatly enhancing absorption.</p>
				<!--<wb:inline idref="digest_histology_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
				<p><em>Placeholder for digt</em></p>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
