<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_46">
	<head>
		<title>Overview of Absorption</title>
		<objref idref="digest_absorp_overview_LO"/>
		<objref idref="digest_histology_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The mechanical and chemical digestive processes that begin in the mouth and continue
			through the small intestine have one endpoint: to convert food into substances that can
			be absorbed from the lumen by epithelial cells in the lining of the GI tract and then
			enter blood or lymphatic vessels. Absorbable substances are the monosaccharides,
			glucose, galactose, and fructose from carbohydrates; single amino acids, dipeptides, and
			tripeptides from proteins; and monoglycerides, glycerol, and fatty acids from lipids
			such as triglycerides.</p>
		<p>Most nutrients are absorbed into digestive epithelial cells by <activity_link
				idref="levels_cell_membrane_active1" target="new">active transport
				mechanisms</activity_link>. Nutrients not absorbed through active transport include
			lipids, lipid-soluble vitamins, and most water-soluble vitamins. With the help of bile
			salts, the breakdown products of lipids are transported into intestinal cells in
			structures called micelles. These absorbed fats then aggregate into chylomicrons for
			transport.</p>
		<p>These substances absorbed into the epithelial cells of the digestive tract are then
			absorbed into either the circulatory or lymphatic capillaries for transport where needed
			by body cells for metabolism. Absorption from the GI lumen is enhanced by increasing the
			surface area. Most absorption occurs in the small intestine, the longest organ of the GI
			tract. Several anatomical structures at the organ, tissue, and cell level also improve
			nutrient, water and electrolyte absorption.</p>

		<section>
			<title>Plicae circulares</title>
			<body>
				<p>On the organ scale, the inside lining of the small intestine lumen is not smooth.
						<term>Plicae circulares</term>, are permanent ridges or folds forming
					successive rings along the length of the small intestine. These folds increase
					the surface area of the lining exposed to contents in the lumen for a given
					length of small intestine, which allows increased absorption.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Villi</title>
			<body>
				<p>At the microscopic tissue level, there are finger-like extensions of the
					epithelial and connective tissue called <term>villi</term>. The villi increase
					the surface area of the epithelial tissue exposed to contents moving through the
					lumen. This allows more superficial epithelial cells to absorb within a square
					millimeter of the lining than if this same millimeter surface were flat. Within
					each villi, deep to the epithelial basement membrane, the connective tissue
					supports the villi structure as it extends into the lumen. Capillary networks
					that pick up and transport absorbed substances through the body extend from the
					deeper connective tissue into each villus (singular of villi). These include
					blood capillaries and a central specialized lymph capillary, called a
						<term>lacteal</term>, for lipid absorption.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Microvilli </title>
			<body>
				<p>At the cellular level, the apical surface of each epithelial cell has cell
					membrane extensions into the lumen called <term>microvilli</term>. These cells are
					collectively known as <term>brush border</term> cells because their combined microvilli along
					the surface of each villus looks like the surface of a brush under the
					microscope. Because of the microvilli, each epithelial cell has a longer cell
					membrane exposed to the lumen contents than it would if its apical surface were
					smooth, improving cellular absorption. Embedded in the cell’s folded plasma
					membrane are different cell membrane proteins: transporters and enzymes. The
					transporters absorb by active transport, but the <term>brush border enzymes</term> are
					catalysts that complete the digestion of only partially digested proteins and
					carbohydrates at the cell surface, so they can pass through the adjacent
					transporters.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
		
		<youtube src="nm7CSDf1egw">
			<title>Surface Area</title>
			<caption>Explanation of increased surface of the small instestine due to the characteristics of its structures.</caption>
		</youtube>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_histology_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>



	</body>
</workbook_page>
