<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_44">
	<head>
		<title>Movement of Material Through the Digestive System</title>
		<objref idref="digest_movement_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Both voluntary skeletal muscles and involuntary smooth muscles are involved in propelling
			food material through the digestive system. Skeletal muscles of the tongue are involved
			in the voluntary first phase of swallowing, but then it becomes an involuntary reflex
			with skeletal muscles of the pharynx. You will learn more about this swallowing process
			called <term>deglution</term> in the next module. </p>

		<p>The smooth muscle of the GI tract is arranged in two layers: longitudinal along the
			length of the tube and circular around the diameter of the tube. Coordinated contraction
			and relaxation of these two layers creates a wave-like propulsion of the food called
				<term>peristalsis</term>. Muscles in the esophagus mechanically transport the food via peristalsis from the mouth
			to the stomach. An extra smooth muscle layer in the stomach adds a churning movement
			within the stomach. Peristalsis continues to propel food through the small and large
			intestines. </p>

		<p>Controlling the rate of food moving from one organ of the digestive tract to the next are
			specialized circularly arranged skeletal and smooth muscles called sphincters.
			Sphincters are typically contracted and relax only to allow food to move from one organ
			to the next. The majority of sphincters along the length of the GI tract are involuntary
			smooth muscle structures. The <term>esophageal sphincter</term> helps separate the
			esophagus from the stomach to maintain linear movement and protect the esophagus from
			acidic chemicals of the stomach. The <term>pyloric sphincter</term> separates the stomach from the small intestine; again
			there is a physical separation for compartmentalization and to maintain directionalized
			movement.</p>

		<p>Material then snakes its way through the small intestine and the <term>iloeocecal
				sphincter</term> controls movement into the large intestine or colon. The <term>anal
				sphincter</term> muscle is skeletal muscle controlled consciously to relax during
			defecation. There is also a <term>hepatopancreatic sphincter</term> that controls the release of
			accessory secretions from the liver and pancreas into the beginning of the small
			intestine.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="digest_movement_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_movement_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
