<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_17">
	<head>
		<title>Organs of the Digestive System</title>
		<objref idref="digestive_organs_LO"/>

	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The digestive system is generally divided into two main categories: organs of the
			alimentary canal (<em style="italic">aliment</em> = “nourish”) and accessory digestive
			organs. The <term>alimentary canal</term>, also called the <term>gastrointestinal (GI)
				tract</term> or <term>gut</term>, is a continuous muscular tube that runs from the
			mouth to the anus. The internal space of this tube is called the <term>lumen</term>. The
			GI tract is involved with the digestion of food –its breakdown into smaller fragments –
			and the absorption of digested food fragments from the lument through the alimentary
			canal wall and into the bloodstream. The accessory digestive organs contribute to
			secretions to the GI tract, but the food doesn't pass through these organs.</p>
		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M2_12Labeled.jpg" width="400"
			alt="Selective organs of the Digestive System in context of the body">
			<caption>Digestive System organs. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>

		<p>Different digestive system organs are responsible for different digestive processes and
			functions. These functions include: extracting nutrients from food and removing waste.
			The processes by which these occur are called <term>ingestion</term>,
				<term>motility</term> of food through the GI tract lumen, <term>mehcanical</term>
			and <term>chemical digestion</term> of the food, <term>absorption</term> and breakdown
			of products, <term>defecation</term> to remove residues.</p>
		<table rowstyle="alternating">
			<tr>
				<th><em style="bold">Organ</em></th>
				<th><em style="bold">Major Functions</em></th>
				<th><em style="bold">Other Functions</em></th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Mouth</em></td>
				<td>Ingests food; Mechanical chewing of food; <term>Salivary amylase</term> begins
					chemical breakdown of starch; Swallows food and propels it into pharynx</td>
				<td><term>Salivary mucus</term> helps dissolve food; Release of flavors stimulates
					tastebuds allowing us to appreciate its taste; <term>Saliva</term> moistens
					food, and tongue helps create a <term>bolus</term> that can be swallowed; Saliva
					cleans and lubricates the teeth and oral cavity</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Pharynx</em></td>
				<td>Propels bolus from oral cavity to esophagus</td>
				<td>Mucus lubricates food passageways</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Esophagus</em></td>
				<td><term>Peristaltic waves</term> propel food bolus to stomach</td>
				<td>Mucus lubricates food passageways</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Stomach</em></td>
				<td>Peristaltic waves combine food with <term>gastric juice</term> and move it into
					the <term>duodenum</term>; <term>Pepsin</term> begins protein digestion; Absorbs
					some fat-soluble substances (e.g., alcohol, aspirin)</td>
				<td><term>Hydrochloric acid</term> neutralizes ingested pathogens and stimulates
					protein-digesting enzymes; Mucus lubricates and protects the stomach;
						<term>Intrinsic factor</term> allows vitamin B12 to be absorbed in
					intestines</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Small intestine</em></td>
				<td>Mixes contents with digestive juices for digestion and absorption;
						<term>Brush-border enzymes</term> digest food; Absorbs breakdown products of
					carbohydrates, protein, fat, and nucleic acid digestion, along with vitamins,
					water, and electrolytes</td>
				<td><term>Alkaline mucus</term> helps neutralize acidic <term>chyme</term> from the
					stomach</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Large intestine</em></td>
				<td><term>Enteric bacteria</term> digest some food residue and vitamins; Absorbs
					most residual water, electrolytes, and vitamins produced by enteric bacteria;
					Propels feces toward rectum; <term>Defecation</term> reflex eliminates
					feces</td>
				<td>Residues are concentrated and temporarily stored prior to defecation; Mucus
					smoothes passage of feces through colon</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Accessory organs</em></td>
				<td><em>Liver</em>: produces <term>bile</term>; <em>Gall bladder</em>: stores and
					concentrates bile; <em>Pancreas</em>: produces enzymes that digests food</td>
				<td>Gall bladder releases bile, which emulsifies fat and stimulates the digestion of
					fat and the absorption of fatty acids, monoglycerides, cholesterol,
					phospholipids, and fat-soluble vitamins; Bicarbonate-rich <term>pancreatic
						juice</term> helps neutralize acidic chyme (from the stomach) and provide
					optimal environment for enzymatic activity</td>
			</tr>
		</table>

		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="digestive_organs_lbd1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				<wb:inline idref="digestive_organs_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="digestive_organs_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
