<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m1_intro_01">
	<head>
		<title>Major Functions of The Digestive System</title>
		<objref idref="describe_digestive_LO"/>

	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The digestive system moves water, nutrients and electrolytes from the external
			environment to the internal environment. Within the digestive system, the
			gastrointestinal tract is a continuous hollow tube from the mouth to the anus and is
			technically contiguous with the external environment. This internal space is called a
			lumen. All digestive system organs play vital roles in breaking down food moving through
			the gastrointestinal tract into its chemical building blocks, absorbing these building
			blocks into the blood, and eliminating residual indigestible materials.</p>

		<p>Different parts of the digestive system will secrete substances into the digestive tract
			lumen. These secretions come from both the cells that make up the epithelial lining of
			the digestive tract and from exocrine accessory organs that have ducts emptying into the
			tube. These substances will assist with the movement of food from one part of the tract
			to the next (such as mucus) and with the digestion of the food while it is in the tube
			(such as enzymes). </p>
		

		<p>In order to absorb digested substances, that material has to be first moved from the
			lumen, into the apical or tube-side of the epithelial cells lining the digestive tract,
			then out of the other basal side of those cells, into the body’s interstitial fluid, and
			into blood or lymph capillaries for transport through the body. This process can happen
			passively or require ATP cellular energy. You may want to review <activity_link idref="levels_membrane_osmosis1" target="new">membrane transport</activity_link> in
			the cell module. Various chemicals secreted into the lumen can enhance the absorption
			of some material, such as vitamins and lipids. Anatomical structures that increase the
			area of the absorptive surface exposed to the digested substances in the tube will also
			enhance absorption. </p>
		
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<p>Many different digestive dysfunctions have very similar symptoms. Understanding
					the biochemical and cellular functions of the digestive system can help in
					understanding some of the various causes.Celiac disease is a digestive system
					disorder that is also known as gluten intolerance. Gluten is made up of amino
					acids and is found in wheat. When the enzyme transglutiminase reacts with gluten
					in the digestive system, it can cause an autoimmune response that destroys the
					lining of the small intestine. This causes improper absorption and associated
					symptoms.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_diseases_la" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>

		<p>There will be another kind of secretion involved in regulating this whole process,
			including how long food stays in one section of the digestive tract for the most
			efficient digestion or absorption. These are endocrine secretions from cells that are
			part of the digestive organs themselves. These hormones are secreted into the blood, not
			the digestive lumen, and transported by blood to target cells of the digestive system
			organs. In this way, it helps regulate and coordinate the functions among the different
			organs. The autonomic nervous system also plays a role in regulating and coordinating
			the digestive system.</p>
		
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				
				<p>Some people with Panic Disorder have been found to have an inherited metabolic
					defect that prevents them from producing a digestive system hormone called
					cholecystokinin (CCK). CCK controls the release of digestive secretions from the
					liver/gall bladder and pancreas into the small intestine. CCK also acts as a
					central nervous system neuropeptide, affecting neuron communication in parts of
					the brain that regulate anxiety and stress. People with this particular genetic
					condition may experience Gastro-Esophageal Reflux Disease (GERD) or Irritable
					Bowel Syndrome (IBS), sometimes for years before they ever have a panic attack
					experience.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_digestive_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
			</body>
		</section>

		<p>We usually don't think about the digestive system until something goes wrong with it –
			when we get indigestion, nausea, or diarrhea. We seldom appreciate that the digestive
			system is a complex string of organs that make up the body's engine, turning fuel from
			the food we eat into energy that keeps us going. Each organ of the digestive system
			performs specific functions but all these organs work together to digest the foods we
			eat and absorb the nutrients into our bodies. Feel free to review the overall
				<activity_link idref="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_02" target="new">Digestive
				system</activity_link> in the course Introduction.</p>

		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				
				<p> Lactose intolerance is a digestive system disorder related to the
					biochemical processes. In this genetic disorder, the person doesn’t produce
					enough lactase to digest lactose in their diet, so lactose isn’t absorbed in the
					small intestine. When it moves on to the large intestine, lactose upsets the
					water homeostasis and bacteria can metabolize it, creating the various
					symptoms.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_diseases_la2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
