<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bones_2"><head><title>Bones: Classification by Microscopic Structure</title><objref idref="skeletal_sys_bone_micro" /></head><body><image id="cb36a91d3f84471a91f59a46dd38f195" src="../../webcontent/Bone_cross-section.jpg" alt="cross section of a long bone" style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><caption><p id="ac87d522736294699b342dd59236a5d30"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c3631591e3934b44a37166044fbb7aaa">The bones of your body are mineralized structures that make up a major portion of your skeleton. In the broad sense, a bone is composed of bone tissue, cartilage, ligaments, tendons, vasculature, and nervous tissue. Bone tissue is a collection of specialized cells (osteoblasts, osteoclasts, osteocytes), organic extracellular matrix proteins (collagen and proteoglycans) and inorganic salt crystals that work together to provide strength and flexibility. </p><p id="f8ae77fe74f34c8fbc0c3bd054f90fab">Although all bones have a similar composition, their large-scale structures and functions differ. One way to classify bone tissue is based on their microscopic structure.</p><ul id="bcb68f3aeb5f4538a43c9ac0a7d56dfd"><li><p id="af99d5f347884e3d86844bd919ac3789">Bone tissue with a tightly packed microstructure arranged into rings is called <term>compact bone</term> (also called cortical or lamellar bone). Compact bone structure gives bones their stiffness. However, if bone structures were made only of compact bone, they would be very heavy and brittle.</p></li><li><p id="a1e5c411310b41f3ae206d787b7911d7">Bone tissue with a porous microstructure is <term>spongy bone</term> (also called cancellous or trabecular bone). Spongy bone consists of branching bone structures called <term>trabeculae</term>. Spongy bone helps to reduce the weight and brittleness of bone, and is found at the ends of bone where forces are high. Spongy bone allows bones to bend a slight amount without cracking.</p></li></ul><image id="d790c986dc2145c5bd4f4620339be2bc" src="../../webcontent/compact-spongy.png" alt="cross section of bone with samples of bone type cell structure" style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="ab6bf0cf2fc01476b848a77193ecd2221"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="da0aa534fa0a4c22a1b9b433a5d8e1cb">Most bones of the body are composed of both spongy and compact bone tissues, so that they are stiff, resilient and lightweight.</p><wb:inline idref="skeletal_sys_bone_micro_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="skeletal_sys_bone_micro_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
