<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_3b">
    <head>
        <title>Appendicular Skeleton Anatomy</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_appendicular"/>
        <objref idref="skeletal_structure"/>
       
    </head>
    <body>
           
            <image src="../../webcontent/appendicular_skeleton_diagram.jpg" width="400" style="block" alt="Appendicular
                 skeleton with all components pointed out"></image>
            <p>The appendicular skeleton is composed of the upper limbs, lower limbs, pectoral
                girdle, and pelvic girdle. The appendicular skeleton functions to anchor the
                limbs to the axial skeleton.</p>
            <p>The <term>pectoral girdle</term> consists of a scapula and clavicle on each
            side of the body. The pectoral (shoulder) girdle permits movement of the upper limbs by
            connecting the upper limbs to the axial skeleton.</p>
            <p>The <term>upper limbs</term> of the appendicular skeleton are composed of
            the humerus or upper arm bone, the radius and ulna, which complement each other to form
            the forearm, and the wrist. The hand subdivides into smaller bones of the palm
            and fingers. </p>
            <p>The <term>pelvic girdle</term> of the appendicular skeleton is composed of two coxal
            bones (fused ilium, ischium and pubis bones), which attach to the vertebral column and
            the lower limbs.</p>
            <p>The <term>lower limbs</term> each consist of the femur, or thigh bone; the tibia, or
            shinbone and the fibula, or calf bone; and the foot. The patella is the bone located at
            the point where the femur and tibia articulate with each other. The foot subdivides into
            smaller bones of the ankle, instep, and toes.</p>
            <p>The table below lists the location and function of the major bones of the
                appendicular skeleton:</p>
            <table rowstyle="alternating">
                <tr>
                    <th>Bone(s)</th>
                    <th>Location</th>
                    <th>Function</th>
                    <th>Major grouping of appendicular skeleton</th>
                </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Scapula</em></td>
                <td>Flat, triangular bone located on the posterior side of each shoulder</td>
                <td>Articulates with the clavicle and humerus</td>
                <td>Pectoral girdle</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Clavicle</em></td>
                <td>Located in each shoulder at the base of the neck<?oxy_comment_end?></td>
                <td>Helps to keep the shoulders in place as part of the pectoral girdle</td>
                <td>Pectoral girdle</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Humerus</em></td>
                <td>Extends from the scapula to the elbow</td>
                <td>Provides attachments for muscles that move the shoulder and upper arm at the
                    proximal end; articulates with the radius and ulna at the distal end</td>
                <td>Upper limbs</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Radius</em></td>
                <td>Located on the lateral side of the forearm between the elbow and wrist</td>
                <td>Provides attachment for muscles that rotate and bend the arm at the elbow and muscles that
                    allow movement of the wrist</td>
                <td>Upper limbs</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Ulna</em></td>
                <td>Located on the medial side of the forearm between the elbow and wrist</td>
                <td>Provides attachment for muscles that bend and straighten the arm at the elbow
                    and muscles that allow movement of the wrist</td>
                <td>Upper limbs</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Ilium</em></td>
                <td>Located on the superior portion of the coxal bone</td>
                <td>Connects the bones of the lower limbs to the axial skeleton</td>
                <td>Pelvic girdle</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Femur</em></td>
                <td>Extends from the hip to the knee</td>
                <td>Provides attachment for muscles of the lower limbs and buttocks; distal end
                    articulates with the tibia and patella</td>
                <td>Lower limbs</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Tibia</em></td>
                <td>Located on the medial side of the leg between the knee and the ankle</td>
                <td>Articulates with the femur, on its superior side, to form the knee joint;
                    articulates with the fibula on the lateral side; articulates with the patella on
                    the anterior side; and the tarsels to form the ankle joint</td>
                <td>Lower limbs</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Fibula</em></td>
                <td>Located on the lateral side of the tibia between the knee and ankle</td>
                <td>Forms the lateral part of the ankle joint</td>
                <td>Lower limbs</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><em style="bold">Patella</em></td>
                <td>Located on the anterior surface of the articulation between the femur and
                    tibia</td>
                <td>Supports movement of the knee joint</td>
                <td>Lower limbs</td>
            </tr>
            </table>
        
        <section purpose="learnbydoing">
            <title/>
            <body>
              <wb:inline idref="_u5_append_axial_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
                <wb:inline idref="skeletal_appendicular_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            </body>
        </section>
        
        
        <section>
            <title/>
            
           <body>
               
               <section purpose="didigetthis">
                   <title/>
                   <body>
                       <wb:inline idref="skeletal_appendicular_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
        <wb:inline idref="skeletal_appendicular_digt2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
        <wb:inline idref="_u5_append_axial_DIGT_inline" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                   </body>
               </section>
           </body>
        </section>
        
        
    </body>
</workbook_page>

