<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u5_m1_review"><head><title>Skeletal Structures and Functions Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="eee787defb3147a8a3dc13cc54f4413b">The skeletal system consists of several types of connective tissue: </p><ul id="aab0e375d2994bc7beee7d11d132f028"><li><p id="adf80340d219d4135a69ee4bb727f7d3e">Bones – protect vital structures; body locomotion through coordination with the muscular system; generation of blood cells; storage and release of inorganic minerals</p></li><li><p id="aa684e0ddaf7e4ab087e9e035e1117b15">Cartilage – coats the ends of bones where they articule with one another, provides protection, shape maintenance and support, lubrication, and shock absorption</p></li><li><p id="aba86b5929e2749cf9e55578132a1a3f1">Ligaments – connect bones to one another and stabilize articulations</p></li><li><p id="ad8e8be0c612243119971e8680ff78db4">Tendons – connect bones to muscles</p></li></ul><p id="f449bc05dcca4ae28fef82e1498647c0">The adult skeleton, which is composed of 206 bones, is divided into the axial skeleton and the appendicular skeleton. The axial skeleton is composed of the skull, hyoid bone, vertebral column, and the thorax (ribs and sternum). The axial skeleton functions to protect and support organs of the head, neck, and trunk. Make sure you understand the similarities and differences between the bones and the functions of the axial and appendicular divisions of the skeleton.</p><p id="fa778c8c63cf4f9ab6e06e97ec1e207c">Bone tissue is a collection of specialized cells (osteoblasts, osteoclasts, and osteocytes), organic extracellular matrix proteins (collage and proteoglycans) and inorganic salt crystals that work together to provide strength and flexibility. A common way to classify individual bones of the skeletal system is based on their shapes. Make sure you understand the shape and function of the four main shapes of bones (long bones, short bones, flat bones and irregular bones).</p><activity idref="_u5_skeletal_anatomy_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
