<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_4.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>

<assessment id="u3_m2_independence2_tutor2">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>Recall the delivery services example:</p>
         <p>It is vital that a certain document reach its destination within one day. To maximize
            the chances of on-time delivery, two copies of the document are sent using two services,
            service A and service B, and the following probability table summarizes the chances of
            on-time delivery:</p>
         <image src="../webcontent/lbd001.gif" alt="probability tables of two different delivey services"/>
         <p>Are the delivery times of the two services independent? In other words, are the events A
            and B independent? Common sense would say that there will be some degree of dependence
            between A and B, since the reasons that would cause one service to be delayed (like bad
            weather, airport delays, etc), would most likely also affect the other service, and
            cause it to be delayed too. Let's review the four possible methods that we can use to
            check whether events A and B are independent:</p>
         <p>Two events A and B are independent if any one of the following hold:</p>
         <p>P(B | A) = P(B)</p>
         <p>P(A | B) = P(A)</p>
         <p>P(B | A) = P(B | not A)</p>
         <p> P(A and B) = P(A) * P(B)</p>
         <p>Use the four different methods to check whether events A and B are independent, and see that indeed all four are leading you to the same conclusion.</p>
      </body>
      <short_answer id="A"/>
      <part>
         <response input="A" match="*" score="1"/>
         <explanation>
            <p>Our answer:</p>
            <p>&#8226; P(B | A) = P(B and A) / P(A) = .75/.90 = .833 while P(B) = .8. Since the two are not equal, events A and B are not independent.</p>
            <p>&#8226; P(A | B) = P(A and B) / P(B) = .75/.80 = .9375 while P(A) = .9. Since the two are not equal, events A and B are not independent.</p>
            <p>&#8226; P(B | A) = P(B and A) / P(A) = .75/.90 = .833, while P(B | not A) = P(B and not A) / P(not A) = .05/.10 = .50.  Since the two are not equal, events A and B are not independent.</p>
            <p>&#8226; P(A and B) = .75 while P(A) * P(B) = .90 * .80 = .72. Since the two are not equal, events A and B are not independent.</p>
            <p>Note that all four methods lead us to the same conclusion.</p>
         </explanation>
      </part>
   </question>
</assessment>
