<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_m1_intro_00-DONOTUSE">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction to Anatomy and Physiology</title>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>Everyone has a
            body<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20111208T135750-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
            and, by adulthood, a general understanding of how it works. But truly appreciating the
            intricate functions of the human body—and the problems that occur when something goes
            wrong—requires an organized approach. This course will help you understand the functions
            of the human body. We will discuss the details of many complex functional systems, but
            will also look at how all of these systems work in harmony to keep you healthy.</p>

        <section>
            <title>Structures and Functions</title>
            <body>
                <p>As we move through this course, we will keep four main themes in mind. The first
                    of these themes is the connection between structure and function. You know from
                    the course title that we will be studying both <term>anatomy</term>, which
                    focuses on the body’s structures, and <term>physiology</term>, which focuses on
                    the body’s functions. In fact, it is virtually impossible to study one without
                    the
                    other<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20111208T135830-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    because function relies so completely upon structure. For example, the structure
                    of our skeletal system provides the support necessary for the function of
                    walking upright. The shape of the vocal
                    c<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20111208T140414-0500" content="h"?>ords
                    is essential to the production of sound waves. The coordinated movements of the
                    bones in the knee joints dictate the direction in which our legs bend. And the
                    list goes on.</p>
            </body>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Homeostasis</title>
            <body>
                <p>Our second theme will be <term>homeostasis</term>, or the body’s natural tendency
                    to maintain a stable environment. We will examine the manner in which all of the
                    body’s functions are driven by homeostasis. Homeostasis occurs at the cellular
                    level through processes such as osmosis, which maintains the balance of
                    nutrients within cells. Homeostatic processes also affect an entire organism at
                    once. Your body automatically shivers to generate heat and maintain temperature
                    balance. When you feel hungry, it is because your body needs to be brought back
                    into nutritional balance. </p>
            </body>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Levels of Organization</title>
            <body>
                <p>The third theme of our course will include a study of the structural levels of
                    the body. The most basic is the <term>chemical level</term>, in which atoms and
                    molecules interact to process nutrients and produce substances needed for life.
                    These particles combine in specialized structures, <term>cells</term>, which are
                    the smallest unit of life. Cells of
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20111208T140547-0500"?>a
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>similar type combine to form <term>tissues</term>, and tissues
                    are combined into <term>organs</term>. Organs do not work independently; they
                    are organized into <term>organ systems</term> that complete more complex tasks.
                    The digestive system, for example, includes the mouth, stomach, intestines, and
                    many other organs—all of which are integral to proper functioning of the system
                    as a whole. The organ systems work together to support life in the entire
                        <term>organism</term>, in our case a human being.</p>
            </body>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Integration of Systems</title>
            <body>
                <p>Finally, in each section of the course we will discuss the integration of all the
                    body’s systems. In order to carry out its functions, every organ system relies
                    on the healthy functioning of other systems. When these systems all work
                    together, the organism thrives.</p>
            </body>
        </section>







    </body>

</workbook_page>
