<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="skeletalintro_3"><head><title>The Components of the Skeletal System</title><objref idref="_u5_components" /></head><body><p id="a6fc8c782f794026a14b36c246d43a00">The skeletal system consists of bones, cartilage, and ligaments, which all fall into the category of connective tissue. There are approximately 206 bones in the human body. Bones are classified by their shape. Some are long, some are short, others are flat, and the rest have an irregular shape. The reason that we have an “approximate” number of bones in the body is because we sometimes form small bones within our tendons in response to stress. These bones are called sesamoid bones. The patella (kneecap) is an example of a sesamoid bone. Although we all tend to have a patella, we don’t all have the same number of other sesamoid bones, making the total number of bones vary slightly from person to person. </p><p id="fc9e002e6a384e1089add129baac87c4">There are two types of bone (osseous) tissue. One is cancellous (nicknamed spongy bone due to its sponge-like appearance) and the other is more dense and known as compact bone. Both types of bone are found in every bone (note there is a difference between bone tissue and a bone), but compact bone (a tissue) is stronger and always found on the outside of the bone.</p><p id="f89367310b964ba28c78460dde6efe0b">All bone consists of bone cells of various functions. These are osteocytes, osteoblasts, osteoclasts, and osteoprogenitor cells. Notice they all have the prefix “osteo”. Osteo is derived from the Greek word (osteon) for bone. The suffix “blast” means “to make” while the suffix “clast” means “to break down”. Osteoblasts are important for forming bone while osteoclasts break down bone and remove calcium. These cells will be studied in additional detail in this unit.</p><p id="f6f1e615b8744d5b953537625e74398a"></p><p id="adadc67a631b4aa1b104a529b2ab0513">Besides bones, the other two structures considered as parts of the skeletal system are cartilage and ligaments. A specific type of cartilage, hyaline cartilage, is found covering the ends of bones that move with respect to one another. The areas of the bone surfaces that interact in these movements are called the articular surfaces (articulate means “to join”) and the hyaline cartilage in these same areas is called articular cartilage. Here it reduces friction and cushions the surfaces of the joint. The degeneration of this cartilage is the cause of osteoarthritis.</p><p id="cb1d4f2ec04e4a5385bf1da193f95573">Hyaline cartilage is also important for longitudinal bone growth. In this case it is not hyaline cartilage, as it is not located on the surface of the bone, but instead is a thin band of hyaline cartilage within the end of the long bone, in an area known as the epiphyseal plate (or growth plate). During growth, the layer of cartilage first expands, before developing into new bone tissue.</p><p id="ec0f8b6195a74c7b98d7a08444f2b283">Ligaments are a type of dense regular connective tissue that is very strong, and inelastic. Ligaments join bones together to provide stability to the joint. A sprain occurs when a ligament is damaged. Ligaments consist mainly of the structural protein collagen and have a white appearance.</p><p id="f8553a7f617f4fcb82fd19f480b14e2a">You will read more about these components of the skeletal system in this unit.</p><wb:inline idref="_u5_components_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
