<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="skeletal_2"><head><title>Bones and Their Articulations</title><objref idref="skeletal_structure" /><objref idref="skeletal_structure_B" /></head><body><section id="f4f65f666984483995a8fa8630df09c6"><title>Bones</title><body><p id="e5c117e3d3a54e978b256b1d38255b9b">Bones are the primary organs in the skeletal system. Their functions include:</p><ul id="f3df6ddef0ea4680a70c2000f8a3aac1"><li><p id="ac8a29d43bdd74c5eba37666302aaa68c">protection of vital structures, such as the spinal cord, brain, heart, and lungs.</p></li><li><p id="ac5d9acf43ff541e98045827456a597f9">support of body structures.</p></li><li><p id="acd4cf0aad96c49469722b91ae810963a">body locomotion through coordination with the muscular system.</p></li><li><p id="ae24574ce6ed645198f3633ad35ff30f2">hematopoiesis, or generation of blood cells, within the red marrow spaces of bones.</p></li><li><p id="ac4e038584fd14c2e896f9cd3c91c6bcc">storage and release of the inorganic minerals calcium and phosphorous, which are needed for functions such as muscle contraction and neural signal conduction.</p></li></ul></body></section><p id="cc0b73b2450842acb6a5c2b7eb50d52d">It&apos;s common to think of the skeletal system as being made up of only bones, but the skeletal system contains many types of structures. In addition to localizing blood cell formation and storing calcium, bones come together at locations called <term>articulations</term> (or joints) to allow for locomotion and work. In any complex system that moves (such as a bicycle or car), allowing functional, repetitive motion requires a lot of control and support.</p><section id="f4d479136fbd4121b01e0863c9e229dc"><title>Connective Tissues</title><body><p id="bc1392322aca4ad6a19ad78e78fc2107">In addition to bones, the skeletal system contains other important connective tissues including: <term>cartilage</term> and <term>ligaments</term>. <term>Tendons</term>, technically a structure of the muscular system, is also an important connective tissue for stabilizing joints and supporting structures. </p><p id="c4a2c61fcb564bc78ff05a7b34e6af68">Cartilage is a firm yet pliable substance that performs a variety of functions: protection, shape maintenance and support, lubrication, and shock absorption. Its primary function is to coat the end of the bones where they articulate with one another, providing a smooth, cushioned surface. Furthermore, cartilage can serve as a template for bone formation during development and bone healing (this will be further discussed in the section about bone ossification).</p><image id="a44585ac70b648dba1e8a5e8c32dfd43" src="../../webcontent/knee_cartilage.jpg" alt="normal cartilage in knee joint" style="block" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a9cfba4085694260961b669b25777507">Ligaments and tendons support articulations and control the muscle attachment to the bones. Ligaments connect bones to one another and stabilize articulations. Tendons connect bones to muscles.</p><image id="a06f4aa5e1234b789eb008c1f7f77de7" src="../../webcontent/tendon-lig.jpg" alt="tendons and ligaments in the ankle" style="block" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a4f0a7a519b244329543ffcbaa2349de">The structures of ligaments and tendons are similar, in that both tissues are made of fibrous proteins aligned in the direction of force. The types of proteins and differences in stretch and recoil distinguish the mechanical behavior of ligaments and tendons. Ligaments are stiffer, but deform more, since they stabilize articulations. Tendons are wrapped with a continuation of the fascia that surrounds muscle cells to help transmit and dissipate force. </p></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u5_skeletal_intro_inline_a" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
