<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletalintro_2">
	<head>
		<title>The Skeletal System and Homeostasis</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_homeo"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Let’s check out the skeletal system in action in the following case study.</p>
		<p>One afternoon, 74 year old, Anne Teak was walking down the steps in her home to answer
			the front door. With a sharp cry of pain, her hip gave way and Anne fell down the steps.
			Luckily, her granddaughter, Sarah, was at the door, heard the noise and ran into the
			house. She saw Anne lying at the bottom of the steps, crying in pain.</p>
		<p>“What happened, grandma?” Sarah worriedly asked, as she quickly dialed 911 for an
			ambulance.</p>
		<p>“I don’t know,” Anne cried. “I was walking down the steps when I felt a sharp pain in my
			hip, my leg gave out underneath me and I fell down the steps.”</p>
		<p>The ambulance quickly arrived and took Anne and Sarah to the local emergency room. There,
			an x-ray confirmed a fractured femur. The ER doctor, Dr. Brown, spoke to Anne, Sarah,
			and Sarah's mother, Susan. The doctor explained that Anne’s bones were very weak and
			that she has a disease known as osteoporosis.</p>
		<p>“The bone cells that make bone are not working as fast as the cells that break bone down
			and Anne’s bones are becoming weaker.” Dr. Brown told them. “In fact, Anne’s femur broke
			because it was too weak to support her weight and that is why she fell, she didn’t break
			her femur from the fall.”</p>
		<p>“What can be done to help my mother’s bones become stronger?” Susan asked.</p>
		<p>Dr. Brown replied, “Bones are living tissues that respond to stress. Exercising and
			eating a diet high in calcium can help bone tissue become stronger. Your mother will
			need a cast to protect the healing bone and then she will start physical therapy so we
			can strengthen the bones and the muscles.”</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_homeo_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

		<p>As you know, homeostasis is the ability of an organism to regulate its internal
			environment so that normal functioning continues. In fact, disease often occurs when the
			body loses control over homeostasis. Some diseases, such as Anne’s osteoporosis, occur
			when the bone mineralization decreases to the point where the bones become weaker (less
			able to withstand forces on them). This leads to increased risk of fractures, sometimes
			even with normal functioning. In this example, Anne was just walking down the stairs
			when her femur broke. </p>
		<p>Bones are not the dried out structures you often see in lab. They are crucial contributors
			homeostasis. As mentioned in the homeostasis unit, the
			skeletal system contributes to the maintenance of blood calcium levels. Blood calcium is necessary for
			cardiac, and smooth muscle contraction, as well as for determining how easy it is to stimulate all forms of muscle cells to contract. Calcium is also important for blood clotting, neuron and
			hormone function. The bones are a storage site of calcium. If blood calcium levels
			decrease, such as not getting enough in one’s diet, calcium is taken from the bones and put
			into the blood. This makes bones weaker. When blood calcium levels increase, extra
			calcium is deposited into bones for storage. This makes bones stronger. If Anne follows
			Dr. Brown’s recommendation she will make sure she eats plenty of calcium to ensure she
			has enough intake to maintain blood calcium levels, as well as enough extra that can be deposited into her bones.</p>
		<p>Bones also protect organs. Think about how easy trauma
			could damage your brain, spinal cord, heart, and lungs if they were not protected by
			bone. Bone is very strong yet typically has some flexibility, which makes it the perfect tissue for this
			function.</p>
		<p>One other important role of bones is in hemopoiesis (hematopoeisis). Bone tissue contains red bone
			marrow which contains the stem cells for the formation of all blood cells. The stem cell
			is known as the hemocytoblast and ultimately forms all red blood cells, white blood
			cells, and platelets. Red blood cells are critical for transporting oxygen and carbon
			dioxide in the blood. White blood cells are the main cellular component of our immune
			response, and platelets are necessary for hemostasis (blood clotting).</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
