<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u5_m0_review">
    
    <head>
        <title>Skeletal System Introduction Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        
        <p>There are 206 bones in a healthy human body. Bones form the bulk of the skeletal system and have many important functions. 
            They are critical for maintaining our structure and body shape, protecting vital organs, and serving as a reservoir for calcium.
            Skeletal muscles insert on bones and pull them for movement.</p>
        
        <p>The skeletal system consists of bones, cartilage, and ligaments, all of which are connective tissues. There are two types of bone
            (osseous) tissue. One is cancellous (nicknamed spongy bone due to its sponge-like appearance) and the other is more dense and known
            as compact bone. Both types of tissue are found in every bone, but compact bone is stronger and always found on the outside of the bone.</p>
        
        <p>All bone consists of bone cells: osteocytes, osteoblasts, osteoclasts, and osteoprogenitor cells. Know the specific function of each cell 
            towards supporting and maintaining the skeleton. Hyaline cartilage is found covering the ends (articular surface) of bones. The degeneration 
            of this cartilage is the cause of osteoarthritis. Hyaline cartilage is also important for bones to grow longer. Ligaments are a type of 
            dense regular connective tissue which are very strong, and inelastic. Ligaments join bones together to provide stability to the joint.</p>
        
        <!--  Quiz  --> 
        <activity idref="_u5_skeletal_intro_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
    </body>
    
</workbook_page>

