<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<!--Created by OLI Author v2.0-->
<assessment id="u1_m1_center3_lbd_tutor2">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
        
        <question id="q1">
            <!--LO:Determine a possible mean from a histogram-->
            <body>Which of the following is a possible value of the mean number of days that
                patients were depressed?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A"><p>155</p></choice>
                <choice value="B"><p>30</p></choice>
                <choice value="C"><p>120</p></choice>
                <choice value="D"><p>178</p></choice>
                <choice value="E"><p>Unable to determine from the information provided.</p></choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Not quite right. It is true that the mean is near the bar that
                        contains 160. However, since there are three outliers with large values, the
                        mean must be greater than 155.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems as though you’re looking at the middle
                        highest bar, without considering the effect of the large
                        outliers.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Since the distribution is skewed right, the mean has
                        to be higher than the scores represented by the middle bar; this bar is on
                        the left side of the middle bar, instead of the right side of the middle
                        bar.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Yes, you have located the center of the data set. Since the
                        mean is influenced by outliers and there are large outliers on the right
                        hand side of the distribution, the most likely score is around
                        178.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. There is enough information to make a
                        determination.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>You are trying to find the possible value of the mean. The mean is the average
                    of a set of observations.</hint>
                <hint>Look the shape of the distribution and note any possible outliers. What would
                    be a possible value of the average number of days patients were
                    depressed?</hint>
                <hint>Since there are 105 patients and two outliers (in the 500 to 540 range), we
                    know that the mean must be above the midpoint score of 53. What is a possible
                    value of the mean?</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
       
    </page>
</assessment>
