<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<!--Created by OLI Author v2.0-->
<assessment id="u1_m1_center3_lbd_tutor1">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
        <question id="q1">
            <!--LO:Determine a possible median from a histogram-->
            <body>Which of the following is a possible value of the median number of days that
                patients were depressed?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A"><p>53</p></choice>
                <choice value="B"><p>170</p></choice>
                <choice value="C"><p>220</p></choice>
                <choice value="D"><p>290</p></choice>
                <!--<choice value="E"><p>Not enough information to tell</p></choice>-->
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Not quite right. It is true that the median is the 53rd observation,
                        but what is the possible value for that observation?</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. The median is the 53rd observation, whose value is 170 days.<!--Not quite right: It seems as though you’re computing the average of 40
                        and 520, which approximates the middle of the range of the number of
                        depression days, rather than determining the number of days which divides
                        the group of patients into two equal parts.--></feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems you are looking at the number of bars
                        and not the number of observations. The median may not be at the center of
                        the distribution.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems you are computing the average of 40
                        and 520, which approximates the middle of the range of the number of
                        depression days, rather than determining the number of days, which divides
                        the group of patients into two equal parts.<!--Correct. Yes, you have located the center of the data set.--></feedback>
                </response>
                <!--<response match="E">
                    <feedback>Incorrect: There is enough information to make a
                        determination.</feedback>
                </response>-->
                <hint>You are trying to find the possible value of the median. The median is the
                    number of days at which 50% of the patient scores fall above and 50% of the
                    patient scores fall below. Is the number of patients an even or odd
                    number?</hint>
                <hint>Look at the number of patients. If it is even, divide by 2. If the total
                    number of patients is odd, add one to the total number and divide by 2. That
                    gives you the position of the median. What would be a possible value of the
                    number of days for the patient at that position?</hint>
                <hint>Since there are 105 patients, 53 (105/2) is the position of the median. Locate
                    the bar that includes the 53rd observation; the range of possible values of the
                    median would fall between the endpoints of that bar.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
       
    </page>
</assessment>
