<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_4.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u1_m1_histogram1_digt_tutor1">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>Thirty-two students were asked the number of servings of fruits and vegetables they eat daily. The results are displayed in the histogram below.</p>
         <image src="../webcontent/didigetthis_histogram1_02.gif" alt="histogram of fruit and vegetable consumption"/>
         <p>How many of the students surveyed eat at least 4 servings of fruits and vegetables daily?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
         <choice value="Res1">4</choice>
         <choice value="Res2">8</choice>
         <choice value="Res3">12</choice>
         <choice value="Res4">20</choice>
         <choice value="Res5">28</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
         <response match="Res1" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You have found the number that eat more than 4 servings daily.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res2" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You have found the number that eat exactly 4 servings daily.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res3" score="10">
            <feedback>Correct. "At least 4" means "4 or more," which is 8 + 3 + 1 = 12.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res4" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You have found the number that eat less than 4 servings daily. The word
               <em style="italic">least</em> is often confused with <em style="italic">less than</em>.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res5" score="0">
            <feedback>You have found the number that eat 4 or less servings daily. Although at least 4 does include 4, you have confused <em style="italic">least</em> with <em style="italic">less than</em>. "At least 4" means "4 or more."</feedback>
         </response>
      </part>
   </question>
   <question id="q2">
      <body>
         <p>What percentage of the students surveyed eat no more than 3 servings of fruits and vegetables daily?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
         <choice value="Res1">20</choice>
         <choice value="Res2">31.2%</choice>
         <choice value="Res3">37.5%</choice>
         <choice value="Res4">62.5%</choice>
         <choice value="Res5">68.8%</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
         <response match="Res1" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that 20 students eat no more than 3 servings daily, this is
               not a percentage.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res2" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You have found the percentage of students who eat less than 3 servings daily.
               "No more than 3 servings" would also include those students who eat exactly 3
               servings daily.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res3" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You have found the percentage of students who eat more than 3 servings daily. The question asked for "no more than 3" servings daily.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res4" score="10">
            <feedback>Correct. There are 20 students who eat no more than 3 servings daily and a total of 32 students. So, 20/32 = 0.625, or 62.5%.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res5" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You have found the percentage of students who eat 3 or more servings daily. The question asks for "no more than 3" servings daily.</feedback>
         </response>
      </part>
   </question>
   <question id="q3">
      <body>
         <p>What proportion of the students surveyed eat exactly 5 servings of fruits and vegetables daily?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
         <choice value="Res3">0.063</choice>
         <choice value="Res4">0.094</choice>
         <choice value="Res5">0.156</choice>
         <choice value="Res1">2</choice>
         <choice value="Res2">3</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
         <response match="Res3" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You used 2/32 to find the proportion, but 2 is the number of servings that 5
               students ate. The question wants the proportion of students who eat exactly 5
               servings daily.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res4" score="10">
            <feedback>Correct. There are 3 students who ate exactly 5 servings of fruits and vegetables daily and a total of 32 students. So, 3/32 = 0.09375, which can be rounded to 0.094.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res5" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. You used 5/32 to find the proportion, but 5 is not the number of students, it is the number of servings.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res1" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. 2 is the number of servings that 5 students ate. The question wants the proportion of students
               who eat exactly 5 servings daily. Also, 2 is not a proportion.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res2" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that 3 of the students eat exactly 5 servings daily, 3 is not
               a proportion.</feedback>
         </response>
      </part>
   </question>
</assessment>
