<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u1_m1_histogram1_tutor1">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>What percentage of students earned less than a grade of 70 on the exam?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
         <choice value="Res1">9%</choice>
         <choice value="Res2">15%</choice>
         <choice value="Res3">47%</choice>
         <choice value="Res4">53%</choice>
         <choice value="Res5">93%</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
         <response match="Res1" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. This is the <em style="italic">number</em> of students who scored between 60 and 80. To find the percentage of students who earned less than a grade of 70, add the number of students in each interval <em style="italic">below</em> 70, divide that number by the total number of students in all intervals, then multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.<!--To find this percentage, divide the number of
               students who earned less than a grade of 70 by the total number of students, then
               multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.--></feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res2" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. This is the total number of students, or observations. To find the percentage of students who earned less than a grade of 70, add the number of students in each interval <em style="italic">below</em> 70, divide that number by the total number of students in all intervals, then multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.<!--To find this percentage, divide the number of
               students who earned less than a grade of 70 by the total number of students, then
               multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.--></feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res3" score="10">
            <feedback>Correct. The data displays information about a total of 1 + 2 + 4 + 5 + 2 + 1
               = 15 students. Out of these 15 students, 1 + 2 + 4 = 7 earned less than a grade of 70
               on the exam. To calculate the percentage, divide 7 (the number of students who earned
               less than a grade of 70) by 15 (the total number of students, and then multiply by
               100 to change the decimal to a percentage: 7/15 = 0.47 = 47% of the
               students.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res4" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. This is the percentage of students who earned <em style="italic">more</em> than a grade of 70 on the exam. The question asks for the percentage of students that earned <em style="italic">less</em> than a grade of 70 on the exam.<!--To find this percentage, divide the number of
               students who earned less than a grade of 70 by the total number of students, then
               multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.--></feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res5" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. This is the percentage of students who earned less than a grade of <em style="italic">80</em> on the exam. To find the percentage of students who earned less than a grade of 70, add the number of students in each interval <em style="italic">below</em> 70, divide that number by the total number of students in all intervals, then multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.<!--To find this percentage, divide the number of
               students who earned less than a grade of 70 by the total number of students, then
               multiply by 100 to change the decimal to a percentage.--></feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>Using the table, calculate the total number of students in the class. Then calculate how many students earned less than a grade of 70.</hint>
         <hint>The total number of students is 15; the number who earned less than a grade of 70 is
            7. Use these numbers to calculate the percentage.</hint>
         <hint>To calculate the percentage, divide 7 (the number of students who earned less than a
            grade of 70) by 15 (the total number of students in the class), and then multiply by 100
            to change the decimal to a percentage. So we find that 7/15 = 0.47 and 0.47 * 100 =
            47%.</hint>
      </part>
   </question>
</assessment>
