<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>


<assessment id="u1_m1_histogram3_tutor1">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>What is the most likely shape of the distribution of age of death from trauma (accident, murder, suicide, drug  overdose, etc.) when represented by a histogram?<!--What do you think the shape of the distribution of age of death from trauma (accident, murder, suicide, drug overdose, etc.) would be when represented by a histogram? Why?--></p>
         <p>Recall that we talked earlier about the shape of the distribution of age of death from natural causes (heart disease, cancer, etc.). Use a similar type of reasoning for the age of death from trauma.
			</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
         <choice value="Res1">Symmetric&#8212;uniform</choice>
         <choice value="Res2">Skewed left</choice>
         <choice value="Res3">Skewed right</choice>
         <choice value="Res4">Symmetric&#8212;unimodal</choice>
         <choice value="Res5">Symmetric&#8212;bimodal</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
         <response match="Res1" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. If the distribution is symmetric&#8212;uniform, this
               would mean that deaths from trauma are equally likely to happen at any age. In fact,
               deaths from accidents, suicide, or drug overdose are more likely to happen to young
               people.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res2" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. If the distribution is skewed left, this would mean
               that the bulk of deaths from trauma happen to the elderly. In fact, deaths from
               accidents, suicide, or drug overdose are more likely to happen to young people.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res3" score="10">
            <feedback>Correct. The bulk of deaths from trauma (accidents, suicide, drug overdose,
               etc.) happen at a younger age, and fewer at an older age. Therefore, we expect the
               distribution of age of death from trauma to be skewed right.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res4" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. If the distribution is symmetric&#8212;unimodal, this
               would mean that the bulk of deaths from trauma happen to middle-aged people. In fact,
               deaths from accidents, suicide, or drug overdose are more likely to happen to young
               people.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res5" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. If the distribution is symmetric&#8212;bimodal, this
               would mean that the bulk of deaths from trauma happen at two different times of life.
               In fact, deaths from accidents, suicide, or drug overdose are more likely to happen
               to young people.</feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>Review the shape and characteristics of each distribution.</hint>
         <hint>At what age do the bulk of deaths from trauma happen? </hint>
      </part>
   </question>
</assessment>
