<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.1//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="_u5_skeletal_intro_inline">
  <title><?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111217T010354-0500" comment="I did not read this file, since these are repeated questions and the text does not lnk to this file."?>Skeletal<?oxy_comment_end?>
    System: Introductions</title>
  <page>
    <question id="skeletal_intro_q1">
      <body>
        <image src="../webcontent/Knee_diagram_wm.png" width="450" alt="The ACL (anterior cruciate ligament)"/>
        <p>The ACL (anterior cruciate ligament) is found in the knee and often needs repair in
          athletes. Which of the following functions do you think the ACL does?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
        <choice value="a">stabilizes the knee joint</choice>
        <choice value="b">connects the knee to the quadriceps (thigh muscle).</choice>
        <choice value="c">softens the impact at the ends of the leg bones in the knee</choice>
        <choice value="d">the ACL is the kneecap</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
        <response match="a" score="1">
          <feedback>Correct. The ligaments stabilize articulations. With ACL injuries, the knee is
            unstable and can even separate!</feedback>
        </response>
        <response match="b" score="0">
          <feedback>Incorrect. This is the job of a tendon. Tendons connect bones to muscles
            and ligaments connect bone to bone and stabilize articulations.</feedback>
        </response>
        <response match="c" score="0">
          <feedback>Incorrect. That's the job of the cartilage. There are many examples of cartilage
            injury in the knee, but it is different than an ACL (ligament) tear.</feedback>
        </response>
        <response match="d" score="0">
          <feedback>Incorrect. The kneecap (or patella) is a bone. </feedback>
        </response>
        <hint>The ACL is a ligament; think about what ligaments <em style="italic">do</em>.</hint>
      </part>
    </question>
  </page>
  <page>
    <question id="skeletal_intro_q2">
      <body>
        <image src="../webcontent/Tennis_elbow.jpg" width="300"/>
        <p>"Tennis elbow" is a condition wherein the outside of the elbow, as indicated above, is
          sore and tender from repeatedly using the muscle. Which parts of the skeletal system are
          most likely impacted?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice>
        <choice value="a">ligament</choice>
        <choice value="b">tendon</choice>
        <choice value="c">cartilage</choice>
        <choice value="d">bone</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
        <response match="b" score="1">
          <feedback>Correct. Tendons connect bones to muscle and, in the case of the elbow, the
            tendon runs along the outside of the articulation.</feedback>
        </response>
        <response match="a" score="0">
          <feedback>Incorrect. Ligaments stabilize joints but are typically found inside the
            joint.</feedback>
        </response>
        <response match="c" score="0">
          <feedback>Incorrect. Often people have arthritis or other damage to the cartilage in the
            elbow, but cartilage damage is not associated with tennis elbow.</feedback>
        </response>
        <response match="d" score="0">
          <feedback>Incorrect. Bones come together at the elbow, but there is no damage to the bone
            with tennis elbow.</feedback>
        </response>
        <hint>"Outside the elbow" likely does not involve the articulation itself.</hint>
        <hint>This is not a muscle injury, but does invlove the muscle.</hint>
      </part>
    </question>
  </page>
</assessment>
