<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_physio_knee_inline"><title>Articulations Activity</title><question id="artic_q1"><body><p>The knee allows movement independently front to back and by rotation. As such, it is classified into two articulation types. What are they?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="a">gliding and hinge</choice><choice value="b">pivot and saddle</choice><choice value="c">pivot and hinge</choice><choice value="d">hinge and ellipsoid</choice></multiple_choice><part id="artic_q1_p1"><skillref idref="skeletal_articulations_SKILL" /><response match="c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The knee moves front-and-back, and can rotate slightly. As such, it is a pivotal hinge joint. </feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hinge is correct, but ellipsoid is not. The knee joint might seem like an ellipsoid joint, since it seems nonsymmetric, but the knee allows rotation, so anatomically it is not ellipsoid.</feedback></response><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hinge is correct, but gliding is not; gliding joints move out of the plane; they allow sliding and twisting.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Pivot is correct, but saddle is not. Saddle joints move in multiple directions, but are not as strong as hinge joints.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the types of joints that only go in one direction.</hint></part></question><question id="artic_q2"><body><p>We typically are concerned only with our shin bones, but there are two bones between the knee and the ankle. These are called the tibia (the major bone, or shin bone) and the fibula (the minor bone). They don&apos;t move much in relation to one another. What are the articulations between the tibia and fibula called? </p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="a">synarthrosis</choice><choice value="b">amphiarthrosis</choice><choice value="c">diarthrosis</choice><choice value="d">gliding joint</choice></multiple_choice><part id="artic_q2_p1"><skillref idref="skeletal_articulations_SKILL" /><response match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Amphiarthrosis comes from amphi (on both sides, like ambidextrous) and arthrosis (joint). These bones are bound together by a fibrous ligament.</feedback></response><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Synarthrosis comes from &quot;syn&quot; (together or the same, like synonym) and &quot;arthrosis&quot; (joint). Synarthrosis articulations have no movement.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Diarthrosis comes from &quot;di&quot; (the Greek prefix for &quot;two&quot;) and &quot;arthrosis&quot; (joint). A diarthrosis articulation is a freely moving joint.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A gliding joint is just one type of diarthrosis articulation.</feedback></response><hint>Articulations are first classified by their ranges of motion. Leg bones have limited motion.</hint></part></question></assessment>
