<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_skeletal_intro_inline_b"><title>Tennis Elbow</title><page><question id="skeletal_intro_q2"><body><image alt="bent arm with area just above the elbow highlighted" src="../webcontent/Tennis_elbow.jpg" width="300" /><p>&quot;Tennis elbow&quot; is a condition where the lateral side of the elbow, as indicated by the shaded area above, is sore and tender from repeatedly using the joint and associated muscles. Which of the joint structures are most likely impacted?</p></body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">ligaments</choice><choice value="b">tendons</choice><choice value="c">cartilage</choice><choice value="d">bones</choice></multiple_choice><part id="skeletal_intro_q2_p1"><skillref idref="skeletal_structure_B_SKILL" /><response match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Tendons connect bones to muscles and, in the case of the elbow, the tendon for muscles that extend and stabilize your wrist is attached to bones on the lateral side of this joint. They are the ones that are most likely inflamed from repeated stress at elbow..</feedback></response><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Ligaments stabilize joints but they connect bone to bone. Althought they can be damaged by tennis and other overhead sports, they would not typically be damaged by repeated muscle use without force or trauma. Damaged ligament typically causes instability of joint, not just pain.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Arthritis or other damage to the articular cartilage in the elbow can cause pain, but cartilage damage is not associated with tennis elbow.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Bones come together at the elbow joint, but there is no damage to the bone with tennis elbow.</feedback></response><hint>A pain &quot;Lateral the elbow&quot; likely does not involve the joint capsule and articulation itself.</hint><hint>This is not a muscle injury, but does involve a joint structure associated with the muscle.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
