<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="skeletal_levels_macro_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>A greenstick fracture of the femur is an incomplete break in which one side of the bone is broken and the other is bent, similar to what often happens when you try to bend/break a “green stick” Which of the following would explain why this phenomena is more common in children than in adults?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The bones in children are thinner than in adults</choice><choice value="B">The bones in children are more brittle than in adults</choice><choice value="C">Children are more likely to have osteoporosis than adults</choice><choice value="D">Children have a higher cartilage to calcium ratio than adults</choice></multiple_choice><part id="e73c10b69a7848adb50ef881cf76aee9"><skillref idref="skeletal_sys_anatomy_bone_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the bones of children are thinner, this does not explain why greenstick fractures occur more commonly in them.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The bones of children are generally considered less brittle than in adults because children have more “flexible bones”.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteoporosis occurs when bone mass decreases. Children have not developed their bone mass yet.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Their collagen content provides tensile strength on the side of the bone that is stretched, but the side experiencing compressive forces often breaks.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which of the following cells is not properly matched with its function in bone formation?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Mesenchymal - stem cells differentiate into osteoprogenitor cells.</choice><choice value="B">Osteoblasts - become trapped in the matrix, where they differentiate into osteocytes.</choice><choice value="C">Osteocytes- secrete bone matrix.</choice><choice value="D">Chondroblasts- differentiate into chondrocytes.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i82ef24a184c943ee82e08d8f59b437a5"><skillref idref="skeletal_sys_anatomy_bone_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Mesenchymal stem cell do differentiate into osteoprogenitor cells.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteoblasts that are trapped on the osteiod matrix do become osteocytes.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osteoblasts secrete the matrix, osteocytes are mature bone cells.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Chondroblasts do differentiate into mature chondrocytes</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
