<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Receptor Mediated Endocytosis" movieroot="">
    <step stepURL="swfs/glossary.swf" menustep="Overview">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Many macromolecules are taken into the cell by a process described as endocytosis. The macromolecules do not pass through the membrane directly to the cytoplasm but instead are taken up by the cell, processed by cell and then delivered to the cytoplasm. For many of the endocytic processes, the uptake of the molecule is very specific and is controlled by recognition of the molecule by a specific receptor on the surface of the cell. This process is called Receptor Mediated Endocytosis.
	This simulation describes the process of Receptor Mediated Endocytosis that involves all of the components illustrated on the stage in the lower right panel. Each component is labeled and will be introduced as the simulation proceeds. The lower left panel provides a breakdown of the steps involved and the green play arrow advances the animation through the separate steps providing a simulation of each step. It is possible to repeat a step by clicking on the name of that step in the lower left panel.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/transition.swf"  menustep="Zoom in">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Starting with the detail of the plasma membrane and the binding of the LDL particle to the LDL receptor, the animation will not focus on the process of endocytosis. To bring all of the players to the same scale we will successively zoom in from the plasma membrane with the full lipid bilayer illustrated to simplified symbols for each of the components.
&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/introduction.swf"  menustep="LDL particle">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Receptor Mediated Endocytosis is initiated when a molecule or particle specifically binds to a structurally complementary receptor on the surface of a cell. This recognition is a form of biodiscrimination and allows targeting of the molecule or particle to be processed only by cells containing that receptor. The receptor is generally an integral, transmembrane protein. 
For the purposes of this simulation the model for the Receptor Mediated Endocytosis is uptake of LDL (Low-Density-Lipoprotein) mediated by the specific interaction of the LDL with the cell surface LDL Receptor. As the LDL particles pass by the cells, an equilibrium binding condition exists between the particle and the receptor. Because of the high affinity of the LDL for the receptor, the specific binding initiates the process of endocytosis.
The LDL particle is composed of a monolayer of phospholipids in a micelle arrangement that encapsulates a volume of cholesterol. Imbedded in the lipid monolayer is a set of signaling proteins. Clicking on the LDL particle will reveal this arrangement of molecules in the structure.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/equilibrium.swf"  menustep="Equilibrium">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The first stage, highlighted on the overview stage of the receptor mediated endocytosis, involves the binding of the LDL particle with the LDL receptor that then through conformational changes causes responses to the binding by events on the inside of the cell. A form of signal transduction, this step involves transmission of information across the membrane without transporting a molecule across the membrane. 
The binding of the DLD particle triggers the formation of the coated pit through progressive binding of the adaptin molecule to the receptor and clathrin to the adaptin molecule. The result is a matrix of interwoven clathrin molecules that coat the membrane in a patch opposite of the LDL particle binding.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/coated_pit.swf"  menustep="Coated Pit Formation">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The first stage, highlighted on the overview stage of the receptor mediated endocytosis, involves the binding of the LDL particle with the LDL receptor that then through conformational changes causes responses to the binding by events on the inside of the cell. A form of signal transduction, this step involves transmission of information across the membrane without transporting a molecule across the membrane. 
The binding of the DLD particle triggers the formation of the coated pit through progressive binding of the adaptin molecule to the receptor and clathrin to the adaptin molecule. The result is a matrix of interwoven clathrin molecules that coat the membrane in a patch opposite of the LDL particle binding.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/endocytosis.swf"  menustep="Endocytosis">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Progressive expansion of the clathrin matrix results in the budding off of the plasma membrane as a coated vesicle in the cytoplasm of the cell. Note that the LDL particles that were bound to the receptors on the outside of the cell are still bound to the receptor but are now facing the interior of the vesicle and are therefore isolated from the cytoplasm by the vesicle membrane (plasma membrane). The result is the formation of a clathrin-coated vesicle containing the LDL particles.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/uncoated_vescicle.swf"  menustep="Uncoated Vesicle Formation">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Once the clathrin coated pit buds from the plasma membrane, a set of ancillary proteins, Hsc70 and Auxilin, bind to the clathrin coated pit resulting in the dissolution of the clathrin matrix around the coated vesicle. The released clathrin and adaptin are then recycled to initiate another coated pit formation triggered by addition LDL particles binding to the surface receptors.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/LDL_release.swf"  menustep="Fusion with endosome">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The newly formed vesicle in the cytoplasm now initiates the processing of its contents, the LDL particle in this case. The first processing step is to fuse the vesicle with an early endosome. The early endosome has a slightly lowered internal pH that decreases the pH of the environment of the LDL particle when the two vesicles are fused. The stripped, transmembrane pores in the early endosome represent proton pumps responsible for maintaining the lower pH in the endosome.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/rec_recycling.swf"  menustep="Receptors recycling">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;One feature of the endocytic pathway is the ability to recycle materials once they have accomplished their function.  The recycling of the clathrin and adaptin have already been demonstrated. Another set of molecules to be recycled is the LDL receptors but they must first be separated from the LDL particle.
Upon fusion with the early endosome the environment about the LDL particle and the receptor has changed by the lowering of the pH. [Note: the pH scale to the right of the stage] This lowering of the pH results in the release of the LDL particle from the receptor. Upon release the LDL particles are free to randomly distribute throughout the vesicle. Their release also triggers the receptor segment of the vesicle to bud off of the vesicle and recycle to the surface of the cell. Once at the surface the receptor-containing vesicle fusses with the plasma membrane. The receptors that were inside the vesicle are now exposed to the surface. The exposure of the inside of the vesicle to the outside environment results in a return to pH 7 and the unbound structural state of the receptor.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;red&gt;Click the play button to advance through the scenes.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/division.swf"  menustep="Formation of a new vesicle">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The early endosomes now containing the LDL particles begin to migrate further toward the center of the cell and subdivide into multiple smaller vesicles. These more mature late endosomes are now ready to fuse with other vesicles to further process their contents, the LDL particles.
Two pathways have been found to create lysosomal type vesicles capable of ‘digesting’ the LDL particle. One pathway starts with the fusion of the LDL containing late endosome with a transport vesicle from the Golgi apparatus containing the lysosomal enzymes. The second pathway starts with the fusion of the LDL containing late endosome with an existing lysosome.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/fusion.swf"  menustep="Fusion">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/option1.swf"  menustep="      1) with a Golgi vesicle">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The origin of the lysosomal enzymes is the vesicles budding from the Golgi apparatus derived from the endomembrane system. The budding vesicles from the Golgi fuse with the late endosome containing the LDL particle. Upon fusion the pH of the combined vesicles is lowered due to the proton pumps present in the late endosome and thus the lysosomal enzymes become active resulting in the ‘digestion’ of the LDL particle and release of the cholesterol to the inside of the cell.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/option2.swf"  menustep="      2) with a lysosomeX">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The lysosome already contains the necessary enzymes, in an active state, to ‘digest’ the LDL particle. Fusion of the late endosome containing the LDL particle with an existing lysosome results in the exposure of the LDL particle to the active lysosomal enzymes. Digestion of the LDL particle results in the release of the cholesterol to the cell.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
  <!--  <step stepURL="endocytosis/swfs/glossary.swf"  menustep="References">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Many of the details within this animation come directly from sources within the current research community or databases.  We want to say more here and list the references we used within either the clip or this text box.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step> -->  
    
 </TUTORIAL>