<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD3"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The inner-most layer, the stratum basale, has keratinocyte stem cells with large intracellular structures including, endoplasmic reticulum structures and mitochondria. What is the primary purpose of this level?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">cells rapidly divide to produce more cells to replace upper layers</choice><choice value="b">cells primarily produce melanin </choice><choice value="c">cells primarily produce keratin</choice><choice value="d">cells produce nutrients to feed the upper layers</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. This layer produces more cells that differentiate and die as they as they move superficially from the dermis.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Melanocytes produce melanin.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Keratinocytes produce keratin, but the keratinocyte stem cells are responsible for self-renewal of cells.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Nutrients diffuse into the epidermis from the blood supply in the dermis.</feedback></response><hint>Cells in the stratum basale are metabolically active and undergo rapid proliferation.</hint><hint>Consider the definition of stem cells: cells that self-renew and differentiate into other cell types.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>The stratum lucidum is one of the superficial layers of the epidermis. This structure is nearly translucent. Why?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">Intracellular organelles have been degraded.</choice><choice value="b">Organelles transition to transparent phenotype for enhanced cell function.</choice><choice value="c">This layer is only extracellular matrix with no cells.</choice><choice value="d">Cell-cell connections give a transparent appearance.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Cells no longer need organelles to perform functions, so they are lost.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There is no longer cell function.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There are still cells at the outermost layers, but they are all dead.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Loss of subcellular structures leads to the transparent appearance.</feedback></response><hint>The outermost layer of cells on the epidermis are dead.</hint><hint>Dead cells no longer undergo cellular processes including protein production and ATP synthesis.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
