<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="ident_size_scale_integration_LBD2"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What molecule binds to oxygen for efficient transport throughout the body?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">heme</choice><choice value="b">water</choice><choice value="c">surfactant</choice><choice value="d">lipids</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="ident_size_scale_integration_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Oxygen binds to the iron molecule at the center of the planar heme molecule.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oxygen is poorly soluble in water.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oils are solubilized by surfactants, including bile, but oxygen is not transported by these molecules.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Red blood cells have lipid membranes, but the lipids do not bind to oxygen.</feedback></response><hint>A majority of oxygen is transported by hemaglobin. Consider the functional unit of the macromolecule.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What cells transport oxygen throughout the body?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">red blood cells</choice><choice value="b">lung epithelium</choice><choice value="c">immune cells</choice><choice value="d">endothelial cells</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="ident_size_scale_integration_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Trillions of red blood cells travel through the body at a time to distribute oxygen.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oxygen passes through the epithelium of the lung, but is transported through the body by the red blood cells.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Immune cells are found near oxygen exchange and in blood vessels to ensure that there are no pathogens exchanged from the environment.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Endothelial cells are found in the capillaries of the cardiovascular system, but oxygen is carried by red blood cells.</feedback></response><hint>The iron of the heme has a bright red color.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
