<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD1"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What are rugae?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">folds</choice><choice value="b">nerves</choice><choice value="c">texture for absorption</choice><choice value="d">texture for secretion</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Rugae are found in the wall of the stomach as well as the wall of the bladder.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There are nerves in the wall of the bladder to sense distension, but they are not called rugae.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The bladder does not have any absorption or secretion; it is only for containment.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The bladder does not have any absorption or secretion; it is only for containment.</feedback></response><hint>Ruga is latin for “crease” or “wrinkle”.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What is the purpose of these rugae?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">to allow distension of the bladder to hold more liquid</choice><choice value="b">contains glands for secretion into the urine</choice><choice value="c">to receive signals such as hormones from the endocrine system</choice><choice value="d">to interface with other tissues of the lower abdomen</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Rugae unfold to allow the bladder to expand, after elimination the rugae refold to reduce internal volume.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Secretion occurs before the ureter and bladder.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The rugae unfold based on mechanical distension not endocrine regulation.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Interaction between the bladder and other organs of the lower abdomen occurs on the external face of the bladder. rugae are found primarily on the inside.</feedback></response><hint>In the stomach, rugae unfold after eating to hold the food for acid and enzymatic processing.</hint><hint>Consider the use of excess folds for distension of the bladder.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
