<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="ident_size_scale_integration_LBD1"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What movement of what molecules are primarily responsible for electricity in the heart?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">Ions</choice><choice value="b">proteins</choice><choice value="c">water</choice><choice value="d">DNA</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="ident_size_scale_integration_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The movement of sodium and potassium across cell membranes generate an action potential.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Ion channels, which are proteins, control movements of ions. They, themselves don’t move.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Water moves throughout the cytosol but is not responsible for electrical conduction, ions are.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. DNA has a charge, but since it is localized within the nucleus, it does not impact charge.</feedback></response><hint>Although numerous macromolecules are involved in generating electricity in the heart, only one type of molecules moves.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What cells are responsible for electrical stimulation in the heart?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">pacemaker cells</choice><choice value="b">pacesetter cells</choice><choice value="c">cardiomyocytes</choice><choice value="d">endothelial cells</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="ident_size_scale_integration_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The pacemaker cells are specialized cardiac muscle cells.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are responsible for electrical conduction in smoothe muscle cells.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Pacemaker cells are specialized cadiomyocytes, but are usually referred to by a special descriptor.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cells line blood vessels and the inside of the heart, but they do not have electrical function.</feedback></response><hint>Although different cells within the heart conduct electricity, specialized cells initiate the electrical stimulation.</hint><hint>When these cells fail, an artificial device with the same name is implanted.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>In what region of the heart is the electrical stimulation started?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="a">SA Node</choice><choice value="b">AV Node</choice><choice value="c">Purkinje fibers</choice><choice value="d">Bundle of His</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="ident_size_scale_integration_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The pacemaker cells are located in the sinoatrial node.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The AV node coordinates the electrical conductivity, but electricity is not stimulated there.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These fibers transmit electricity through the ventricles, but electricity is not stimulated there.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The Bundle of His anatomically connects the AV node with thee purkinje fibers, but electricity is not stimulated there.</feedback></response><hint>Consider the region of the heart where the electricity originates not the conduction system.</hint><hint>The electrical signal starts in the atrial region of the heart. “atria” is in the name.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
