<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u10_m0_intro_01a"><head><title>Major Functions of the Endocrine System</title><objref idref="endo_functions_LO" /><objref idref="endo_diseases_LO" /></head><body><p id="db223b89c4974cdfb8fac2bbc49fd654">The major function of the endocrine system is to participate in homeostatic feedback loops by acting as a means of communication between integrators and effectors, and sometimes acting as the sensor as well. Since the function of the endocrine system is to maintain homeostasis, there will be many system level examples at the end of this chapter. This is an excellent time to review the <activity_link idref="_u3_m1_homeostasis_00" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">concept and formal structure of homeostasis</activity_link>.</p><p id="a2552a1f22624c7ab4fb908f81e41afb">The endocrine system is also involved with growth, development and adaptation. Within all of these changing processes, our bodies tolerate fluctuations within certain limits but still overall homeostasis needs to be maintained.</p><example id="f4b6fa0dd9634651a0707f9fce0245c8"><title>Endocrine System Homeostasis and Integration with Other Systems</title><p id="dd8222e2956d450880289e099917d447">When we grow in height, our bones increase in length. However, proper homeostasis must be maintained to ensure that we always have calcified bone to support our weight. Muscles, tendons and ligaments must also grow proportionately. The endocrine system integrates these changes while still maintaining homeostasis. </p></example><section id="bbcc8629b1a646db9202e493f1811082" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="endo_intro_functions_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="d99f8560f88b42b18a64ce513612f987"><title>Common Dysfunctions of the Endocrine System </title><body><p id="a2952e2ab8d543f7b131b5f45c00fbb4">We feel the effects of changes in the endocrine system at various points in our lives. Hormone levels fluctuate during puberty, and even after we eat a meal. Common dysfunctions of the endocrine system include an inability to regulate glucose, called diabetes mellitus, and an inability to regulate calcium levels in the bones, which may lead to osteoporosis. Other common disorders of the endocrine system include over- or under-production of thyroid hormone (hyperthyroidism and hypothyroidism, respectively), which impacts energy metabolism. In this unit, you will learn about dysfunctions of the endocrine system and the downstream results of such dysfunctions.</p></body></section><section id="f7c8a93d48d346158fa0e4f8a5c2252f"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="endo_intro_compare_lbd" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="endo_functions_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
