<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_lab_lymphatic"><head><title>B-cell Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</title><objref idref="lymph_leukemia_LO" /></head><body><p id="d710030086b44d5caed21792fb0f0f0f">Below is an activity that provides several sections of content and questions that will help you recall, organize and apply what you have learned in this unit to a the condition of B-cell Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia. Explore the following activity to learn how this most common form of Leukemia affects the body. </p><p id="d5b7c22a5b654ee0ad2a79dec6191791">The activity consists of three sections.</p><ul id="ef7f0d23cf1f441c864b1546856c16ec"><li><p id="ae28da0973fb548968a8c64f4973535a5">The top left panel contains an image with hotspots to be used for navigation.</p></li><li><p id="ad4df0ec3c7b24962b3ee3778b795a0a3">The top right panel contains the information you will need to solve the problems and questions that appear for each section.</p></li><li><p id="aa153d725543c472f9cac20e8ef274688">The bottom panel presents activities and questions unique to each section.</p></li></ul><p id="a7885d31285b48f893a2df6009aaf165">Be sure to click on each hotspot to ensure you complete all of the questions within this activity. When you are sure you have finished each section, complete the follow-up activity directly below this one. </p><multipanel id="multiID" purpose="learnbydoing"><title>B-cell Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</title><image_hotspot id="lymphatic_lab_fig" src="../webcontent/lymphatic-hotspot.png" alt="" width="274" height="330" hotspots="transparent"><hotspot shape="circle" coords="208,22,12" title="fatigue and loss of appetite" panel_ref="one" activity_ref="2" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="186,52,12" title="lymph node and spleen swelling" panel_ref="two" activity_ref="3" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="200,86,12" title="Shortness of breath" panel_ref="three" activity_ref="4" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="212,121,12" title="liver enlargement" panel_ref="four" activity_ref="5" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="183,154,12" title="repeated infections" panel_ref="five" activity_ref="6" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="174,285,12" title="bone and/or joint tenderness/pain" panel_ref="six" activity_ref="7" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="221,233,12" title="spotting, easy bleeding and bruising" panel_ref="seven" activity_ref="8" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="42,203,12" title="blood cell count" panel_ref="eight" activity_ref="9" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="45,247,12" title="blood cell morphology" panel_ref="nine" activity_ref="10" /></image_hotspot><panels intro_panel_ref="ex_intropanel"><panel id="ex_intropanel" title="Introduction"><p id="e6b5c0d58e1f4a95871990af2985aca0">Most people who hear the word leukemia consider it an ominous word. It means “white blood,” a term coined by one of the fathers of oncology, Rudolf Virchow, in 1847. Over the past two centuries, research has shown cancer to have many types with many different outcomes. Leukemia itself has many varieties depending on the cell type that proliferates (divides) abnormally, from acute aggressive to chronic, slowly developing types.</p><p id="c7dcddc9cf2547c1adf5ff2095dcd60e"><term>B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia</term> is the most common form of leukemia. It affects B cell lymphocytes, which are produced in the bone marrow and develop in lymph nodes. Their primary function is to fight infections by producing a variety of antibodies. In this form of leukemia, abnormal B cells begin to grow out of control and accumulate - effectively crowding out healthy blood cells. </p><p id="b98067de60b2408e853e141588f0c632"><em style="italic">Consider the following scenario:</em> A middle-aged man presents with complaints of acute onset of abdominal discomfort and fullness, as well as weight loss. The patient also complains of shortness of breath and fatigue. Observe the diagram below, showing the results of a physical examination. Using the hotspots, explore the various symptoms of his condition. After exploring each of these sections, complete the activity below this lab. </p></panel><panel id="one" title="Fatigue and Loss of Appetite"><p id="a00e6792cd5c4976ad52fb83f6463270">Fatigue is a complex symptom that can have a variety of causes, however it is mostly associated to lack of energy. Take a moment to consider where energy comes from in our bodies.</p></panel><panel id="two" title="Lymph Node and Spleen Swelling"><p id="ba05472fafb449e4be6190b0f48aedd6">Lymphadenopathy and splenomegaly are the words for swelling of lymph nodes and spleen. They both belong to the lymphatic system, although they differ in several aspects.</p><image id="dc96040cb9614cebacae6e57afb58627" src="../webcontent/AP-Lymph_lab-1.png" alt="side-by-side image displaying an enlarged spleen and enlarged lymphnodes." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel><panel id="three" title="Shortness of Breath"><p id="d3b14127f6af4517b353b517d3c152c5">The main function of the respiratory system is to obtain oxygen from the air and eliminate carbon dioxide from the tissues. Oxygen crosses from the alveoli in the lungs to the blood, where it is transported in hemoglobin. </p><image id="dfbc71a4260a46eabca0160222ce6afd" src="../webcontent/ap_lymph-blood-exchange.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel><panel id="four" title="Liver Enlargement"><p id="e65179fd035049089b6b31a53a28d4b7">The liver is the body’s largest internal organ. It is also required for survival, due to its many important functions.</p><image id="ddfc239d088c4c5b9ce75ea781127172" src="../webcontent/enlarged-liver.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aa817c72a840c437d9a430216a2228b3c">Enlarged (left) and normal (right) liver in the abdominal cavity. Observe how the enlarged liver presses on the surrounding structures, including the stomach, intestines, and gallbladder (in green).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel><panel id="five" title="Repeated Infections"><p id="de00c76f9d5d45d2a6e4a83e493cef09">Leukemia patients have a tendency to suffer from repeated infections. During infections, microorganisms such as bacteria, viruses, fungi, or parasites penetrate the body’s defenses causing diseases. When healthy, the immune system is remarkably efficient keeping invaders at bay.</p></panel><panel id="six" title="Bone and/or Joint Tenderness/Pain"><p id="be020da1cfc443848ef7958f0352a6ef">It is a common misconception to see bones as static and unresponsive. In fact, bones are very dynamic organs, with a rich supply of blood and nerves through their periosteum. Think about the pain of a damaged bone but also the speed of its recovery- much faster than that of cartilage. Processes affecting the structure of bone and the shape of joints tend to be painful.</p></panel><panel id="seven" title="Spotting, Easy Bleeding and Bruising"><p id="eb1428cfcb574f10a3d1febfb19e5165">Bruises are normally caused by rupture of small blood vessels under the skin if we get hit or bump into something. In the case of B-CLL patients, bruises appear without any major trauma, in addition to easy bleeding of the mucosa. These symptoms point to deficiencies in blood hemostasis</p></panel><panel id="eight" title="LAB TEST: Blood Cell Count"><p id="cfe5e93e78704046b12ff1f035d33db8">Here is a summary of some relevant blood tests for a B-CLL patient.</p><table id="f7b37a34f0364568937eba02fc01d80b" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i12778fb5370d4126976f031433581831" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab1895a25e35b42acb6c93f72405491f7">TEST</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaf281da9e1f34621b9385f31ec0383f4">Normal</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aef66d90249dc44b7b44c592e212d9bc9">B-CLL</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aac13f57e3d724696ab471f18525c06f5">White blood cell count ( per ?l)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa8db2a79ee6c47cf84bbf61e500b2cb3">4,500-11,000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adb1d97262fe147efbe182a3e4946533d">Elevated</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad5c0499673fa4ef992dc07803d95fdec">Lymphocyte count (per ?l)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa334a67451cd4dc89e12ec54c19f8855">1,200-4,000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa59c1791530d4f0eb5c06dd4b2b191db">&gt;10,000/?l</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aecdfff36f34c43de84acf8e892ae5969">Hemoglobin (g/dl)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afe3758c0fb1e4dc58a4379b29bfd592c">12-18</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adfdd245817144d349c75638ef25b8cce">11&lt;</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="c010705e065f41a38680c4a8c9026f2b">Platelets (10<sup>3</sup> per ?l)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="acdd14545f9434b7e958e9043ae57f89b">150-400</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad25ecf4d0fd743eab365a00e62d8371b">100&lt;</p></td></tr></table></panel><panel id="nine" title="Blood Cell Morphology"><p id="cd765153ab7c40819eea11a79e4b8aa2">All blood cells derive from <activity_link idref="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_09" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">hematopoietic stem cells in the bone marrow</activity_link>. In leukemias and lymphomas, differentiation of cells stop at a certain stage, and immature cells divide aggressively, “drowning out” other normal populations. One way to diagnose or further explore leukemias is to observe the morphology of the cells in the blood or the bone marrow. The slide below is a bone marrow aspirate of a B-CLL patient- you can observe an elevated number of large lymphocytes with an immature appearance.</p><image id="d8402a43fdae4342a8547ace699c50e7" src="../webcontent/B-cell_chronic_lymphocytic_leukemia_(B-CLL).jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel></panels><wb:inline idref="ap_lab_lymphatic-inline" purpose="learnbydoing" /></multipanel><activity idref="flow_cytometry_LM" purpose="learnmore" /></body></workbook_page>
