<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="flow_cytometry_LM"><head><title>Immunophenotyping Using Flow Cytometry</title></head><body><p id="dfe3a340b99d42bca66020623a37b234">You may wonder how is it possible to diagnose BCLL based on rather nonspecific symptoms and cell morphology. In fact, definitive diagnosis of BCLL (and any leukemia or lymphoma) requires some more advanced techniques. You recall the figure of the blood cell lineages (see figure p294). Hematopoietic stem cells in the bone marrow can specialize, differentiate, into different types of blood cells depending on chemical and cellular signals around them. As they acquire more specialized characteristics, they are said to be “committed” to a certain lineage (myeloid, lymphoid etc) from where they cannot go back. As they move on with the differentiation process they become more mature and more capable of performing their functions, until they reach their fully functional final stage. Leukemias are classified according to the step in this process that the cells are arrested, and in general the earlier the defect, the more aggressive the disease tends to be, as the cells are more immature.</p><p id="e9779f9bb8e645e8adbacb734c5be1ce">Certain leukemic cells have a very typical morphology, making them easy to diagnose from a blood smear (example would be “hairy cell leukemia” where the lymphocytes acquire a hairy appearance- picture?). However, in other cases, the cancerous cell will be identified using cell surface molecules (“markers”) typical of the disorder Antibodies recognizing specific molecules have been used in serology for many years. The exquisite specificity of antibodies allows distinguishing molecules or organisms in complex mixtures such as blood or serum. You may have seen/heard about the “strep kit,” where the physician can determine from a throat swab if there is a “strep throat” infection in mere minutes. Antibodies against molecular markers of the Streptococcus bacterium responsible for this infection are used in this case. A similar but more sophisticated approach can be used to diagnose leukemias, using antibodies targeting specific cell markers on blood cells.</p><p id="e352187801ac46c69a6d3f8ae4a4ba87">The CD (cluster of differentiation) system is a way to name and classify molecules present on the surface of blood cells. You are probably familiar with CD4 and CD8 T cells, bearing the names of molecules typical of the cell type. In the case of B cells, characteristic markers are CD19 and CD20. Normal B cells usually do not express T-cell associated markers such as CD5, but leukemic cells do. Moreover, BCLL cells often present abnormal B cell receptors. So a good support for a BCLL diagnosis would be detection in the blood of a large number of B lymphocytes expressing abnormal BCR and CD5. </p><p id="a274a3eb20b242199ee9e77f5dcc5ca2">How to detect those cells in the blood is a technical feat. Fluorescently labeled antibodies are directed against cellular markers of the cells, which will attach to them. In order to visualize the cells, a very sophisticated instrument called a flow cytometer separates the cells into individual droplets and analyzes them one by one. A graphic representation of each cell as a dot is obtained, mapped to parameters such as cell size, cell granulosity, expression of markers, etc. How so?</p><image id="d6d6ae6fc6a248f58e9acb0cac3e8dc4" src="../webcontent/flow_cytometry-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="aadda049737142e3838d945c2d318c96">What you see in the image above is a graphic representing the size of the cell, detected by a laser measuring the so-called “Forward scattering” (FSC), and how granular the cells are, detected by a laser measuring “Side scattering” (SS). Each dot represents a cell, and similar cells form “clouds” that can be selected by “gating,” meaning drawing a shape around them. In this graph 3 populations have been gated, A, B, and C.</p><wb:inline idref="flow_cytometry_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /><p id="f93c9814b2024c66915de29f8aa89216">In a similar way, cell populations expressing different markers can be found. Observe the following graph:</p><image id="b818329a073b442b8dc0520261a5e863" src="../webcontent/flow_cytometry-2.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="aa18b125f48249b097a86d3f5c963741">The left graph (“dot plot”) is from the blood of a healthy individual, while the right dot plot shows the results of a BCLL patient. The letters FITC and PE refer to the fluorescent dye attached to the antibodies against the selected markers: CD5 and CD19. Laser beams are able to detect the different wavelengths of the dyes. The scale in the axis refers to the intensity of the fluorescence = the higher the value, the more antibodies are bound to the cell = the more of the markers are expressed by the cell.</p><p id="c1eed02fbc954bdc82761942eeb3f5da">See if you can interpret the results of the graph.</p><wb:inline idref="flow_cytometry_DIGT2" purpose="didigetthis" /><p id="d0e52ec1b8404c75b363f2b1f135be1c">This is, of course, a very simplified presentation of what flow cytometry can do. More complex analyses can provide more detailed information, and even physically separate cells if necessary. </p></body></workbook_page>
