<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u13_m3_review">
    
    <head>
        <title>Lymphatic Homeostasis Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        
        <p> lymphocytes come in several varieties. They are helper T (Th) cells and cytotoxic T cells (Tc). Each type plays an important role 
            in the adaptive immune response. Helper T cells bind to cells and release cytokines needed for coordinating virtually all immune 
            responses. Cytotoxic T cells bind to cells and lyse them to destroy them. Most mature T cells are naïve because they have not yet
            encountered a pathogen. However, when an antigen enters the body only a select few T cells have T-cell receptors (TCRs) that can 
            recognize and bind to that specific antigen. Recall that TCRs recognize and bind only to foreign antigen fragments that are presented 
            in MHC/epitope complex.</p>
        
        <p>The most significant difference between an innate and adaptive immune response is immunological memory. This process only occurs with
            adaptive immunity. Innate responses do not produce any memory cells. When an adaptive response is initiated and the T and B cells 
            proliferate, specialized memory cells are created along with the effector cells. Now, present in the tissues, are many long-surviving
            cells able to recognize the antigen. If the antigen enters the body a subsequent time, a rapid and more robust immune response occurs.</p>
        
        <p>The proper functioning of body cells depends on precise regulation of the composition of the interstitial fluid surrounding them. The 
            composition of interstitial fluid changes as substances move back and forth between it and blood and lymph. Sometimes, the lymph nodes 
            and appendix become overwhelmed from fighting pathogens, resulting in homeostatic imbalance. Lymph nodes can become swollen and tender 
            as the pathogen they are designed to fight infect them and result in inflammation. </p>
        <!--  Quiz  --> 
        <activity idref="u13_homeo_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
    </body>
    
</workbook_page>

