<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u13_m1_review"><head><title>Lymphatic Structures and Functions Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="d757a2f283ce4eb2bcdb4fbb018b3e1d">The lymphatic system has 3 main functions: </p><ol id="cdab594d376943679e4f32a949775804" style="decimal"><li><p id="abcba566b8b7f4764983a412a4ddeae8f">To collect and recycle the excess interstitial fluid and its dissolved substances</p></li><li><p id="aebf46e1599e74c98a2470e8704808529">To absorb fats and other substances from the digestive tract (this topic will be discussed in the Digestive System Unit)</p></li><li><p id="ac1c2a422e2e94bf4b9917affbecb3cf2">To initiate and coordinate an immune response to remove cellular debris, bacteria, toxins, fungi, parasites, and viruses that accumulate in our bodies</p></li></ol><p id="f8fcbb63ae0641e78b8a9652ce431279">Like the circulatory system that carries blood throughout the body, the lymphatic system is made of a series of vessels, capillaries, and organs. These structures collect excess fluid and cellular debris from the tissues and return them back to the blood. The lymphatic system consists of many different tissues and organs that are found throughout the body. Some organs provide the environment for the development and maturation of leukocytes. Other tissues and organs trap pathogen and are the sites where leukocytes can interact with the pathogen. The circulatory and lymphatic systems interact to connect these organs and tissues.</p><p id="e798693b74e44e9ba8194b27cfd19445">The immune system, as part of the lymphatic system, can be viewed as may subsystems constantly guarding its host against microbial invasion. Immunity (resistance) has an innate component and an adaptive component. Both of these components depend on the responses of white blood cells (leukocytes). A bridge between the innate and the adaptive components is the inflammatory response. Although many soluble factors, blood proteins and cells participate in this response, the main purpose of all of the factors is to enable phagocytic leukocytes and plasma components to leave the blood circulation and enter into damaged and/or infected tissues. </p><activity idref="u13_sf_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
