<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u13_m2_review">
    
    <head>
        <title>Lymphatic Levels of Organization Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        
        <p>Blood and interstitial fluids contain three main types of antimicrobial proteins that interfere with microbial growth: 1) interferons, 2) complement, and 3) iron-binding proteins.
            Among the substances that contribute to inflammation are: 1) histamine, 2) kinins, 3) prostaglandins (PGs), 4) leukotrienes (LTs) and 5) complement. Make sure you understand all these
            substances and their functions.
        </p>
        
        <p>The immune system produces a powerful response to foreign molecules, but does not attack its own molecules. To avoid attacking self, the body has established several mechanisms. 
            The immune response can differentiate between pathogenic organisms (bacteria, viruses, parasites and fungus) and human cells. Pathogens express pathogen-associated molecular 
            patterns (PAMPs) that are common to groups of pathogens, but are generally not found on human cells. Antigens are substances that bind to receptors on immune cells. Entire 
            microbes or parts of microbes may act as antigens. T and B lymphocytes, also called T and B cells, are the mediators of the adaptive immune response. They are lymphocytes with
            receptors that bind to antigens. Individual T and B cells recognize only one antigenic determinant. This is like a lock and key system where only one key can open the lock. The
            antigenic determinant is the key. The lock is the receptor on the T or B cell. This T cell receptor (TCR) or B cell receptor (BCR) only fits that one key and opens it (activates 
            it) to initiate an immune. Because T and B cells only recognize one antigen, each T and B cell is said to be antigen-specific.
        </p>
        <p>Low-molecular weight proteins, called cytokines, stimulate or inhibit many cell functions such as cell growth and differentiation.
            These proteins are secreted by white blood cells and various other cells in the body such as endothelial cells, fibroblasts, liver cells and kidney cells. The two principle regulators
            of the immune response are helper T cells and macrophages. cytokines regulate the intensity and duration of the immune response. Cytokines affect the immune response by stimulating 
            or inhibiting the activation, proliferations and/or differentiation of various cells and by regulating the secretion of antibodies and other cytokines.</p>
            
        <p>The lymphatic system consists of many different tissues and organs that are found throughout the body. The red bone marrow is the site where hematopoietic stem cells are found. 
            Hematopoietic stem cells differentiate into the red blood cells (erythrocytes), platelets (thrombocytes) and white blood cells (leukocytes). Leukocytes participate in the immune 
            response and further differentiate into mast cells, granulocytes (neutrophils, eosinophils and basophils), monocytes (macrophages), dendritic cells and lymphocytes (natural killer
            cells, B-cells and T-cells).The thymus is located in the chest, just in front of the heart and behind the sternum of the rib cage.Immature, pre-T cells (thymocytes) migrate from the
            red bone marrow to the cortex of the thymus where they mature. As the lymph fluid moves from the capillary beds through the lymphatic vessels, and before it flows back into the general 
            circulation it enters into areas of small swellings in the vessels called lymph nodes. Lymph nodes are primarily a site for immune system activation. Specialized immune cells, 
            including B lymphocytes, T lymphocytes, and macarophages, leave the bone marrow or thymus gland and reside within the lymph node. In addition to lymph nodes, the lymphatic system 
            includes the spleen. The spleen is located in the left, superior corner of the abdominal cavity, just posterior to the stomach, and protected by the rib cage. 
        </p>
        <!--  Quiz  --> 
        <activity idref="u13_LOO_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
    </body>
    
</workbook_page>

