<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment 2.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_2_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_assessment_2_3.css"?>
<assessment id="_u3_m2_checkpoint1" max_attempts="3" recommended_attempts="1">
    <title>Designing Studies Checkpoint 1</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you
            are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window
            will ask "This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?",
            click "OK" if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p>
        <p>If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost.
            After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to
            be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p>
    </introduction>
    <!--<content available="instructor_only">
        <p><em>Instructors: you can download the solution set for this checkpoint by clicking on the
                following link:</em>
            <link href="../webcontent/_u3_m2_checkpoint1.pdf">Solution Set</link>.</p>
    </content>-->
    <multiple_choice id="pd1" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>In a study, which of the following is the <em style="bold">most important</em> reason to use random
                allocation of subjects to the different treatments?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">To ensure that each subject in the trial receives the best possible
                treatment. </choice>
            <choice value="B">To guarantee that approximately the same number of subjects is
                assigned to each treatment group. </choice>
            <choice value="C">To protect the experimenters from legal action in the event that the
                experiment goes drastically awry. </choice>
            <choice value="D">To ensure that the different treatment groups are as similar as
                possible in every way <em>except</em> for the treatment received. </choice>
            <choice value="E">To guarantee that the results of the experiment can never be
                duplicated. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that "treatments" in a study don’t necessarily refer
                    to making the subjects "better," and random allocation wouldn’t ensure that
                    anyway. <!--Think about the other choices.--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that random allocation would ensure roughly
                    the same number of subjects per treatment group, that’s not the most
                        important reason for the random allocation.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Random allocation in a study is important for a reason
                    involving the interpretation of the results, not for legal protection; and
                    random allocation wouldn’t ensure legal protection, anyway.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. By ensuring that the treatment groups are as similar in every
                    possible way except for the imposed treatment, random allocation <em style="italic">eliminates
                        lurking variables</em>and thus allows conclusions of <em style="italic">causation</em>.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Random allocation doesn’t prevent the experimental results from
                    being replicated by other researchers. If it did, we wouldn’t do it, since
                    replication is important to verify experimental results.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd2" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>It is known that, in the United States, well-educated people are less likely to smoke.
                But what about other nations, where there may be different cultures and/or attitudes
                toward smoking? In a 1998 study of the relationship between education and smoking
                in France, a random sample of 334 French men was classified according to their
                education level (elementary, high-school, or university) and their smoking habits
                (smoker or nonsmoker).</p>
            <p>Which of the following statements about this study is correct?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; This study is an experiment, since each subject was
                classified into one of the six possible combinations of education level and smoking
                habits. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; This study is an experiment, since it was based on a
                random sample. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; This study is an observational study, since researchers
                did not assign the men to be smokers or non-smokers, or to one of the education
                levels. </choice>
            <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; This study is a combination of both an experiment and an
                observational study. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Merely having subjects classified according to variables isn’t
                    enough to make a study an experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling</em> method isn’t what determines whether a
                    study is an experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. A study is <em style="italic">experimental</em> if the researchers
                        assigned the subjects to different values of the explanatory
                    variable, and it’s <em style="italic">observational</em> otherwise. In this case, since
                    subjects were only classified according to their own personally decided smoking
                    habits, and since their education level also certainly wasn’t assigned by the
                    researchers, this study was observational. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A study cannot be a mix of experiment and observation. A study
                    is <em style="italic">experimental</em> if the researchers assigned the subjects to
                    the explanatory variable, and it’s <em style="italic">observational</em> otherwise. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd5" select="single">
        <body>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T190254-0400" comment="This is the same question (with the same choices) that was used as an exercise in this module. Is that OK? "?>In
            an experiment to see if aspirin reduces the chance of having a heart attack, which of
            the following would be a placebo? <?oxy_comment_end?></body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; The place where the subjects go when they have a heart
                attack. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; A dummy pill that looks like aspirin but has no active
                ingredients. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; A procedure for deciding who gets the aspirin treatment. </choice>
            <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; The sampling method. </choice>
            <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; The randomization procedure. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The word <em style="italic">placebo</em> doesn’t refer to a place.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. A placebo is a non-active treatment used in a study for proper
                    comparison. In this case, it ensures that any comparative effect in the aspirin
                    group is really due to the active ingredient rather than just due to the
                    "placebo effect." </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">placebo</em> isn’t a procedure, and it doesn’t determine who
                    gets the treatment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">placebo</em> isn’t a sampling method.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">placebo</em> isn’t a procedure, and it doesn’t cause
                    randomization.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd10" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following is the main advantage of experiments over observational
                studies?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; A well-designed experiment can give good evidence that
                the treatment actually causes the response. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; An experiment can compare two or more groups. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; An experiment is typically cheaper. </choice>
            <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; An experiment is typically shorter. </choice>
            <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; We can include more than one explanatory variable in an
                experiment.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. An <em style="italic">experiment</em> is a study in which the treatments are
                        <em style="italic">assigned by the researchers</em>. This allows the possibility of random
                    assignment, which eliminates lurking variables and thus allows
                        causation to be determined. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Observational studies can also compare groups. Merely having
                    comparison of groups isn’t what makes something an
                    experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An experimental study is not necessarily cheaper than
                    an observational study; and cost-savings wouldn’t be the most important
                    benefit, anyway.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An experimental study is not necessarily shorter in
                    duration than an observational study; and time-savings wouldn’t be the
                    most important benefit, anyway.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Observational studies can also have more than one explanatory
                    variable. The number of explanatory variables isn’t what makes something an
                        experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd12" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T191010-0400" comment="This exact question was used as one of the exercises in the section. Is that OK?"?>Students
                in a large statistics class were randomly divided into two groups. The first group
                took the midterm exam with soft music playing in the background, and the second
                group took the exam with no music playing. After the exam was completed, a
                researcher compared deidentified exam scores of the two groups.<?oxy_comment_end?>
            </p>
            <p>Which of the following is the reason this experiment was <em style="bold">not</em>
                blind?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">The sample sizes in both groups was large.</choice>
            <choice value="B">Researchers looked at exam scores for the two groups.</choice>
            <choice value="C">The students knew whether or not music was playing while they were
                taking the exam. </choice>
            <choice value="D">Some of the students may not have studied for the exam.</choice>
            <choice value="E">Students were randomized into the two groups.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Blinding in study design has nothing to do with the size of
                    the samples.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Since the researcher looked at scores without student names and
                    conditions after the exam was complete, she was “blind” to which students were in
                    each of the two conditions.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Blinding in study design is when the subjects don’t know which
                    treatment they’re getting. In this case, the treatments are background music or
                    no background music. The students would certainly be aware of whether music was
                    playing during the exam, so they would know which treatment they got.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Blinding in study design does not refer to whether the
                    students know the answers on the exam. It refers to whether the subjects are
                    aware of something else pertaining to the study.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Having two randomized groups isn’t what determines whether or
                    not a study is blind.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd15" select="multiple">
        <body>
            <p>To test an herbal treatment for depression, 100 volunteers who suffered from mild
                depression were randomly divided into two groups. Each person was given a month's
                supply of tea bags. For one group, the tea contained the herb mixed with spice tea,
                whereas for the other group, the bags contained only the spice tea. Participants
                were not told which type of tea they had, and were asked to drink one cup of tea per
                day for a month. At the end of the month, a psychologist evaluated them to determine
                if their mood had improved. The psychologist did not know which of the subjects had
                the tea with the herbal ingredient added. </p>
            <p>Which of the following statements is true regarding this study? Check all that
                apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; This study is an observational study. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; This study is double-blind. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; The "only spice tea" group serves as the control group.
            </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A study is observational when the researcher doesn’t play any
                    role in determining what treatment each subject might get. But in the study
                    described, the researchers assigned each subject which tea to use, so the study
                    wasn’t observational. Also, there is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study is double-blind, because the
                    subjects didn’t know which tea they got (which protects against the placebo
                    effect), and the psychologist also didn’t know (which helps guard against
                    researcher bias). However, there is at least one other true
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the "only spice tea" group serves as the
                    control group, because they didn’t get any active herbal ingredient. However,
                    there is at least one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study is double-blind, because the
                    subjects didn’t know which tea they got (which protects against the placebo
                    effect), and the psychologist also didn’t know (which helps guard against
                    researcher bias). However, a study is observational when the researcher doesn’t
                    play any role in determining what treatment each subject might get. But in the
                    study described, the researchers assigned each subject which tea to use, so the
                    study wasn’t observational.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the "only spice tea" group serves as the
                    control group, because they didn’t get any active herbal ingredient. However, a
                    study is observational when the researcher doesn’t play any role in determining
                    what treatment each subject might get. But in the study described, the
                    researchers assigned each subject which tea to use, so the study wasn’t
                    observational.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The study is double-blind, because the subjects didn’t know which
                    tea they got (which protects against the placebo effect), and the psychologist
                    also didn’t know (which helps guard against researcher bias). Also, the "only
                    spice tea" group serves as the control group, because they didn’t get any active
                    herbal ingredient. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study is double-blind, because the
                    subjects didn’t know which tea they got (which protects against the placebo
                    effect), and the psychologist also didn’t know (which helps guard against
                    researcher bias). Also, you are correct that the "only spice tea" group serves
                    as the control group, because they didn’t get any active herbal ingredient.
                    However, there is at least one other true statement. However, a study is
                    observational when the researcher doesn’t play any role in determining what
                    treatment each subject might get. But in the study described, the researchers
                    assigned each subject which tea to use, so the study wasn’t
                    observational.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd16" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>For their 1992 study, "The Effect of Country Music on Suicide"
                (published in <em style="italic">Social Forces</em>, vol. 71, p. 211), researchers
                Stack and Gundlach investigated various American communities, recording the number
                of minutes of daily radio airtime devoted to country songs and the suicide rate.
                They found a moderately strong positive correlation. </p>
            <p>In their paper, the researchers explain the results by saying that
                &#x201C;&#x2026;the themes found in country music <em style="italic"
                    >foster</em> a suicidal mood ...&#x201D; (emphasis added). A news
                headline (The Independent [London], October 1, 2004, p. 15) about the research
                echoed these sentiments when it said, &#x201C;Strange But True: Country Music Saps
                Will to Live.&#x201D; The research is even cited on various suicide-prevention
                websites, some with headings such as &#x201C;Country Music Increases Suicide
                Risk.&#x201D; </p>
            <p>Based on this study, can we have confidence in causality between country music and
                suicide? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; Yes, as long as the communities were sampled randomly,
                and the number of communities (the sample size) was sufficiently large. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; Yes, causality is indicated by the moderately strong
                correlation. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; Yes, since different communities listened to different
                levels of country music, meaningful experimental comparisons can be made. </choice>
            <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; No, because the lack of assignment of communities to
                different levels of country music listening means there is a possibility of lurking
                variables. </choice>
            <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; No, causality can only be demonstrated by investigating
                the entire population. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em>sampling</em> method only determines whether the
                    relationship seen in the study can be generalized to the population (within the
                    uncertainty of natural variability), but not whether the relationship
                    demonstrates causation or merely association. The sample <em>size</em> only
                    helps to determine the uncertainty due to natural variability, but not whether
                    the relationship demonstrates causation.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation only measures the strength of the relationship,
                    but it doesn’t indicate whether the relationship demonstrates
                    causation.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Only <em>experiments</em> can determine causation, but it’s not
                    merely having comparisons that makes something an <em>experiment</em>. There can
                    be comparisons in observational studies, too.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. <em>Causation</em> can only be determined if the <em>explanatory
                        variable is randomly assigned</em>. But in this case, the researchers didn’t
                    randomly assign different amounts of country music to be played in different
                    communities. So the study design doesn’t rule out lurking variables.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The entire population doesn’t need to be investigated to
                    determine causation. A relationship can be determined to be causative based on
                    the study design.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</assessment>
