<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment 2.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_2_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_assessment_2_3.css"?>
<assessment id="_u2_m1_checkpoint1" max_attempts="3" recommended_attempts="1">
    <title>Examining Distributions Checkpoint 1</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you
            are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window
            will ask "This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?",
            click "OK" if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p>
        <p>If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost.
            After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to
            be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p>
    </introduction>
    <!--<content available="instructor_only">
        <p><em>Instructors: you can download the solution set for this checkpoint by clicking on the
                following link:</em>
            <link href="../webcontent/_u2_m1_checkpoint1.pdf">Solution Set</link>.</p>
    </content>-->
    <selection count="1" exhaustion="reuse">
        <pool id="_u2_m1_pool1">
            <title>Pool1</title>
            <section id="_u2_m1_pool1_section1">
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_percentage" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                            trauma (accidents and homicides) that were observed in a certain
                            hospital during a week.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif"/>
                        <p>What percentage of deaths were individuals younger than 35?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 34% </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 60% </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 68% </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 70% </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; 80% </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that 3 + 18 + 13 = 34 out of the 50 fall
                                below age 35 (those within the first three bars). However, note that
                                the problem asks for <em style="italic">percentage</em> rather than
                                count.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is clear from looking at the histogram that
                                more than 50% of the observations fall below 35 (i.e., within the
                                first three bars), the percentage is actually higher than 60%. Count
                                the number of observations below 35 and then use that number to
                                calculate the percentage.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. From the histogram we can ﬁnd that 3 + 18 + 13 = 34
                                out of the 50 observations fall below age 35 (those within the first
                                three bars), and since the question asks about the <em
                                    style="italic">percentage</em> of observations, the answer is
                                (34/50) * 100 = 68%. </feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is clear from looking at the histogram that
                                more than 50% of the observations fall below 35 (those within the
                                first three bars), the percentage is actually lower than 70%. Count
                                the number of observations below 35 and then use that number to
                                calculate the percentage.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is clear from looking at the histogram that
                                more than 50% of the observations fall below 35 (those within the
                                first three bars), this is not quite as high as 80%. Count the
                                number of observations below 35 and then use that number to
                                calculate the percentage.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_shape" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                            trauma (accidents and homicides) that were observed in a certain
                            hospital during a week.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif"/>
                        <p>Which of the following best describes the shape of the histogram?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; Symmetric </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; Left-skewed with no outliers </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; Right-skewed with no outliers </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; Left-skewed with a possible outlier </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; Right-skewed with a possible outlier
                        </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. The shape of the distribution is clearly skewed.
                                Where is the “tail,” and are there any possible outliers?
                            </feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that the distribution is skewed,
                                recall that the direction of the skewness is determined by where the
                                “tail” is. Also, look at the distribution carefully. Are there any
                                possible outliers?</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the distribution is skewed
                                right, however note that one of the other answers more accurately
                                describes the distribution.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that the distribution is skewed,
                                recall that the direction of the skewness is determined by where the
                                “tail” is.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The distribution of ages is skewed right (which is
                                where the “tail” of the distribution is). Also the largest
                                observation&#8212;approximately equal to 90&#8212;is a possible high
                                outlier. </feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_mean_median" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                            trauma (accidents and homicides) that were observed in a certain
                            hospital during a week. </p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif"/>
                        <p>For the data described by the above histogram, which of the following is
                            a correct statement about the median?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; The median will be bigger than the mean. </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; The median will be smaller than the mean. </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; The median and the mean will be about the
                            same. </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; The median and the range will be about the
                            same. </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Notice this distribution is skewed to the right
                                (the tail is towardthe right), and we also see a suspected outlier
                                on the right side. Remember that both of these shape features will
                                tend to “pull” the <em style="italic">mean</em> more than they would pull the
                                median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The mean is more sensitive than the median to the
                                “tail” of a distribution, and also to outliers. We see that this
                                distribution is skewed to the right (the tail is towards the right)
                                and we also see a suspected outlier on the right side. Both of these
                                shape features will tend to “pull” the mean toward the tail more
                                than they would pull the median, meaning that the median will be
                                smaller than the mean.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that we would expect the mean and the median
                                to be nearly the same only if the distribution was nearly symmetric.
                                But notice this distribution is skewed to the right (the tail is
                                towards the right) and we also see a suspected outlier on the right
                                side. Remember that both of these shape features will tend to “pull”
                                the mean more than they would pull the median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="italic">range</em> is the length from
                                lowest value to highest value. So, for this distribution, the range
                                is approximately 80. But remember that the <em>median</em> is the
                                middle value. Half the people must be older than the median, so the
                                median will be much less than 80, because all but one of the people
                                were younger than 80.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_median" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                            trauma (accidents and homicides) that occurred in a certain hospital
                            during a week. </p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif"/>
                        <p>Which of the following is a possible value of the median in this
                            example?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 23 </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 45 </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 50 </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 33 </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; It is impossible to answer without seeing
                            all of the data. </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. Only
                                21 people out of 50 could be younger than age 23, as represented by
                                the total height of the two left bars on the display. So 23 is too
                                low to be the median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. Only
                                10 people out of 50 could be older than age 45, as represented by
                                the total height of the four bars on the right side of the display.
                                So 45 is too large to be the median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the value of the middle
                                person, not the middle of the range. Only 10 people out of 50 could
                                be older than age 50, as represented by the total height of the four
                                bars on the right side of the display. So 50 is too large to be the
                                median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The median is the middle value. There are 50
                                people in the data, so the median must be the age between the 25th
                                youngest person and the 26th youngest person. These people will both
                                be represented in the third bar from the left on the display. Since
                                that bar represents ages from 25 to 35, the median could be any
                                value between those ages.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_outlier_mean_median" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                            trauma (accidents and homicides) that were observed in a certain
                            hospital during a week. </p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif"/>
                        <p>Assume that the largest observation in this dataset is 90. If this
                            observation were wrongly recorded as 900, then what would happen to the
                            mean and median?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; <!--Both the mean and the median will not-->Neither the mean nor the median would change.</choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; Both the mean and the median would change. </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; The mean would stay the same, but the median
                            would change. </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; The mean would decrease, but the median would not
                            change. </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; The mean would increase, but the median would not
                            change. </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the median would not change, because
                                pulling 90 to 900 would not change the 25th or the 26th value in the
                                data. But remember that the <em style="italic">mean</em> tends to be “pulled” by an
                                outlier. So moving the largest value, 90, farther to the right, to
                                900, would tend to pull the mean to the right, making it
                                larger.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the mean would change, because mean
                                tends to be “pulled” by outliers. But remember that the
                                    <em style="italic">median</em> is the middle value. Moving 90 to 900 would not
                                change the 25th or the 26th value in the data, so the median would
                                be the same.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="italic">mean</em> tends to be
                                “pulled” by an outlier. So moving the largest value, 90, farther to
                                the right, to 900, would tend to pull the mean to the right. So
                                the mean would change. But the <em style="italic">median</em> is the middle
                                value. Pulling 90 to 900 would not change the 25th or the 26th value
                                in the data, so the median would be the same.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the median would not change, because
                                moving 90 to 900 would not change the 25th or the 26th value in the
                                data. But remember that the <em style="italic">mean</em> tends to be “pulled” by an
                                outlier. Moving the largest value, 90, farther to the right, to 900,
                                would tend to pull the mean to the right, making it increase, not
                                decrease.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The mean will increase, because the mean tends to be
                                “pulled” by an outlier. So moving the largest value, 90, farther to
                                the right, to 900, would tend to pull the mean to the right. The
                                    <em style="italic">median</em> would not be affected, because moving 90 to 900
                                would not change the 25th or the 26th value in the data. </feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="identify_mode" select="single">
                    <!--LO:Define and identify mode(s) for a given set of data-->
                    <body><p>The following data, on the number of children <!--ever -->born per 1,000
                            women, is from the <em style="italic">Current Population Reports—Fertility of American Women: 2008</em></p>
                        <table>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Number of Children</em></td>
                                <td align="center">0</td>
                                <td align="center">1</td>
                                <td align="center">2</td>
                                <td align="center">3</td>
                                <td align="center">4</td>
                                <td align="center">5 or more</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Frequency</em></td>
                                <td align="center">45.7%</td>
                                <td align="center">17.0%</td>
                                <td align="center">21.1%</td>
                                <td align="center">10.6%</td>
                                <td align="center">3.9%</td>
                                <td align="center">1.8%</td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>
                        <p>What is the modal number of children born to American women in
                        2008?</p></body>
                    <input shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A">0</choice>
                        <choice value="B">1</choice>
                        <choice value="C">2</choice>
                        <choice value="D">3</choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The most commonly occurring value is 0; therefore,
                                0 is the modal number of children born to American women, in
                                2008.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. The third-most frequently occurring value is 1.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. The second-most frequently occurring value is 2.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. The fourth-most frequently occurring value is 3.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
            </section>
            <section id="_u2_m1_pool1_section2">
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_percentage_alternate" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p> This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                            animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png"/>
                        <p>What percentage of the rats navigated the maze in less than 5.5
                            minutes?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 21% </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 60% </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 68% </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 70% </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; 84% </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that 3 + 8 + 6 + 4 = 21 out of the 25
                                rats fall below 5.5 minutes (first four bars). However, the question
                                asks about the percentage of observations rather than the
                                count.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is clear from looking at the histogram that more than 50% of the observations fall below 5.5 minutes (i.e., within the first four bars), the percentage is actually higher than 60%. Count the number of observations below 5.5 and then use that number to calculate the percentage.<!-- From the histogram we can find that 3
                                + 8 + 6 + 4 = 21 out of the 25 rats fall below 5.5 minutes (first
                                four bars). Since the question asks about the percentage of
                                observations, the answer is 21/25 * 100 = 84%.(E) is the correct
                                answer.--></feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is clear from looking at the histogram that
                                more than 50% of the observations fall below 5.5 minutes (i.e.,
                                within the first four bars), the percentage is actually higher than
                                60%. Count the number of observations below 5.5 and then use that
                                number to calculate the percentage.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is clear from looking at the histogram that more than 50% of the observations fall below 5.5 minutes (i.e., within the first four bars), the percentage is actually higher than 70%. Count the number of observations below 5.5 and then use that number to calculate the percentage.<!--While it is clear from looking at the histogram that
                                more than 50% of the observations fall below 5.5 minutes (i.e.,
                                within the first four bars), the percentage is actually higher than
                                68%. Count the number of observations below 5.5 and then use that
                                number to calculate the percentage.--></feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. From the histogram we can find that 3 + 8 + 6 + 4 =
                                21 out of the 25 rats fall below 5.5 minutes (first four bars).
                                Since the question asks about the percentage of observations, the
                                answer is 21/25 * 100 = 84%.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_shape_alternate" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                            animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png"/>
                        <p>Which of the following best describes the shape of the histogram?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; Symmetric </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; Left-skewed with no outliers </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; Right-skewed with no outliers </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; Left-skewed with a possible outlier </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; Right-skewed with a possible outlier
                        </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. The shape of the distribution is clearly skewed.
                                Where is the tail, and are there any possible outliers?</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that the distribution is skewed,
                                recall that the direction of the skewness is determined by where the
                                tail is. Also, look at the distribution carefully. Are there any
                                possible outliers?</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the distribution is skewed
                                right. However, note that one of the other answers more accurately
                                describes the distribution.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that the distribution is skewed,
                                recall that the direction of the skewness is determined by where the
                                tail is.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The distribution of times is skewed right (which is
                                where the tail of the distribution is). Also, the largest
                                observation—approximately equal to 9 minutes—is a possible high
                                outlier.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_mean_median_alternate" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                            animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png"/>
                        <p>For the data described by the above histogram, which of the following is
                            a correct statement about the median?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; The median will be smaller than the mean. </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; The median will be larger than the mean. </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; The median and the mean will be about the
                            same. </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; The median and the range will be about the
                            same. </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. When the distribution is skewed right, the mean is
                                “pulled up” by the large observations in the “tail” of the
                                distribution. The median, on the other hand, is only determined by
                                the order of the observations, and is not affected by their
                                magnitude. Therefore, in this case, the median is smaller than the mean.<!--: the median is smaller than the mean.--></feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. When the distribution is skewed right, the mean is
                                “pulled up” by the large observations in the “tail” of the
                                distribution. The median, on the other hand, is only determined by
                                the order of the observations, and is not affected by their
                                magnitude.<!-- Therefore, in this case: mean &gt; median.--></feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. When the distribution is skewed right, the mean is
                                “pulled up” by the large observations in the “tail” of the
                                distribution. The median, on the other hand, is only determined by
                                the order of the observations, and is not affected by their
                                magnitude.<!-- Therefore, in this case: mean &gt; median-->.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="italic">range</em> is the length from
                                lowest value to highest value. So, for this distribution, the range
                                is approximately 7. But remember that the <em style="italic">median</em> is the
                                middle value. Half of the times must be greater than the median, so
                                the median will be much less than 7, because all but two of the
                                times were less than 7.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_median_alternate" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                            animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png"/>
                        <p>Which of the following is a possible value of the median in this
                            example?</p>
                    </body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 3.3 </choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 3.9 </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 4.6 </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 5.5 </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. There
                                are 25 observations (odd number) and therefore the median is the
                                13th ranked observation. Only 11 observations fall below 3.5, so 3.3
                                is too low to be the median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. There are 25 observations (odd number), and therefore
                                the median is the 13th ranked observation. If we look at the
                                histogram, we can figure out that the 13th observation falls in the
                                third interval (3.5–4.5 minutes). The only option with such a number
                                is 3.9 minutes.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. There
                                are 25 observations (odd number) and therefore the median is the
                                13th ranked observation. Only 8 observations fall above 4.5, so 4.6
                                is too high to be the median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. There
                                are 25 observations (odd number) and therefore the median is the
                                13th ranked observation. Only 5 observations fall above 5.5, so this
                                is too high to be the median.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="histogram_outlier_mean_median_alternate" select="single">
                    <body>
                        <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                            animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png"/>
                        <p>Assume that the largest observation in this dataset is 8.6 minutes. If
                            this observation were wrongly recorded as 86, then what would happen to
                            the mean and median?</p></body>
                    <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; <!--Both the mean and the median will not
                            change. -->Neither the mean nor the median would change.</choice>
                        <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; Both the mean and the median would change. </choice>
                        <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; The mean would stay the same, but the median
                            would change. </choice>
                        <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; The mean would decrease, but the median would not
                            change. </choice>
                        <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; The mean would increase, but the median would not
                            change. </choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                                observations, whereas the median is determined by their order. While
                                the median would stay the same, changing the largest observation from
                                8.6 to 86 would have an impact on the mean.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                                observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                                Therefore, changing the largest observation from 8.6 to 86 would have
                                an impact on the mean. However, the median would stay the
                                same.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you confused the impact of an outlier on
                                the mean and median. The mean is affected by the actual values of
                                the observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                                Therefore, changing the largest observation from 8.6 to 86 would have
                                an impact on the mean, while the median would stay the
                                same.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                                observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                                While the median would stay the same, changing the largest
                                observation from 8.6 to 86 would have an impact on the mean. But
                                remember that the mean tends to be “pulled” by an outlier. Moving
                                the largest value, 8.6, farther to the right, to 86, would tend to
                                pull the mean to the right, making it increase, not
                                decrease.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="10">
                            <feedback>
                                <p>Correct. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                                    observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                                    Therefore, changing the largest observation from 8.6 to 86 would
                                    have an impact on the mean, while the median would stay the same.
                                    So moving the largest value, 8.6, farther to the right, to 86,
                                    would tend to pull the mean to the right. The median would not
                                    be affected, because moving 8.6 t o 86 would not change the 13th
                                    value in the data.</p>
                                <p>Actually, we can figure out the <em style="italic">exact</em>
                                    impact that the change will have on the mean: By changing 8.6 to
                                    86, the sum of all the observations is increased by 86 - 8.6 =
                                    77.4, and therefore the mean of the 25 observations is increased
                                    by 77.4 / 25 = 3.1 minutes.</p>
                            </feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
                <multiple_choice id="identify_mode_alternate" select="single">
                    <!--LO:-->
                    <body><p>A survey was conducted to determine the number of servings of
                            vegetables eaten, per day, by adolescents in the United States. The
                            following table shows the results:</p>
                        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/mode_1_.png"/>
                        <p> What is the modal number of vegetable servings eaten, per day, by
                            adolescents in the United States?</p></body>
                    <input shuffle="false">
                        <choice value="A">0</choice>
                        <choice value="B">1</choice>
                        <choice value="C">2</choice>
                        <choice value="D">3</choice>
                        <choice value="E">More than 3</choice>
                    </input>
                    <part>
                        <response match="A" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. The least frequently occurring
                                value is 0.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="B" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. The second-most frequently occurring
                                value is 1.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="C" score="10">
                            <feedback>Correct. The most commonly occurring value is two; therefore,
                                2 is the modal number of vegetable servings consumed, per day, by
                                U.S. teenagers.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="D" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. The fourth-most frequently occurring
                                value is 3.</feedback>
                        </response>
                        <response match="E" score="0">
                            <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the mode is the most frequently
                                occurring value. “More than 3” is the third-most frequently
                                occurring value.</feedback>
                        </response>
                    </part>
                </multiple_choice>
            </section>
        </pool>
    </selection>
    <!--  <section id="myresponse">
		<content>
			<p> Please answer the question below. Your response will not be graded, but will be
				available for your instructor to read.</p>
		</content>
		<short_answer id="short_answer_numerical_measures" grading="automatic">
			<body>What determines which numerical measures of center and spread are appropriate for
				describing a given distribution of a quantitative variable? Which measures will you
				use in each case?</body>
			<part>
				<response match="*" score="0">
					<feedback>Thank you for your response. It has been recorded and will be
						available for your instructor to read.</feedback>
				</response>
				<no_response>
					<feedback>You did not enter a response for this question.</feedback>
				</no_response>
			</part>
		</short_answer>
	</section>-->
</assessment>
