<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_levels_org_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Urinary Levels of Organization</title><introduction><p id="b9142871a0e94f65bd4caf72e9d9abaa">You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window will ask &quot;This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?&quot;, click &quot;OK&quot; if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p><p id="f993ba48388a44e1946b86b43c8c7532">If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost. After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p></introduction><page id="f811a05868994b5b8b3f22dcd83baef9"><multiple_choice id="urea_q1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad43f8e6d1d8f43129cc34581efbfb279">What is the component of urine that is an organic breakdown product of nitrogenous materials, is indicative of overall kidney functioning, and reveals a person&apos;s protein balance?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="afc4158bb4514805bb671fefea2bf47f" labels="false"><choice value="A">Chloride</choice><choice value="B">Potassium</choice><choice value="C">Creatinine</choice><choice value="D">Urea</choice></input><part id="urea_q1_p1"><skillref idref="identify_urine_comp_molecular" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab2b0538a1b1c4d8ba479ee09bf6bd45e">Incorrect. Chloride helps keep an adequate balance of body fluids and aids in maintaining an acid-based balance in the body. Urea is an organic breakdown product of nitrogenous materials, reveals a person&apos;s protein balance, and gives and indication of overall kidney functioning.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac00578d0dc4a4ef8ba95bc7f48220391">Incorrect. Potassium is instrumental in proper functioning of nerves and muscles and has an inverse relationship with sodium. Urea is an organic breakdown product of nitrogenous materials, reveals a person&apos;s protein balance, and gives and indication of overall kidney functioning.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab11a8d295ed54014a37b1f2106099c1e">Incorrect. Like urea, creatine helps evaluate overall kidney functioning. However, creatine also gives an indication of other chemicals in the body such as the amount of protein. On the other hand, urea is an organic breakdown product of nitrogenous materials and reveals a person&apos;s protein balance.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad4c43c5e4a7a4a76ab35010c9e187413">Correct. Urea is an organic breakdown product of nitrogenous materials. The level of urea in a urine test reveals a person&apos;s protein balance. In addition, excretion of urea is indicative of overall kidney functioning.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="volume_urine_day_q2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aeeb8ca4a08d3481e8198d11feea6052b">How much water content is a clinical characteristics of normal urine?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="c856952df626400882e9d4e8b9e0121e" labels="false"><choice value="A">59 to 79 percent</choice><choice value="B">95 to 97 percent</choice><choice value="C">100 percent</choice><choice value="D">50 percent</choice></input><part id="volume_urine_day_q2_p1"><skillref idref="determine_physical_chemical_urine" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa183243a5d1641fcb8fda7aa47d86459">Incorrect. Despite the volume of liquid varying from day to day, the total water content remains the same and ranges from 95-97%.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab86ce12f585d454cbc870c323982ba68">Correct. Despite the volume of liquid varying from day to day, the total water content remains the same and ranges from 95-97%.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe0c87cbb9284ce1887593b386c443bf">Incorrect. Despite the volume of liquid varying from day to day, the total water content remains the same and ranges from 95-97%.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac78a92aad84842b2b8e29bd94523d03c">Incorrect. Despite the volume of liquid varying from day to day, the total water content remains the same and ranges from 95-97%.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="loophenle_reabosorption_q3" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad6e9cde6863946b1b866db09153bc62f">The thin and thick parts of the ascending and descending limbs are distinct parts of the __________ which is involved with _________.</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="e9b8d509df694500bdfde722ef0d39ef" labels="false"><choice value="A">The loop of Henle; reabsorption</choice><choice value="B">Capillaries of the nephron; filtration</choice><choice value="C">Collecting duct; secretion</choice><choice value="D">Peritubular Capillaries; reabsorption</choice></input><part id="loophenle_reabosorption_q3_p1"><skillref idref="explain_role_loop_henle" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac344f126b70b4dbbb619da7b64f3970a">Correct. The descending limb of the nephron loop the first part of the nephron loop drops into the renal medulla. Deep in the renal medulla, it makes a sharp, almost 180-degree turn back toward the renal cortex as the ascending limb of the loop of Henle. The ascending and descending limbs have two distinct parts: a thin limb and a thick limb. The loop of Henle is involved with reabsorption.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae3732c24ab0b4f7681eeb62a24d50661">Incorrect. The thin and thick parts of the ascending and descending limbs are distinct parts of the loop of Henle which is involved with reabsorption.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad560ab321c91451e94b5a0539129b4a5">Incorrect. The thin and thick parts of the ascending and descending limbs are distinct parts of the loop of Henle which is involved with reabsorption.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="afcdacb3b21e5404a9d369fd1aa8840c0">Incorrect. The thin and thick parts of the ascending and descending limbs are distinct parts of the loop of Henle which is involved with reabsorption.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="collecting_duct_q4" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa2d1c45290b04228b7fc34aee9e89bbb">The role of the collecting duct is...</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="acf9e1b8dcae41ae93f889426a988980" labels="false"><choice value="A">secreting certain substances from the blood into the tubular lumen.</choice><choice value="B">transporting some substances from the tubular fluid back into blood.</choice><choice value="C">accumulating any material that is not returned to blood and reabsorbing water under the influence of anti-diuretic hormone.</choice><choice value="D">retain proteins and blood cells.</choice></input><part id="collecting_duct_q4_p1"><skillref idref="identify_mechanisms_nephron_collecting_ducts" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac9904222856643209bfec68648ca6c1c">Incorrect. Peritubular Capillaries secrete certain substances from the blood into the tubular lumen. The collecting duct accumulates material that is not returned to blood in the preceding segments of the nephron.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aafab88b80d8f485fa438747eb1fe4a15">Incorrect. Peritubular Capillaries transport some substances from the tubular fluid back into blood. The collecting duct accumulates material that is not returned to blood in the preceding segments of the nephron.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaeca0278d1d04dd8a268bfe5095737ab">Correct. The role of the collecting duct is accumulating any material that is not returned to blood in the preceding segments of the nephron. The collecting duct also reabsorbs water under the influence of anti-diuretic hormone. Anything left in the distal end of the collecting duct will be excreted as urine.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe827e2397fd4bcca096917372e70413">Incorrect. The glomerulus retains proteins and blood cells. The collecting duct accumulates material that is not returned to blood in the preceding segments of the nephron.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="kidney_symmetrical_q5" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac7a45c0b328948988a673edb4879381f">The kidneys are just above waist level, but are asymmetrical in their exact location. This is because?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="b15e9f3e4aa14b25af9ecef9c590b636" labels="false"><choice value="A">The liver takes up space on the right side of the abdominal cavity, superior to the kidney.</choice><choice value="B">The eleventh and twelfth rib pairs are asymmetrical.</choice><choice value="C">The peritoneum and the posterior abdominal walls are asymmetrical.</choice><choice value="D">None of the above, the kidneys are symmetrical.</choice></input><part id="kidney_symmetrical_q5_p1"><skillref idref="identify_kidneys" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac2640df813a1489b974cb5225347d599">Correct. The asymmetry of the kidneys occurs because the liver takes up so much space on the right side of the abdominal cavity superior to the kidney.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa5b61ad70e9d4b31b6141251eceac626">Incorrect. The asymmetry of the kidneys occurs because the liver takes up so much space on the right side of the abdominal cavity superior to the kidney.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af931588c60e749638828a48140a91fd3">Incorrect. The asymmetry of the kidneys occurs because the liver takes up so much space on the right side of the abdominal cavity superior to the kidney.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="acbee5c708199477eb4b64538399e3165">Incorrect. The asymmetry of the kidneys occurs because the liver takes up so much space on the right side of the abdominal cavity superior to the kidney.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="kidney_tissue_layers_q6" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aae2774b4007148cda564182d926ba1da">Each kidney is enshrouded in three tissue layers which are called:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b95ab9006f01403eacd493ee7e1abbe8" labels="false"><choice value="A">renal hilum, adipose capsule, renal fascia</choice><choice value="B">adipose capsule, renal hilum, renal ptosis</choice><choice value="C">renal hilum, renal ptosis, renal capsule</choice><choice value="D">renal capsule, adipose capsule, renal fascia</choice></input><part id="kidney_tissue_layers_q6_p1"><skillref idref="identify_kidneys" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa4d4fc408ab648b381f85e1914a935d0">Incorrect. For protection, each kidney is enshrouded in three tissue layers: the renal capsule, the adipose capsule, and the renal fascia. The renal hilum is a concave border where the renal artery enters the kidney.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab3b7962e72bf49c2a240096d723db892">Incorrect. For protection, each kidney is enshrouded in three tissue layers: the renal capsule, the adipose capsule, and the renal fascia. The renal hilum is a concave border where the renal artery enters the kidney. Renal ptosis a condition where the kidney literally drops into the pelvis when standing.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae5430c052e034421967e94659815ef82">Incorrect. For protection, each kidney is enshrouded in three tissue layers: the renal capsule, the adipose capsule, and the renal fascia. The renal hilum is a concave border where the renal artery enters the kidney. Renal ptosis a condition where the kidney literally drops into the pelvis when standing.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="af0ae09379e0c4f9790d3ab241e442435">Correct. For protection, each kidney is enshrouded in three tissue layers. The innermost layer is the renal capsule, the adipose capsule is the middle tissue layer, and the renal fascia is the superficial tissue layer. The renal fascia fastens each kidney to neighboring structures and to the abdominal wall.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="kidney_parenchyma_q7" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac76f503833fb4dbfb3f9d17bf678d4a8">In the case of the kidneys, the parenchyma is its’ functional parts. The parenchyma of the kidneys include the _________, which acts as a filter for the blood by removing waste and the _________, which helps maintain the proper balance of salt and water in the blood.</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="bc270500947348748d4790a7de17c210" labels="false"><choice value="A">renal columns; renal lobe</choice><choice value="B">renal cortex; renal pyramids</choice><choice value="C">renal pyramids; renal lobe</choice><choice value="D">renal pyramids; renal columns</choice></input><part id="kidney_parenchyma_q7_p1"><skillref idref="identify_kidneys" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa276033b89ef41809a5e4bcc2c31b4bb">Incorrect. The functional parts of the kidneys are the renal pyramids and the renal cortex. The renal columns are in between the renal cortex. The renal lobe is located near both renal columns.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab563daee61c24e5a8e308eac2c63e99f">Correct. Two structures dominate the internal anatomy of the kidney. The renal medulla is made up of cone-shaped structures called renal pyramids and its’ primary purpose is to maintain the proper balance of salt and water in the blood. The bases of the pyramids border the renal cortex, which acts as a filter for the blood by removing waste.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aca4590e70fcf4a45881185fd9757321f">Incorrect. The functional parts of the kidneys are the renal pyramids and the renal cortex. . The renal lobe is located near both renal columns.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="af58d95f258f0442a94c50d7f916c2c89">Incorrect. The functional parts of the kidneys are the renal pyramids and the renal cortex. The renal columns are in between the renal cortex.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="renal_artery_q8" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af73294affd544ccfbf3365b0af3635bf">The large renal artery divides into several __________ within the kidney that then branch into a number of __________ within the renal sinus.</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d8bb8f1400be4a65bff3ff24ecab33cf" labels="false"><choice value="A">arcuate arteries; cortical radiate arteries</choice><choice value="B">cortical radiate arteries; interlobular arteries</choice><choice value="C">segmental arteries; interlobar arteries</choice><choice value="D">arcuate arteries; interlobar arteries</choice></input><part id="renal_artery_q8_p1"><skillref idref="identify_kidneys" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aed895244c5684fd9aa20b0eae1d3c9a6">Incorrect. The large renal artery divides into several segmental arteries within the kidney that then branch into a number of interlobar arteries within the renal sinus. The arcuate arteries are where the interlobar arteries curve between the renal medulla and cortex at the bases of the renal pyramids. The arcuate arteries then divide into smaller cortical radiate arteries.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="afdf0a8c487da4c14bdbad792b4072f63">Incorrect. The large renal artery divides into several segmental arteries within the kidney that then branch into a number of interlobar arteries within the renal sinus. The arcuate arteries divide into smaller cortical radiate arteries.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac6f71cefc3fc4a5ebf02345dd9166ece">Correct. The large renal artery divides into several segmental arteries within the kidney that then branch into a number of interlobar arteries within the renal sinus.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac8d90b5c9c0f452a99b604aacf58169e">Incorrect. The large renal artery divides into several segmental arteries within the kidney that then branch into a number of interlobar arteries within the renal sinus. The arcuate arteries are where the interlobar arteries curve between the renal medulla and cortex at the bases of the renal pyramids.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="wall_ureters_q9" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abc1cfc1c091044d89c25647a0429f2f4">What is the function of the inner most wall of the ureters?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a9f29943735b4f54923727a78d145edc" labels="false"><choice value="A">It contains transitional epithelium that is capable of stretching which allows the ureter wall to accommodate changing volumes of urine.</choice><choice value="B">It activates stretch receptors which pushes the urine into the bladder.</choice><choice value="C">It creates peristaltic contractions needed to move urine through the ureters and into the bladder.</choice><choice value="D">It innervates both sympathetic and parasympathetic fibers.</choice></input><part id="wall_ureters_q9_p1"><skillref idref="identify_ureters" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae81a399c83f6448b81f8fbeb913a9cf3">Correct. There are three layers in the ureter wall. The innermost mucosa lining contains transitional epithelium that is capable of stretching. This stretching allows the ureter wall to accommodate changing volumes of urine.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aef0b6a54c1cb4a2b9fe4bcf7c92ca7ef">Incorrect. There are three layers in the ureter wall. The innermost mucosa lining contains transitional epithelium that is capable of stretching. This stretching allows the ureter wall to accommodate changing volumes of urine. The adventitia is the external layer of the ureter wall.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa80ebd485f084e2a98998e86052eeedf">Incorrect. There are three layers in the ureter wall. In concert, all are responsible for the peristaltic contractions needed to move urine through the ureters and into the bladder. The innermost mucosa lining, however, contains transitional epithelium that is capable of stretching. This stretching allows the ureter wall to accommodate changing volumes of urine.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad61d69c172b744359195433a70426730">Incorrect. There are three layers in the ureter wall. The innermost mucosa lining contains transitional epithelium that is capable of stretching. This stretching allows the ureter wall to accommodate changing volumes of urine. The entire ureters are innervated by both sympathetic and parasympathetic fibers.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="trigone_q10" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac72e3531c26b4039aeeb9c4e9e16faa0">There are three openings in the bladder that form a triangular region at the base of the bladder called the trigone. What do the openings accommodate?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ba1f196e76f64e7fb8eb79e5b87f811d" labels="false"><choice value="A">Two for the ureters and one for the urethra.</choice><choice value="B">One for a mucosa with transitional epithelium, one for a submucosa, and one for the detrusor muscle.</choice><choice value="C">Two for the ureters and one for the detrusor muscle.</choice><choice value="D">One for the urethra one for the detrusor muscle one for a submucosa.</choice></input><part id="trigone_q10_p1"><skillref idref="identify_urinary_bladder" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad00b391800fe441a8669a1b4c7f21254">Correct. There are three openings in the bladder: two for the ureters and one for the urethra. These openings frame a triangular region at the base of the bladder called the trigone.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab9bc0ba36c224834ab911b48cfce4d43">Incorrect.There are three openings in the bladder: two for the ureters and one for the urethra. These openings frame a triangular region at the base of the bladder called the trigone.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="adfdfadb6de274f1d926e8180900b7a53">Incorrect.There are three openings in the bladder: two for the ureters and one for the urethra. These openings frame a triangular region at the base of the bladder called the trigone.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="afd38b86c099e469cb787aa04a208f480">Incorrect.There are three openings in the bladder: two for the ureters and one for the urethra. These openings frame a triangular region at the base of the bladder called the trigone.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="urethral_sphincters_q11" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af0d52351a8754bf882b01838849d961e">The nature of one of the urethral sphincters is that it opens during contraction and closes during relaxation. Which urethral sphincter functions in this way?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="fca26069a24f417092700cb97cdcc1c8" labels="false"><choice value="A">the external urethral sphincter</choice><choice value="B">the internal urethral sphincter</choice><choice value="C">both the internal and external urethral sphincters</choice><choice value="D">neither the internal and external urethral sphincters</choice></input><part id="urethral_sphincters_q11_p1"><skillref idref="identify_urethra" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="acd9368b302dd4c40a54addde30eacd9d">Incorrect. When urine is not draining from the bladder, this internal urethral sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when not voiding. The nature of this sphincter is unusual; in contrast with other sphincters in the body, it opens during contraction and closes during relaxation.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab2272659783740279bca94b5e893ae98">Correct. When urine is not draining from the bladder, this internal urethral sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when not voiding. The nature of this sphincter is unusual; in contrast with other sphincters in the body, it opens during contraction and closes during relaxation.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae4556c913e204178ae1578627cb9c2bd">Incorrect. When urine is not draining from the bladder, this internal urethral sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when not voiding. The nature of this sphincter is unusual; in contrast with other sphincters in the body, it opens during contraction and closes during relaxation.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab482cd3a767a4d16bb7afd2bd31658d2">Incorrect. When urine is not draining from the bladder, this internal urethral sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when not voiding. The nature of this sphincter is unusual; in contrast with other sphincters in the body, it opens during contraction and closes during relaxation.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="uti_woman_q12" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad4a60ee980eb4d1e833f7a19d43bb3a5">Why are men less likely to have a urinary tract infection when compared to women?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a1b260edba1244abb11cd2f12d71363e" labels="false"><choice value="A">Women and men have an equal chance of having a UTI.</choice><choice value="B">Men are actually more predisposed to UTI’s</choice><choice value="C">The urethras’ of men are longer than those of women’. So, the urethra&apos;s external opening in men is further from the anus.</choice><choice value="D">Men are known to drink plenty of water and, as such, are more likely to urinate soon after sexual activity which helps flush bacteria out of their urethras.</choice></input><part id="uti_woman_q12_p1"><skillref idref="identify_ureters" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="adba359f0310a4cc99a165087a83528c8">Incorrect. Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are shorter than those of men. Consequently, the urethra&apos;s external opening in women is closer to the anus than it is in men and fecal bacteria can easily travel up the urethra.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab80329ecdf2c484ea0771b0c48ee6025">Incorrect. Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are shorter than those of men. Consequently, the urethra&apos;s external opening in women is closer to the anus than it is in men and fecal bacteria can easily travel up the urethra.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="abef3909573fb45b4a4fa5e7b5f66f2e0">Correct. Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are shorter than those of men. Consequently, the urethra&apos;s external opening in women is closer to the anus than it is in men and fecal bacteria can easily travel up the urethra.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ada98b4b9f6e24c3bb778ceb85aa76f7f">Incorrect. Men do not necessarily known to drink &quot;plenty&quot; of water. It has more to do with the location of the urethra to the anus.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
