<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u12_m5_integration_wrapup"><head><title>Urinary Integration of Systems Review</title></head><body><section id="ecc5191f2f1a404e8ed76ebc3c401682"><title>Let’s Summarize</title><body><p id="cf996658794c4444b45f6636ac1461af">The urinary system is one of several excretory systems in the body:</p><ol id="c2e2257cdd654f18ae5e1016c9a57f5c" style="decimal"><li><p id="afa4cc149327e4ebe9b3e8ea7d4c0cc0a">The <em style="bold">digestive system</em> participates in waste removal in two ways. </p><ul id="ec9a98c08e764bc68bb1c8eda303bc34"><li><p id="abf8b3efe3c8e448ab03e7702f180cfbe">Liver detoxifies some substances. </p></li><li><p id="ab816d60346f3448b917e637b339d5d5e">Large intestine eliminates substances through defecation (undigested food, water, carbon dioxide, water, salts, cholesterol and heat). </p></li></ul></li><li><p id="e04469866fc3430083e94023b62f74a0">The <em style="bold">respiratory system</em> removes waste through exhalation (carbon dioxide, some heat and some water vapor).</p></li><li><p id="e55ada45b2884579a08e0463e5d3e92e">The <em style="bold">sweat glands</em> help dispose of excess water, heat, and carbon dioxide.</p></li></ol><p id="b476a1ab262c408897eef587aa9f51bd">The kidneys have an endocrine function.</p><ul id="d9d4943fe7114807a87d9f41198ed2cd" style="none"><li><p id="c3de3d8f830b442dad2cd14770e1cebc"><em style="bold">Renin</em> is an enzyme secreted by the kidneys that initiates the pathway leading to the production of angiotensin II and the secretion of aldosterone.</p></li><li><p id="d0b2aedf20ee41d8902798622dd5c013"><em style="bold">Erythropoietin</em> is secreted by the kidneys when oxygen levels in the kidney decrease. </p></li></ul><p id="ab86bb05bbc94421bd9752577f5f2044">For the cardiovascular system, the urinary system helps regulate blood volume and blood pressure.</p><p id="ff1eb4a7411945d2baf15101e275e26f">For the digestive system, the kidneys produce calcitrol, the functional form of vitamin D necessary for the absorption of dietary calcium.</p><p id="fa18904ed03446cb8c7ee1452ebfc8a7">For the endocrine system, calcitriol promotes bone reabsorption.</p><p id="ff427e3cccce49289ab0c4990491c5e5">For the integumentary system, the skin and kidneys both paly a role in the production of calcitriol.</p><p id="c9881afb9ae846a3865aabcde754f6ab">For the lymphatic system, the urinary system helps regulate the volume of lymph and interstitial fluid.</p><p id="bdf8a394cd964c2192a05a561f32bc93">For the muscular system, the urinary system helps with calcium and phosphate balance for muscular contractions.</p><p id="f9ba1dcba9404bd88f71130f3ebbc4de">For the nervous system, the urinary system is responsible for some gluconeogenesis to insure the availability of glucose for neuron metabolism.</p><p id="e9a2f13ad8c0416797998ed4a641c7d3">For the reproductive system, the urinary system allows for the passage and direction of sperm in males and eliminates metabolic wastes of the fetus (via the maternal cardiovascular system).</p><p id="a48bbdb0e5884af48142d22d67906612">For the respiratory system, the urinary system helps maintain the acid base balance.</p><p id="a7ef3184b8e34e02b818267762fb6b90">For the skeletal system, the urinary system assists with maintenance of calcium and phosphate balance that is essential for bone deposition.</p><p id="f15185ee68374648b2da9b66fb252f8d">For all body systems, the urinary system helps with homeostasis by influencing the volume, pH, and composition of body fluids.</p></body></section><section id="ee2cd5eeb5664e0f89da630308836c6e"><title> </title><body><p id="d9f2cb6b162c435fb200bebdcf8dd78c"></p></body></section></body></workbook_page>
