<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_muscular_homeostasis_4"><head><title>Muscular Integration of Systems</title><objref idref="_u5_problems" /></head><body><p id="c72b6c9de1c54583a85dbcf8d08e34f7">Think of all of the activities you do that require function of your muscular system. These include walking, chewing, swallowing, breathing, talking, etc. Dysfunctions of this system (such as weakness or hypertonia) can prevent the body from carrying out any of these activities normally. This in turn can affect many other systems. For example, if we can’t bring in appropriate nutrients and oxygen, every other system in the body would be affected, as they are all dependent on fuel sources. </p><p id="f2578f6d1a1e408ca964f39e4542fb7b">Muscles require a large amount of energy and thus require a constant supply of oxygen and nutrients. Blood vessels enter muscle at its surface, after which they are distributed through the entire muscle. Blood vessels are found in the connective tissue that surrounds muscles, allowing oxygen and nutrients to be supplied to muscle and metabolic waste to be removed. The epimysium houses the arteries and veins that allow blood to enter and exit muscle. The blood vessels then branch into the epimysium to serve each fascicle and then further branch in the endomysium to form a capillary network that contacts each muscle fiber. The flexible, extensively branched capillary networks are able to withstand muscle contractions without being damaged.</p><p id="ecf1032d08114084ac1a366601672357"></p><p id="c253019a3f2b491d8e69f460df5be27a">Skeletal muscles are under neural control, which means that nerves must be present for the muscle to function. The epimysium contains nerve fibers that branch through the perimysium and epimysium to connect neurons to individual muscle fibers.</p><wb:inline idref="_u5_problems_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
