<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_muscular_homeostasis_2"><head><title>Muscle Homeostasis and Growth</title></head><body><p id="a6743f07665b4c3ab535164addc437c4">Physical training alters the appearance of skeletal muscles and can produce changes in muscle performance. Conversely, a lack of use can result in decreased performance and muscle appearance. As you learned earlier, mature muscle cells grow from hypertrophy, not cell division. The loss of structural proteins and muscle mass occurs during atrophy. Cellular components of muscles can also undergo changes in response to changes in muscle use.</p><example id="fc8b3ea767ab4f3c8bb396e7d2a55ab4"><title>Sarcopenia</title><p id="edf30590acb644829bc978553d1e3720">Although atrophy due to disuse can often be reversed with exercise, muscle atrophy that comes with age is irreversible. This is why even highly trained athletes succumb to declining performance with age, although extensive training may slow the decline. This is especially noticeable in sports that require an explosion of strength and power over a very short period of time. Examples of these kinds of sports include sprinting, competitive weight lifting, gymnastics and diving. The effects of age are less noticeable in endurance sports such as marathon running or long-distance cycling. Age-related muscle atrophy is called sarcopenia. As muscles age, muscle fibers die, and they are replaced by connective tissue and adipose tissue. Because those tissues cannot contract as muscle can, muscles lose the ability to produce powerful contractions. The decline in muscle mass causes a loss of strength, including strength required for posture and mobility. This may be caused by a reduction in the proportion of FG fibers that hydrolyse ATP quickly to produce short, powerful contractions. Muscles in older people sometimes possess greater numbers of SO fibers, which are responsible for longer contractions and do not produce powerful movements. There may also be a reduction in motor units, resulting in fewer fibers being stimulated and less muscle tension being produced.</p></example><example id="f2ac9210de9843efbbb0af12b8ede754"><title>Anabolic Steroids</title><p id="b28a254da693485084dda5afd67dbf34">Some athletes attempt to boost their performance by using various agents that may enhance muscle performance. Anabolic steroids are one of the more widely known agents used to boost muscle mass and increase power output. Anabolic steroids are a form of testosterone, a male sex hormone that stimulates muscle formation, leading to increased muscle mass. They have been used by athletes in many sports, but sprinting is one sport in which the effects of steroids are readily apparent. Because a 100-meter dash can last less than 10 seconds, incredible amounts of power need to be created by the muscles. Increasing the muscle mass increases the numbers of actin and myosin cross-bridges, increasing the power that can be produced by a muscle, which provides a competitive advantage in a sport measured in hundredths of seconds. Similarly, creatine has become a substance used by some athletes to increase power output. Because creatine phosphate provides quick bursts of ATP to muscles in the initial stages of contraction, increasing the amount available to cells is thought to produce more ATP and therefore increase explosive power output. The use of these substances can be controversial in terms of legality in sports and considerations of safety. Current research on the health impacts and current rulings by sports governing bodies should be consulted for the most accurate information. </p></example></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
