<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_muscular_homeostasis_3"><head><title>Muscle and Blood Flow</title><objref idref="_u5_problems" /></head><body><p id="ef8794a98cd5461c8e0f104ff4dfcfb9">Slow fibers are predominantly used in endurance exercises that require little force but involve numerous repetitions. The aerobic metabolism used by slow-twitch fibers allows them to maintain contractions over long periods. Endurance training modifies these slow fibers to make them even more efficient by producing more mitochondria to enable more aerobic metabolism and more ATP production. Endurance exercise can also increase the amount of myoglobin in a cell, as increased aerobic respiration increases the need for oxygen. Myoglobin is found in the sarcoplasm and stores oxygen. Endurance training can also trigger the formation of more extensive capillary networks around the fiber, a process called <term>angiogenesis</term>, to supply oxygen and remove metabolic waste. To allow these capillary networks to supply the deep portions of the muscle, muscle mass does not greatly increase, maintaining a shorter distance for the diffusion of nutrients and gases. All of these cellular changes result in the ability to sustain low levels of muscle contraction for greater periods of time without fatiguing.</p><example id="da0c18e4c65d4ed68d4b4a6fb5e0ff9c"><title>EPO</title><p id="db2785625a5f4785a25dd7a50ebc66e5">Endurance athletes also engage in drug use, but instead of trying to add muscle mass or produce power, they focus on substances that increase muscle endurance and reduce fatigue. This includes trying to boost the availability of oxygen to muscles to increase aerobic respiration by using substances such as erythropoietin, or EPO. EPO is a hormone that triggers the production of red blood cells, which carry oxygen in the blood. This oxygen can then be used by muscles for aerobic respiration. Human growth hormone is another commonly used agent, and although it can facilitate building muscle mass, its main role is to promote the healing of muscle and other tissues after strenuous exercise. Increased growth hormone allows for faster recovery after muscle damage, reducing the rest required after exercise, and allowing for more sustained high-level performance. As with creatine and steroids, these substances are harmful to the body and can negatively impact the homeostasis of other systems.</p></example><p id="c2a0c07c681d42e3b7a61be58d3cd589">As discussed previously, there are a number of proteins that are important in regulating and carrying out the contractile process. Thus there are genetic disorders that lead to altered protein formation and dysfunction of the muscular system. Such dysfunction tends to affect many body systems, of which the respiratory system may be most important. Without the ability to appropriately contract the skeletal muscles of respiration, people cannot live very long. The skeletal muscular system is also very dependent upon a constant supply of ATP. Like many other systems, this requires the intracellular pathways to convert glucose into energy.</p><example id="de597a873c444def882f2bea970df0b2"><title>Beriberi</title><p id="a9e48d1895ca4b2d8f91850c0e228efe">Thiamine (vitamin B1) is a necessary cofactor in the production of ATP from glucose. Deficiencies in thiamine and other vitamins can lead to extreme muscle weakness as well as neurological problems. Thiamine deficiency leads to a disease called beriberi, which was common in people who ate white rice as their major food source. Beriberi can affect skeletal and cardiac muscles as well as the nervous system. Eating a balanced diet and the increase of vitamin-enriched foods have eliminated beriberi from developed countries, but many disorders of vitamin deficiency exist in developing areas.</p></example></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
