<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="ap_muscular_homeostasis_5">
	<head>
		<title>Cardiac and Smooth Muscles</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_cardio_sys"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Although <?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T163905-0500"?>this unit
			has
			primarily<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T163923-0500" content="we have spent much of our time"?>
			focus<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T163944-0500"?>ed<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T163942-0500" content="ing"?>
			on skeletal muscle,
			<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164025-0500"?>don't<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164027-0500" content="let’s not"?>
			forget about cardiac and smooth muscle, both of which play vital roles in the
			cardiovascular system (and smooth muscle in other systems as well). Your heart needs to
			continuously contract in order to keep blood flowing to your organs, and in turn, supply
			them with needed oxygen and nutrients. But smooth muscle also plays a vital role. It is
			found in the walls of all blood vessels except for capillaries, and its function is to
			dilate or constrict, depending on the needs of the body and the downstream tissues. For
			example, if the skeletal muscles in your legs increase their metabolic rate because you
			start running, smooth muscle cells in the arteries feeding these muscles will relax.
			This dilates these arteries, allowing for a greater blood flow to the muscles of the
			legs. In fact, arteries to other regions (such as the
			<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164641-0500"?>gastrointestinal<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164639-0500" content="GI"?>
			tract) may partially constrict in an effort to shunt more blood toward the legs. It is
			these smooth muscles that play a vital role in sending higher amounts of blood to where
			it is needed most. Skeletal muscles also play a role within the cardiovascular system.
			The heart acts as the pump to move blood out to the body cells, but the skeletal muscles
			assist with the movement of blood back to the heart. Because of valves in the veins that
			prevent back<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164728-0500" content="-"?><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164814-0500"?>
			<?oxy_insert_end?>flow, the contraction of skeletal muscles around the major veins
			help<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120109T164752-0500"?>s<?oxy_insert_end?>
			move the blood from one compartment to the next, slowly returning blood back to the
			heart.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_cardio_sys_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_cardio_sys_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
