<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<!--Created by OLI Author v2.0-->
<assessment id="u3_m3_normal8_tutor2">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
        <question id="q1">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>
                <p>What value of x do we need to use with the <em style="bold">normal table</em> in
                    order to solve this problem? </p>
            </body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A">P(X &lt;x) = 0.02</choice>
                <choice value="B">P(X &lt;x) = 0.98</choice>
                <choice value="C">Unable to determine</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Remember, we are looking for the probability that will
                        allow us to determine the score for the top 2% of the SAT-M scores. This
                        value will give us the probability to get a score that reflects where 98% of
                        the scores fall above, rather than below. Please try again.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. We are looking for the value x, so that P(X &gt; x) = 0.02.
                        The same value also satisfies P(X &lt; x) = 0.98. This way of posing the
                        problem works best for us, since our table is set up to work with "less
                        than" rather than "greater than."</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It is possible to determine, from the problem, the value
                        needed to use with the normal table, in order to solve this problem. Recall
                        that our normal table only works with "less than" probabilities, so we need
                        to rephrase our problem accordingly. Remember, looking for the SAT-M score
                        that 2% of students scored higher than is the same as looking for the SAT-M
                        score that 98% of the students scored lower than. Please try
                        again.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>Recall that our normal table only works with "less than" probabilities, so we
                    need to rephrase our problem accordingly.</hint>
                <hint>Remember, looking for the SAT-M score that 2% of students scored higher than
                    is the same as looking for the SAT-M score that 98% of the students scored lower
                    than.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
    <page>
        <question id="q2">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>What z-score is associated with a value x that satisfies P(X &lt;
                x) = 0.98?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">−2.05</choice>
                <choice value="B">0.8365</choice>
                <choice value="C">−1.29</choice>
                <choice value="D">+2.05</choice>
                <choice value="E">0.9798</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. −2.05 is the z-score associated with a
                        probability of 0.02 and therefore is the z-score of the value that marks the
                        bottom 2%. You are looking for the z-score associated with a probability of
                        0.98 (which marks the top 2%)</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. 0.8365 is the table probability associated
                        with a a z-score of 0.98. You need to work with the table in the reverse
                        order in this case. You are looking for the z-score that is associated with
                        a table probability of 0.98.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems you found the z-score
                        associated with the probability closest to 0.098. You are looking for a
                        probability closest to 0.98</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. The closest probability of 0.98 is 0.9798. Looking at the
                        margins, we see that this probability corresponds to a z-score of 2.05. This
                        means that in order to be in the top 2% of SAT-M scores (and thus be
                        considered for the engineering school) a student must score more than 2.05
                        standard deviations above the mean.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. 0.9798 is the closest probability to
                        0.98 in the body of the table, however you are asked to find the z-score
                        associated with this probability. The z-score is obtained by looking at the
                        margins of the table that correspond to this probability value. Please try
                        again</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>You are looking for the z-score (in the margins of the table) that is
                    associated with a probability of 0.98 (or closest to it) in the body of the
                    table. </hint>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
    <page>
        <question id="q3">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>What score (after rounding) must a student have in order to be in considered for
                the engineering school?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single">
                <choice value="A">735</choice>
                <choice value="B">280</choice>
                <choice value="C">616</choice>
                <choice value="D">1150</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. In order to be in the top 2% of SAT-M scores (and thus be
                        considered for the engineering school) a student must score more than 2.05
                        standard deviations above the mean. 2.05 standard deviations above the mean
                        is a score of 507 + 2.05(111) = 734.55. Since SAT-M scores are whole
                        numbers, we conclude that in order to be considered for the engineering
                        school a student must have an SAT-M score of at least 735.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It looks like you calculated the value with the incorrect z
                        score (−2.05 instead of +2.05). Please try again.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It looks like you used the probability (0.9798), instead of
                        the z score in the formula. Remember, the standard deviation needs to be
                        multiplied by the z-score, before it is added to the mean. Please try
                        again.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. You are looking for the score that is 2.05
                        standard deviations above the mean. It seems like used 111 as the mean and
                        507 as the mean, but mistake.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>You are looking for the SAT-M score that has the z-score you found in the
                    previous question.</hint>
                <hint>In question 2, you found that the SAT-M score that marks the top 2% is 2.05
                    standard deviations above the mean. Recall that in this case the mean is 507 and
                    standard deviation is 111.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
