<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u12_m4_homeostasis_wrapup"><head><title>Urinary Homeostasis Review</title></head><body><section id="fb43f982404542cea0815005eab0683b"><title>Let’s summarize</title><body><section id="b7b8a70c83cd471484a5f94791dfd5fa"><title>Regulation of glomerular filtration</title><body><p id="b15d5b6664644a94a821b72c767e6cb0">Glomerular filtration (GFR) remains relatively constant due to renal autoregulation. Renal autoregulation is comprised of:</p><ul id="a0c3ff2be7604b51a68061f54665a9c3"><li><p id="ac0a03ced39ef40c6b4e930d610ba044e">The myogenic mechanism results from the vascular smooth muscle contracting when stretched.</p></li><li><p id="ad09484243aab442d8ac5bd31ceed437a">The tubuloglomerular feedback mechanism that results in the macular densa cells responding to the filtrate’s high sodium concentration by releasing paracrine agent, that causes vasodialation diameter of the afferent arterioles and reduces blood flow.</p></li></ul><p id="de7e147a39dd4099a982c16e8c042088">GFR is regulated by:</p><ul id="a44fc20c03404beba17c31d5468cbc27" style="none"><li><p id="bbbb9cda22044501bffb81ddfcf66a37"><em style="bold">Sympathetic nerve fibers</em>: During extreme stress or blood loss, the sympathetic system will meet the needs of the whole body. The sympathetic nervous can override renal autoregulation and temporarily reduce kidney activity. </p></li><li><p id="e60209d7114f4fcf9ee6b3b4ec8322bc"><em style="bold">Hormones</em>: The enzyme renin produces angiotensin II. When blood pressure is low, Angiotensin II helps maintain pressure in the glomerular capillary and consequently, GFR. </p></li><li><p id="c8fd2458ad6d40029e56468b2b08867d"><em style="bold">Atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP)</em> increases GFR by relaxing the mesangial cells of the glomerulus, making more surface area available for filtration. This increases GFR. </p></li></ul><p id="d0ffb223a5984609a1b221b67a24330e">Hormonal Regulation of Reabsorption and Secretion.</p><p id="d6ce96b6ce62442eb15acc562106686f">Five hormones control the absorption of water, sodium ions, chloride ions, and calcium ions:</p><ul id="c803e05f27d545729827d0f028e84187" style="none"><li><p id="b02516f8272349a0a917a5ea0ad41386"><em style="bold">Angiotensin II</em>: Angiotensin II stimulates the adrenal cortex to secrete aldosterone. </p></li><li><p id="b9f7f23faaf44905b2d5cea89da2d355"><em style="bold">Aldosterone</em>: Aldosterone stimulates an increase in secretion of potassium and reabsorption of sodium ions and results in increased water reabsorption, leading to increased blood volume. </p></li><li><p id="de8b3d2f83c74d30b5f103aa23d2287c"><em style="bold">Antidiuretic hormone (ADH)</em>: ADH decrease urine production by increasing the water permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct. This, increases facultative water reabsorption. </p></li><li><p id="aa422f53c85b4b27a30df87c82b2b1a5"><em style="bold">Atrial natriuretic peptide</em>: This is released from the heart in response to large increases in blood volume. The action of ANP inhibit reabsorption of water and sodium ions in the proximal convoluted tubule and collecting duct. </p></li><li><p id="e024b113d6b241d2922794a494d705b2"><em style="bold">Parathyroid hormone (PTH)</em>: This is released by the parathyroid glands in response to a reduced concentration of calcium ions in the blood. It results in decrease in phosphate reabsorption in the proximal convoluted tubule and an increase in calcium reabsorption in the distal convoluted tubule. </p></li></ul><section id="c0aca752c392409787af1dc516886f9c"><title>Aging and urinary system homeostasis</title><body><p id="a9ea01fd34044ed6af9c8e2a7f439052">When taking all body systems into account, none undergoes as many age-related changes as the urinary system: </p><ul id="fa518957a17a41808ca25d5d8e86d0d7"><li><p id="aee654888f7ac41399049ca4ca9b1c65e">decreased bladder capacity and bladder emptying</p></li><li><p id="aa1ce3373518a45d08cd6912fa431d05c">loss of sphincter muscle tone</p></li><li><p id="ad1ba1fd9d79a460484b0dd136fd21542">reduced ability to delay voiding.\</p></li></ul></body></section><p id="e2afa599df534f63b0c5a225e5ffc2a8">Age-related conditions such as stroke and Alzheimer&apos;s disease can affect the micturition center in the brain. </p></body></section></body></section></body></workbook_page>
