<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m4_homeostasis_01">
	<head>
		<title>Homeostasis</title>

		<!--  <objref idref="explain_analyze_homeostatic_mechanisms_urinary"/>-->
		<objref idref="identify_describe_factors_regulating_urine"/>
	</head>
	<body>




		<!--  	<p>Hi Mike, here are the sub objectives to write to in this section.</p>
		<p>Provide specific examples to demonstrate how the urinary system responds to maintain
			homeostasis in the body.</p>
			<p>Explain how the urinary system relates to other body systems to maintain homeostasis.</p>-->

		<section>
			<title>Regulation of Glomerular Filtration</title>
			<body>
				<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Provide specific examples to demonstrate how the urinary
					system responds to maintain homeostasis in the body, particularly related to the
					diseases presented in the introduction.</p>-->

				<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe mechanisms of glomerular filtration and other
					mechanisms of nephron regulation; contrast neural versus endocrine
					regulation</p>-->
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the myogenic and tubuloglomerular feedback
					mechanisms and explain how they affect urine volume and composition</p>-->
				<p>In a healthy body, GFR remains relatively constant even in the face of
					substantial changes in arterial blood pressure. By adjusting resistance to the
					flow of blood, <term>renal autoregulation </term>prevents significant
					fluctuations in GFR when systemic arterial blood pressure rises or falls. Two
					mechanisms are involved in this intrinsic control. The <term>myogenic mechanism
					</term>results from the inherent tendency of vascular smooth muscle to contract
					when stretched. This means that the diameter of afferent arterioles changes in
					response to fluctuations in blood pressure. Increasing blood pressure in the
					afferent arteriole stretches the smooth muscle in the wall of the arteriole. As
					a result, the smooth muscle will contract and the arteriole will vasoconstrict.
					This reduces the diameter of afferent arterioles, and blood flow. Decreasing
					blood pressure in the afferent arteriole removes the stretch of the smooth
					muscle in the wall of the arteriole. As a result, the smooth muscle will relax
					and the arteriole will vasodilate. This increases the diameter of afferent
					arterioles and blood flow. In both cases, the result is a relatively stable
					GFR.</p>

				<p>The second element of renal autoregulation is the <term>tubuloglomerular feedback
						mechanism</term> The macular densa cells of the distal convoluted tubule are
					part of the juxtaglomerular apparatus and are responsible for the
					tubuloglomerular feedback mechanism. The macula densa cells respond to the
					sodium concentration in the filtrate that flows from the ascending limb of
					nephron loop into the distal convoluted tubule. The sodium concentration in the
					filtrate is directly related to the rateglomerular filtration rate (GFR). When
					GFR is high, there is not enough time for reabsorption, and the filtrate will
					have a high sodium concentration. The macular densa cells respond to this high
					sodium concentration by releasing the vasoconstrictor adenosine, which narrows
					the diameter of the afferent arterioles. Reduced blood flow lowers the net
					filtration pressure and the GFR, which enhances sodium chloride reabsorption.
					Conversely, when GFR is low the filtrate will have a low sodium concentration.
					The release of the paracrine agent by macula densa cells is inhibited. As a
					result, the afferent arterioles dilate and increase tje blood flow into the
					glomerulus. The result is to increase net filtration pressure in the glomerulus
					and increase GFR. This has the opposite effect of macula densa cell activation:
					it increases the amount of filtered sodium, and it reduces sodium reabsorption. </p>
				<p>These two autoregulatory mechanisms help keep the flow of blood through the
					kidneys relatively constant when mean systemic arterial blood pressure is within
					a range of approximately 80 mm Hg to 180 mm Hg. However, autoregulation cannot
					adjust for changes in systemic blood pressure that are outside of this
					range.</p>

				<section>
					<title>Neural Regulation</title>
					<body>
						<p>The sympathetic nerve fibers that innervate renal blood vessels provide
							an extrinsic regulatory mechanism for GFR. During extreme stress or
							blood loss, the sympathetic nervous system must meet the needs of the
							body as a whole, for example, by temporarily reducing kidney activity
							and redirecting blood to other vital organs. In such situations, neural
							controls override renal autoregulation. The sympathetic nerve fibers
							release the neurotransmitter norepinephrine. Norepinephrine activates
								<term>alpha-adrenergic receptors </term>on vascular smooth muscle
							and causes afferent arterioles to constrict. The resulting reduced blood
							flow into glomerular capillaries lowers net filtration pressure and GFR.
							This decreased renal blood flow helps maintain blood volume by reducing
							urine output and increasing perfusion to other body tissues.</p>
					</body>
				</section>

				<section>
					<title>Hormonal Regulation</title>
					<body>
						<p>Hormones also regulate GFR. One such mechanism is activated when
							jutaglomerular (JG) (or granular) cells are stimulated to secrete the
							enzyme renin. This enzyme begins a process that results in the
							production of angiotensin II, a powerful systemic vasoconstrictor that
							also constricts the afferent and efferent arterioles. Angiotensin II
							also stimulated the contraction of mesangial cells resulting in a
							decrease in the surface area of the glomerulus. Because renin is
							released when blood pressure is low, the resulting constriction of the
							efferent arteriole helps maintain net filtration pressure in the
							glomerular capillary and consequently, GFR. Another hormone, atrial
							natriuretic peptide (ANP) increases GFR. ANP is released when the atria
							of the heart is stretched, for example, in heart failure when blood
							volume increases due to sodium and water retention. ANP relaxes the
							mesangial cells of the glomerulus, making more surface area available
							for filtration. This increases GFR.</p>
					</body>
				</section>



				<p><em style="bold">Glomerular Filtration Regulation</em></p>
				<table rowstyle="alternating">
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Regulation</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Primary Stimulus</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Mechanism/Activity Site</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Effect</em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Renal autoregulation</td>
						<td>Systemic rising or falling of arterial blood pressure </td>
						<td> Adjusts resistance to the flow of blood, when systemic arterial blood
							pressure rises or falls </td>
						<td> Prevents significant fluctuations in GFR </td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Myogenic mechanism</td>
						<td>Smooth muscle fibers in walls of afferent arteriole are stretched when
							blood pressure increases</td>
						<td>Contraction of smooth muscle fibers narrows lumen of afferent
							arterioles</td>
						<td>GFR decrease</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Tubuloglomerular feedback</td>
						<td>Increased delivery of sodium ions and chloride ions to the macula densa
							when blood pressure increases</td>
						<td>Constriction of afferent arterioles due to the release of adenosine by
							macula densa cells</td>
						<td>GFR decrease</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Vasoconstrictor adenosine</td>
						<td>Decreased delivery of sodium ions and to the macula densa when blood
							pressure drops</td>
						<td>Dilation of afferent arterioles due to inhibition of adenosine release
							by macula densa cells</td>
						<td>GFR increase</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Neural regulation</td>
						<td>Release of norepinephrine due to increased activity of renal sympathetic
							nerves</td>
						<td>Constriction of afferent arterioles due to activation of
							alpha-adrenergic receptors and renin release</td>
						<td>GFR decrease</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Hormone regulation</td>
						<td> Stimuli cause justaglomerular cells to secrete renin. </td>
						<td>Once justaglomerular cells secrete renin, angiotensin II is
							produced.</td>
						<td>Maintains GFR</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Angiotensin II</td>
						<td>Production of angiotensin II due to decreased blood volume or blood
							pressure</td>
						<td>Constriction of afferent arteriole and contraction of mesangial cells </td>
						<td>GFR decrease</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>ANP</td>
						<td>Secretion of ANP due to stretching of atria of heart</td>
						<td>Capillary surface area available for filtration increased due to
							relaxation of mesangial cells in glomerulus</td>
						<td>GFR increase</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Hormonal Regulation of Reabsorption and Secretion</title>
			<body>

				<!-- <p>Five hormones control the absorption of water, sodium ions, chloride ions, and
					calcium ions: aldosterone, angiotensin II, antidiuretic hormone, atrial
					natriuretic peptide, and parathyroid hormone. The renin-angiotensin-aldosterone
					system kicks in when blood volume and blood pressure decrease. This blood
					pressure decline reduces the amount of stretch in afferent arteriole walls and
					stimulates juxtaglomerular cells to release renin into the blood. Renin release
					is also stimulated directly by sympathetic nerve fiber activity. Renin sets in
					motion a cascade of events that leads to the creation of the hormone angiotensin
					II. This hormone plays three primary roles. First. it constricts afferent
					arterioles, which reduces GFR. Second, it stimulates an exchange mechanism. This
					leads to an increase in the reabsorption of water, sodium ions, and chloride
					ions by stimulating an exchange mechanism. Finally, the hormone prompts the
					adrenal cortex to secrete the hormone aldosterone. The result is an increase in
					the reabsorption of sodium ions and chloride ions. Aldosterone also increases
					the secretion of potassium ions by principal cells in the collecting duct.
					Because of the increased reabsorption of sodium ions and chloride ions, less
					water is excreted, which effectively increases blood volume.</p> -->

				<p>Five hormones control the absorption of water, and sodium, chloride, and calcium
					ions: angiotensin II, aldosterone, antidiuretic hormone, atrial natriuretic
					peptide, and parathyroid hormone. </p>
				<p>Let’s look at each: </p>


				<section>
					<title>Angiotensin II </title>
					<body>
						<p>The renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system is stimulated when blood volume
							and blood pressure decrease. A decrease in blood pressure reduces the
							amount of stretch in afferent arteriole walls and stimulates
							juxtaglomerular cells to release renin into the blood. Renin release is
							also stimulated directly by sympathetic nerve fiber activity. Renin sets
							in motion a cascade of events that leads to the production of the
							hormone angiotensin II.</p>
						<p>Angiotensin II plays three primary roles. First, it constricts afferent
							arterioles, resulting in a reduction in GFR. Second, it stimulates an
							exchange mechanism. This leads to an increase in the reabsorption of
							water, sodium ions, and chloride ions. Finally, the hormone prompts the
							adrenal cortex to secrete the hormone aldosterone. </p>
					</body>
				</section>

				<section>
					<title>Aldosterone</title>
					<body>
						<p>The release of aldosterone from the adrenal cortex is stimulated by the
							presence of angiotensin II as well as an increased concentration of
							potassium ions. Aldosterone stimulates the insertion of sodium channels
							in the apical membrane and sodium/potassium pumps in the basolateral
							membranes of the principal cells of the distal convoluted tubules and
							the collecting ducts. The result is an increase in the reabsorption of
							sodium ions. Aldosterone also increases the secretion of potassium ions
							by principal cells in the collecting duct. Because of the increased
							reabsorption of sodium ions, more water is reabsorbed and blood volume
							is effectively increased.</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Antidiuretic hormone (ADH)</title>
					<body>
						<p>Antidiuretic hormone (ADH)acts to decrease urine production by increasing
							the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule
							and the collecting duct, thus increasing facultative water reabsorption.
							Without ADH, the apical membranes of principal cells are relatively
							water-impermeable. ADH also stimulates the insertion of aquaporins in
							the apical membrane, allowing water molecules to move more quickly from
							tubular fluid into the cells and then through the always fairly
							permeable basolateral membrane and into the blood. When you are
							dehydrated, ADH is released, and the kidneys conserve
							water by producing a small volume of very concentrated urine. ADH
							secretion is controlled bv a <term>negative feedback system</term>. When
							the water concentration of plasma and interstitial fluid decreases
							(i.e., when osmolarity increases), more ADH is secreted into the blood,
							making principal cells more water-permeable. This restores plasma
							osmolarity towards normal.</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Atrial natriuretic peptide</title>
					<body>
						<p>Atrial natriuretic peptide is released from the heart in response to
							large increases in blood volume. This hormone inhibits the reabsorption
							of water and sodium ions in the proximal convoluted tubule and
							collecting duct. It also inhibits aldosterone and ADH secretion. The
							resulting increased sodium ion excretion in urine and the increased
							urine output lower blood volume and pressure.</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Parathyroid hormone (PTH)</title>
					<body>
						<p>Parathyroid hormone (PTH) affects calcium and phosphate ion reabsorption.
							It is released by the parathyroid glands in response to a reduced
							concentration of calcium ions in the blood. PTH stimulates increased
							reabsorption of calcium ions in the early distal convoluted tubule. PTH
							also inhibits the reabsorption of phosphate ions in the proximal
							convoluted tubule, prompting the excretion of phosphate ions in the
							urine.</p>
					</body>
				</section>

				<wb:inline idref="urinary_hormone_stimulus" purpose="learnbydoing"
					src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
					<param name="interfaceDescription"
						>../webcontent/urinary_hormone_stimulus_layout.xml</param>
				</wb:inline>

				<p><em style="bold">Hormones Involved in the Regulation of Reabsorption and
						Secretion</em></p>
				<table rowstyle="alternating">
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Hormone</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Stimulus for Release</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Result</em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Aldosterone</td>
						<td>Increased levels of angiotensin II and plasma potassium ion (K+)</td>
						<td>Increased secretion of K+ and reabsorption of sodium ions (Na+) and
							chloride ions; increased water reabsorption, leading to increased blood
							volume</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Angiotensin II</td>
						<td>Reduced blood volume or reduced blood pressure</td>
						<td>Increased reabsorption of solutes (including Na+) and water, leading to
							increased blood volume</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Antidiuretic hormone</td>
						<td>Increased osmolarity of extracellular fluid or decreased blood
							volume</td>
						<td>Increased facultative reabsorption of water, leading to reduced
							osmolarity of body fluids</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Atrial natriuretic peptide</td>
						<td>Stretching of atria of heart</td>
						<td>Increased excretion of Na+ in urine; increased urine output reduces
							blood volume</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Parathyroid hormone</td>
						<td>Decreased plasma calcium ion (Ca2+) level</td>
						<td>Increased Ca2+ reabsorption, leading to decreased reabsorption of
							phosphate ions in the proximal convoluted tubule and increased excretion
							of phosphate ions in urine</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</body>
		</section>



	</body>
</workbook_page>
