<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m4_homeostasis_02">
	<head>
		<title>Homeostasis Functions</title>

		<objref idref="explain_analyze_homeostatic_mechanisms_urinary"/>
		<!-- <objref idref="identify_describe_factors_regulating_urine"/> -->
	</head>
	<body>


		<section>
			<title>Homeostasis Functions of the Kidneys</title>
			<body>

				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Explain how the urinary system relates to other body systems to
			maintain homeostasis</p>-->
				<p>The kidneys do most of the work of the urinary system. In addition to being the
					major excretory organs, the kidneys are important regulators of the volume and
					chemical composition of blood, and they maintain the correct balance between
					water and salts, and between acids and bases, in the body. They also regulate
					blood glucose levels, produce hormones, and metabolize vitamin D to its active
					form, calcitriol.</p>
				<table rowstyle="alternating">
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Function</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Description</em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Regulate ionic composition of blood</td>
						<td>Homeostatic maintenance of plasma levels of ions, including sodium,
							potassium, phosphate, calcium, and chloride ions</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Regulate blood pH</td>
						<td>Buffer hydrogen ion levels in the blood by excreting some in urine and
							by conserving bicarbonate ions, which buffer hydrogen ions in the
							blood</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Regulate blood volume</td>
						<td>Either conserve water or eliminate it in urine</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Regulate blood pressure</td>
						<td>Secrete renin, which activates the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system
							and increases blood pressure</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Maintain blood osmolarity</td>
						<td>Regulate water loss and solute loss in urine</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Produce hormones</td>
						<td>Help control calcium homeostasis with calcitriol and stimulates the
							formation of red blood cells with erythropoietin</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Regulate blood glucose</td>
						<td>Perform gluconeogenesis, releasing glucose into blood to maintain normal
							levels</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Excrete waste/foreign substance</td>
						<td>Form urine, which eliminates unneeded substances, wastes from metabolic
							reactions (e.g., ammonia, bilirubin, uric acid), and foreign substances
							(e.g., drugs, environmental toxins)</td>
					</tr>
				</table>

			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="urinary_blood_prop_urinary_sys" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<section>
			<title>Aging and Urinary System Homeostasis</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Predict factors or situations affecting the urinary system
			homeostasis related to aging</p>-->
				<p>Aging affects all body systems, but perhaps none undergoes as many age-related
					changes as the urinary system. Among the physical changes in urinary tract
					function that occur with aging are decreases in bladder capacity and bladder
					emptying, loss of sphincter muscle tone, and a reduced ability to delay voiding.
					In addition, age-related conditions such as stroke and Alzheimer's disease can
					affect the micturition center in the brain. These are some of the reasons why
					urinary incontinence is so common in the elderly, affecting up to a third of
					older men and more than half of older women. Age-related changes in the kidneys
					include a decrease in organ size, decrease in renal blood flow, and impaired
					sodium conservation. The number of functional nephrons and the glomerular
					filtration rate (GFR) also decline with age. In fact, only about two percent of
					adults over age 70 have normal renal function. In about two thirds of the
					elderly, the GFR rate is less than 60 milliliters (2 ounces) per minute compared
					with the normal rate of 120 milliliters (4 ounces) per minute. This has
					important implications for the many drugs used to treat a variety of age-related
					conditions. Medication dosages must often be adjusted to compensate for the
					reduced renal clearance.</p>


			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="urinary_reduced_kidney_function" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

		<section>
			<title>Common Dysfunction of the Urinary System</title>
			<body>
				<!--  <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Identify major diseases associated with the urinary system and their causes.</p>-->

				<p>As noted earlier in the unit, the entire process of urination is known as
					micturition. A healthy, well functioning urinary system begins with urine being
					produced by the nephrons in the kidneys, continues via the process of
					peristalsis bringing the urine into the bladder, and ends with urine exiting
					through the urethra. However, the urinary system sometimes is compromised when
					it is permeated by bacteria. Thus far, we have discussed two dysfunctions: renal
					ptosis, where the fat deposit that holds the kidneys in place fails resulting in
					one or both kidneys dropping into the pelvis, and urinary tract infections, the
					most common type of urinary bacterial infections. Later on in the unit, you be
					introduced to kidney stones, deposits that occur within the urinary tract.
					Several other urinary disorders are also discussed. </p>

				<section>
					<title>Pyelonephritis</title>
					<body>
						<p>A specific type of kidney infection, pyelonephritis, starts in either the
							bladder or urethra and ultimately migrate to the kidneys. If the
							infection does not move to the bladder, it is then referred to as
							cystitis. Common causes of Pyelonephritis and cystitis are either
							Escherichia coli or sexual activity and may include flu like symptoms
							such as fever, vomiting, chills, nausea, and/or frequent, painful,
							urination. Pyelonephritis and cystitis are usually treated with
							antibiotics.</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Kidney Stones</title>
					<body>
						<p>Kidney stones or renal caculi are relatively large calcium deposits that
							occur within the urinary tract. Much like pyelonephritis, symptoms can
							be flu like and include vomiting, nausea, fever, chills. However, the
							flu like symptoms are usually in combination with flank pain, or pain
							located one side of the body at the upper abdomen and lower back. Common
							causes of kidney stones include obesity, dehydration, and a calcium rich
							diet. Treatment can range from medicinal to lithotripsy, a surgery that
							employs shock waves to break up the stones to a size that can be passed
							through the urinary tract, to uteroscopy, a surgery that inserts a scope
							through the urethra, urinary bladder, and ureter to beak and remove the
							stone.</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Kidney Failure</title>
					<body>
						<p>Kidney failure, also called renal insufficiency, is a medical condition
							wherein the kidneys cannot filter enough toxins and urea from the blood
							to maintain proper homeostasis. Kidney failure can
							occur as either acute and chronic problems. Many of the symptoms of
							kidney failure as associated with the build up of toxic elements in the
							blood including:</p>
						<ol style="lower-alpha">
							<li>increased urea</li>
							<li>increased phosphates</li>
							<li>increased potassium</li>
							<li>general fluid retention</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Those in the beginning stages of renal insufficiency might experience
							swelling from the body retaining fluids. In addition, initial symptoms
							might include bloody stools, a metallic taste in the mouth, and easy
							bruising. Treatment for renal insufficiency varies depending on the
							stage and can include: dietary changes (diet high in carbohydrates
							and low in protein, salt, and potassium), antibiotics, diuretics
							to help remove fluid, and/or renal replacement therapy. Renal
							replacement therapy involves dialysis treatment to aid in the removal of
							the toxic elements from the blood.</p>

					</body>
				</section>

			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
