<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="altitude_sickness">
 <head>
  <title>Disorders of the Respiratory System: Altitude Sickness</title>
 </head>

 <body>
  <p>Altitude sickness, also called acute mountain sickness, can strike people
   climbing to elevations above 8,000 feet (although it typically occurs only at
   altitudes much higher than this). At elevations high above sea level, there is
   the same percentage of oxygen (21%), but much less atmospheric pressure, which
   lowers the partial pressure of the oxygen being inhaled so less oxygen enters
   the body. If the body doesn’t adapt well well, a person can experience altitude
   sickness ranging from mild to severe forms. Mild to moderate altitude sickness
   can cause nausea, vomiting, tachycardia, shortness of breath with exercise, or
   difficulty sleeping. Mild to moderate cases usually resolve themselves when the
   person descends to a lower altitude. However, severe cases are another matter.
   They can result in cyanosis, pulmonary congestion confusion and stupor, a cough
   with or without blood, a gray or very pale complexion, the inability to walk a
   straight line, if at all, and shortness of breath when at rest. These cases
   require immediate evacuation to lower altitudes. Without treatment, severe
   altitude sickness may result in death due to pulmonary complications or brain
   swelling. The good news is that altitude sickness can be prevented. Individuals
   who climb to extremely high altitudes, like Mount Everest, should do so slowly
   to allow their bodies to become accustomed to the atmospheric differences.</p>
 </body>



</workbook_page>
