<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="rds_newborn_infants">
 <head>
  <title>Disorders of the Respiratory System: Respiratory Distress Syndrome of the Newborn
   Infants.</title>
 </head>

 <body>
  <p> Respiratory distress syndrome of newborn infants (RDS) most commonly affects premature infants
   whose lungs have not developed fully, children born by caesarean section and diabetic mothers .
   The lungs of these infants cannot make sufficient quantities of surfactant, making it very
   difficult for the affected infants’s lungs to expand properly to breathe. Most cases of RDS
   occur in infants born before 28 weeks gestation as the cells of the lungs responsible for
   surfactant production, called type II alveolar cells, are generally not very active until later
   in pregnancy.</p>
  <p>Neonates with RDS struggle to breathe, leading to poorly oxygenated blood and cyanosis
   (appearance of blue skin). Additional symptoms generally include apnea (periods of breathing
   cessation) or rapid, shallow breathing. Laboratory procedures can be done to determine the level
   of fetal lung maturity.</p>
  <p>Treatment for RDS often involves administration of a higher fraction of inhaled oxygen (above
   the normal 21%), or the use of a ventilator. Artificial surfactant can be given, but is still
   considered experimental. If a premature birth is likely, the expectant mother may be given a
   steroid such as cortisol to promote maturation of the fetal lungs before birth. Prognosis is
   dependent upon the severity of the disorder. Children often worsen within the first few days
   after birth, but then usually recover with appropriate treatment.</p>
 </body>



</workbook_page>
