<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="bp_lymph">


  <head>
    <title>The Big Picture of the Lymphatic System and Immunity</title>
    <objref idref="lymph_bp_LO"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <p>Let’s start our discussion by examining the Big Ideas of Anatomy and Physiology and exploring
      some ways these Big Ideas may be seen in the functioning of the Lymphatic System and Immunity.
      These ideas have been identified as common throughout the body systems, and will provide
      secure footing as we begin to build our understanding of these key functions.</p>
    <ol>
      <li><p>Living organisms are causal mechanisms whose functions are to be understood by
          applications of the laws of <term>physics</term> and <term>chemistry</term>.</p>
        <p>When molecules and atoms leave tissues and enter the lymph vessels as lymph fluid the
          driving forces behind those movements are chemical processes, namely osmosis and
          diffusion. Movement of the lymph fluid relies on capillary action as wells as differential
          changes in the pressure on the fluid inside the lymph vessels. The immune function of the
          lymphatic system uses the partial charges and shapes of larger biomolecules like proteins
          to determine the fit of a cell surface receptor for a variety of molecules. In the immune
          and lymphatic system recognition of histocompatibility markers by cell surface receptors
          and recognition of foreign antigen by the immune cells relies on these underlying
          properties of molecules </p>
      </li>
      <li><p><term>The cell</term> is the basic unit of life.</p>
        <p>A key piece of the lymphatic and immune systems is the bone marrow, which produces white
          blood cells that can protect the body by attacking pathogens that have entered the blood
          stream. The bone marrow contains stem cells which are not only capable of replication but
          remain multipotent. The division of the stem cells and further differentiation of those
          daughter cells into functioning cells of the immune system allows the body to defend
          against foreign invaders as well as monitor cells which may have change and are growing in
          way which could disrupt homeostasis. </p></li>
    </ol>
    <wb:inline idref="lymph_bp_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    <ol start="3">
      <li><p>Life requires <term>information flow</term> within and between cells and between the
          environment and the organism.</p>
        <p>The cornerstone of the immune system is its ability to distinguish self from non-self, in
          the molecular sense. Once the recognition has occurred, multiple waves of information
          within the cells and between cells take place, mobilizing immune cells and provoking
          changes in them in order to attack and destroy the invader. In addition, damaged tissues
          and cells release signalling molecules which activate not only other cells but also
          protein cascades which promote blood clotting, wound healing and activation of a several
          kinds of cells which may be involved in the immune response.</p></li>
      <li><p>Living organisms must obtain matter and energy from the external world. This matter and
            <term>energy must be transformed and transferred</term> in varied ways to build the
          organism and to perform work.</p>
        <p>Energy ingested and digested can be stored as high energy molecules like ATP but can also
          be used to construct large biological molecules like those found in and on cell membranes,
          as well as RNA and DNA. Cell functioning requires proper transcription and translation of
          the DNA and well as accurate replication of the DNA when the cell divides--in other words,
          the DNA runs the machinery of the cell. In the lymphatic system that energy is used for
          the replication of cells to build and maintain the lymphatic vessels, the cells of the
          immune system which fight pathogens directly and the cellular manufacture of antibodies
          which are proteins and require energy for their manufacture. Additionally, some degree of
          fever is beneficial for the immune response as it enhances metabolism, and that way
          increases the activity of the cells.</p></li>
    </ol>
    <wb:inline idref="lymph_bp_digt2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    <ol start="5">
      <li><p>Homeostasis (and “stability” in a more general sense) maintains the internal
          environment in a more or less constant state compatible with life.</p>
        <p>The lymphatic system contributes to homeostasis in several ways. The lymph and lymph
          vessels drain away excess fluid and molecules which could contribute to edema and swelling
          disrupting tissue integrity. The immune response helps to neutralize pathogens which may
          not only disrupt homeostasis on a local tissue level but could result in a systemic
          disruption as well. Likewise, loss of control of lymphatic functions which would normally
          contribute to maintaining homeostasis can also lead themselves to a disruption of
          homeostasis. Inflammation should stop as soon as it is not necessary anymore, because the
          presence of those powerful molecules may cause damage to tissues. Many conditions are
          caused by an inflammatory process that goes on, such as rheumatoid arthritis or Crohn’s
          disease.</p></li>
      <li><p>Understanding the behavior of the organism requires understanding the relationship
          between <term>structure and function</term> (at each and every level of organization).</p>
        <p>Lymphatic vessels have larger openings than blood vessels allowing them to pick up and
          transport larger molecules back to blood circulation. B lymphocytes with a small cytoplasm
          become, upon the right stimulus, plasma cells with large amounts of rough endoplasmic
          reticulum churning out amazing amounts of antibodies. A set of small plasma proteins,
          called complement, self-assemble to form a deadly ring that opens a hole in the membranes
          of invading cells. Lymph nodes and and the spleen have much larger total cross-sectional
          areas than the vessels feeding into them. This structural arrangement decreases the
          velocity of flow through these structures, providing more time to detect and react with
          foreign pathogens. </p></li>
      <li><p>Living organisms carry out functions at many different <term>levels of
            organization</term> simultaneously.</p>
        <p>Generally speaking the molecules of the immune system, antibodies, complement, cell
          surface receptors, cell recognition molecules and pathogen recognition molecules stimulate
          a response within the appropriate cells of the immune system. The cellular immune
          responses may result in changes to the affected tissues such those found associated with
          the inflammatory response. The lymph fluids, lymph vessels and other specialized lymph
          structures continue to support the immune response while also providing a means for the
          tissues to remove excess fluids, cellular debris and dead and dying cells and pathogens.
        </p></li>
      <li><p>All life exists within an <term>ecosystem</term> made up of the physiochemical and
          biological worlds.</p>
        <p>The body can be viewed as interacting with two ecosystems, 1) the external ecosystem of
          the world around us and 2) the internal ecosystem, which contains symbiotic bacteria and
          in which your cells and tissues must function. The lymphatic system serves at the
          interface of both those ecosystems. The immune function modulates the impact that other
          organisms living in the external ecosystem may have as pathogens. The lymphatic impact on
          the internal ecosystem involves not only immune function but includes the inflammatory
          response to tissue injury, the transport of large lipid molecules away from the digestive
          system and helping to maintain fluid and molecular balances for a healthy internal
          ecosystem.</p></li>
      <li><p><term>Evolution</term> provides a scientific explanation for the history of life on
          Earth and the mechanisms by which changes to life have occurred.</p>
        <p>The lymphatic and immune systems have become more complex during evolution. But even in
          the context of the immune response we can observe examples of evolutionary changes. For
          one, many microbes mutate (change) in a short time, provoking the immune system to develop
          a new response each time (ever wondered why you need a new flu shot every year?) On the
          other hand, the antibodies produced during the immune response can also be switched to be
          complementary to new antigens, resulting in more effective antibodies.</p>
        <p>Humans live with organisms inside their internal environment as well as free-living
          organisms found in the external environment. Random mutation in genetic material is the
          source for change in an organism or species. Must mutations are either neutral or
          deleterious. A very small percentage of mutations result in new trait or character which
          allows that organism to thrive in a changing environment. Organisms which have rapid
          reproductive cycles can change much more quickly as a species than organisms which have a
          long reproductive cycle. In bacteria the reproductive cycle is often hours compared to
          humans which may be 20+ years. The lymphatic system can adapt to changes in pathogenic
          organisms by rearranging the genes used to make antibodies, activating a different clone
          of lymphocytes or altering the expression of cell surface molecules on white blood cells.
        </p></li>
    </ol>
    <wb:inline idref="lymph_bp_digt3" purpose="didigetthis"/>

  </body>
</workbook_page>
