<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="mp_lymph"><head><title>Components of the Lymphatic System and Immunity</title><objref idref="lymph_components_LO" /></head><body><p id="fd65039d187e41ddb40f77eec55369e4">Click on the different parts of the lymphatic system, identified in the image below, to learn about how the Big Ideas are exemplified in the functioning of the lymphatic and immune systems and show that you understand these connections by completing the activities below.</p><multipanel id="multiLymph" purpose="learnbydoing"><title>The Lymphatic System</title><image_hotspot id="components" src="../webcontent/Lymphatic_1A.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="589" hotspots="transparent"><hotspot shape="rect" coords="137,46,290,67" title="Adenoids" panel_ref="one" activity_ref="2" /><hotspot shape="rect" coords="148,63,301,115" title="Tonsils" panel_ref="two" activity_ref="3" /><hotspot shape="rect" coords="162,118,295,146" title="Thymus" panel_ref="three" activity_ref="4" /><hotspot shape="rect" coords="183,180,296,215" title="Spleen" panel_ref="four" activity_ref="5" /><hotspot shape="rect" coords="189,298,295,325" title="Bone Marrow" panel_ref="five" activity_ref="6" /><hotspot shape="rect" coords="2,456,149,488" title="Lymph Vessels" panel_ref="six" activity_ref="7" /><hotspot shape="rect" coords="3,305,134,330" title="Lymph Nodes" panel_ref="seven" activity_ref="8" /></image_hotspot><panels intro_panel_ref="ex_intropanel"><panel id="ex_intropanel"><p id="badaf132b3bc4076a74b0f80d798ed04">Our body is in constant exchange with the environment, through breathing, eating and other activities. Therefore, it is important to screen the body and its components regularly to identify foreign invaders that might enter during these activities (or in any other manner). Further, it is important to rapidly and effectively remove these invaders before they can cause significant harm. Our body has specialized transport systems to carry out these functions. The cardiovascular and lymphatic systems work together to transport excess fluids (blood and lymph fluid, respectively) away from body tissues. The cardiovascular and lymphatic systems also participate in the function of immunity, helping defend the body&apos;s cells from foreign organisms that may enter the body tissues or fluids.</p></panel><panel id="one"><p id="fccffdad43fb431eb27e35f1d75e45a3">The adenoids are an aggregation of lymphoid cells located in the posterior superior wall of the nasopharynx.</p><p id="d6b163ad65654246b5aaaba0fed9158d">Since the the adenoids are contained by a supporting network of reticular fibers we refer to them as belonging to the category of lymphoid nodules. They are positioned such that most of the air which is inhaled through the nose passes across the surface of the adenoids. The adenoids structure and function relates to several of the underlying foundations of physiology known as the Big Ideas. The adenoids provide the first interface between the external ecosystem and the internal one. When a pathogen or potentially harmful foreign molecule crosses the surface of the adenoids, the cells in the germinal center of the adenoids may be stimulated to divide to react the harmful pathogen or molecule. The energy to do this has been stored within the individual cells but ultimately came from the energy ingested and processed through digestion. </p></panel><panel id="two"><p id="ac37a25340eb4df1b5ccca3eb0c49ca2">The tonsils include both the palatine tonsils located posteriorly in the oral cavity near when the pharynx the meets the soft palate and the lingual tonsils, which are not visible because they are found near the base of the tongue.</p><p id="ec344989b0bb40b2a43187f176f0c646">The structure and the function of the tonsils enable them to efficiently trap particulate matter which may include bacterial, virus particles,mold spores, and inert particles which may be either inhaled or ingested. Their location near the junction of the oral cavity and the pharynx provides access to the inhaled air of the respiratory system as well as ingested items. The surfaces of the tonsils are highly convoluted increasing the surface area of the interface with the external ecosystem. The highly convoluted nature of the tonsils surfaces can work against this adaptation of this system. It is possible for particles to become physically trapped in the folds of the tonsils. In this situation the tonsils themselves may become infected and abscessed and actually contribute to a disruption of homeostasis. </p></panel><panel id="three"><p id="dac48a93edc64a9f8685cd8b947307d2">The thymus is &quot;A lobular (of or pertaining to a lobe) structure, which contains many immature, inactive lymphocytes. As the lymphocytes mature, they leave the thymus to attack infected cells in lymphatic tissues throughout the body.&quot; <activity_link idref="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_07" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">Follow this link to review the overview of this unit presented in Unit 1: Introduction of Systems.</activity_link></p><p id="f3f0b1637e564f3dae2dc1b91e1cb122">The lobes of the thymus can be divided into an outer cortex region and an inner medulla. The cortex region contains lymphoid stem cells. The daughter cells of the lymphoid stem cells will differentiate into mature T cells. The mature T cells migrate into the medulla and from their will enter the bloodstream. T cells while being housed in the thymus are not active as functioning T cells and are actually sequestered from the the antigens circulating in the bloodstream. While maturing in the thymus the cells which may be self- reactive are eliminated. The clones which survive and multiply are those which do not react with self tissues. The thymus reaches its greatest size during adolescence and then is gradually replaced with adipose tissue. </p></panel><panel id="four"><p id="a17d7c4fa4dc4afdaaca4a8d5e7fec3f">The spleen is the largest of the lymphatic organs, and it houses lymphocytes for potential immune response. The resident phagocytes within the spleen perform the basic function of removing cell debris from the blood.</p><p id="bc520aeca5ae4aa28d0980c37cf53b57">The spleen’s dark red color arises because it serves as a reservoir for a large volume of blood. Consequently the blood flow through the spleen is rather slow allowing it to remove abnormal blood cells, both red and white, and other blood components through a process called phagocytosis. The spleen is organized into red pulp and white pulp. The white pulp inside the splenic nodule contains lymphocytes which may become active during an immune response to foreign invaders.</p></panel><panel id="five"><p id="f08aab639f77455a898c5003eb92466d">Bone marrow can be found in the cavities both compact and spongy bone. It is frequently identified as either red marrow or yellow marrow. Red marrow contains the pluripotent stem cells that divide and eventually produce the myeloid stem cells which lead to the differentiation of erythrocytes, granulocytes and monocytes. The pluripotent stem cells in the red marrow are also capable of cell division and differentiation into the lymphoid line which is responsible for T and B lymphocytes. Yellow bone marrow is associated with the development of fat tissue. In times of extreme physiologic stress such as extreme blood loss, yellow marrow is capable of differentiating into red marrow which would increase the rate of blood cell production.</p></panel><panel id="six"><p id="a10aa5228ce843eb8400e59db9ce5084">Lymph vessels are sometimes referred to as lymphatics. They carry lymph (tissue fluid that has entered lymphy vessels) back to the venous blood system. Like blood vessels the smallest lymphatics are referred to as capillaries. The are very thin consisting of only endothelial cells. Unlike blood capillaries lymph capillaries start as a blind pouch. There are gaps between the endothelial cells so large that bigger molecules, like proteins and viruses, have a way to get inside, since they would be too large to cross the endothelial cell membrane. Similarly the red blood cells and white blood cells can squeeze through the gaps to get inside. The capillaries flow into lymphatic vessels. The lymph vessels are not connected to any kind of pump and when standing they must work against the flow of gravity. To accomplish this some of of the lymph vessels have one way valves to prevent backflow of fluid. The larger lymph vessels actually have smooth muscle in their walls which contracts rhythmically to help propel the lymph fluid in the lymph vessels toward their connection to the venous blood system where it can be recycled.</p></panel><panel id="seven"><p id="f6c8b125cc9f45748e0a03cc23157f22">Lymph nodes are small bean-shaped structures found along the lymph vessels. The contain lymphocytes capable of clonally expanding with the correct antigen stimulus and are designed to filter the lymph running through them. Lymph nodes have and external capsule keeping the cells and the lymph separate from other parts of the body. In addition, the velocity of flow is decreased because the larger size of the lymph nodes increases total cross-sectional area.</p></panel></panels><wb:inline idref="lymph_mp_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></multipanel><p id="c86368835b4348d98248aa33e933acdf"><activity_link idref="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_07" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">Follow this link to review the overview of this unit presented in Unit 1: Introduction of Systems.</activity_link></p></body></workbook_page>
