<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement with Magnifying Glass</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/index.htm?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/index.htm?slide={{position}}" href-swf="/"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>Variables</title>
		<content>Variables Scale of measurement Nominal Ordinal Interval Ratio Variables Scale of measurement Nominal Ordinal Interval Ratio </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the previous section, a simple distinction was made between quantitative and categorical variables. However, there is a more precise method of categorizing variables: it is called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;scale of measurement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. The scales of measurement become increasingly precise with each level,  while retaining the characteristics of the level below it. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; For instance, ordinal data builds on the characteristics of nominal level data and, therefore, is more precise than it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now we are going to take a closer look at the characteristics of these 4 levels of measurement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Nominal Variables  Differences Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Nominal Variables  Differences Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The first level of measurement is nominal. It is the least precise measure of data as it only indicates &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;differences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. Nominal level&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; data uses discrete categories to describe &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;qualitative differences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Example of a Nominal Variable  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement     Types of Pets Birds Fish Cats Dogs Example of a Nominal Variable  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement     Types of Pets Birds Fish Cats Dogs </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;An example of a nominal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; variable is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;types of pets. For instance, types&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of pets could include birds, fish, cats, and dogs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. None of the categories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; (in this case, types of pets) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;is implicitly better than the other.  Rather, the categories reflect different types &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;of pets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Other Examples of Nominal Variables  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Gender (Male, Female, Transgender)  Eye color (Blue, Green, Brown, Hazel)  Type of house (Bungalow, Duplex, Ranch) Type of resident (homeowner, renter)  Other Examples of Nominal Variables  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Gender (Male, Female, Transgender)  Eye color (Blue, Green, Brown, Hazel)  Type of house (Bungalow, Duplex, Ranch) Type of resident (homeowner, renter)  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Other examples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of nominal variables include:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Gender&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Eye color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Type of house and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Type of resident&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; categories for each of these nominal variables reflect qualitative differences.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content> Ordinal Variables Ordered Differences Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement  Ordinal Variables Ordered Differences Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now let’s take a closer look at Ordinal Variables&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The second level of measurement is ordinal. Ordinal level data is more precise than nominal data as the differences can now be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;ranked ordered&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;; however, it does not indicate that the differences between two numbers are fixed or equal. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Example of Ordinal Variable An ordinal variable is a categorical variable for which the possible values are ordered.  Ordinal variables can be considered “in between” categorical and quantitative variables. Order of Finishes in a Race 1st Place 2nd Place Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Example of Ordinal Variable An ordinal variable is a categorical variable for which the possible values are ordered.  Ordinal variables can be considered “in between” categorical and quantitative variables. Order of Finishes in a Race 1st Place 2nd Place Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;An example of an&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; ordinal variable is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;the order of finishes in a race. For instance,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;we can say that Tanesha finished first and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Alexis finished second; however, we do not know the degree of difference. It could be that Tanesha won by 2 seconds or 20 minutes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Educational level:&amp;#x0A;    1: Elementary school education&amp;#x0A;    2: High school graduate&amp;#x0A;    3: Some college&amp;#x0A;    4: College graduate&amp;#x0A;    5: Graduate degree Survey Question Responses:       “My general health is……..”           1: Poor&amp;#x0A;          2: Reasonable&amp;#x0A;          3: Good&amp;#x0A;          4: Excellent Other Examples of Ordinal Variables  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Educational level:&amp;#x0A;    1: Elementary school education&amp;#x0A;    2: High school graduate&amp;#x0A;    3: Some college&amp;#x0A;    4: College graduate&amp;#x0A;    5: Graduate degree Survey Question Responses:       “My general health is……..”           1: Poor&amp;#x0A;          2: Reasonable&amp;#x0A;          3: Good&amp;#x0A;          4: Excellent Other Examples of Ordinal Variables  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Other examples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of ordinal variables include:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Educational Level and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Some Survey Question responses&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; categories for each of these ordinal variables show order, but not the magnitude of difference between two adjacent points.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Interval Variables  Ordered Differences with Equal Intervals Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Interval Variables  Ordered Differences with Equal Intervals Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The third level of measurement is interval. It builds upon the characteristics of ordinal data through the addition of meaningful differences between two numbers. That is, the distance between pairs of consecutive numbers is assumed to be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;equal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. However, interval variables do not have a meaningful zero point. Thus, a zero does not mean the absence of the attribute, but rather is a particular (but arbitrary) point on the scale. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Temperature in Celsius Example of Interval Variable  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Temperature in Celsius Example of Interval Variable  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;For instance, when temperature is measured in Celsius, the one degree difference between 35 degrees and 36 degrees, is assumed to be the same as the one degree difference between 25 degrees and 26 degrees. However, zero degrees in Celsius&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;does not mean the absence of heat, since there are below freezing temperatures, such as 20 below.  The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;same characteristics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;also hold true for temperature measured in Fahrenheit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Other Examples of Interval Variables IQ Scores SAT Scores Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Other Examples of Interval Variables IQ Scores SAT Scores Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Other examples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of interval variables include:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;IQ Scores and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;SAT Scores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;For each of these interval&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; variables, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;the distance between pairs of consecutive numbers is assumed to be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;equal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; but they&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; do not have a meaningful zero point. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Ratio Variables  Ordered Differences with Equal  Intervals and Meaningful Zero Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Ratio Variables  Ordered Differences with Equal  Intervals and Meaningful Zero Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The fourth and final level of measurement is ratio. It has all the characteristics of interval data plus a meaningful zero point. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement   Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;A good example of ratio level data is age.  For&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; instance, w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;e know that someone, who is 40 years old, is twice as old as someone, who is 20 years old. There is also a meaningful zero point; that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;it is possible to have the absence of age.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Other Examples of Ratio Variables Height Weight Cost of a Car, in Dollars Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Other Examples of Ratio Variables Height Weight Cost of a Car, in Dollars </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Other examples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of ratio variables include:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Cost of a Car, in Dollars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;For each of these ratio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; variables, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;the distance between pairs of consecutive numbers is assumed to be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;equal &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;and there is a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;meaningful zero point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Changed from Most Precise Level of Measurement to a Less Precise Level of Measurement Age in Years (ex. 3 years, 10 years) is Ratio Level Age Groups (ex. Toddler, Adolescent, Young adulthood, Middle Age)  is Ordinal  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Changed from Most Precise Level of Measurement to a Less Precise Level of Measurement Age in Years (ex. 3 years, 10 years) is Ratio Level Age Groups (ex. Toddler, Adolescent, Young adulthood, Middle Age)  is Ordinal  Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;to note that more precise data can always be scaled down to less precise data. For instance, a ratio level variable like age can be scaled down into a ordinal variable of age groups, including  toddler, adolescent, young adulthood, and middle age.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Age Groups (ex. Toddler, Adolescent, Middle Age) cannot be changed into Years (ex. 3 years, 10 years) Cannot change a less precise level of measurement into a more precise level of measurement    Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement Age Groups (ex. Toddler, Adolescent, Middle Age) cannot be changed into Years (ex. 3 years, 10 years) Cannot change a less precise level of measurement into a more precise level of measurement    Characteristics of the Different Scales of Measurement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Less&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;precise data, however, cannot be made into more precise data. That&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is, an ordinal level variable, like age groups, cannot be changed into a ratio level variable, such as age in years.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>+</title>
		<content>+ Final Thoughts about Scale of Measurement  + Final Thoughts about Scale of Measurement  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;So, why is it important understand scale of measurement?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Statistical methods are ways of summarizing analyzing and interpreting data, and are designed for specific types of data. Researchers need to know the level of measurement of their data when selecting a statistical method since using an incorrect method for analyzing data can affect the reliability and accuracy of the results.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Be sure to keep these levels of measurement in mind whenever you are planning to analyze data.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Produced and edited by  Margo Coleman-Seiffert and Kim Larson Produced and edited by  Margo Coleman-Seiffert and Kim Larson </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Developed as part of  Next Generation Courseware Grant     Developed as part of  Next Generation Courseware Grant     </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>Attributions Bird https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:YellownapedAmazon.jpg#/media/File:YellownapedAmazon.jpg by Matt Edmonds CCBY 3.0 Fish href=&amp;quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Goldfish_Bubble_Eye.jpg#/media/File:Goldfish_Bubble_Eye.jpg by Lerdsuwa CCBY 3.0 Ribbons by M. Coleman-Seiffert CCBY NC SA 3.0 Cat by M. Coleman-Seiffert CCBY NC SA 3.0 Dog by K. Larson CCBY NC SA 3.0 Thermometer  by M. Coleman-Seiffert CCBY NC SA 3.0 Silhouettes http://www.shutterstock.com/pic-22805611/stock-vector-people-stages-of-development.html used with permission By Arbit © Cartoon https://www.causeweb.org/cwis/r1619/cartoon_correlation__regression_caveats by John Landers CCBY NC SA 3.0 Attributions Bird https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:YellownapedAmazon.jpg#/media/File:YellownapedAmazon.jpg by Matt Edmonds CCBY 3.0 Fish href=&amp;quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Goldfish_Bubble_Eye.jpg#/media/File:Goldfish_Bubble_Eye.jpg by Lerdsuwa CCBY 3.0 Ribbons by M. Coleman-Seiffert CCBY NC SA 3.0 Cat by M. Coleman-Seiffert CCBY NC SA 3.0 Dog by K. Larson CCBY NC SA 3.0 Thermometer  by M. Coleman-Seiffert CCBY NC SA 3.0 Silhouettes http://www.shutterstock.com/pic-22805611/stock-vector-people-stages-of-development.html used with permission By Arbit © Cartoon https://www.causeweb.org/cwis/r1619/cartoon_correlation__regression_caveats by John Landers CCBY NC SA 3.0 </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
