<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u3_introduction1"><head><title>Introduction to Producing Data</title></head><body><p id="d20a6d11320c414f88091e88fa3344e2">Recall &quot;The Big Picture,&quot; the four-step process that encompasses statistics: data
 production, exploratory data analysis, probability, and inference. </p><p id="f7e0b4e134574dbcb3c62e5174b6deff">In the previous unit, we considered exploratory data
 analysis—the
 discovery of patterns in the raw data. First we need to choose the individuals from the population that will be
 included in the sample. Then, once we
 have
 chosen
 the individuals, we need to collect data from them. The first stage is called
 <em style="italic">sampling</em>, and the second stage is called <em style="italic">study design</em>.</p><image id="e0b4c527c36540cdbf13897258d0b658" src="../webcontent/big_picture_producing_data.gif" alt="The Big Picture         of Statistics. First, a set of data was created from subset of the population. This is the Producing         Data step. Then, we perform exploratory data analysis on the data. With these results, we apply         probability which is our first step in drawing conclusions about the population from the data. After         we have applied probability to the data, we can draw conclusions. This is called inference, the second         step in drawing conclusions. In this unit we will be looking at the Producing Data step." style="block" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a2d7b725c3c84b279becf44f07fa8f98"> As we have seen, exploratory data analysis seeks to
 illuminate
 patterns in the data by summarizing the distributions of quantitative or categorical
 variables, or the relationships between variables. In the final part of the course,
 statistical inference, we will use the summaries about variables or relationships that
 were obtained in the
 study
 to draw conclusions about what is true for the entire population from which the sample
 was chosen. For this process to &quot;work&quot;
 reliably,
 it is essential that the <em style="italic">sample</em> be truly <em style="italic">representative</em> of the larger
 population. For example, if researchers want to determine whether the
 antidepressant
 Zoloft is effective for teenagers in general, then it would not be a good idea to only
 test it on a sample of teens who have been admitted to a psychiatric hospital, because
 their depression may be more severe, and less treatable, than that of teens in general.
 Thus, the very first stage in data production,
 <em style="italic">sampling</em>,
 must be carried out in such a way that the sample really does represent the population
 of interest.</p><p id="f7620d148ee6499cbe66e852e7ecba7a">Choosing a sample is only the first stage in producing data, so it is not enough to just make
 sure that the sample is representative. We must also remember that our summaries of
 variables and their relationships are only valid if these have been assessed properly.
 For instance, if researchers want to test the effectiveness of Zoloft versus Prozac for
 treating teenagers, it would not be a good idea to simply compare levels of depression
 for a group of teenagers who happen to be using Zoloft to levels of depression for a
 group of teenagers who happen to be using Prozac. If they discover that one group of
 patients turns out to be less depressed, it could just be that teenagers with less
 serious depression are more likely to be prescribed one of the drugs over the other. In
 situations like
 this,
 the <em style="italic">design</em> for producing data must be considered carefully. Studies should be
 designed to discover what we want to know about the variables of interest for the
 individuals in the sample. In particular, if what you want to know about the variables
 is whether there is a causal relationship between them, special care should be given to
 the design of the study
 (since,
 as we know,
 association
 does not imply causation).</p><p id="bb570f922f2a4aa699134536d9980c2a">In this unit, we will
 focus on these two stages of data production: obtaining a sample, and
 designing a study. </p><image id="a8874add9eb04fabb3e11bf76c8dcf34" src="../webcontent/image002.gif" alt="The two stages of data production. Sampling occurs, then Design occurs." style="block" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d9f69fef040e4fddb102c41db8026d9e">Throughout this unit, we establish guidelines for
 the
 ideal production of data. While we will hold these guidelines as
 standards to strive for, realistically it is rarely possible to carry out a study
 that
 is completely free of flaws. Common sense must frequently be applied in order to decide
 which imperfections we can live with and which ones could completely undermine a study&apos;s
 results.</p><p id="cf2221f1444f41928ca260c5eed4ac2a"> A sample that produces data
 that
 is not representative because of
 the
 systematic under- or over-estimation of the values of the variable of
 interest is called <em style="italic">biased</em>. Bias may result from either a poor sampling plan or
 from a poor design for evaluating the variable of interest. </p><p id="e0a8ae5fa9f04684bb9ee9556f53348b">We begin this unit by focusing on what constitutes a
 good—or
 a
 bad—sampling
 plan. In the second
 module,
 we will discuss study design.</p></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
