<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m4_homeostasis_00">
	<head>
		<title>Heart Attack and Congestive Heart Failure</title>
		<objref idref="predict_factors_disrupt_cardio_homeostasis_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="predict_problems_cardio_cannot_homeostasis_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Cardiac output is homeostatically maintained throughout our lifetime so that it
			constantly meets the needs of the body’s tissues. When the heart becomes damaged, such
			as after a heart attack, it may not be able to maintain adequate flow. This causes blood
			pressure to fall, initiating homeostatic feedback loops to try to bring blood pressure
			(and cardiac output) back to normal.</p>

		<p>One way that the heart can become damaged is through a heart attack. This occurs when
			coronary blood vessels, which supply the cells of the heart itself with oxygen and
			nutrients, become significantly narrowed or completely blocked with a combination of
			plaque and thrombus (clot). During a heart attack, cells lack oxygen, causing them to
			die. If enough heart muscle cells die, the heart weakens so that it can’t pump as much
			blood, leading to the various negative effects associated with this condition.</p>

		<p>Congestive heart failure is another common condition affecting cardiac output. It may
			develop after someone has a heart attack, or as a consequence of many other cardiac
			conditions. The problem with congestive heart failure is that the heart muscle is
			weakened to the point that it doesn’t do a good job pumping out the blood that is
			flowing into it (the blood flowing into the heart is called venous return). In fact, one
			of the main feedback loops that regulates blood pressure does so by adjusting the amount
			of blood in the body. This is because the more blood we have, the greater our venous
			return, and the higher the cardiac output – assuming a healthy heart. With the weakened
			heart associated with congestive heart failure, more venous return can actually lead to
			less cardiac output. A lowered cardiac output decreases blood pressure, signaling the
			body to increase blood volume, increasing venous return, and making cardiac output lower
			still. Because this loop continually makes the problem with cardiac output and blood
			pressure worse, it is a positive feedback loop – and not one we want to experience. </p>

		<wb:inline idref="predict_factors_disrupt_cardio_homeostasis_DIGT-a" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<!--<p>The <term>renin-angiotensin</term> system increases blood volume by stimulating the
			kidneys to keep more fluid in the body. This increases venous return and increases the
			work that the heart must perform. In people with healthy hearts, cardiac output
			increases by the <term>Frank-Starling mechanism</term>. But in those with damaged
			hearts, it may not be enough to bring blood pressure back to normal. The body will
			continue to retain fluid, overstretching the heart. This overstretching pulls the actin
			and myosin in the myocytes past their optimal overload, leading to a decrease in force
			of contraction and cardiac output with further increases in venous return. This
			condition is called congestive heart failure and can be a positive feedback loop leading
			to death if untreated.</p>-->

	</body>
</workbook_page>
