<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m4_homeostasis_01">
	<head>
		<title>Other Homeostatic Imbalances of the Cardiovascular System</title>
		<objref idref="predict_factors_disrupt_cardio_homeostasis_OBJ"/>
		<!--<title>Homeostasis and Blood Clotting</title>
		<objref idref="explain_pos_feedback_loops_hemostasis_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="explain_procoagulants_anticoagulants_fibrinolytic_drugs_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>We have discussed mechanisms within the heart that regulate cardiac output. For example,
			an increased heart muscle contraction will increase with an increase in venous return.
			Thus the healthy heart can pump more blood when there is more blood to pump.</p>

		<!--NOTE: link to ‘changes in cardiac output’-->

		<p>There are other controls of heart function and cardiac output from the nervous system and
			endocrine system, which we will discuss in the integration of systems. It is important
			to note that we do not consciously change our heart rate or cardiac output. Instead we
			can indirectly adjust the nervous and endocrine feedback loops by initiating activities
			such as exercise or relaxation techniques.</p>

		<section id="_u9_m4_imbalances_plasma">
			<title>Homeostatic Imbalances of the Plasma Constituents</title>
			<body>
				<p>Although most people realize the importance of red blood cells in distributing
					oxygen to the body’s tissues, it is important to realize that the plasma
					(non-cellular) fraction of blood is also critically important. One function of
					the plasma is to form blood clots when blood vessels are cut or torn in order to
					prevent excessive blood loss. Blood clotting needs to be limited to the vessels
					that are damaged in order for the system to function appropriately.
						<term>Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)</term> is a serious
					condition in which the clotting cascade becomes activated in many non-injured
					blood vessels at one time. This occurs secondary to a significant insult to the
					body such as burns, cancer, infections, etc. With this generalized activation of
					the clotting cascade, small blood clots are formed, some of which limit or block
					off the flow of blood within vessels. This cuts off the flow of oxygen to
					organs, and if prolonged, can results in tissue necrosis (cell death), and the
					organ may stop functioning altogether. The random coagulation throughout the
					body leads to the coagulation proteins, as well as platelets, being used up,
					lowering the concentration of the essential clotting factors in the plasma. Once
					the coagulation process is disrupted, the patient suffers from abnormal bleeding
					from GI tract, respiratory tracts, and from the tiniest wounds in the
					body.<!--The abnormal activity of clotting 
					proteins in DIC will eventually lead to the consumption of these proteins. Once this occurs, patients with DIC are at serious risk of severe 
					bleeding from even a simple cut or injury.--></p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="predict_factors_disrupt_cardio_homeostasis_DIGT-b" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section id="_u9_m4_imbalances_blood">
			<title>Homeostatic Imbalances of Red Blood Cell Concentration</title>
			<body>
				<p>Red blood cell concentration is sensitive to changes in oxygen levels. Prolonged
					exposure to low oxygen causes increased production of RBCs, raising the
					concentration of red blood cells in the blood (known as hematocrit), in order to
					maintain homeostatic oxygenation of the tissues. However, hematocrit levels that
					get too high can also lead to dysfunction, leading to a condition called
						<term>polycythemia</term>. With polycythemia, the blood will have increased
					viscosity, making it thicker and harder for the heart to pump this blood through
					the body. This can lead to heart failure in severe cases. Polycythemia can
					either be primary, where it is associated with an abnormality in the bone marrow
					that causes overproduction of red blood cells, or secondary, where red blood
					cell production is normally stimulated, but continues to the point of developing
					polycythemia.</p>

				<p>An example of secondary polycythemia is chronic mountain sickness (Monge’s
					disease), which is an uncommon condition that occurs in certain people living at
					high altitudes (above 12,000 feet) for months or years. At higher altitudes, the
					atmospheric pressure decreases, resulting in less oxygen availability due to
					lower partial pressure of oxygen in the atmosphere. This stimulates RBC
					production to bring people to a slightly higher hematocrit, which then levels
					off. In those that develop polycythemia, their RBC production continues over
					time, making their hematocrit very high. As mentioned previously, as their
					hematocrit increases, so does blood viscosity. An increase in viscosity makes it
					more difficult for blood to move through blood vessels and results in the heart
					pumping vigorously to get blood circulating through the body. This increased
					resistance of blood places an excessive strain on the heart that may lead to
					inadequate pumping of blood and decreased oxygenation of tissue. This can lead
					to cardiac ischemia and hypertension due to the body’s effort to return to
					homeostasis. Treating chronic altitude illness requires the removal of blood
					(about a pint) as a form of temporary relief. However, the only effective form
					of treatment is to descend to a lower altitude.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="predict_factors_disrupt_cardio_homeostasis_DIGT-c" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section id="_u9_m4_imbalances_vessels">
			<title>Homeostatic Imbalances Caused by Vessel Dysfunction</title>
			<body>
				<p>The tissues throughout the body regulate flow to themselves by sending signals
					that can constrict or dilate the blood vessels that “feed” them. If these
					vessels don’t have an ability to make the adjustments, the tissues won’t be able
					to appropriately match blood flow with their metabolic activity.</p>
				<p>One example of this is stable angina, where people experience chest pain on
					exertion. Stable angina is associated with atherosclerotic plaque that has
					developed in the main coronary arteries, which deliver flow to the cardiac
					muscle. Because of the plaque, these vessels can’t dilate appropriately when the
					needs of the heart muscle increases. Any type of increase in physical activity
					is not met with the normal coronary artery vasodilation in these individuals.
					This leads to low oxygen levels in their tissues, which can cause pain, as well
					as prevent the heart from functioning optimally, limiting their activity
					level.</p>
				<!--<p>Physiological stress ranges from physical activity to shock (a life-threatening
					condition caused by insufficient blood flow). Everyone knows that the heart
					beats more rapidly during exercise, and when the heart works harder, cardiac
					output increases. The heart rate increases because exercise stimulates the
					proprioceptors in muscles and joints that send signals to the brain that the
					muscles need more blood flow. With more vigorous exercise, muscular activity
					sends more venous blood back to the heart, increasing the preload on the right
					ventricle. In addition, more blood flows through the pulmonary circuit and then
					returns to the left atrium. Additionally, the afferent signals from the
					peripheral stretch receptors and the tendon organs activates the respiratory
					centers of the medulla oblongata, causing increased rate and depth of
					respiration. The greater thoracic movement aid in increasing the venous return.
					As a result, the higher venous return, and following the Frank-Starling
					principle, the cardiac output increases as the function of the increased stroke
					volume and heart rate. A number of control mechanisms help make adjustments for
					changes in the distribution of blood flow and BP, involving communication with
					the cardiovascular center in the brain.</p>-->
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="predict_factors_disrupt_cardio_homeostasis_DIGT-d" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
