<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m4_homeostasis_02">
	<head>
		<title>Local Control of Blood Flow</title>
		<objref idref="explain_cardio_other_systems_homeostasis_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_examples_maintain_homeostasis_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p><term>Autoregulation</term> refers to a tissue's ability to meet its 
			metabolic needs by automatically altering its blood flow. Autoregulation is
			particularly important in organs such as the heart and skeletal muscles, whose 
			need for oxygen, nutrients, and the removal of wastes during exercise can be up 
			to 10 times higher than when the body is at rest. In addition to increasing perfusion 
			in the heart and muscles during physical activity, autoregulation manages regional blood 
			flow to other tissues as well, including the brain. Individual mental and physical tasks 
			require significantly different patterns of blood distribution. When a person is on the telephone, 
			for example, motor speech areas of the brain receive more blood when talking, and auditory areas 
			get more blood flow when listening. Autoregulatory changes in blood flow occur in response to 
			local signaling molecules that cause constriction or dilation of local arterioles.</p>
		
		<section id="_u9_m4_vasconstrictors_vasodilators">
			<title>Vasoconstrictors and Vasodilators</title>
			<body>
				<p>The diameter of blood vessels can be changed by chemicals secreted by various cells, such as white blood cells, 
					smooth muscle cells, platelets, endothelial cells, and macrophages. Metabolically active tissue cells can release 
					vasodilating chemicals such as potassium ions, hydrogen ions, lactic acid, and adenosine. Endothelial cells can also 
					release the vasodilator nitric oxide. Tissue that is injured or inflamed secrete vasodilating compounds of the 
					prostaglandin family. Chemicals that cause vasoconstriction include serotonin (released from platelets) and endothelins 
					(from endothelial cells).</p>
				
				<p>Changes in local oxygen concentrations elicit two very different autoregulatory reactions in the pulmonary and systemic circulations. 
					In the systemic circulation, decreased oxygen levels in the tissues cause blood vessels to dilate, increasing the delivery of oxygen. 
					In the pulmonary circulation, low oxygen levels in poorly ventilated alveoli cause the blood vessels feeding those alveoli to constrict. 
					As a result, blood avoids most of the alveoli in the lungs that have poor  ventilation. Instead, most blood flows to well-ventilated alveoli.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="explain_cardio_other_systems_homeostasis_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_cardio_other_systems_homeostasis_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
