<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="calculate_relative_freq_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_calculate_relative_freq" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>It is known that 4% of children carry a certain virus, but a leading health
                researcher suspects that the percentage is actually higher. Which of the following
                provides the most convincing evidence to support the researcher’s suspicion? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Out of 20 randomly chosen children, 1 child carries the virus. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Out of 60 randomly chosen children, 3 children carry the virus. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Out of 5,000 randomly chosen children, 250 children carry the virus. </choice>
            <choice value="D">Out of 5,000 randomly chosen children, 210 children carry the virus.
            </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that 1/20 = 0.05 = 5% is larger than 4%,
                    recall that the more repetitions that are performed, the closer the relative
                    frequency gets to the probability it estimates. There is another option that
                    provides more convincing evidence. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that 3/60 = 0.05 = 5% is larger than 4%,
                    recall that the more repetitions that are performed, the closer the relative
                    frequency gets to the probability it estimates. There is another option that
                    provides more convincing evidence.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The relative frequency of children carrying the virus is 250/5,000
                    = 5% which is larger than 4% and has the largest number of repetitions.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that the relative frequency of children
                    carrying the virus is 210/5,000 = 0.042 is larger than 4%, there is another
                    option that provides more convincing evidence. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_calculate_relative_freq" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>It is known that roughly 5% of the general population carry a certain virus. A health
                researcher believes that among caucasian males the percentage is actually lower.
                Which of the following will provide the most convincing evidence to support the
                researcher’s suspicion? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Out of 25 randomly chosen caucasian males, 1 male carries the virus. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Out of 70 randomly chosen caucasian males, 3 males carry the virus. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Out of 6,000 randomly chosen caucasian males, 288 males carry the
                virus. </choice>
            <choice value="D">Out of 6,000 randomly chosen caucasian males, 240 males carry the
                virus. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that 1/25 = 0.04 = 4% is smaller than 5%,
                    recall that the more repetitions that are performed, the closer the relative
                    frequency gets to the probability it estimates. There is another option that
                    provides more convincing evidence to support the researcher’s suspicion.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that 3/50 = 0.043 = 4.3% is smaller than 5%,
                    recall that the more repetitions that are performed, the closer the relative
                    frequency gets to the probability it estimates. There is another option that
                    provides more convincing evidence. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that the relative frequency of caucasian males
                    carrying the virus is 288/6,000 = 0.048 = 4.8% is less than 5%, there is another
                    option that provides more convincing evidence. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The relative frequency of caucasian males carrying the virus is
                    240/6,000 = 0.04 = 4% which is less than 5%. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_calculate_relative_freq" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Suppose Joan has a fair four-sided die with sides that are numbered 1, 2, 3, and 4. </p>
            <p><image src="../webcontent/image012.png" /></p>
            <p>Image attribution: <link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/" target="new">CC BY NC 3.0</link> by <link href="http://www.ck12.org/user:ZWFkYW1zQGNhcmx0b24uazEyLm1uLnVz/book/ISD-93-Carlton-High-School-Probability-and-Statistics/section/1.1/" target="new">CK-12</link></p>
            <p>After she rolls it 20 times, Joan finds that she’s rolled the number 3 six times.
                What is the empirical probability that Joan rolls a 3? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">6% </choice>
            <choice value="B">20% </choice>
            <choice value="C">25% </choice>
            <choice value="D">30% </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because Joan rolled a 3 six
                    times. However, we would need to take into account how many times Joan attempted
                    to roll the die. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because Joan rolled the die
                    20 times. However, we would need to take into account how many times Joan rolled
                    a 3 to compute the empirical probability. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because it is the <em style="italic">theoretical</em> probability of rolling a 3. Indeed, of the 4
                    different equally likely outcomes, this is one of them (1/4 = 25%). However,
                    this is not the <em style="italic">empirical</em> probability that Joan
                    demonstrated.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. In six of the 20 different attempts, Joan rolled a 3. So
                    the probability is 6/20 = 30%. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_calculate_relative_freq" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Suppose Joan has a fair four-sided die with sides that are numbered 1, 2, 3, and 4. </p>
            <p><image src="../webcontent/image012.png" /></p>
            <p>Image attribution: <link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/" target="new">CC BY NC 3.0</link> by <link href="http://www.ck12.org/user:ZWFkYW1zQGNhcmx0b24uazEyLm1uLnVz/book/ISD-93-Carlton-High-School-Probability-and-Statistics/section/1.1/" target="new">CK-12</link></p>
            <p>After she rolls it 20 times, how many times does she roll the number 3? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">3 </choice>
            <choice value="B">5 </choice>
            <choice value="C">6 </choice>
            <choice value="D">It is impossible to tell. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is <em style="italic">possible</em> that the number 3
                    will appear three times, we do not know that this is what will happen when Joan
                    rolls the die. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because the probability of
                    rolling a 3 is 25%, and 25% of 20 is 5. However, while this is the <em style="italic">most likely</em> number of times Joan will roll a 3, we do
                    not know that this is what will happen. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is <em style="italic">possible</em> that the number 3
                    will appear three times, we do not know that this is what will happen when Joan
                    rolls the die. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. While we may be able to compute the theoretical probability of
                    rolling a 3, we can’t use that information to determine how often a 3 actually
                    appears when Joan (or anyone else for that matter) rolls the die. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q5_calculate_relative_freq" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Suppose Joan has a fair four-sided die with sides that are numbered 1, 2, 3, and 4. </p>
            <p><image src="../webcontent/image012.png" /></p>
            <p>Image attribution: <link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/" target="new">CC BY NC 3.0</link> by <link href="http://www.ck12.org/user:ZWFkYW1zQGNhcmx0b24uazEyLm1uLnVz/book/ISD-93-Carlton-High-School-Probability-and-Statistics/section/1.1/" target="new">CK-12</link></p>
            <p>After she rolls it 2,000 times, she finds that she rolled the number 2 a total of 187
                times. Which of the following is true? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Joan has demonstrated that this is a fair die, since the relative
                frequency of rolling a 2 is nearly equal to the theoretical probability. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Joan has provided evidence that calls into question whether or not
                this is a fair die because the relative frequency of rolling a 2 is quite different
                than the theoretical probability even after repeating the experiment many times. </choice>
            <choice value="C">We cannot draw any conclusions from Joan’s experience with this die
                because there is only a very weak link between the relative frequency of an event
                and the theoretical probability. </choice>
            <choice value="D">We cannot draw any conclusions from Joan’s experience with this die
                without also knowing how many times the other numbers appeared. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The theoretical probability of rolling a 2 is 1/4 = 25%, while
                    Joan’s experience has the relative frequency at 187/2,000 = 9.35%. Joan’s
                    experience includes a large number of trials so the Law of Large Numbers would
                    suggest that the theoretical and empirical probabilities should be similar.
                    Since these numbers are not too similar, it would not be appropriate to use
                    Joan’s experience as evidence that the die is fair. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The theoretical probability of rolling a 2 is 1/4 = 25%, while
                    Joan’s experience has the relative frequency at 187/2,000 = 9.35%, which is quite
                    different. Joan’s experience includes a large number of trials so the Law of
                    Large Numbers would suggest that the theoretical and empirical probabilities
                    should be similar. Therefore, her experience does call into question the die as
                    possibly not being fair. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. With 2,000 trials, Joan’s experience includes a large number of
                    trials so the Law of Large Numbers would suggest that the theoretical and
                    empirical probabilities should be similar. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While knowing the number of times other numbers appeared would
                    potentially add additional ways in which the die may not be fair, it is not
                    necessary to know the other values to make a conclusion. With 2,000 trials,
                    Joan’s experience includes a large number of trials so the Law of Large Numbers
                    would suggest that the theoretical and empirical probabilities should be
                    similar. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
