<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="def_prob_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_def_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>There are 40 students in a course: 15 freshmen, 8 sophomores, 12 juniors, and 5
                seniors. One student is selected at random to attend a workshop and report back to
                the class. What is the probability that the chosen student is a junior?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">12% </choice>
            <choice value="B">30% </choice>
            <choice value="C">40% </choice>
            <choice value="D">50% </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 12 juniors
                    in the course. However, to find the probability of selecting a junior, we also
                    need to take into account the total number of students in the course.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since there are 12 juniors in the course out of a total of 40
                    students, the probability of selecting one is 12/40 = 30% </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 40 students
                    in the course. However, to find the probability of selecting a junior, we also
                    need to take into account the number of juniors in the course. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because the chosen student is
                    either a junior or not - but these two possibilities are not equally likely.
                    Note that there are 12 juniors out of 40 students in the course. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_def_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>There are 40 students in a course: 15 freshmen, 8 sophomores, 12 juniors and 5
                seniors. One student is selected at random to attend a workshop and report back to
                the class. What is the probability that the chosen student is a sophomore?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">8% </choice>
            <choice value="B">20% </choice>
            <choice value="C">40% </choice>
            <choice value="D">50% </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 8
                    sophomores in the course. However, to find the probability of selecting a
                    sophomore, we also need to take into account the total number of students in the
                    course. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since there are 8 sophomores in the course out of a total of 40
                    students, the probability of selecting one is 8/40 = 20%. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 40 students
                    in the course. However, to find the probability of selecting a sophomore, we
                    also need to take into account the number of sophomores in the course.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because the chosen student
                    either is or is not a sophomore, but these two possibilities are not equally likely.
                    Note that there are 8 sophomores out of 40 students in the course. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_def_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>An urn contains 22 marbles consisting of 10 red marbles, 7 blue marbles, and 5 yellow
                marbles. What is the probability of randomly selecting a blue marble from the urn?
                Some answers have been rounded to the nearest percentage.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">7% </choice>
            <choice value="B">22% </choice>
            <choice value="C">32% </choice>
            <choice value="D">50% </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 7 blue
                    marbles. However, to find the probability of selecting a blue marble we also
                    need to take into account the total number of marbles in the urn. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 22 marbles
                    in the drawer. However, to find the probability of selecting a blue marble we
                    also need to take into account the number of blue marbles in the urn.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since there were 7 blue marbles out of the 22 in the urn, the
                    probability of selecting one is 7/22 = 32%. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because the marble selected
                    either is or is not blue, but these two possibilities are not equally likely. Note
                    that there are 7 blue marbles and 15 not-blue marbles. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_def_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>An urn contains 22 marbles consisting of 10 red marbles, 7 blue marbles, and 5 yellow
                marbles. What is the probability of randomly selecting a red marble from the urn?
                Some answers have been rounded to the nearest percentage.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">10% </choice>
            <choice value="B">22% </choice>
            <choice value="C">45% </choice>
            <choice value="D">50% </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 10 red
                    marbles. However, to find the probability of selecting a red marble we also need
                    to take into account the total number of marbles in the urn. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because there are 22 marbles
                    in the drawer. However, to find the probability of selecting a red marble we
                    also need to take into account the number of red marbles in the urn. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since there were 10 red marbles out of the 22 in the urn, the
                    probability of selecting one is 10/22 = 45%.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because the marble selected
                    either is or is not red, but these two possibilities are not equally likely. Note
                    that there are 10 red marbles and 12 marbles that are not red. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
