<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="estimate_prob_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_estimate_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Suppose that P(A) = 0.99. Which of the following is the best interpretation of this
                statement?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Event A will always occur. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Event A will occur more often than not, but it is not extremely
                likely. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Event A is extremely likely, but in a long sequence of trials, it occasionally will not occur.<!--Event A is extremely likely, but it will not occur once in awhile in
                a long sequence of trials.--></choice>
            <choice value="D">Event A will never occur. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event will always occur only if its probability is 1. Here,
                    P(A) = 0.99, which means that the event will almost always occur, but after
                    numerous repetitions, the event occasionally will not occur.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that if P(A) = 0.99, then it will occur more often
                    than not. However, it is incorrect that it is not extremely likely. P(A) = 0.99
                    is very close to 1, which indicates that event A is extremely likely, but after
                    numerous repetitions, the event occasionally will not occur. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since P(A) = 0.99 is very close to 1, then event A is extremely
                    likely. In other words, event A will almost always occur, but occasionally, in a long sequence of trials, it will not occur.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event will never occur if its probability is 0. Here,
                    P(A) = 0.99 which is means that the event will almost always occur, but after
                    numerous repetitions, the event occasionally will not occur. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_estimate_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Suppose that P(A) = 0.30. Which of the following is the best interpretation of this
                statement?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Event A will always occur. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Event A will occur less often than not, but it is not extremely
                unlikely. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Event A is extremely unlikely, but it will occur once in awhile in a
                long sequence of trials.</choice>
            <choice value="D">Event A will never occur. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event will always occur only if its probability is 1. Here,
                    P(A) = 0.30 which is means that event A will not frequently occur. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since P(A) = 0.30 is less the 0.50, event A will occur less often
                    than not. Since the probability of 0.30 is not very close to 0, event A is not
                    extremely unlikely. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that since P(A) = 0.30 is less than 0.50, it will
                    not frequently occur. However, an event that occurs 30% of the time is not
                    highly unlikely.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event will never occur only if its probability is 0. Here,
                    P(A) = 0.30 which means that event A will not frequently occur. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_estimate_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following valid probabilities represents an event that is
                impossible?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">−1 </choice>
            <choice value="B">0 </choice>
            <choice value="C">0.0001</choice>
            <choice value="D">1</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. By definition probabilities can not be less than zero or more
                    than one so this is not a <em style="italic">valid</em> probability. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. An event with a probability of 0 is impossible: it cannot
                    happen! </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this choice because the probability is
                    very small. However, the event is still possible (while very unlikely) if the
                    probability is 0.0001. Note that the event described is <em style="italic">impossible</em>. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event with probability 1 is an event that is certain, that
                    is, it <em style="italic">always</em> happens. Note that the event described is
                        <em style="italic">impossible</em>. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_estimate_prob" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following probabilities could describe an event that is likely but not
                certain?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">0.2 </choice>
            <choice value="B">0.5 </choice>
            <choice value="C">0.8</choice>
            <choice value="D">1</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event with a probability of 0.2 is less likely to happen
                    than one with an even chance (50-50), so it could not describe a likely
                    event.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. An event with a probability of 0.5 is equally likely to happen
                    or not happen, so it would not be a good way to describe an event which is
                    likely.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. An event with probability more than 0.5 and less than 1 is
                    considered to be likely. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have selected this answer because an event with
                    probability 1 is certain, but the question specifies that the event is not
                    certain. There is a better answer. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
