<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_CMIR_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>B cells are capable of making antibody when exposed directly to an antigen. However, the process works better if the antigen is presented to the B cell by another cell that also expresses the correct MHC proteins. What could the antigen presenting cells be?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Cytotoxic T cells</choice><choice value="B">Dendritic cells</choice><choice value="C">Macrophages</choice><choice value="D">Helper T cell</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_CMIR_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Cytotoxic T cells kill pathogens or abnormal somatic cells.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Dendritic cells are involved with the innate response.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Macrophages may present antigen but the do not present it to B cells.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Helper T cells boost the naive B cell response to an antigen.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Why does immunological memory occur?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">T cells and B cells which have become specialized for antigenic response live forever.</choice><choice value="B">Our brain remembers what we have encountered before and tells the cells of the immune system what to do.</choice><choice value="C">When your immune system encounters a new antigen in addition to creating effector cells it also creates some memory cells which are capable of clonal expansion at a later time.</choice><choice value="D">We maintain circulating levels of antibodies against every antigen we have ever encountered.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_CMIR_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. T and B cells do not live forever although memory cells may live for years.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. You brain does not become involved in your immune response.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Part of an initial immune reaction is to create memory cells which can respond upon later exposure to the same antigen.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Cytotoxic T cells and NK cells both result in the death of a cell the body may find threatening. What is the biggest difference?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">NK cells are found in your body and Cytotoxic T cells come from transplants.</choice><choice value="B">Cytotoxic T cells are part of cell-mediated immunity and work on pathogen infected cells. NK cells are believed to be part of tumor surveillance.</choice><choice value="C">NK cells are not lymphocytes.</choice><choice value="D">Necrotic cell death happens with Cytotoxic T cells.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_distinguish_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Cytotoxic T cells are part of your normal immune arsenal.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both cells pick up cells that have abnormal markers on their cells surfaces, but they seem to be targeting different types of markers.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. NK cells are lymphocytes.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Cytotoxic T cells are capable of initiating a controlled sequence of events in the cell which result in cell death.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
