<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_CMIR_digt3"><title>tutor</title><page id="cc68934813c34718a7b8d2599bac3b4a"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="d64af4ee22e140fb9fcbd1a5ba2a5a03">Which of the following sequences are ordered correctly in the cell-mediated immune response to an exogenous antigen?</p><p id="fa7a4739d857492295ffbaa827bc3975">1. costimulation of B7 on APC and CD28 on helper T cells</p><p id="e9ba53ad804041cfbf56f54257ef7830">2. presentation of antigen by APC, and recognition of antigen fragments associated with class I MHC/epitope by CD8 and T-cell receptor on naïve cytotoxic T cell</p><p id="f305ccc0412644e0aaf5af8b192a8d39">3. elimination of pathogen through the release of granzymes, perforin, and granulysin, that leads to cell death</p><p id="d0586fdcbb134148a6bccdde3b446946">4. proliferation and differentiation of helper T cell to produce clones of functional helper T cells and memory helper T cells</p><p id="a193dd73ac074a6ca710bcffea3f2b65">5. antigen processing and presentation by dendritic cell</p><p id="cce95b7ad8b1454babcf2f7eedf366e6">6. presentation of antigen by APC, and recognition of antigen fragments associated with class II MHC/epitope by CD4 and T-cell receptor on naïve helper T cell</p><p id="a8d26f0232bf40b2a4caf4459fb62aff">7. secretion of cytokines, such as interleukin-2, by activated helper T cells</p><p id="a28e0aa0af74427db376ad9ba90641df">8. migration of dendritic cell to lymphatic tissue to act as an APC</p><p id="a20a1876c8ce4733a184dbdb0347ab13">9. costimulation of B7 on APC and IL-2 from helper T cells</p><p id="cd5d2fb88bb948c3bc0919e32e64a46e">10. proliferation and differentiation of cytotoxic T cell to produce clones of functional cytotoxic T cells and memory cytotoxic T cells</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="b15a19cc00db45ebb4a439dd6979db7d" labels="false"><choice value="A">5, 8, 2, 1, 4, 7, 6, 9, 10, 3</choice><choice value="B">8, 5, 2, 1, 4, 7, 6, 9, 10, 3</choice><choice value="C">5, 8, 6, 9, 10, 3, 2, 1, 4, 7</choice><choice value="D">5, 8, 6, 1, 4, 7, 2, 9, 10, 3</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_CMIR2_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab6ef0a4fe93b4afaab8f2c31ceb45448">Incorrect. Bbefore costimulation and activation of a naïve helper T cell, two things must occur: presentation of antigen by APC; and recognition of antigen fragments associated with class II MHC/epitope by CD4 and T-cell receptor on naïve helper T cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aac10a7cbadd247a98f2af3ade7937b66">Incorrect. The dendritic cell processes and presents antigen before it micrates to the lymphatic tissue to act as an APC.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae8c84b5505304a1b8a45a8930f9518fd">Incorrect. Helper T cells need to be activated before a cytotoxic T cell. Cytotoxic T cells need the costimulation of IL-2 secreted by the helper T cells before they can become activated.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="af6429aa48d744aa28d62a07d2474690c">Correct. Antigens need to be processed by an APC and presented in the context of the self-antigens. Then a naive T-helper cell can become activated and in turn activate cytotoxic T cells.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page><page id="c744081858114985904a1fd2db6b4558"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q2"><body><p id="aa56a729a595b4a168b56a260220aea47">According to the graph of the production of antibodies in the primary and secondary responses to a given antigen, what features of a secondary immune response distinguish it from a primary immune response.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="dadf6115b95e4684975c852eea2d5156" labels="false"><choice value="A">The response of circulating IgG is more rapid and robust with nearly 1000 fold the primary peak of IgG. IgG antibody levels continued to be elevated for greater than two weeks.</choice><choice value="B">The response is the same except for the 1000 fold increase in IgG.</choice><choice value="C">The response if IgM is the same, however, IgG levels quadrupled in the secondary response. The two immune responses developed at about the same rates.</choice><choice value="D">During the initial primary exposure, IgG is the most prominent antibody secreted. The second and all subsequent times that the adaptive immune system encounters this same antigen, the immune response will only take 1–3 days to reach its maximal level and IgM is the prominent antibody secreted.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_CMIR2_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="af59333afebcc43979bf535587ae469f4">Correct.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad9b1dff708b449ed92f727b4ead1ac24">Incorrect. Notice the primary response took 7 days for IgG to begin to rise, and 14 days to reach its peak. IgG began to rise within days for the secondary response.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae43297ebecc8411aa05d2a4c63d55cac">Incorrect. It is true the IgM response appears to be the same in both immune responses, however, IgG appeared more rapidly and nearly 1000 times greater in the secondary response. IgG also remained in the titer longer.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab8a1ef9a468d48fa992252bca12eb11f">Incorrect. IgM is the prominent antibody secreted in the primary response, and IgG is the prominent antibody in the secondary response.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
