<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_phases_cardiac_cycle_DIGT2-6-9"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The sounds heard during auscultation (collecting information by listening) of the heart are commonly described as a “lub-dub” sound that is repeated. But because the sounds occur in a repeated fashion (lub-dub, lub-dub, lub-dub), you might expect that health care workers could become confused and think that two sounds from different cardiac cycles (dub-lub) are from the same heart beat. What is most likely to prevent this confusion from happening? </body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">The sounds are very distinct, clearly sounding different from one another.</choice><choice value="b">The sounds are close together in time, then a pause, and then the combination of sounds again.</choice><choice value="c">The sounds are heard from different areas of the chest, so that the “lub” is heard from one region, and the “dub” from another.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="relate_heart_sounds_cardiac_cycle_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although some people can distinguish between the two sounds, others interpret the sounds to be very similar.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The second heart sound occurs soon after the first in most people. Then there is a longer pause before the heart sounds from the next cardiac cycle are heard.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the combination might be heard best from one region of the chest or another, the stethoscope is typically held in one place to listen to both sounds. Then the stethoscope may be moved to listen again.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
