<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="relate_CO_HR_SV_LBD2-g"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Refer to the following diagram to answer this set of questions. <image src="../webcontent/diagram_LBD2-g.jpg" /><p>What is the end diastolic volume of this person?</p></body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">50 mL</choice><choice value="b">115 mL</choice><choice value="c">130 mL</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="define_EDV_ESV_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. 50 mL is the volume in the ventricle at the end of contraction, not before.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. But this is the volume in the ventricle after the passive filling phase of diastole. Active filling (atrial diastole) still needs to take place.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. There is 130 mL of blood in the ventricle at the end of diastole.</feedback></response><hint>Evaluate the position of the Ventricular volume line at the end of diastole.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What is the end systolic volume of this person?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">50 mL</choice><choice value="b">115 mL</choice><choice value="c">130 mL</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="define_EDV_ESV_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. At the end of systole there is 50 mL left in the ventricle.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. But this value is obtained while the ventricle is filling, not right after the ventricle ejects.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect, this is the end diastolic volume.</feedback></response><hint>Evaluate the position of the ventricular volume line at the end of systole.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>What is the stroke volume in this person?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">50 mL</choice><choice value="b">65 mL</choice><choice value="c">80 mL</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="define_cardiac_output_stroke_vol_heart_rate_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the end systolic volume in this person.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although this is a typical stroke volume, it is not the correct answer in this scenario.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Stroke volume is the EDV – ESV, which in this case is 130 mL – 50 mL = 80 mL</feedback></response><hint>The stroke volume is the difference between the end diastolic volume (EDV) and the end systolic volume (ESV).</hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body>If this person has a heart rate of 70 beats per minute, what is their cardiac output?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">5 liters/min</choice><choice value="b">3.5 liters/min</choice><choice value="c">5.6 liters/min</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="define_cardiac_output_stroke_vol_heart_rate_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although this is a typical value, it is not the correct answer in this scenario.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In order for this to be the correct answer for this HR, the stroke volume would have to be 50 ml (70 beats/min x 50 mL/beat = 3500 mL/min = 3.5 L/min).</feedback></response><response match="c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Cardiac output is heart rate (HR) x stroke volume (SV), so 70 beats/min x 80 mL/beat = 5600 mL/min.</feedback></response><hint>Consider the relationship of cardiac output to heart rate and stroke volume.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
