<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u11_m2_review">
    
    <head>
        <title>Respiratory Structures and Functions Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        
        <p>The upper respiratory tract begins with the nose. As the air passes posteriorly through the nasal cavity, it enters the pharynx. This 
            structure encompasses three distinct areas and connects the nasal passage to the larynx in the throat.
            The paired pharyngeal tonsils, also known as the adenoids, lie in the posterior wall of the nasopharynx. The other tonsils, the tubal 
            tonsils, protect the auditory tubes and middle ear against entering microorganism. After air leaves the pharynx, it enters the larynx, 
            a complex structure that extends from the laryngopharynx and the hyoid bone to the trachea. </p>
        
        <p>The lower respiratory tract starts at the trachea. The bronchial tree is so named because it resembles a tree that has been turned
            upside-down. The trachea would be the trunk, the progressively smaller bronchi and bronchioles are the branches, and the alveoli are
            the leaves. Branching of the trachea into the right and left primary bronchi occurs after the last cartilage in the trachea at the level
            of the seventh thoracic vertebrae. </p>
        
        <p>The lungs are two of the largest organs of the body, but they are among the lightest. Along with the heart, the lungs take up nearly all 
            of the space in the thorax, superior to the diaphragm. As an organ, the lung is made up of airway tubes and alveoli, giving it little weight.
            The lungs have a dual blood supply. The pulmonary artery brings oxygen-poor blood from the right ventricle of the heart. This blood passes 
            through the pulmonary capillaries, where some carbon dioxide will leave the blood and a large amount of oxygen will be acquired. The newly 
            oxygenated blood enters the pulmonary veins and returns back to the left side of heart. Each lung is found in a pleural cavity bounded by the pleural membrane, 
            a double sided membrane that contains a thin layer of pleural fluid.</p>
        
        <p>Make sure you understand the mechanisms of respiratory function, pulmonary ventilation, and  respiratory volumes (IRV, TV, ERV, and RV) and the 
            respiratory capacities (IC, FRC, VC, and TLC)..</p>
        <!--  Quiz  --> 
        <activity idref="respiratory_structures_functions_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
    </body>
    
</workbook_page>

