<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_2_4.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_assessment_2_3.css"?>
<assessment id="_u3_m1_checkpoint1" max_attempts="3" recommended_attempts="1">
    <title>Sampling Checkpoint</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you
            are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window
            will ask "This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?",
            click "OK" if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p>
        <p>If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost.
            After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to
            be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p>
    </introduction>
    <!--<content available="instructor_only">
        <p><em>Instructors: you can download the solution set for this checkpoint by clicking on the
                following link:</em>
            <link href="../webcontent/_u3_m1_checkpoint1.pdf">Solution Set</link>.</p>
    </content>-->
    <multiple_choice id="pd3" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>When conducting a survey, which of the following is the most important reason to use
                a <em style="italic">random</em> sample?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">To get a significant result</choice>
            <choice value="B">To avoid bias and to get a representative sample</choice>
            <choice value="C">So that we can make causal conclusions</choice>
            <choice value="D">To ensure truthful answers to the survey's questions</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback> Incorrect. A random sample does not guarantee a <em style="italic">significant</em> result, it
                    guarantees a <em style="italic">representative</em> result. Although randomness is a necessary
                    part of any study that produces significant results, it is not the most
                    important reason for random selection.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Random selection ensures that the sample is
                        <em style="italic">unbiased</em> on average, so that the results of the study can be
                    generalized to the population. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Random selection is not what allows us to determine
                    causation; that would be ensured only by random <em>assignment</em> to
                    treatments.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The truthfulness of the subjects is not affected one way or the
                    other by the way the subjects were selected.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd4" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>In order to obtain a sample of undergraduate students in the United States, a simple
                random sample of 10 states is selected. From each of the selected states, 10
                colleges or universities are chosen at random. Finally, from each of these 100
                colleges or universities, a simple random sample of 20 undergraduate students is
                selected. Thus, the final sample consists of 2,000 undergraduates. </p>
            <p>This is an example of which type of sampling strategy?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Simple random sampling</choice>
            <choice value="B">Stratified sampling</choice>
            <choice value="C">Multistage sampling</choice>
            <choice value="D">Convenience sampling</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that a <em style="italic">simple</em> random sample of undergraduates
                    would have selected directly from the pool of undergraduates, without first
                    selecting states or colleges.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that <em style="italic">stratified</em> sampling of undergraduates
                    would have initially viewed the nation’s undergrads as being separated into
                    "strata" according to some feature. It wouldn’t have involved any initial
                    selection of states or universities.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is an example of multistage sampling, because first a sample
                    of a few states was selected, and then in each of those states another sample of
                    a few universities was selected, and finally in each of those universities a
                    sample of a few students was selected. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">convenience</em> sample of undergrads would have selected
                    directly from undergrads (without first selecting states or colleges), and it
                    would have been only from students conveniently nearby (so it would not have
                    involved random selection from the whole nation).</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd7" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>The faculty senate at a large university wanted to know what proportion of the
                students thought foreign language classes should be required for everyone. The
                statistics department offered to cooperate in conducting a survey, and a simple
                random sample of 500 students was selected from all the students enrolled in
                statistics classes. A survey form was sent by email to these 500 students. </p>
            <p>In this case, which of the following is the population of interest?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">All students at the university</choice>
            <choice value="B">All students enrolled in a statistics class</choice>
            <choice value="C">The 500 students who got the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="D">The students who responded to the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="E">All students who think that foreign language classes should be
                required for everyone</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The faculty senate wanted to know what proportion <em style="italic">of the
                        students</em> supported the proposal. The senate put no restriction on
                    their group of interest, so they want to gauge the opinion of all students at
                    the university.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that only statistics students were
                        <em style="italic">surveyed</em>, that wasn’t the group that the faculty senate wanted
                    information about.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the sample of students who were sent the survey. A
                        <em style="italic">sample</em> isn’t the same thing as a <em style="italic">population</em>. The
                    population is the large group whose opinion the faculty senate wanted to
                    gauge.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the sample of students who completed the survey. A
                        <em style="italic">sample</em> isn’t the same thing as a <em style="italic">population</em>. The
                    population is the large group whose opinion the faculty senate wanted to
                    gauge.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. If the senate only got replies from the students who
                        <em style="italic">support</em> the proposal, there wouldn’t be any way to gauge what
                    fraction of the student body that might be. In that case, every student in the
                    study would be guaranteed to say yes. But remember that, in any study, the
                    response has to be able to <em style="italic">vary</em> from person to person.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd8" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>The faculty senate at a large university wanted to know what proportion of the
                students thought foreign language classes should be required for everyone. The
                statistics department offered to cooperate in conducting a survey, and a simple
                random sample of 500 students was selected from all the students enrolled in
                statistics classes. A survey form was sent by email to these 500 students. </p>
            <p>Which of the following is the appropriate sampling frame in this scenario?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">All students at the university</choice>
            <choice value="B">All students enrolled in a statistics class</choice>
            <choice value="C">The 500 students who got the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="D">The students who responded to the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="E">All students who think that foreign language classes should be
                required for everyone</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that the faculty senate wants
                    information about all students at the university, notice that the study doesn’t
                    select from among that group. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of
                    potential individuals from which the sample gets selected. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of potential individuals
                    from which the sample gets selected. In this case, that list is restricted to
                    students enrolled in a statistics class. This is an example in which the
                    sampling frame does not match the population that the faculty senate wants
                    information about. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> isn’t the same thing as the
                        <em style="italic">sample</em>. It is the list of potential
                    individuals from which the sample gets selected. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of potential
                    individuals from which the sample gets selected. In this case, the sampling
                    frame would be the list of students from which the 500 were selected to receive
                    the survey.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of potential
                    individuals from which the sample gets selected. Notice that the survey could be
                    sent to some students who don’t support the proposal.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd9" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>The faculty senate at a large university wanted to know what proportion of the
                students thought foreign language classes should be required for everyone. The
                statistics department offered to cooperate in conducting a survey, and a simple
                random sample of 500 students was selected from all the students enrolled in
                statistics classes. A survey form was sent by email to these 500 students. </p>
            <p>True or false? Even though the sample is random, it is not representative of the
                population of interest.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">True</choice>
            <choice value="B">False</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although the 500 survey recipients were selected randomly from
                    a larger sampling frame, there are two reasons this study is not representative
                    of the population of interest: (1) The sampling frame was only students in
                    statistics (so the sampling frame didn’t match the population of interest), and
                    (2) returning the survey was voluntary (so the study results were potentially
                    biased and thus not representative, even of just statistics
                    students).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Although the 500 survey recipients were selected randomly from
                    some larger sampling frame, the study is not representative of the intended
                    population of all students at the university because (1) the sampling frame was
                    only students in statistics (so the sampling frame didn’t match the population
                    of interest), and (2) returning the survey was voluntary (so the study results
                    were potentially biased and thus not representative, even of just statistics
                    students).</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd11" select="single">
        <body>
            <p><em style="italic">Ross Times</em>, the student newspaper of Ross College, printed a
                "What do you think?" column feature asking, "Do you think that the college is doing
                enough to provide student parking?" Anyone could mail in a response or use the
                paper's Web site to respond. In all, 126 answers were received. </p>
            <p>This is an example of what type of sample?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">A voluntary response sample</choice>
            <choice value="B">A multistage sample</choice>
            <choice value="C">A simple random sample</choice>
            <choice value="D">A convenience sample</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The response was voluntary, since the only responses that were
                    recorded were from students who <em style="italic">decided on their own</em> to voice an
                    opinion. This means the survey result could be <em style="italic">biased</em>, because it only
                    represents the opinions of those students who, for whatever reason, <!--bothered-->chose to
                    write a response rather than fairly reflecting the opinion of the whole
                    college. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">multistage</em> sample <!--would be when there was-->involves more than
                    one level of selection. In this story, there was only a single level of
                    selection, at the level of individual students (who decided to voice an
                    opinion), rather than, for instance, first selecting certain classrooms or
                    first selecting certain types of students, such as athletes or
                    freshmen.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Notice that the students who voiced an opinion were not
                    selected by the newspaper using any randomized method. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although the survey method was probably relatively convenient
                    for the newspaper, it was not a <em style="italic">convenience sample</em>because the students
                    were not all selected from any certain location that would have happened to suit
                    the needs of the researcher.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="pd17" select="single">
        <body> Which of the following is an example of stratified sampling? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; A sample of 351 people called a radio show to express
                their opinions about the verdict in a murder trial. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; In order to assess students' satisfaction with the food
                establishment on campus, the first 50 students who came out of the student center
                were interviewed. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; A poll asked a random sample of 1,112 adults whether
                they believe that the use of marijuana for medical reasons should be legalized. </choice>
            <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; A health educator wanted to study the sleeping habits of
                the undergraduate students in her university. For her study, the researcher chose a
                simple random sample of size 150 from each of the classes (150 freshmen, 150
                sophomores, 150 juniors, and 150 seniors) for a total of 600 sampled students. </choice>
            <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; The human resources department of a large bank wanted to
                assess the job satisfaction of the bank's workers. The department chose four of the
                bank's branches at random and used all of the workers in those four branches as the
                subjects for the study. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a simple <em style="italic">voluntary</em> sample.
                    There is no indication that the population of listeners was viewed as divided
                    into separate strata according to some feature.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a simple <em style="italic">convenience</em> sample.
                    There is no indication that the population of students was viewed as divided
                    into separate strata according to some feature.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a <em style="italic">simple random</em> sample. There
                    is no indication that the population of adults was viewed as divided into
                    separate strata according to some feature, and no attempt was made to
                    intentionally select a few people from separate strata of adults.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The researcher viewed the students as being divided into four
                    separate strata (freshmen, sophomores, juniors, and seniors), and a few
                    students from each stratum were selected. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a <em style="italic">cluster</em> sample. Remember that in
                    stratified sampling, the population is viewed as divided into separate strata
                    according to some feature, and then a few <em style="italic">people</em> (not strata) are
                    selected from each stratum (not from only some of the
                    strata).</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</assessment>
