<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Protein Synthesis" movieroot="">
<step stepURL="swfs/structure.swf" menustep="tRNA Structures">
          <text>&lt;html&gt; The biosynthesis of proteins involves translation of the information contained in the mRNA into a polypeptide sequence. Each triplet of bases in the mRNA encodes one amino acid.  The translation is accomplished by the ribosome with the use of specialized RNA molecules called transfer RNA, or tRNA.  The tRNA molecules bind to the mRNA and deliver the correct amino acid to the growing polypeptide chain. 
        
        During this tutorial you will learn about the structure of tRNA molecules, how the correct amino acid become associated with each tRNA, and how the tRNAs act in concert with the Ribosome to synthesize a polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="swfs/primary.swf" menustep="   Primary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The primary structure of a tRNA is a linear polymer of ribonucleic acid containing approximately 70 nucleotide bases.  The 3' end of the tRNA contains the nucleotide sequence CCA, which is shown in black. The last base of this sequence will be joined to an amino acid during charging of the tRNA. If you hit the play button the tRNA will fold from its primary structure to its secondary structure, the traditional cloverleaf shape. Note the anticodon loop in the lower part of the diagram. This part of the rRNA binds to one codon in the mRNA.  &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="swfs/secondary.swf" menustep="   Secondary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The secondary structure of the tRNA is stabilized by hydrogen bonds between the anti-parallel strands as well as base stacking interactions, forming short helices of type A RNA that are similar in structure to the double helix in DNA.   By pressing the play button, you can see how the tRNA folds from its secondary structure into a complex tertiary structure. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>      
<step stepURL="swfs/tertiary.swf" menustep="   Tertiary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The biosynthesis of proteins involves translation of the information contained in the mRNA into a polypeptide sequence. Each triplet of bases in the mRNA encodes one amino acid.  The translation is accomplished by the ribosome with the use of specialized RNA molecules called transfer RNA, or tRNA.  The tRNA molecules bind to the mRNA and deliver the correct amino acid to the growing polypeptide chain. 
        
        During this tutorial you will learn about the structure of tRNA molecules, how the correct amino acid become associated with each tRNA, and how the tRNAs act in concert with the Ribosome to synthesize a polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
    <step stepURL="swfs_bc/charging.swf" menustep="Charging tRNAs">
        <text>
            &lt;html&gt;The correct charging of tRNAs by the 20 aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (aa-RS) is essential to the cell because once it is attached to a tRNA, an amino acid will be incorporated into protein strictly on the basis of the codon-anticodon interaction at the ribosome.
This animation shows: 
1. the basic steps of Met charging; and 
2. how the tRNAIle synthetase achieves an error frequency 1/10,000 even though the charging and hydrolysis steps are only about 99% accurate.&lt;/html&gt;  
        </text>
    </step>
    <step  menustep="   Met-tRNA with Met" stepURL="swfs/charging_met.swf">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;When fatty acids or phospholipids are added to water they self-assemble into aggregates such that the charged or polar heads groups make contact with the water and the hydrophobic hydrocarbon tails are restricted to water-free areas. In the case of fatty acids and other detergent like molecules, they will orient at an air-water interface such that the non-polar tails project into the air. In addition, some fatty acids will enter the water and spontaneously form single shelled structures called micelles.
            
Click the play button to advance through the scenes.&lt;html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step menustep="   Ile-tRNA with Ile" stepURL="swfs/charging_ile.swf">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;This synthetase has two active sites:
1.  Aminoacylation site where isoleucine is attached to tRNAIle  with the release of AMP + PPi.
2.  Editing site where any mischarged aminoacyl-tRNAIle are hydrolyzed with the release of the tRNA and the incorrect amino acid.
            
The aminoacylation site is complementary to Ile in size, shape, and polarity.  Hence, Ile binding in the first step is favored over any other amino acid by .>100-fold.
The newly attached Ile is next passed to the editing site where it does not bind because it is too large.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step  menustep="   Ile-tRNA with Val" stepURL="swfs/charging_va.swf">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Valine is similar to Ile in shape and polarity, but is smaller by one methyl group.  
Valine binds and is mischarged onto tRNAIle at about 1% the rate of Ile charging.
The newly attached Val is next passed to the editing site where because of its size, it does bind.  Since the mischarged val-tRNAIle  fits into this site, it is hydrolyzed.  Both the tRNAIle and separated Val dissociate.  The editing reaction is >99% efficient.
Thus, the overall, fidelity of charging tRNAIle  with Ile vs Val is the product of the accuracy for each step: 99.99%.&lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step menustep="   Ile-tRNA with Phe" stepURL="swfs/charging_phe.swf">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Discriminating against larger amino acids such as Phe, Try, Trp, is a simpler matter.  As shown, the Phe R-group is too large to fit into the aminoacylation site.  In general, cases of steric clash are far more unfavorable (+DG) than is the loss of favorable (-DG) interactions for a smaller group.&lt;/html&gt;</text>
    </step>   
<step stepURL="swfs/ribo1.swf" menustep="Ribosome Structure">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The ribosome is an enormous particle composed of both ribosomal RNA (rRNA) molecules as well as many different proteins.  The ribosome normally exists as separate 30s and 50s subunits, however during translation both of these subunits  become associated to form a 70s particle. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/ribo2.swf" menustep="   3 Sites">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;There are three sites on the 70S ribosome that bind tRNAs:
            A: The amino-acyl site binds tRNA charged with the next amino acid that is to be added to the growing chain. This site also contains the growing peptide at one point in the elongation cycle.
            P: The peptidyl site contains a tRNA with the growing peptide chain attached to it.
            E: The exit site briefly holds the uncharged tRNA before it is released from the ribosome.  &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>   
    <step stepURL="swfs/polypeptide.swf" menustep="Building a Polypeptide">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;This animation depicts the stages of translation (protein synthesis) in prokaryotic organisms. The basic steps are the same in eukaryotic organism. The actual synthesis of a polypeptide involves three distinct phases:
            &lt;b&gt;Initiation:&lt;/b&gt; The mRNA, f-Met charged tRNA, and the 30s subunit form an initiation complex.  This complex then recruits the 50s subunit to form the 70s particle.
            &lt;b&gt;Elongation:&lt;/b&gt; Additional amino acids are added to the growing polypeptide chain.
            &lt;b&gt;Termination:&lt;/b&gt; The presence of a stop codon in the mRNA signals termination of the process and release of the completed polypeptide chain.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation1.swf" menustep="   Initiation 1">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Formation of the 30S initiation complex starts with the mRNA, an &lt;b&gt;Initiation Factor&lt;/b&gt; and the small (30S) subunit of the ribosome. In prokaryotic organisms the alignment for specific binding of the mRNA to the small (30S) subunit of the ribosome is accomplished through the recognition of the &lt;b&gt;Shine-Dalgarno sequence&lt;/b&gt; on the mRNA and coordinate binding with an initiation factor.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation2.swf" menustep="   Initiation 2">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;GTP hydrolysis provides the energy for the binding of the fMet-tRNA complex through its anti-codon sequence to the complementary start codon on the mRNA that is bound to the 30S subunit of the ribosome. This is accompanied by the loss of the initiation factor. This completes the formation of the &lt;b&gt;"30S initiation complex"&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation3.swf" menustep="   Initiation 3">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The initiation factors function to prevent the association of the large (50S) and small (30S) subunits of the ribosome when translation is not occurring With the loss of the initiation factor in the previous step, the 50S ribosomal subunit joins the complex to form the &lt;b&gt;"70S initiation complex"&lt;/b&gt;. The fMet-tRNA is hydrogen bonded to the start codon on the mRNA and occupies the P or peptidyl site on the 70S complex. This complex is now ready to bind the second charged aminoacyl-tRNA.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/elongation1.swf" menustep="   Elongation 1">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Using energy from the hydrolysis of GTP, the second charged tRNA whose anticodon is complementary to the second triplet codon on the message (mRNA) binds to the mRNA and occupies the A (Aminoacyl-tRNA site or Acceptor site) on the 70S complex. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/elongation2.swf" menustep="   Elongation 2">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;With fMet-tRNA in the P site and the next charged aminoacyl-tRNA in the A site, peptidyl transfer occurs without any additional energy input, e.g. ATP or GTP hydrolysis. Peptidyl transfer involves exchange of the ester bond attaching the fMet amino acid to the fMet-tRNA in the P site to form a peptide bond with the alpha amino group of the amino acid attached to the charged aminoacyl-tRNA occupying the A site. After this process, the newly formed peptide chain is found in the A-site.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/elongation3.swf" menustep="   Elongation 3">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The next step involves the &lt;b&gt;translocation&lt;/b&gt; of the mRNA along the ribosome moving the newly formed peptide chain to the P site. Translocation requires the action of several specific proteins and the hydrolysis of GTP. The result is the movement of the newly-formed peptidyl-tRNA to the P-site and the corresponding movement of the uncharged tRNA to the E-site, from which it quickly dissociates. The complex now has an open A-site which binds the next charged-tRNA corresponding to the next triplet codon on the mRNA.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/elongation4.swf" menustep="   Elongation 4">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;This process continues until the stop signal is reached.  The addition of each amino acid requires the hydrolysis of two GTP molecules, one for loading of the charged tRNA and one for translocation, or moving, of the ribosome.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/termination1.swf" menustep="   Termination 1">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;A protein called the release factor binds to the stop codon on the mRNA.&lt;/html&gt;</text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/termination2.swf" menustep="   Termination 2">
        <text>The &lt;b&gt;release factor&lt;/b&gt; allows water to hydrolyze the bond between the finished peptide and the last tRNA molecule.  Then the entire complex dissociates, releasing the completed peptide.&lt;/html&gt;</text>
    </step>
</TUTORIAL>
