<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Protein Synthesis" movieroot="">
<step stepURL="swfs/structure.swf" menustep="tRNA Structures">
          <text>&lt;html&gt; The biosynthesis of proteins involves translation of the information contained in the mRNA into a polypeptide sequence. Each triplet of bases in the mRNA encodes one amino acid.  The translation is accomplished by the ribosome with the use of specialized RNA molecules called transfer RNA, or tRNA.  The tRNA molecules bind to the mRNA and deliver the correct amino acid to the growing polypeptide chain. 
        
        During this tutorial you will learn about the structure of tRNA molecules, how the correct amino acid become associated with each tRNA, and how the tRNAs act in concert with the Ribosome to synthesize a polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="swfs/primary.swf" menustep="   Primary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The primary structure of a tRNA is a linear polymer of ribonucleic acid containing approximately 70 nucleotide bases.  The 3' end of the tRNA contains the nucleotide sequence CCA, which is shown in black. The last base of this sequence will be joined to an amino acid during charging of the tRNA. If you hit the play button the tRNA will fold from its primary structure to its secondary structure, the traditional cloverleaf shape. Note the anticodon loop in the lower part of the diagram. This part of the rRNA binds to one codon in the mRNA.  &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       
<step stepURL="swfs/secondary.swf" menustep="   Secondary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The secondary structure of the tRNA is stabilized by hydrogen bonds between the anti-parallel strands as well as base stacking interactions, forming short helices of type A RNA that are similar in structure to the double helix in DNA.   By pressing the play button, you can see how the tRNA folds from its secondary structure into a complex tertiary structure. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>      
<step stepURL="swfs/tertiary.swf" menustep="   Tertiary">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The biosynthesis of proteins involves translation of the information contained in the mRNA into a polypeptide sequence. Each triplet of bases in the mRNA encodes one amino acid.  The translation is accomplished by the ribosome with the use of specialized RNA molecules called transfer RNA, or tRNA.  The tRNA molecules bind to the mRNA and deliver the correct amino acid to the growing polypeptide chain. 
        
        During this tutorial you will learn about the structure of tRNA molecules, how the correct amino acid become associated with each tRNA, and how the tRNAs act in concert with the Ribosome to synthesize a polypeptide chain. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
</step>       

</TUTORIAL>
