<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_3"><head><title>Immunity</title><objref idref="lymph_immunity_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_diseases_LO" /></head><body><section id="f72558f6f1424b46b8b869eca4c1ce75"><title>Historical Perspective and Overview of Immunity</title><body><p id="b614e12ed90841c08c7eed7eafaccff9">In relative terms, the study of immunity is a new science that started with Edward Jenner’s discovery in 1796, that individuals exposed to cowpox were often resistant to human smallpox. He also observed that people who had recovered from even a mild case of smallpox were seldom infected a second time. Jenner experimented with placing weakened (attenuated) strains of disease-causing agents into otherwise healthy individuals to provide protection from disease. He called his procedure vaccination. Adding to Jenner&apos;s work, in the 1880s, Robert Koch and Louis Pasteur showed that most infectious diseases were caused by microorganisms. Today it is generally accepted that these disease-causing agents (pathogens) may be microscopic like viruses, bacteria, protozoa and yeast or larger like molds and helminths. Scientists discovered a substance in the serum of vaccinated individuals, which they termed antibodies, that could bind to the pathogen that was used in the vaccination. It was shown that <em style="bold"><em style="italic">anti</em></em>bodies could be <em style="bold"><em style="italic">gen</em></em>erated against a variety of substances and the term <em style="bold">antigen </em>was created to describe these substances. As we will learn shortly, not all antigens stimulate the immune system to produce antibodies so a more general use of the term antigen refers to any substance capable of being recognized during the immune response.</p><image id="cba1a35da2cd477dbc4a4b16f4c6f5a8" src="../webcontent/image1.jpeg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption><p id="c4f01f2168ff41f0baf8c16a34de7028">by Gaston Mélingue <link href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fichier:Melingue_Jenner.jpg" target="new" internal="false">Edward Jenner vaccinating James Phipps, a boy of eight, on May 14, 1796</link>. Public domain.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ce2df501f3e3424487f97d3f6e20968f">Basically the immune system, as part of the lymphatic system, can be viewed as may subsystems constantly guarding its host against microbial invasion. These systems may be viewed both as an armory (chemical substances), with it tools and weapons, and as an army (cells) capable of using these tools and weapons in defense of the host. Immunity (resistance) has an <term>innate component </term>and an <term>adaptive component</term>. Both of these components depend on the responses of <term>white blood cells</term> (<term>leukocytes</term>).</p><p id="f55cb7c242864baabf5240f7b3135acc">Innate immunity is the natural resistance with which a person is born and is the result of actions of both external and internal systems. First lines of defense against infection include mechanical and chemical barriers, such as skin and saliva, the effectiveness of which is enhanced by antimicrobial substances. Microbes that succeed in passing the external barriers next encounter the second line of defense, the internal systems. The internal system includes antimicrobial substances and subsets of leukocytes called granulocytes and macrophages. Granulocytes contain an arsenal of cytoplasmic granules that can be released during an immune response. Several of these granulocytes and the macrophages are <term>phagocytic </term>which means they are able to ingest and destroy pathogens. They use <term>pattern-recognition receptors (PRRs) </term>to recognize pathogens. These receptors recognize and bind to molecules found on a wide variety of microbial cells and on damaged or infected host cells. Thus they recognize in a broad and general way the presence of harmful microbes and can quickly attack and usually prevent the spread of the microbes. In addition, the innate immune system includes <term>complement</term>, a set of soluble molecules that can bind to certain molecules common to microbial cells. This binding can lead to the direct destruction of the microbe and can also trigger increased activity of phagocytic cells against the microbe.</p><p id="af607b2e625b4263a14a27eed5e7a51c">A bridge between the innate and the adaptive components is the <term>inflammatory response</term>. Although many soluble factors, blood proteins and cells participate in this response, the main purpose of all of the factors is to enable phagocytic leukocytes and plasma components to leave the blood circulation and enter into damaged and/or infected tissues. The phagocytes in the tissue carry out an array of activities at the inflamed site, the main one being to rid the area of microorganisms and damaged tissue and thus to set the stage for healing. As will be described more completely in a later module, all events between the initial damage and the final restoration of the tissue may be considered parts of the inflammatory response.</p><p id="ca3232baaec04b4382e53beaaa1eb05b">Sometimes, however, the innate immune components cannot quickly eliminate the infectious agents especially viral infections. In such instances, cells of the innate system interact with <term>T lymphocytes</term> (<term>T cells</term>) and <term>B lymphocytes</term> (<term>B cells</term>) to initiate adaptive immune responses against the threatening pathogens. The lymphocytes of the adaptive immune response have receptors that are generated by random rearrangement of DNA segments. Such receptors are able to identify and bind a far greater range of substances than can be detected by the PRRS of the innate response. Lymphocytes can detect, with great specificity, threats and proliferate rapidly to act against them in a targeted manner.</p><p id="deac11eb00b84dec97ed3b7091e394cd">The interaction between the innate and adaptive immune responses begins when macrophages and dendritic cells process pathogens and display them in a way that leads to activation of a subset of T lymphocytes (<term>helper T cells</term>). The activated T helper cells can then interact with a variety of other cells, including another subset of T lymphocytes (<term>cytotoxic T cells</term>) and the B lymphocytes. Some cytotoxic T cells become directly involved in attacks against the infection, while the B lymphocytes produce antigen-specific antibodies. The function of antibodies in the immune system is to recognize and neutralize microbes. Once inititated by cells of the innate response, adaptive responses lead to an expansion of the numbers of lymphocytes able to recognize and bind the pathogen in question. In responding to the pathogen, the lymphocytes not only act directly on the substance providing the threat, but may also recruit cells, for example phagocytic cells, and molecules, for example complement, from the innate system and together both the innate and the adaptive immune responses focus their destructive capabilities on removing the threat. Unlike the innate response that operates at a relatively constant level, adaptive immune responses generate memory B and T lymphocytes that produce more vigorous responses upon subsequent encounters with the same microbe.</p><p id="bd727b2ad06d4edba1454a51cf133081">One essential component of the immune response is that it must be able to distinguish self, which belongs in the body, from nonself (foreign). Agents or molecules classified as nonself may enter the body from the outside or represent an unacceptable change within the body (for example, a virus infected self-cell or a self-cell becoming cancerous). B lymphocyte receptors recognize foreign molecules not associated with self-cells (for example bacterial cells or their toxins). However, T lymphocyte receptors recognize foreign molecules <em style="italic">only </em>in association with self-cells (for example a virus-infected cell). Therefore, this recognition involves two considerations: self versus nonself and threat versus nonthreat. Immune cells distinguish self from nonself through cell-surface receptors. All nucleated cells of the body express <term>major histocompatibility complex</term> (<term>MHC</term>) molecules. MHC molecules associated with foreign proteins allow T lymphocytes to recognize self that is threatened and needs to be removed by immune responses.</p><p id="e1011e15fffb4d4191530ac6fc6a0bdc">In summary, because of the wide variety of pathogens located within the body and at its surfaces, host defense requires a wide variety of recognition and defense mechanisms. Innate immunity serves the first line of defense, but is unable to recognize certain pathogens and unable to provide improved defenses that prevents re-infection. Adaptive immunity is based on lymphocytes with receptors that can potentially recognize any foreign antigen. In addition to the adaptive immune response that can eliminate a pathogen, memory lymphocytes are generated that can produce a more rapid and effective response on re-infection.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_immunity_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="cb6dc5027a7e4e01a656768c2a2a86dc"><title>Common Dysfunctions of the Immune Response</title><body><p id="f91ba6b3bca6479eb8d792c7bab7e052">The immune system works remarkably well. Unfortunately, at times it breaks down and fails to function properly. Autoimmune diseases, such as systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), celiac disease and diabetes mellitus type I, arise from an inappropriate immune response against components normally present in the body. Allergies arise from an exaggerated immune reaction to agents that are not normally harmful and lead to release of chemicals such as histamine. Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (AIDS) is caused by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). HIV infects a subset of T cells in the body, thus compromising the immune system. Cancers that affect either T or B cells are collectively called lymphomas. Some are aggressive and fast-growing lymphomas, while others are non-aggressive and slow growing. In a later module we’ll take a closer look at these immune problems of clinical significance.</p><wb:inline idref="lymph_diseases_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
