<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_innate_cellular_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The innate immune response utilizes many different kind types of white blood cells, some of which circulate in with the blood and some of which are found in the tissues. Which answer correctly describes the cells and their locations?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Pus is made from a collection of of cells, mostly macrophages, cell debris and excess interstitial fluid, and is usually found associated with bacterial infections.</choice><choice value="B">Dendritic cells are found in the subcapsular space of the lymph node, where they capture antigen found in the lymph and present it to T cells.</choice><choice value="C">Neutrophils are granulocytes found circulating in the blood stream. When they encounter bacteria they are capable of phagocytizing it. Neutrophils circulating in the bloodstream are not very long-lived so their numbers may fluctuate greatly during the course of a bacterial infection.</choice><choice value="D">Mast cells release histamine, which not only triggers the inflammatory response, but acts as a cytokine and calls in the basophils from the nearby tissues.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_defenses_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_innate_cellular_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Pus contains mostly neutrophils, which are key cells in the reponse to bacterial infections.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Everything in this answer is correct. However, it pertains to adaptive immunity and not innate.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Rapidly rising neutrophil counts are often a diagnostic indicator for a bacterial infection. Dropping neutrophil counts suggest that therapy is working and the bacterial infection is waning.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Mast cells and basophils both release histamine, but the basophils do not leave the blood in response to a mast cell histamine release.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
