<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_pamps_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="de29146a4a4c42d89d9b280c86b3aebf"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="c42b33fa5e3e4eb6b327e7bc415d65d0">The cells of the innate immune system must be able to recognize a potential foreign invader without any kind of previous exposure or memory cell. They evolved to recognize molecules that are foreign to human cells but occur regularly in or on potential pathogens such as bacteria. These molecules are called PAMPs (Pathogen-associated Molecular Patterns) and they recognize which of the following?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="b2c7ec8464834cacb33f2822364f59e4" labels="false"><choice value="A">Segments of RNA from virus</choice><choice value="B">Proteins associated with bacterial flagella</choice><choice value="C">The lipids found on Gram negative bacteria</choice><choice value="D">Peptide sugar complex found on Gram positive bacteria</choice><choice value="E">All are correct</choice><choice value="F">None is correct</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_molecule_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_pamps_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae15c0fee032848369378a395a594e24b">Incorrect. Viral RNA is one thing that is recognized.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae48cf70c0bca4a118e0a93ccb126525e">Incorrect. They have several ways to recognize bacteria.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe5bf79fa4a14a6583043e0c6f1dc5be">Incorrect. In addition to recognizing Gram negative they can also recognize Gram positive.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa8a7984069134585818272a09bd6cb0f">Incorrect. They can also recognize Gram negative bacteria.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback><p id="afeb09e628a4c4a4088e4becd0b1d525d">Correct. PAMPs are found associated with many things.</p></feedback></response><response match="F" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad9a33ebe09eb4e80b107eb174e8e4e91">Incorrect. They all are correct.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="ac42f729722d642eda3f0d34c5b43a9de">One way to understand how PAMPs work is to think about different kinds of music or art where the ear and the eye are the receptors. The ear is capable of recognizing repeating themes and rhythms in music, which can be classified genres. Likewise in art the eye can recognize a particular school of painters or period without actually knowing the name of the painter or the when the period occurred. Thinking about PAMPs and innate bacterial and viral immunity, how might this analogy apply if bacterial PAMPs are musical and viral PAMPs are visual art?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="bb36d7547d0d49be94863daeef83e21c" labels="false"><choice value="A">The immune system encounters viral RNA remembers it and goes to the viral RNA memory cell library and finds the exact match. Your eye recognizes the painting and looks it up in an art history book.</choice><choice value="B">The immune system pick up piece of a bacterial cell and recognizes it as belonging to a group known as Gram positive. The ear recognizes the music as rock and roll but can identify the artist or title of the song.</choice><choice value="C">The immune system interacts with a virus protein coat and it is so much like another virus protein coat it has already seen it makes antibodies that cross react with the new virus coat protein. The picture was in the paint by numbers kit in the art store at the mall.</choice><choice value="D">The lipids on the bacterial cell wall are recognized as belonging to E. coli. The ear recognizes the genre and the artist.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_molecule_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_pamps_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aab73408119bc44a198d4a21ad4f862db">Incorrect. This specific recognition would be part of the adaptive immune response. In terms of art, the PAMP would be recognizing the school of artists, i.e. the Impressionists, rather than a specific artist such as Monet.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac96f6994ab364dc0b26df8d5feac32d5">Correct. Gram positive bacteria stain purple with crystal violet due to the peptidoglycans on their cells surface. PAMP recognition would be for all Gram positive bacteria. In terms of music this would be mean that the PAMP is for classic rock, but you cannot identify the artist or the song, i.e. Led Zeppelin&apos;s &quot;Stairway to Heaven.&quot;</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab7fb941ebe2f4efd83c7b23c4855b67a">Incorrect. The antibody response is an adaptive response. In the art world, this would be the equivalent of a forgery where the antibody recognizes the artist and the painting, but it is not exactly the right painting and will be sold at the art auction anyway.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae1be940885244f6485ef8382b8745f29">Incorrect. This is a specific response to specific species of bacteria, which is part of the adaptive response. In other words, this is not only a country song but is &quot;Walk the Line&quot; by Johnny Cash.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
