<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_cytokines_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="b5d6fb85944343a69e9cef46745bb89d"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="aad00cb2fe7944a25aea2c3ac1fa1365b">A cytokine known as T cell growth factor exhibits the following properties: It is secreted by helper T cells, it is required for almost all immune response, and it causes proliferation of cytotoxic T cells and B cells and activated NK cells. By what other name is this cytokine known?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="e626273aaa6a47c0bab33b2b39bcdb02" labels="false"><choice value="A">IL-1</choice><choice value="B">IL-2</choice><choice value="C">IL-4</choice><choice value="D">TNF-α</choice><choice value="E">INF-γ</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_cytokines_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="acd80b335a1a44abda254e6efd6eb6690">Incorrect. IL-1 is secreted by macrophages and stimulates inflammation and fever.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaf93cd0c5b4e47949398041626f8c124">Correct. I L-2 is secreted by T cells that have been stimulated by macrophages.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa15d9c8c23f34ff5b69d2df014bc843f">Incorrect. IL-4 is secreted by activated T helper cells and stimulates the clones of B cells which are programmed to secrete IgE which is usually part of an allergic response.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab79a3d4e94a84377a104d9e798f669d2">Incorrect. TNF-alpha is secreted by macrophages as part of the inflammatory response and stimulates neutrophil migration.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac2d5eb30800842a9ada23347b721bb8d">Incorrect. This interferon is secreted by NK and NKT cells leading to the activation of macrophages.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="aed28bcc22a0a42dcabe79fdc5dfbe2c1">True or False: A cytokine is a small protein secreted by immune cells that works only on other immune cells?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="d5a0f996e308419486e4de9fdf4d205b" labels="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_cytokines_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aab368879e2d6469d8fdc060aeb6f3da2">Incorrect. Cytokine is a general term used to describe small cell-signalling molecules that serve as a means of intercellular communication. Cytokines are found in all tissues and are not unique to the immune response cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab03e565ca6994237a1e695dbd7de8843">Correct. Cytokine is a general term used to describe small cell-signalling molecules that serve as a means of intercellular communication. Cytokines are found in all tissues and are not unique to the immune response cells.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p id="f6dbcd1dd4494dc48c5be7fe919b4acd">Cytokine names are usually a combination of letters and numbers. The letters explain the source or the action of the cytokine and the number indicates which particular cytokine in that category it is. For the list of cytokines below, which statement is <em style="bold">NOT</em> correct? </p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="b013a8e30b08491aa9d9d717240b24c8" labels="false"><choice value="A">IL- Interleukin is made by a variety of white blood cells called leukocytes and as a group stimulate many other cells. The leukin refers to white blood cell</choice><choice value="B">Interferons interfere with viral replication and are made by cells macrophages and other cells which do participate the humoral (antibody mediated immune response)</choice><choice value="C">Chemokines are made by the chemiosmotic membrane of the mitochondria and they cause cells to stay in place and not migrate.</choice><choice value="D">Tumor necrosis factor was first isolated from the middle of larger tumors where the cells had started to die. In the immune system it stimulates part of the inflammatory response.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_cytokines_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abb1bfc401bc1432d80354074cf7826bb">Incorrect. The statement is true and a helpful way to remember something about interleukins.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="af326bb74636a4a11a8ceae9454b5c6d0">Incorrect. This statement is true. Macrophages, NK cells and imflammotory T cells all are capable of producing interferons.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="acdb64fde07f149e0b566ad3a06089858">Correct. Chemokines cause cells to move not remain stationary. The chemiosmotic membrane of the mitochondria is used for oxidative phosporalation.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aea6e370260a541b5bd9a669a3f8bc78d">Incorrect. This statement is true. Necrosis actually means cells rotting so it makes sense that TNF would stimulate the inflammatory response.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
