<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_distinguish_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="e172021b829a4c818b04e5b7de22cfa6"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="ae08e69c972584325b16ce200cdf272c5">Your body does an adequate job of protecting you against harmful pathogens in general, however there is also a a component to your immune system that mounts a specific response to a particular antigen. Your innate immune system __________________ while the adaptive is ________________________. Which answer correctly fills in the blanks?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="af03454b454049829a03021f6f9a17e9" labels="false"><choice value="A">contains responses you are born with, activated only through vaccinations</choice><choice value="B">responds quickly because the components are already working, slower because it requires a specific clone of cells to divide and expand</choice><choice value="C">helps to activate the inflammatory response, only involved with killing pathogens</choice><choice value="D">is the main response target by vaccinations, not very important</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_distinguish_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abd3ba67e28b240fc8cce89e4af525191">Incorrect. The adaptive immune response starts to work once the immune cells are fully functional.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaa32f115f41e480aa17ceb42e6aece5f">Correct. The clonal expansion of the adaptive immune response can take days.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aec994cf8dd0345c0a37145bd17049583">Incorrect. The adaptive immune response can also stimulate the inflammatory response.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab91f3fce665041a69ae0a1b61d5a24b4">Incorrect. The adaptive immune response is the target for vaccinations.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="adc529140675b4fa8a371698daf1f630f">Each naive T and B cell reacts to one epitope on the antigen in a certain three dimensional arrangement. Why is there sometimes cross reactivity?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="d06bfb11d49048639a49d566c9f2c110" labels="false"><choice value="A">Related molecules have very similar structures and could have the same or very similar epitopes.</choice><choice value="B">Clonal expansion results in a loss of specificity.</choice><choice value="C">Adaptive immunity developed during childhood has errors.</choice><choice value="D">An allergic response takes over.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_distinguish_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad86fb4c6199f488285372f28dc2e456f">Corrrect. Molecules made by related organisms may be evolutionarily conserved and have identical or almost identical structures.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae7e2f9467c2d4ac3a27125136b200212">Incorrect. Clonal expansion is usually very precise.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa8f06bf1bedd4b52b1ef496549d11001">Incorrect. Adaptive immunity acquired during childhood may lose its potency over time, which is why you need booster shots..</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aab7cf204116f480486b9e81375a78e38">Incorrect. An allergic response can be a form of adaptive immunity if IgE antibodies are secreted.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p id="ae9b30f95e73d4df4b0ec35da7bf36e5a">What are two main differences between the innate and adaptive immune response?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="dd82f84a8e8042c3a8b77713ad103292" labels="false"><choice value="A">The cells involved and location of responses.</choice><choice value="B">Time of the immune response due to the immunologic specificity and immunologic memory.</choice><choice value="C">Adaptive responses occur in the lymph node while innate responses occur in the blood.</choice><choice value="D">Inflammatory response and lysis of pathogens by phagocytic cells.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_distinguish_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abd1dfa94f0ee4c06a1a0c5fe6100c7a0">Incorrect. Although different cells are categorized into innate and adaptive immunity, both innate and adaptive cells respond to pathogens in the same locations of the body.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aab38c1f4711e464eafdc4ec3224f95bf">Correct. These are the two main differences between the innate and adaptive immune responses.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="afd6e1c135f23432a8541e998e818c403">Incorrect. Adaptive and innate responses both occur in the lymph nodes, and the blood transports both adaptive and innate cells to tissues where they will respond to pathogens.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="add05b3a1b2bf4f9985ff95ea81e091fb">Incorrect. Both of these immune responses are categorized as innate responses.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p id="ad04d2c8e9a7e4909aa9f86e175807551">Memory cells are an essential part of the adaptive immune response. What cell type can become a memory cell?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="ce9375bf1b0b43f1bd32cf6e1b25600e" labels="false"><choice value="A">phagocytic cell</choice><choice value="B">T and B cells</choice><choice value="C">T cells only</choice><choice value="D">erythrocytes</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_distinguish_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="af26784e1447244018df9c7e2257b85b2">Incorrect. Phagocytic cells are categorized as cells of innate immunity because they lack memory.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="abcce3141d90e408cab27fd66378db415">Correct. The immune system has both T helper Cells and B cells which can respond to an antigen the body has seen before.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="adc687a05b306466d819f4efc37a3c80e">Incorrect. T cells are part of adaptive immunity and develop memory cells; however, another answer is more complete and therefore more correct.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="abd2241e27b1e4e618eddafd2be2a1fa3">Incorrect. These cells carry oxygen in the blood but are not part of immunity.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
