<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_adaptive_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>A CBC or complete blood count is often a routine part of a physical examination. However, it can be very helpful from a diagnostic perspective especially when a differential white blood cells count is performed. Using an automated cell counter or a light microscope, it is possible to individually count the following white blood cells: neutrophils, also known as polymorphonucleocytes (polys for short); basophils; eosinophils; lymphocytes; and monocytes. If a person was suffering from a viral illness for several days, which of the following would you expect to happen and why?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The neutrophil (poly) count would increase within 24 hours of getting sick, because the neutrophils are often the first responders.</choice><choice value="B">The eosinophils would be much higher than normal because the virus was stimulating an allergic reaction.</choice><choice value="C">The lymphocytes stay the same but the number of monocytes dramatically increases, because the monocytes are picking up the virus particles.</choice><choice value="D">They lymphocyte count would increase. T cells and B cells were proliferating in the process of mounting antibody response or a Cytotoxic T cell response.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_wbc_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Neutrophils are usually first responders in bacterial infections, not viral.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Eosinophils do respond to allergic reactions, but generally viral infections do not trigger an allergic response.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The number of monocytes may increase, but they would not be the only agranulocyte to increase in number.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The lymphocyte count would increase because these are the cells circulating in the blood that normally respond to viral infections.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
