<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_defenses_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Adaptive immunity includes the part of the immune system that provides specific memory for a particular pathogen, which thus serves as the basis for vaccination. The adaptive immunity accomplished through vaccination utilizes which of the following?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">Memory T cells</choice><choice value="B">Memory B cells</choice><choice value="C">Memory T and B cells</choice><choice value="D">Natural killer (NK) cells</choice><choice value="E">None of the above</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_defenses_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Partially correct. Memory T cells are not the only answer.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Partially correct. Memory B cells are not the only answer.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both types of lymphocytes are capable of producing memory cells for latter secondary responses.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. NK cells are not part of the secondary immune response.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Memory cells are required for this mechanism to work.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>When thinking about the different ways in which the body defends itself from agents of the external environment, it is important to realize what a monumental task this is on a daily basis. Every form of immune response requires energy expenditure. The innate immune response, while less specific, may be more efficient energetically why?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">A. Neutrophils attack bacteria in general and do not require the clonal expansion of a specific T or B cell subset requires rapid cell division which uses a lot of energy.</choice><choice value="B">B. The production of antibodies to a specific antigen requires protein synthesis, which can be energy expensive, while the receptors for PAMPs are normally found on the surface of the cell and do not require new synthesis of receptor proteins.</choice><choice value="C">C. Anatomical and physiological barriers prevent many agents from entering the body, and therefore very little energy is expended to respond to a specific agent.</choice><choice value="D">None of the responses A, B or C is correct.</choice><choice value="E">All of the responses A, B or C are correct.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_defenses_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is only part of the correct response. Rapid cell division requires synthesis of many new molecules. Synthesis reactions generally require energy to be put into a biological system.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is only part of the correct response. A general low level response, while not addressing every potential pathogen, will keep many pathogens from disrupting homeostasis, which could save energy over the long term.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is only part of the correct response. The high level response to a single agent that has created a systemic infection would use more energy than maintaining chemical and physical barriers, which thwart the access of many agents.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is only part of the correct response. There are correct responses included in the answer.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback>Correct. All of the answers correctly address the energy requirements of the innate and adaptive immune responses.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
