<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_mhc_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="adccc432bfc54ceda08e23f7dec74904"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="af0aea59a36e4cf6966f101a9e6edbd8">The MHC complex is loosely referred to as your tissue type. The cells in the immune system early in development must learn to distinguish self from non-self. It is is important to try to match tissue types when someone needs a bone marrow or organ transplant. Why is tissue type important for you everyday immune function? Pick the answer that is <em style="italic">not</em> a normal function of MHC proteins. </p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="de1e975a6d6241ababad3ed5fc4dfcfd" labels="false"><choice value="A">T lymphocytes will react to viral proteins expressed on the surface of the cell that also expresses the appropriate MHC proteins</choice><choice value="B">Immune cells may be able to recognize a mutated or precancerous cells that is expressing the correct MCH proteins on its surface with some other abnormal or mutated protein</choice><choice value="C">Antibodies only work in the organism that made them</choice><choice value="D">The correct MHC proteins expressed on the surface of a cell along with new or unusual proteins signal a potential threat</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_molecule_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_mhc_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab93e2942ce3740389520eb941a834f9b">Incorrect. This is an important part of your body’s defense against viruses</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abdd3792d572a4482bd847feab0ea3073">Incorrect. This function is believed to be an important part of controlling cancer. As people age their immune function declines which may be why the incidence of cancer in general increases with increasing age</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="afae6e961282c4cb1ac92f49f28cf450e">Correct. Antibodies can be passed from one individual to another often referred to as passive immunity. This is how mothers help give their newborns some immunity until the baby’s immune system mature</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac67f1cc6dd22495ca644d47f52b349b6">Incorrect. Your body needs to determine self vs. non-self as part of its ongoing threat assessment.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="abb1b45e3215d46acac0842e6dc2977b4">Unless someone is an identical twin, they have a unique configuration of proteins on the surfaces of the cells. These proteins termed___________________ are inherited from your parents., However, you only get a few from each parent not the full range the parent has. Consequently, siblings may not have exactly identical ________________ meaning they will not always be a _______________ for a transplant. This group of proteins is different from your ________________ which is a different group of proteins found on your red blood cells.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="ae7923140746480aaca5c7e4b9bee1df" labels="false"><choice value="A">sister chromatids, tissue types, compatible donor, Rh factor</choice><choice value="B">major histocompatiblity complex antigens, blood type, compatible donor, blood type</choice><choice value="C">major histocompatiblity complex antigens, tissue type, compatible donor, blood type</choice><choice value="D">blood proteins, transplant type, incompatible donor, donor ID</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_molecule_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_mhc_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae9a646b880f640cf870403b2d95f8ab3">Incorrect. Sister chromatids are found in the nucleus during meiosis and the Rh factor is only one of several proteins which contribute to blood type.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab2bc5874469543ba9b704ad26ff491c4">Incorrect. The MHC proteins make up your tissue type not your blood type.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae31ea7b49d9c4ce5b6d467889782c238">Correct. Tissue type and blood type are two different systems of cell identification. Donors and transplant patients should have the same blood types and tissue types as closely matching as possible.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae912932867bb4927add453db9df58d44">Incorrect. MHC proteins are found on somatic tissue cells not blood cells.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
