<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_tissues_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What is the major difference between lymph and interstitial fluid?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Composition of electrolytes</choice><choice value="B">White blood cells are present in lymph</choice><choice value="C">Location</choice><choice value="D">Types of proteins present</choice><choice value="E">Red blood cells are present in interstitial fluid</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_LOO_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_tissues_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The composition of electrolytes will be the same in both fluids.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. White blood cells are found in interstitial fluid and blood.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Lymph runs through the lymph ducts and interstitial fluid is found within the tissues.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Proteins found in the interstitial fluid may also be found in the lymph.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Red blood cells should only be present in the vessels of the cardiovascular system. Finding them in the lymph or interstitial fluid means there has been damage to the blood vessels.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Lymph tissues serve two main function. They transport lymph and they house the cells that participate in the immune response. Which statement is <em style="bold">not</em> correct? </body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The diffuse lymph tissues are found in mucosal membranes and scattered around other lymph tissues such as Peyer’s patches.</choice><choice value="B">The fluids encountered by lymph tissues and as well as the spleen are interstitial fluids or lymph.</choice><choice value="C">MALT lymph nodules are special because they are scattered throughout the mucosa of the gastrointestinal tract and the respiratory tract.</choice><choice value="D">Many of the lymph tissues have germinal centers which house cells capable of dividing when stimulated by the correct antigen.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_LOO_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_tissues_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The spleen encounters only blood.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true. The MALT associated tissue are an important protection against antigens which we may ingest in our food.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Lymph immune tissues are generally quiescent unless stimulated by an antigen. The presence of germinal centers housing the appropriate stem cells allows for a rapid response.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
