<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_structures_functions_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Respiratory Structures and Functions</title><introduction><p id="a282631314a244f4bd07a77e54f82455">You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window will ask &quot;This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?&quot;, click &quot;OK&quot; if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p><p id="a670f22a054b4442bc82587d600a0daf">If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost. After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p></introduction><page id="e91036774a9d4bf891ae691d635f2b78"><multiple_choice id="not_upper_respiratory" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abbd6ca463c484bb2a0ed31817ff44f1a">Which of the following is not considered to be a part of the upper respiratory tract?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="c957fc265d4e4472a34619046e017f9f" labels="false"><choice value="A">Paranasal Sinuses</choice><choice value="B">Adenoids</choice><choice value="C">Epiglottis</choice><choice value="D">Alveoli</choice></input><part id="not_upper_respiratory_p1"><skillref idref="identify_gross_anatomy_respiratory_system" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="add0b932e33a1452398d1bd3f7a7c06c5">Incorrect. The paranasal sinuses are located in the nasal cavity of the nose which is located in the upper respiratory tract.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="af1147e5ac9d044c6b3c54579f591d4df">Incorrect. The adenoids are located in the nasopharynx which is the most superior portion of the pharynx. Which is part of the the upper respiratory tract.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab9edf8454bca48f8802cfce694c3ba86">Incorrect. The epiglottis is located superiorly to the trachea and prevents food from entering the airway. Which is part of the the upper respiratory tract.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa81c8221d7e94d3eb765e804f121507e">Correct. The alveoli are located at the ends of the terminal bronchial tubes in the lungs and are part of the lower respiratory tract.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="conchae" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac6b6bcfc3b154751a6230ec8d0fd539a">Which of the following structures contains membranes with mucus glands and blood vessels to help humidify and warm air?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ecac4d302fd44a8ebe5022ca919c5455" labels="false"><choice value="A">Conchae</choice><choice value="B">Auditory tube</choice><choice value="C">Epiglottis</choice><choice value="D">Trachea</choice></input><part id="conchae_p1"><skillref idref="describe_nasal_structure" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="abb0f919ee62740a38b2df7ed8375d7e0">Correct. The conchae increase the surface area of the nasal cavity and are responsible for helping to warm and humidify the incoming air.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae15fa4a781e94d1586487f7720d5ce97">Incorrect. The auditory tube functions to equilibrate the air pressure between the environment and middle ear.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab8193417832c403fa1eb509a1016275e">Incorrect. The epiglottis is composed of cartilage that allows it to prevent food from entering the trachea.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aeaa5d5630a4845ed9e70454ac03aa392">Incorrect. The trachea is composed of three layers: the mucosa, submucosa and adventitia. The three layers allow for production and movement mucus.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="blockage_terminal_bronchiole" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aabb1eac6034541858bbf9dac52a88385">If there was a blockage in a terminal bronchiole a person would not be able to breath at all.</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d4fdce37d79143a6b648c26801a775e5" labels="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></input><part id="blockage_terminal_bronchiole_p1"><skillref idref="identify_parts_bronchial_tree" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae0ed3141c730451d98bf2e770b1c59a4">Incorrect. A blockage of the terminal bronchiole would impair a person’s ability to breath but the terminal bronchioles are the smallest branch of the bronchial tree and would not prevent a person from breathing at all.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="abc1b6e78f4c643aba086e30957542d9d">Correct. A blockage of the terminal bronchiole would cause some impairment because the alveolar sac attached to that terminal bronchiole would not be able to inflate, but it would not completely block the person’s ability to breath.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="conducting_zone" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abc2251d60a21402f8e64ca9bccaf6359">Which of the following is not considered to be a part of the conducting zone?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="adf4bc0daac84e088ca28824499b3db7" labels="false"><choice value="A">Nose</choice><choice value="B">Pharynx</choice><choice value="C">Trachea</choice><choice value="D">Alveoli</choice></input><part id="conducting_zone_p1"><skillref idref="distinguish_between_conducting_respiratory_zones" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac6ce641c01924b3f8d21effede4257de">Incorrect. The nose is where air will enter the body but not be absorbed.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac2345636141c42bcbdb73bbfb344a47f">Incorrect. The pharynx is part of the system of tubes that connects the mouth to the lungs.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af3ff01dddd1b475e883f37cae928d0c9">Incorrect. The trachea or windpipe is part of the conducting system but it does not participate in the exchange of gases.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab8dbfcdb406f4357a64bb8303368b860">Correct. The alveoli are part of the respiratory zone because this is where the exchange of gases occurs.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="ciliate_cells" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad0b8ee347a1d4697bab4dd550b757cce">Smoking causes the paralysis and destruction of the ciliate cells of the conducting zone. What is a possible result of this?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b3fc8e45588749a981cce11da4121ff0" labels="false"><choice value="A">The air will not reach the appropriate level of humidity and will damage the thin-walled alveoli.</choice><choice value="B">The hairs of the nose will not be able to trap large particles.</choice><choice value="C">The mixture of mucus and particles will not be moved to the esophagus to be swallowed.</choice><choice value="D">The carbonic anhydrase will not be able to function properly.</choice></input><part id="ciliate_cells_p1"><skillref idref="describe_function_cilia" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aca65055fcc504858bcac1921d9aca056">Incorrect. The humidity is provided by the membranes of the nose and mouth.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab53adac0e980473b9b953563abe1e5d4">Incorrect. The hairs of the nose are not the same as cilia which are hair like projections of cells. The hair will still act as a physical barrier.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae376b5767c034eed9f67479b1750e323">Correct. With the cilia paralyzed or destroyed the mucociliary elevator will not work properly and the mucus will not move out of the lungs to the esophagus. This results in the classic “smoker’s cough.”</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae7140908e85249b1b53ca2a3d746a935">Incorrect. The carbonic anhydrase is affected if the temperature of the incoming air is too cold.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="pulmonary_ventilation" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae3527b362c5048c6a179704e9bffbc24">Pulmonary ventilation involves which of the following processes?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="ebe825b29bb34e56bb1c4da38c738488" labels="false"><choice value="A">Expiration</choice><choice value="B">Inspiration</choice><choice value="C">Cellular respiration</choice><choice value="D">Both A and B</choice></input><part id="pulmonary_ventilation_p1"><skillref idref="explain_pulmonary_ventilation" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac44e3f8d3d704393b5b798bfaf75d216">Incorrect. Expiration or exhalation is half of pulmonary ventilation where air is exiting the body.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac309d19fcb184c08a775561d18aaccc2">Incorrect. Inspiration or inhalation is half of the pulmonary ventilation where air is entering the body.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab1f7ea2dfe1448b1957fce9ff255f5b1">Incorrect. Cellular respiration occurs in the cell where oxygen is used to convert nutrients into cellular energy.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac5077346b1674e42b3c999ea419784f0">Correct. Pulmonary ventilation is the process of exchanging air with the atmosphere. This process includes both expiration and inspiration.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="atmospheric_pressure" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad789eebc7ef9447088cb806a1c452a24">If a person travels to Denver, CO they may feel short of breath until their body adjusts because:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="abdb6097f9b34ed786dacb9aca9e82a7" labels="false"><choice value="A">The percentage of oxygen in the atmosphere is lower.</choice><choice value="B">The atmospheric pressure is lower</choice><choice value="C">The percentage of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere is higher</choice><choice value="D">The application of Boyle’s Law</choice></input><part id="atmospheric_pressure_p1"><skillref idref="apply_boyles_law" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="adb47efc5a69540d1a6d5c5c496ea7b9a">Incorrect. The percentage of oxygen is the same as you change altitudes</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac406a8b796884a6589923453eba3f72b">Correct. The atmospheric pressure is lower at higher altitudes which means the difference between the atmospheric pressure and the alveolar pressure is less. This makes it harder to move air into and out of the body.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aefd778134913493a8f35caa2b8c145e1">Incorrect. The percentage of carbon dioxide is the same as you change altitudes.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe139585abf1416b83180d07be5cf2e4">Incorrect. Boyle’s law describes the relationship between volume and pressure. For example as the thoracic cavity increases in volume it decreases in pressure. It does not explain why a person feels short of breath.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><fill_in_the_blank id="thoracic_cavity" grading="automatic"><body><image id="a2065159cb234d1b801d997269128b42" src="../webcontent/r_m1_19aa.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="350" width="300"><caption><p id="ac4274affaf2b4674b96183be9ae8681e"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d121b48694e148ac92eee3a2351e0e74">Referring to the picture above, answer the following two questions.</p><p id="dfddfd3ff11a4c37a173b380ab4b4ba0">As the rib cage moves out and the diagram moves down the volume of the thoracic cavity <input_ref input="A" /> and the pressure in the thoracic cavity.<input_ref input="B" /></p></body><input shuffle="false" id="A"><choice value="one">increase</choice><choice value="two">decrease</choice></input><input shuffle="false" id="B"><choice value="one">increase</choice><choice value="two">decrease</choice></input><part id="p1"><skillref idref="apply_boyles_law" /><response match="one" score="10" name="increase" input="A"><feedback><p id="ac42cab6b4fb24738bdcf8f203ec2ccf6">Correct. The volume will increase as the muscles contract and pull the ribs out and the diaphragm down. </p></feedback></response><response match="two" score="0" name="decrease" input="A"><feedback><p id="ace55e67f4fb9458f9df8a5400c5f0837">Incorrect. As the muscles of the ribs and the diaphragm contract they will shorten, pulling the ribs out and the diaphragm down. </p></feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="explain_pulmonary_ventilation" /><response match="one" score="0" name="increase" input="B"><feedback><p id="abc21d594292240b09111fee1b4f98d0e">Incorrect. Volume and pressure have inverse relationships, so in order for the pressure to increase the volume would have to decrease and this would result in air moving out of the lungs. </p></feedback></response><response match="two" score="10" name="decrease" input="B"><feedback><p id="afc4e6c3f4cc845cf87994b13eaba52e0">Correct. Volume and pressure have inverse relationships, so as the volume increases the pressure decreases. This results in air moving into the lungs. </p></feedback></response></part></fill_in_the_blank><multiple_choice id="thoracic_cavity_1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><image id="f138ab5c5ce84690859017ef67d72822" src="../webcontent/r_m1_19aa.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="350" width="300"><caption><p id="ab4766807fdd1476fbb96f6d020de5376"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ad2665d7bcca548fea7c7c3dd868beefa"> Air will be moving into the body in this diagram.</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="c63664e51596453f8ae50f2e6ed05331" labels="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></input><part id="thoracic_cavity_1_p1"><skillref idref="apply_boyles_law" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="abe772726087a4f7dba2848131e4c8565">Correct. As the volume of the thoracic cavity increases, the pressure decreases. This results in air flowing from the area of higher pressure outside the body to the area of lower pressure inside the body.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abcd7d7f66b5849cb9936d33c26003acf">Incorrect. As the volume of the thoracic cavity increase the pressure will decrease. As the pressure decreases the air can move into the body.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="lung_compliance" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac6424ce4714e454f82eb0673bc45642f">Compliance of the lungs depends on what two characteristics?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="fc87f8ab93fe4febb8b7d8f2466e7c59" labels="false"><choice value="A">Elasticity of the connective tissue and bronchiolar constriction</choice><choice value="B">Elasticity of the connective tissue and alveolar surface tension</choice><choice value="C">Elasticity of the connective tissue and bronchiolar dilatation</choice><choice value="D">Alveolar surface tension and bronchiolar dilatation</choice></input><part id="lung_compliance_p1"><skillref idref="describe_compliance_lungs" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abcc1dde7b6484a3d99a41fbd0fcdc7da">Incorrect. The elasticity of the connective tissue of the lungs will affect the compliance of the lungs, but bronchiolar constriction will increase the resistance of the lungs not the compliance.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab9f897484ae747f79733d79bb0a1ef83">Correct. The compliance of the lungs explains the relationship between the pressure and volume change in the ease of breathing and is affected by the elasticity of the connective tissue and the alveolar surface tension.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad198213431574409af961bbaf5c4f738">Incorrect. The elasticity of the connective tissue of the lungs will affect the compliance of the lungs, but bronchiolar dilatation will decrease the resistance of the lungs not the compliance.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aedd9b267361f46d8a7a9c2e71f56357f">Incorrect. The surface tension of the alveoli will affect the compliance of the lungs, but bronchiolar dilatation will increase the resistance of the lungs not the compliance.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="spirometry" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aef9255053d984d17a350a12abd91bd41">Which of the following is not evaluated through the process of spirometry?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="aadc0ce9bdf848c6b18ff7b801de3ece" labels="false"><choice value="A">Lung volume</choice><choice value="B">Dead space</choice><choice value="C">Lung capacity</choice><choice value="D">Flow rate</choice></input><part id="spirometry_p1"><skillref idref="interpret_spirogram" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa345b46815014f3bab2dc4e4ac81874d">Incorrect. Lung volumes such as the tidal volume, inspiratory reserve volume and expiratory reserve volume are frequently measured with spirometry.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad6ea62d8b01246b488d61d33c1955c5e">Correct. Dead space is measured using a nitrogen washout or Folwer’s method test.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab85f4914fdaa4cb09f325fd0a38c2cc4">Incorrect. Lung capacities are combinations of lung volumes such as the vital capacity which is the TV+ IRV+ ERV</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa2117a3494524e6c9ab24926a70e4382">Incorrect. The flow rate is measured using a spirometer and used to help diagnose obstructive and restrictive disorders.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="residual_volume" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="afeea2625111849e4818afe961dc26975">Which of the following would not be increased by an olympic swimmer training to hold their breath for a long period of time?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f31e4eb630b648798e2d309ccd48f491" labels="false"><choice value="A">Inspiratory Capacity</choice><choice value="B">Inspiratory reserve volume</choice><choice value="C">Residual Volume</choice><choice value="D">Vital capacity</choice></input><part id="residual_volume_p1"><skillref idref="interpret_spirogram" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abbcec9206e584638a559146c8fbedb83">Incorrect. The inspiratory capacity is equal to the sum of the TV and the IRV. An olympic swimmer will train to be able to breath in more and increase this capacity.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae8b8af1ebbfc40abbc1321fd476464c0">Incorrect. The inspiratory reserve volume will increase as a the swimmer trains be be able to inhale more air as they hold their breath.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad3a29317c19f42c0a4e238568cedaaa8">Correct. The residual volume is the amount of air remaining in the lungs after the ERV has been expelled. The residual volume will remain in the lungs even after death.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae95485e913a149b39df25cc89071718c">Incorrect. The vital capacity is the TV+ IRV+ERV. As the IRV increases so will the viatal capacity.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="asthma" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa1c9ad2fc3254e74a54f927c2a71a55c">Which of the following is an example of an obstructive lung disorder?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="df745acb1a434bbfb3ad3d60676b3eeb" labels="false"><choice value="A">Tuberculosis</choice><choice value="B">Fibrosis</choice><choice value="C">Muscular dystrophy</choice><choice value="D">Asthma</choice></input><part id="asthma_p1"><skillref idref="differentiate_respiratory_disorders" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="afd9b7a4caf1047c5ae8f1f1150230ed4">Incorrect. Tuberculosis will lower the compliance of the lungs and by changing the lung tissue so is a restrictive disorder.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa51132e64e594fbb80f8c7e241b11418">Incorrect. Fibrosis will lower the compliance of the lungs and by changing the lung tissue so is a restrictive disorder.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="abf7e2a71696e4dae8939fdd6a58b0461">Incorrect. Muscular dystrophy will impeded the normal muscular function and lower the ability of the chest wall to constrict and relax normally so is a restrictive disorder.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad5faa0b315c347a9ac987f1682ad60a1">Correct. Asthma will increase the resistance of the lungs to airflow and increase the amount of time it takes for air to enter and exit the lungs.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
