<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_9a">
    <head>
        <title>Other Important Regulatory Factors</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_homeo_bone"/>
        <objref idref="skeletal_homeo_disorders"/>
    </head>
<body>
    
            <p><term>Vitamin</term> D is a group of lipid soluble compounds involved in
            calcium regulation. Vitamin D can be made in the skin through exposure to sunlight, or
            acquired from the diet and dietary supplements. Under the influence of the parathyroid
            hormone, vitamin D is converted to an active molecule, <term>calcitriol</term>.
                Calcitriol circulates through the blood to maintain normal blood calcium levels. When
            your body does not have sufficient levels of calcitriol, the intestines do not absorb as
            much calcium, and blood calcium levels decrease. Vitamin D also inhibits calcium loss in
            urine.</p>
            <p>The activity of osteoblasts and osteoclasts in the bone is tightly regulated by the
            activity of the parathyroid hormone, calcitonin and vitamin D. Nutritional deficiencies
            in vitamin D, calcium or phosphate lead to a disease called osteomalacia.</p>
            <p><term>Osteomalacia</term> (from <em style="italic">osteo</em><em
                style="italic">-</em>, meaning "bone," and <em style="italic">mal</em><em
                style="italic">-</em>, meaning "bad"), also known as rickets when it occurs in
            children, is a disease that is most commonly caused by a lack of vitamin D in the body.
            Remember that vitamin D helps to increase the amount of calcium that the body absorbs
            and, as a result, helps the body build the mineralized extracellular matrix in bone
            tissue. If a person lacks sufficient vitamin D, calcium absorption is slowed, and bone
            growth is affected.</p>
            <p>In children, the lack of calcium absorption prevents new bone tissue from ossifying
            properly. As a result, the bones become weak and rubbery. Because their bones are less
            able to support the body and withstand the pressure of the body's weight, children with
            rickets may develop bowed legs and deformed skeletons.</p>
            <p>In adults, osteomalacia prevents bones from healing and remodeling properly.
                Recall that bone tissue is being continually formed and broken down by
                osteoblasts and osteoclasts. If insufficient calcium is available, the new bone
                that forms may not calcify properly. As a result, the bones may become painful
                and brittle.</p>
    
    <image src="../../webcontent/Rickets.jpg" alt="Osteomalacia" width="400"></image>    
            <!--  
                <p><em style="bold">LEARNING ACTIVITY: Osteomalacia  </em> </p>
            -->
            
            <!-- Osteomalcia activity -->    
            <wb:inline idref="_u5_skel_homeostasis_02" purpose="learnbydoing"/> 
            
            <p><term>Osteoporosis</term> is a condition in which the balance between
                calcium deposition and calcium loss in bones is disrupted. In people with
                osteoporosis, the bones lose more calcium than they deposit. As a result, the
                bones become brittle and break easily.</p>
            
            <p>Osteoporosis is most common in post-menopausal women. As a woman goes through
            menopause, her levels of estrogen decrease significantly. Estrogen and testosterone are
            important hormones that affect the reproductive system, but they also can stimulate
            osteoblast activity. As concentrations of these hormones decrease, osteoblasts become
            less active, and less calcium is deposited in the extracellular matrix. In addition to
            resulting in weak bones, this is also an issue because there is a reduced reserve of
            calcium in the body for other tissues.</p>
            <p>Osteoporosis can be affected by diet and lifestyle. People who consume very
                little calcium and vitamin D are at increased risk of osteoporosis. (For
                example, women with anorexia nervosa, who eat very little, may develop
                osteoporosis in their late twenties and thirties.) Weight-bearing exercise, such
                as running, helps to build bone mass and can reduce the chances of developing
                osteoporosis.</p>
            <!--  
                <p><em style="bold">LEARNING ACTIVITY: Osteoporosis  </em>    </p>          
            -->
            <wb:inline idref="_u5_skel_homeostasis_03" purpose="learnbydoing"/> 
    <section purpose="didigetthis">
        <title/>
        <body>
            <wb:inline idref="skeletal_homeo_disorders_SC" purpose="myresponse"></wb:inline>
            <wb:inline idref="skeletal_homeo_disorders_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
            
        </body>
        
    </section>
    
   
            
   
    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
