<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_9b">
    <head>
        <title>Bone Response to Force</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_homeo_bone_force"/>
    </head>
<body>
    
            <p>You learned that osteocytes become embedded within bone matrix during mineralization.
            Within bone lamellae, osteocytes interact with each other through a network of cellular
            extensions. These extensions, found in a network of canals referred to as <term>canaliculi</term>, allow external mechanical information to be rapidly
            transmitted to many osteocytes. The response of osteocytes to mechanical force allows
            our skeletal system to maintain itself.</p>
            <p>When bone experiences a mechanical force, this force is transmitted to the fluids and
            cells within the bone. The forces on the fluids are then transferred through the spaces
            of the canaliculi down to the osteocytes. In response to the received forces, osteocytes
            generate a force on the bone tissue. Therefore, the cells and bone matrix constantly
            respond to each other’s mechanical force input.</p>
            <p>Osteocytes in bone tissue act as mechanical strain sensors to convert information
            about mechanical force into chemical messages. These chemical messages control
            osteoblast and osteoclast activity and can result in either bone deposition or bone
            resorption, also known as osteolysis. In response to mechanical force, a two-step
            process occurs. First, mechanically sensitive membrane proteins on the surface of the
            osteocytes are activated. Second, chemical pathways within the osteocytes are activated.
            Activation of these intracellular pathways stimulates osteoblast activity and inhibits
            osteoclast activity.</p>
            <p>As you learned earlier, bone ECM (extracellular matrix) maintains the mechanical
            structure and functional properties of bone tissue. The collagen fibers of bone ECM are
            under constant tension so that the bone ECM is always ready to respond to mechanical
            force. Because osteocytes are attached to the ECM, the tension felt by the collagen
            fibers is balanced by the tension that osteocytes place on the ECM. Therefore,
            osteocytes sense mechanical force and transmit this force to the surrounding ECM. Bone
            ECM is constantly remodeled to maintain optimal strength for applied mechanical
            force.</p>
            <p>Mechanical forces control osteoblast and osteoclast activity through feedback from
            the osteocytes and the ECM. One common type of mechanical force is physical activity.
            Another force that is not as obvious is body mass. With increased mechanical force, such
            as physical activity or weight gain, bone ECM increases to support the force. When the
            mechanical force applied to bone is too high, osteocytes within bone matrix signal for
            remodeling through bone resorption and bone deposition.</p>
            <p>People who routinely lift heavy loads have very strong bones, but the body spends a
            lot of energy to maintain these stronger bones. On the other hand, sedentary individuals
            may lose bone density and strength. However, that can be a problem: a lack of exercise,
            extended bed rest and space travel (for astronauts), during which there is little or no
            force on bones because of inactivity or weightlessness, can cause a significant loss of
            bone mass. </p>
            
            <!--  
                <p> <em style="bold">LEARNING ACTIVITY: Bone Response to Force </em> </p>
            -->
            <wb:inline idref="_u5_skel_homeostasis_04" purpose="learnbydoing"/> 
    <wb:inline idref="skeletal_homeo_bone_force_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
            
    
   
    </body>
</workbook_page>
