<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_9">
    <head>
        <title>Maintaining Calcium Levels in the Bone</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_homeo_bone"/>
    </head>
<body>
    
            <p>The body uses the bones not only for structure and protection, but also for calcium
            storage. Approximately 99 percent of the body's calcium is stored in the bone, and
            calcium plays an important role in most of the body's functions. Free calcium levels
            must remain at a set<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111216T123746-0500"?>
            <?oxy_insert_end?>point for proper body functions. The extracellular levels of calcium
            are affected by calcium intake from foods, excretion of calcium as waste, and the
            storage and release of calcium from the bones. Hormones regulate these processes to
            maintain balanced calcium levels in the extracellular fluid, which is necessary to
            maintain homeostasis.</p>
            <p>Small changes in blood calcium levels can have significant effects on body function.
            For example, if extracellular calcium levels are too low, the nervous system becomes
            overexcited, resulting in tetany (rigid, locked muscles). On the other hand, if calcium
            levels in the body are above normal, the nervous system becomes sluggish. Muscle
            activity of the heart and gastrointestinal tract slows down.</p>
            <p>Milk and dark green vegetables are rich in calcium, and an adequate supply of calcium
            helps maintain healthy bones. When we eat calcium-rich foods, some calcium is absorbed
            into the small intestinal wall, and some of the calcium becomes soluble in the blood
            stream. However, calcium and other divalent
            cations<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111216T124943-0500" comment="Is my addition correct and appropriate? (it seemed like this term should be explained, if it&apos;s going to be used)"?>
            (ions that are missing two electrons) ar<?oxy_comment_end?>e poorly absorbed by the
            small intestine. For this reason, vitamin D is an important dietary supplement. Vitamin
            D increases calcium absorption in the small intestine.</p>
            <p>By altering the function of the osteoblasts and osteoclasts, hormones help regulate
            calcium levels in the blood. There are three hormones that control osteoblast and
            osteoclast activity:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><term>parathyroid hormone</term> or PTH, which increases bone resorption by
                stimulating osteoclasts, leading to increased calcium release from bone.</li>
                <li><term>calcitonin</term>, which acts in children to decrease bone resorption,
                leading to less calcium entering the blood.</li>
                <li><term>calcitriol</term>, (vitamin D) which increases absorption of dietary
                calcium.</li>
            </ul>
            <p><image src="../../../_u3_homeostasis/_u3_m1_feedback/webcontent/feedback_1.gif" alt="generic feedback loop that shows the input entering the system arrow to a receptor arrow to the system checking against references and arrow moving to an effector and then back to input." vertical-align="middle"/></p>
            <p>Parathyroid hormone (produced in the parathyroid glands) controls extracellular
            calcium by regulating how calcium is reabsorbed in the intestines, excreted from the
            body, and exchanged between the extracellular fluid and the bone. The cells of the
            parathyroid gland synthesize and release parathyroid hormone in response to low blood
            calcium levels. To bring blood calcium levels into the normal range, the release of
            parathyroid hormone stimulates osteoclasts to reabsorb bone mineral, therefore releasing
            calcium into the blood. Parathyroid hormone also enhances calcium absorption by the
            intestines, and prevents calcium loss in urine to increase calcium levels in the blood.
            When parathyroid cells sense that blood calcium levels are above normal, cellular
            receptors are activated and the synthesis and release of parathyroid hormone is
            inhibited.</p>
            <p>Calcitonin is produced in the thyroid gland. The function of this hormone is to
            decrease bone resorption and retain calcium in the bones. Therefore, the effects of
            calcitonin counteract the effects of parathyroid hormone. When blood calcium levels are
            high, the thyroid releases calcitonin into the blood. Calcitonin decreases bone
            resorption by decreasing the activity of osteoclasts and decreasing the formation of new
            osteoclasts. In this way, calcitonin shifts the bone balance in favor of bone
            deposition, which requires the removal of calcium from the blood and into the bone.
            Calcitonin also has minor effects on how the intestines and kidney tubules handle
            calcium. In adult humans, calcitonin has weak effects on the regulation of calcium
            levels. We know this because if the thyroid gland is removed, calcium levels are not
            adversely affected.</p>
            
            <!--  <em style="bold">LEARNING ACTIVITY</em> -->
            
            <!-- Homeostasis Bone Activities  -->    
               <wb:inline idref="_u5_skel_homeostasis_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>                              
   <!-- <wb:inline idref="skeletal_homeo_bone_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>-->
    
    </body>
</workbook_page>
