<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_10">
    <head>
        <title>Homeostasis of Cartilage</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_homeo_cart"/>
       <!-- <objref idref="skeletal_homeo_cart_b"/>-->
    </head>
    <body>
        
                <p>You have learned in relation to ossification how cartilage and bone are
                    inherently integrated. Both tissue types are also some of the most
                    force-responsive in the body. This is necessary to maintain stature.
                    Chondrocytes sense force and changes in water movement—associated with the
                    force-induced movement of water—and secrete the appropriate collagen and
                    proteoglycan extracellular matrix proteins.</p>
                
                <p>Recall that cartilage is composed primarily of a network of elastic 
                    <term>type II collagen</term> fibers embedded in gel-like 
                    <term>proteoglycans</term>. Water, electrolytes, and chondrocytes are interspersed
                    within the network. The physical properties of collagen and proteoglycans are
                    largely responsible for the ability of cartilage to respond flexibly to
                    force.</p>
                
                <p>Collagen fibers have significant <term>tensile strength</term>, which
                    means that they can withstand a lot of tension (pulling) without damage.
                    However, collagen fibers have very little <term>compressive
                        strength</term>—that is, under compression (squeezing), they bend easily. You
                    can think of a collagen fiber as a rubber band or string. If you pull on a
                    rubber band, it stretches easily, and then returns to its original shape when
                    you stop pulling. However, if you push on the ends of the rubber band, it folds
                    up easily—it has minimal strength.</p>
                
                <p>Collagen fibers are what give cartilage its strength. The cartilage in different
                    areas of the body contains fibers that are arranged in different ways. The
                    orientation and arrangement of the collagen fibers helps to give each region of
                    cartilage strength to withstand specific types of stress. For example, <term>articular cartilage</term>—the cartilage that forms the
                    articulating surfaces of joints, such as the knee—contains two main regions of
                    collagen fiber orientation. At the surface of the cartilage, the fibers are
                    arranged primarily parallel to the surface. Further from the surface, the fibers
                    are arranged primarily perpendicular to the surface.</p>
                
                <p>Proteoglycans are gel-like, elastic substances. They are highly resilient, which
                    means that they deform easily under stress, but return to their original shape
                    when the stress is removed. Proteoglycans give cartilage its resiliency and
                    elasticity.</p>
                
                <p>The combination of strength and elasticity allows cartilage to respond flexibly
                    and quickly to forces placed on it. For example, the cartilage in your knee can
                    support up to eight to 10 times your body weight for short periods without being
                    damaged. As more force acts on the cartilage, it compresses. Its elasticity
                    allows it to distribute the force evenly, and its strength allows it to
                    withstand the stress without breaking or collapsing. When the stress is removed,
                    the cartilage returns to its original shape. The physical movement of the water
                    in the cartilage also helps to distribute the force of compression.</p>
                
                <p>Cartilage is less complex in response to force than bone, which has multiple
                    integrated cell types. Cartilage is less regulated by hormones, is difficult to
                    overgrow, and grows extremely slowly. Part of the reason for slow growth is a
                    limited amount of nutrients. Cartilage is avascular (a- means "none"), so there
                    are no blood vessels or blood supply to
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111216T233936-0500" comment="Is this portion of my clarification correct?"?>the
                    interior of<?oxy_comment_end?> the cartilage, so nutrient travel is limited to
                    diffusion, and growth is limited.</p>
                <!--  
                <p><em style="bold">LEARNING ACTIVITY: Homeo - cart</em> </p>
                -->    
                <wb:inline idref="_u5_skel_homeostasis_05" purpose="learnbydoing"/> 
                
                <p><term>Arthritis</term> (from <em style="italic">arthro</em><em
                        style="italic">-</em>, meaning "joint," and <em style="italic">–</em><em
                        style="italic">itis</em>, meaning "inflammation") is any inflammation of the
                    cartilage and/or bone tissue within a joint. The most common form of arthritis
                    is <term>osteoarthritis</term>, which is caused primarily by physical
                    damage to the cartilage that cushions many joints. The damage may be caused by a
                    decrease in cartilage flexibility and water content as a person ages, but it may
                    also be a secondary result of a variety of other conditions (including diabetes
                    and mechanical injury to the joint). Osteoarthritis is most common in the
                    elderly, but can affect younger people as well.</p>
                
                <image src="../../webcontent/osteoarthritis.jpg" alt="Osteoarthritis" width="450"></image>
                
                <p>Osteoarthritis begins with physical damage to cartilage tissue in the joints. The
                    damage may be cellular (such as damage cause by an infection), or it may occur
                    at the tissue level. The damage causes the cartilage to break down. As the
                    cartilage breaks down, friction within the joint increases; in severe cases, the
                    ends of the bones themselves may rub together, causing severe pain. Loss of
                    cartilage can also reduce the flexibility of the joint. Pain and loss of
                    flexibility typically cause a person to move the joint less; as a result, the
                    muscles, tendons, and ligaments near the joint may weaken. This in turn can
                    cause additional difficulty moving the joint.</p>
        <p>A different form of arthritis that also causes joint pain, rheumatoid arthritis,  is caused by inflammation of the membranes of the synovial capsule, not the articular cartilage.</p>
                <!-- 
                <p><em style="bold">LEARNING ACTIVITY: Osteoarthritis </em> </p>
                -->
                <wb:inline idref="_u5_skel_homeostasis_06" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        
        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <wb:inline idref="skeletal_homeo_cart_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
                <wb:inline idref="skeletal_homeo_cart_b_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
                
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
