<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u5_m3_review"><head><title>Skeletal Homeostasis Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="e78ed1a7a0df4f26a49ba770d91d8cb9">The body uses the bones not only for structure and protection, but also for calcium storage. Approximately 99 percent of the body&apos;s calcium is stored in the bone, and calcium plays an important role in most of the body&apos;s functions. The extracellular levels of calcium are affected by calcium intake from foods, excretion of calcium as waste, and the storage and release of calcium from the bones. Hormones regulate these processes to maintain balanced calcium levels in the extracellular fluid, which is necessary to maintain homeostasis. There are three hormones that control osteoblast and osteoclast activity:</p><ul id="a6e9251cbbb747f2a4393f19c59d979c"><li><p id="adda7164cba5b40db8b609216312de472">parathyroid hormone, or PTH, which increases bone resorption by stimulating osteoclasts, leading to increased calcium release from bone.</p></li><li><p id="af6263a427e59444298a8f07770cd45c0">calcitonin, which acts in children to decrease bone resorption, leading to less calcium entering the blood.</p></li><li><p id="aefc2b3029ebe4f2dace21105c198a433">calcitriol, (vitamin D) which increases absorption of dietary calcium.</p></li></ul><p id="e0549b19316e4fbc99dc0589fa504c63">Make sure you understand disorders of the skeletal system that can result from calcium deficiency, such as osteoporosis.</p><activity idref="_u5_skeletal_homeostasis_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
