<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_factmyth_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="ce106f6b397d49e0b94124b7e01bc1c9"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="ac6feaaa4b414f5889d7ab697bfad24a">Lymph accumulates toxic waste products over time, so it is recommended to do lymph cleansings regularly.</p><p id="d4904248482444848a5269f336dd472e"><input_ref input="one" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="one"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0" input="one"><feedback><p id="abd1fdf7e536e46379b8c82390f40d3fc">Incorrect. Lymph transports fats and liquids, and also contain white blood cells, but its role is not waste transport. Websites promoting lymph cleansing are not based on science!</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="1" input="one"><feedback><p id="af7bfae1303e34da2b5308d2267f1e0dc">Correct. Lymph transports fats and liquids, and also contain white blood cells, but its role is not waste transport. Websites promoting lymph cleansing are not based on science!</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="a136aa970b2743698e24971ccb4433ec">The human immune system has the ability to make up 10<sup>9</sup> different antibodies.</p><p id="e44f42fc727c4c0d8d37ef9bb5e75557"><input_ref input="two" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="two"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1" input="two"><feedback><p id="af46aef7d4fa24d5c916c8541cb31a710">Correct. The Lego-like structure of the genes that code for antibodies can be “mixed-and-matched” into an amazing set of combinations.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0" input="two"><feedback><p id="aad8495ec672647729d14924f42e196a3">Incorrect. The Lego-like structure of the genes that code for antibodies can be “mixed-and-matched” into an amazing set of combinations.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p id="ca4c86214558433da3bc7547429465b3">The younger we are, the stronger our immune system is.</p><p id="afc6498e9a26487d9e633684038a24df"><input_ref input="three" /></p><p id="afc95871da94d4adfad61fdf7f36848dd">. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="three"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0" input="three"><feedback><p id="aab02474c59474ef09275593a0e913ed7">Incorrect. Although the immune system becomes less efficient when we age, newborn babies have only innate immunity, and rely for protection on antibodies provided by the mother through the placenta and via breast milk.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="1" input="three"><feedback><p id="ae09580bcb8c3406a88c5f4bab2e66d7d">Correct. Newborn babies have only innate immunity, and rely for protection on antibodies provided by the mother through the placenta and via breast milk.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p id="d185c890aac8430db159b10e4ef6dd99">Vaccines can cause autism.</p><p id="df2aa5da97904e6a9f413b1411459bf5"><input_ref input="four" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="four"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0" input="four"><feedback><p id="aa9a12a6dd5a849e99fbb183396e3318c">Incorrect. There was one study supporting this notion, and it was proven manipulated and has been since retracted. Many other studies have found no correlation between vaccination and autism.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="1" input="four"><feedback><p id="abe4f526a96484d9dbf98aa5dfad53afa">Correct. The one study this belief was based on has been proven manipulated and been since retracted. Many other studies have found no correlation between vaccination and autism.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q5"><body><p id="fd6d2d44afec4ba4a87128f9f5c8c9b9">Knowledge of some concepts of immunology date back to the plague in Athens (430 B.C.).</p><p id="aae740ba4051476da6b96c5923a1a2cb"><input_ref input="five" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="five"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1" input="five"><feedback><p id="ab354edcb7dff4ffea069348c66cabdf0">Correct. The fact that people who recover from certain infectious diseases are usually resistant to those particular diseases dates back to Thucydides who noted that only those who had survived the plague could safely assist the sick.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0" input="five"><feedback><p id="ad7ffdb6dbd304ef0b5706d66dc76bf02">Incorrect. The fact that people who recover from certain infectious diseases are usually resistant to those particular diseases dates back to Thucydides who noted that only those who had survived the plague could safely assist the sick. It is true that certain infectious diseases such as measles, mumps and chicken pox usually occur in childhood because a person cannot get these diseases a second time as an adult.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page><page id="c96b73201f624e3599c52d0431e062fd"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q6"><body><p id="d3503589767247369175b24d1d859622">One of the most remarkable features of the immune system is its ability to respond to an apparently limitless array of foreign antigens.</p><p id="a11a259b0b0f4e96b663a7ba8056508e"><input_ref input="six" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="six"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q6_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1" input="six"><feedback><p id="abf48eba5abc84552abd332e9cff7fc66">Correct. The generation of mature B cells first forms during the embryonic stages and continues throughout life. Although only a small fraction of the potential repertoire of B cell receptors is displayed in circulation at any one time, these cells have the capacity to generate greater than 1010 possible antibody –pathogen combining sites. </p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0" input="six"><feedback><p id="ae1646dc33dec4977a541a30c7fce45b8">Incorrect. It is true that individuals are born with an innate immune system that is limited in the array of foreign antigens that can be recognized. However, the adaptive arm of immunity though gene recombination, junctional flexibility and somatic mutations can apparently respond to a near limitless number of foreign antigens.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q7"><body><p id="c719acdc620144bba2b89103725b9578">When you begin to experience the flu or cold symptoms, it is wise to take extra doses of vitamins C and zinc to boost your immune system.</p><p id="e3e1fdecf4684879a5f7d220e2ec2011"><input_ref input="seven" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="seven"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q7_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0" input="seven"><feedback><p id="ac7f2f6763b4e4797a935eb83434aa1de">Incorrect. It is true that vitamins such as C and A and minerals such as zinc are absolutely necessary for a robust immune response. However, as long as an individual eats a balanced diet and follows the recommended daily allowances of vitamins and minerals, their immune system will respond as robustly as possible. More supplements will not improve the immune response and could actually be harmful.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="1" input="seven"><feedback><p id="ad55f0b0a250f46fe8af89fc7abbba504">Correct. It is true that malnourished or undernourished individual have noticed a “boost” in their immune response when supplements of vitamin C and A and the mineral zinc have been added to their daily diets. However, no evidence has been shown to indicate that increases above the normal physiologic values have improved immune function and in the case of vitamin A can actually prove harmful.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q8"><body><p id="eb982c70b3c24411aa6ae891e84465e3">Four year old Sarah has come down with the measles. It would be wise for her mother to keep Sarah away from her six year old brother Ben who has not had the measles.</p><p id="d23fae650582403abc55334e08a4b1c5"><input_ref input="eight" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="eight"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q8_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0" input="eight"><feedback><p id="ae7e409d51c9a43399eef5e08205f5a2b">Incorrect. If Ben is a normally healthy child it would be better for him to develop an immunity to measles while he is young. If Ben is exposed to the virus for the first time in adolescence or adulthood he may develop more unwanted complications from the immune response especially from a high fever.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="1" input="eight"><feedback><p id="afe8fac76f70b4b2ba515e659383d2172">Correct. If Ben is a normal healthy child his body will be able to fight off the virus and he will develop a more rapid and robust immune response if ever he is exposed to the virus in the future. </p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q9"><body><p id="d8e6948814e94766a3a03e1e1c60548a">Only healthy individuals should get the flu shot because you could get the flu from the vaccination.</p><p id="b023e3125f614cff9f1173ff9c0fac1e"><input_ref input="nine" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank shuffle="false" id="nine"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q9_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0" input="nine"><feedback><p id="aeecfeae187c14f5c8ae5d411dd3c1414">Incorrect. Only “killed” and fragmented components of the influenza virus are being introduced in the flu shot and they are incapable of infecting or reproducing in the body. Therefore, it is not possible for someone to actually get the flu from the vaccine. However, the virus fragments can cause the body to mount an immune response against them and this will provide the individual with a more rapid and robust immune response if the individual ever encounters the “live” virus in the future. Because the immune response is activated the individual may have mild symptoms of this response such as chills, fever and fatigue.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="1" input="nine"><feedback><p id="aab10a02f981f40b8a8aa52460355cf65">Correct. The flu shot only exposes the recipient to fragments of the virus which are incapable of infecting and reproducing in the body. Mild symptoms of the immune response, such as chills, fever and general malaise may be experienced. There is a nasal vaccination against the influenza virus that exposes an individual to “live” but weakened virus particles which may be able to infect the individual but incapable of reproducing in the body. This vaccine is only given to young healthy adults.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
