<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_bp_digt2"><title>tutor</title><page id="d48eaffaa6cc49aaaf99178b06ed9052"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q3"><body><p id="aa7fbe8a12a804c9aac9497cc8fcd6503">The immune system monitors and provides information about the external world as well as the changes and perturbations of the body’s internal environment. In addition to the immune reactions, the inflammatory process prevents further internal damage and promote repair. How are these responses triggered? Pick the best answer.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="e4ea01c51e7a4f2f986ee0f9bf49896b" labels="false"><choice value="A">A. In response to noxious stimuli such as extreme heat or cold, damaged cells and immune surveillance cells initiate a local inflammatory response</choice><choice value="B">B. Damaged tissues found internally such as ruptured endothelial cells or to torn muscles and ligaments release chemical signals in the local area which stimulate nearby cells to trigger an inflammatory response</choice><choice value="C">C. Bacterial toxins released into the bloodstream circulate throughout the body and reach the brain where they stimulate systemic responses such as fever, fatigue, anorexia and irritability</choice><choice value="D">One of A, B or C is incorrect</choice><choice value="E">A, B and C are all correct</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac69879f9efd8445facbdb6f04acb916e">Incorrect. This is an example of one way in which the external environment impacts the body and the body uses signals to try to limit the damage.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad41fe504dc4a4e1e9715a725113b8b23">Incorrect. Damaged tissues send out a variety of signals to stimulate changes in the local environment to aid wound repair and prevent further damage.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae83b44a15524419a9b850a2bad595dba">Incorrect. Fever, malaise, fatigue, and loss of appetite are often experienced even with a localized bacterial infection.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab34eac928c9e45adbebae5031c7fd72f">Incorrect. A, B and C are all examples of communication and signalling within the body which monitor changes in both the internal and external environment.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback><p id="af5271d900c7e4722bab54fe721197287">Correct. These are all examples of communication and signalling within the body which monitor changes in both the internal and external environment.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p id="ad10a2b5798504a31a1e015ca1853406f">The phrase “You are what you eat.” has been bantered around for a long time. In terms of immune functions why would what you eat matter?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="da4aa77ec25748cfa93d0917a9bcaf3a" labels="false"><choice value="A">All of the body’s cells and tissues need energy to grow, repair themselves and reproduce. Without ingesting adequate amounts fuel. The cells of the lymphatic system would not be able to make antibodies, Cytotoxic T cells, or maintain the integrity of physical and chemical barriers</choice><choice value="B">If you eat too many high fat foods, the cells in the immune system turn into adipocytes</choice><choice value="C">Actually it doesn’t matter, even people who are malnourished have adequately functioning immune systems</choice><choice value="D">The lymphatics in the digestive system called lacteals pick up the fats you have eaten and degrade them so that you don’t get too many calories</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa5cbc9a49a874b148978db2eb0a68860">Correct. All aspects of your body’s defense mechanisms require fuel.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad4a80ae8217d430aa0199a5583e085a2">Incorrect. As you age the cells in your thymus become replaced by fat cells but immunes system cells do not differentiate into fat cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aaf3c7c8dcbc1497ab0566d69edbda912">Incorrect. People who are malnourished often have immune systems which function at a much lower level.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aee3c100d48384684bd30af286007d026">The lacteals do indeed pick up fats which ultimately end up in the liver to be processed with the other molecules you may have ingested.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
