<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_bp_digt3"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The cliche question, &quot;which came first, the chicken or the egg?&quot; applies to the relationships between structure and function. In the body there are many examples of where function has altered structure or function has changed the structure. Which of the following is <em style="bold">not</em> an example of structure influencing function or function affecting structure?</body><multiple_choice id="mc1" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">The valves in the lymphatic vessels of the legs close tightly in response pressure from the lymph in the vessel. If there is too much fluid, the vessel bulges and may create a lumpy appearance on the leg.</choice><choice value="b">The tonsils which are found in the posterior pharynx have pits and grooves referred to as crypts. In some people the crypts are very deep and may even develop calcium deposits from items which have gotten stuck in the crypts. The people with deep grooves and pits often experience chronic tonsillitis.</choice><choice value="c">A chemical agent has caused a mutation in the genes that produce the proteins which become MHC receptors on the surface. The proteins now have one amino acid in the sequence which is different than it should be. The T cell can no longer distinguish self from non-self.</choice><choice value="d">As the result of a mastectomy a major lymphatic vessels which drains the right arm has been removed. The patient now experiences bouts of swelling that arm.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response input="mc1" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. This is a description of what may happen when the lymphatic vessels have more fluid to drain than they can transport.</feedback></response><response input="mc1" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Chronic tonsillitis is often a problem in people with particularly deep tonsillar crypts.</feedback></response><response input="mc1" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. If the structure of a protein is altered by changing the amino acid sequence, the protein may no longer function in the same way as it did before the mutation.</feedback></response><response input="mc1" match="d" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This scenario is indeed possible however, it is not an example of structure/function interactions because the structure was completely removed, not altered.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>People living in the 21st century think they invented the concept of multi-tasking. However, multi-tasking has been going on millions of years in each and every complex living organism. Pick the best answer which best illustrates this idea.</body><multiple_choice id="mc2" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">A bacterial infection from a splinter in your finger triggers the inflammatory response, an increase in the number of circulating neutrophils and triggers the pain receptors in your finger.</choice><choice value="b">HIV virus infects several necessary lymphocytes and ends up killing them.</choice><choice value="c">Return of lymph to the circulating blood helps to maintain adequate blood pressure.</choice><choice value="d">The RICE treatment (elevation, icing and resting) is the standard protocol for a sprained ankle.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response input="mc2" match="a" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This scenario involves molecular, cellular and systemic responses.</feedback></response><response input="mc2" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the interaction of a molecular virus and cells.</feedback></response><response input="mc2" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. The return of lymph to maintain blood pressure involves two different organ systems put does not illustrate interactions on other levels.</feedback></response><response input="mc2" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. RICE treatment is an anti-inflammatory response treatment on the systemic level.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>The human body is affected by changes in its external environment. The changes in the external environment could lead to changes in the internal environment to compensate for the outside changes. Which pair of events is a good illustration of these interactions?</body><multiple_choice id="mc3" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">The the outside temperature has increased drastically and you find you are too warm. You remove a layer of clothing to stay cooler.</choice><choice value="b">You are on an overnight flight to Europe flying in coach. You kicked off you shoes to try to sleep but now you cannot get them back on.</choice><choice value="c">You are camping and spending the evening sitting around the campfire. The wind shifts and the smoke blows in your face. You start coughing and sneezing and your eyes begin to burn.</choice><choice value="d">You are driving down the highway in the morning. When you started it was very foggy but now the sun had burned through so you need to reach for your sunglasses.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response input="mc3" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Shedding a layer of clothing is not an internal response.</feedback></response><response input="mc3" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an example of where your body did not compensate for a change in your external environment- remaining in the same position too long.</feedback></response><response input="mc3" match="c" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The coughing, sneezing and burning eyes are all part of the innate immune response to keep the particulate matter in the smoke from staying inside your body.</feedback></response><response input="mc3" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Reaching for your sunglasses does not change your internal ecosytem.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body>Taking the very long view, the survival of species depends on its ability to adapt to changes in its external ecosystem and pass those changes along to the next generation. Which is <em style="bold">not</em> an example of evolution working on some scale.</body><multiple_choice id="mc4" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">Some Staphylococcus aureus are now resistant to methicillin resulting in a disease we refer to as MRSA.</choice><choice value="b">In response to a second exposure to a pathogen a B cell memory cell clonally expands.</choice><choice value="c">As <em>Homo sapiens</em> migrated out of Africa and inhibited more northern climates with lower levels of daily sunlight in general the shade of skin pigments became lighter.</choice><choice value="d">Many vertebrate species have immunoglobulin genes which are closely related to each other.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response input="mc4" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. MRSA now occurs because of the acquired drug resistance of the bacteria.</feedback></response><response input="mc4" match="b" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The memory B cells are not passed on to the next generation so this is not an example of evolution.</feedback></response><response input="mc4" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. The is a working theory on why humans have developed so many variations in skin pigment.</feedback></response><response input="mc4" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. The related immunoglobulin genes are one way to show one species is related to another.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q5"><body>One way to think about homeostasis is to think about what happens when you drive a car. The car continues to move down the road but, you see obstacles in the road and you adjust the steering wheel to go around them, You are using gasoline but the engine runs at the same level as long as there is some gas in the tank, If you have an automatic transmission the speed of the engine changes to to provide more force to propel the car uphill or less if you are coasting downhill. When you run out of gas, drain the battery, spin out on a wet road or lose your keys homeostasis can be permanently disrupted to the point where the car can no longer head down the road. Which of the following are part of the lymphatics systems contribution to maintaining the body’s homeostasis.</body><multiple_choice><choice value="A">The mucus membranes in your mouth which trap foreign particles</choice><choice value="B">T cells mature in the thymus so they can distinguish self from non-self.</choice><choice value="C">HIV virus gets inside of the CD4 T cells</choice><choice value="D">The complement pathway activates in response to red blood cells in the tissue</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The mucus membrane in your mouth is part of your innate immunity but not part of the lymphatic system, it works with the lymphatic cells. This would be like using a battery charger to jump start your car. They two work together but one is not really part of the car.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Distinguishing cells from non-self is a key part of the immune system. Otherwise the system would never react or may be overactive. In terms of your car this would be the same as being able to start anyone’s car with your key.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. When HIV gets inside the CD4 cells which are T helper cells it kills them. Your immune system cannot function without T helper cells. This would be akin to running out of gas. As long as you have adequate T helper cells the immune system can function to some extent.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>The complement pathway destroys cells the body had deemed foreign. If is starts destroying red blood cells that leaked into the tissue, which happens. the result would be at the very least a chroinic inflammatory response. In the car world this would be like spinning out on the highway. the car is still running but it has lost its ability to travel in the direction you want. </feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
