<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_mp_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="adenoids"><body>When air passes over the adenoids and contains either a foreign pathogen or stimulatory molecule the tissue containing the lymphoid cells may become swollen and reactive and result in the sensation of a itchy roof of the mouth, of slightly stuffy nose or just feeling like there isn’t enough air. The most plausible explanation for this is</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">The physical abrasion of the air and particles suspended in the air have caused tissue damage.</choice><choice value="b">The microorganisms attacked the first tissue they landed on.</choice><choice value="c">The body is trying to block the entrance to the external ecosystem by physically closing it.</choice><choice value="d">The inhaled microorganisms or harmful particles are stimulating the cells in the adenoids to divide to address the invading microorganism or stimulate the inflammatory response to provide a means to eliminate the potentially harmful particle</choice></multiple_choice><part id="adenoids_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This explanation has some truth especially when breathing cold air, air filled with dust or other particles and relates to interacting with the external ecosystem, however, it doesn’t answer the question when you have been sitting in a quiet stall in the library all day</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Inhaled microorganisms may not find the environment of this particular niche of the internal ecosystem the most advantageous.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It would not be adaptive for the body to severely restrict airflow to prevent the entrance of potentially harmful particles.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If cells with the appropriate cell surface receptors are found in the adenoids they will be stimulated to divide as part of the immune response. In the case of inert particles the inflammatory response will be stimulated to provide a means to aggregate the particles and remove them from the body.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what happens not only when you are outside but sitting quietly in watching television in a clean room with normal air flow. Most of the time you do not react.</hint><hint>Microorganisms grow well in some places and not others the adenoids may not be the best environment for all micro organisms so it is not likely that every inhaled microorganism would find the best possible environment in the adenoids</hint><hint>You need to have air to breathe so blocking the entrance to the airway would hurt other parts of the body and may cause death.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q2"><body>The palatine tonsils are the major culprits in tonsillitis. When they become inflamed they may swell so large that the block the airway. Which aspects of the tonsils may contribute to this pathology?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">The deep crevices trap particles</choice><choice value="B">The tonsils contain receptors interact with commonly found molecules such as food proteins, viruses, pollen and and mold spores</choice><choice value="C">The white blood cells become become pussy and clog the throat</choice><choice value="D">All three are incorrect</choice><choice value="E">Each is correct.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an example of how physical structure can alter function but doesn’t address all the other issues.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The tonsils do contain receptors for molecules which may cross react with “non-harmful” environmental molecules such as food proteins and pollen. In some people this cross reaction would trigger an allergic reaction.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The white blood cells may contribute to pus formation but they are not the sole cause.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback>Correct.</feedback></response><hint>The problem is related to tonsil structure and function.</hint><hint>People with deep crevices in their tonsils are at greater risk for getting in infections but the crevices don’t necessarily make the tonsils larger</hint><hint>An aggregation of white blood cells a response to an infection and would explain the sore throat, drainage and horrible taste in your mouth</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q3"><body>The stem cells for the thymus are found in the cortex while the differentiated T cells are found in the medulla. What is the most likely explanation for why the thymus evolved a method a method to keep maturing T cells sequestered from the bloodstream? </body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Random mutations of the genes in the T cells could produce cells which were capable of stimulating a reaction against the body’s own proteins. Those cells need to be eliminated before entering the circulation.</choice><choice value="B">The T cells evolved from a special set of stem cells that can only be found in the thymus</choice><choice value="C">Random mutation of the cells which make up the structure of the thymus would interfere with T cell function</choice><choice value="D">Adipocytes would gain access to the thymus and kill all the T cells</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. There is even a blood-thymus barrier to keep those cells protected until they are differentiated enough to become functioning T cells.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. All of the cells in the body are descendents of the original one cell zygote.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The cells which make up the structure of the thymus do not influence the maturation of the T cells.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It is correct that the thymus tissue is gradually replaced with adipose as a normal part of the aging process. There is no competition for adipocytes and T stem cells for space in the thymus.</feedback></response><hint>Adipocytes are not competitive with lymphocyte stem cells.</hint><hint>All of the white blood cells arise from stem cells that are found in the bone marrow</hint><hint>Rearrangements of genes within the lymphocyte stem cells allow for responses to a diverse group of antigens.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q4"><body>The spleen is an organ that contributes to homeostasis in several ways affecting several organ systems. Which of the following is not a way in which the spleen contributes to homeostasis?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Filtering out cell debris plus dead and dying cells</choice><choice value="B">Removing large biomolecules from the digestive system through by passing the blood supply</choice><choice value="C">Housing the B and T lymphocytes which would clonally expand when presented with the correct antigen</choice><choice value="D">Regulating blood volume and fluid levels</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The spleen not only filters out debris and dying cells but it also recycles some of the molecules found associated with red blood cells.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Transporting fats from the digestive system to the liver is indeed a lymphatic function, but is performed by lymph vessels called lacteals.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The white pulp of the spleen contains memory cells which are capable of responding to an antigen which the body had previously encountered.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The spleen, while a non-essential organ, is the body’s largest single blood reservoir and plays an important role in regulating blood volume especially in response to rapid blood loss.</feedback></response></part></question></page><page><question id="q5"><body>The interesting fact that yellow bone marrow retains the potential to differentiate into red marrow after extreme blood loss, illustrates several of the overlying principles of physiology. Which principles seem to be best illustrated?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Homeostasis and external and internal ecosystem</choice><choice value="B">Causal Organisms living by the laws of Chemistry and Physics</choice><choice value="C">The Cell is the unit of life and the relationship between structure and function</choice><choice value="D">All of the answers are correct</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. These two Big Ideas are at work here. The body is responding to a significant blood loss which is a drastic change in the internal ecosystem and a threat to homeostasis.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The laws of chemistry and physics still apply here but don’t account for the change.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is not a structure-function issue. While the cellular content of the marrow changes the structure inside the bone cavity hasn’t really changed.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Not all the answers are correct.</feedback></response><hint>While all the answers do refer to at least one Big Idea, not all of the Big Ideas are needed to explain this example</hint><hint>The laws of chemistry and physics are about how molecules interact with each other and the movement of particles in space and time.</hint><hint>The conversion of yellow matter into white matter is about cells, but not really about cells as the basic living unit. There is no alteration in the structure of the bone marrow to accommodate a change in the internal environment.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q6"><body>When a lymph vessel is full of fluid, the valves sometime bulge, giving the vessel a beaded appearance even under normal circumstances. The most logical explanation for this is:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">There has been significant edema and there is too much lymph</choice><choice value="B">Gravity is working on the lymph and the valves are bulging because of the pressure on them</choice><choice value="C">The lymph vessel cells are rapidly dividing</choice><choice value="D">The lymph fluid is very viscous and sticks to the vessel walls.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q6_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If there is too much edema the fluid stays in the tissues; it doesn’t pool in the vessels.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Gravity works on lymph similarly to the way it works on blood.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.The lymph vessel cells do not have a high rate of reproduction.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Lymph fluid is about the same as tissue fluid.</feedback></response><hint>While significant edema could overload the system the swellings can be seen even under normal circumstances</hint><hint>The cells inside the lymph vessels respond to damage but don’t reproduce rapidly.</hint><hint>The lymph fluid is very similar to normal tissue fluid.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="lymph_nodes"><body>The lymph nodes are an excellent example of structure and function because:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">They contain lymphocytes</choice><choice value="B">The often swell and become painful when fighting infection</choice><choice value="C">They have a capsule which keeps them isolated from the internal ecosystem</choice><choice value="D">Of the fact that the anatomic structure causes the transit time across lymph nodes to be long enough for adequate immune surveillance to occur.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="lymph_nodes_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_organs_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The lymphocytes are not really tied to the structure.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The inflammatory response happens anywhere regardless of function.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The capsule is part of the structure but not the major contributor to the function.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The structure directs the fluid flow.</feedback></response><hint>The lymphocytes are important for the immune response but don’t contribute to the structure of the node</hint><hint>The capsule helps to keep the fluid in but doesn’t really protect the internal ecosystem</hint><hint>The inflammatory process causes the swelling and tenderness</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
