<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_bp_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="fae6ba00d159467cb565d81be7cd8822"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="adceb605e020041b48b64c6fbce0e4a0e">Both innate and adaptative immunity require a variety of fully functioning cells to provide the best protection. When someone is undergoing chemotherapy they often experience a decrease in their immune functions as a result of their treatment. Since the cell is the basic unit of life, which of the following is most likely affected?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="c946e1753f8242e69d9c14e1f0e7f2ff" labels="false"><choice value="A">Living things have complex structures and chemotherapy results in the evolution of cells which are highly simplified</choice><choice value="B">Living things need to be able to undergo metabolism and chemotherapy starves the cells</choice><choice value="C">Living things reproduce themselves and chemotherapy inhibits the ability of some key cells such as lymphocytes and the epithelium of mucus membranes to divide quickly in response to damage or and invader.</choice><choice value="D">Chemotherapy inhibits the growth of immune cells by reducing their ability to produce needed molecules.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="adc7bc3df92e345d4901c5fd37c40e0a7">Incorrect. Chemotherapy may alter the differentiation pathway of some stem and pluripotent cells but it does not make the cell any less complex.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ace35da4d2b2946e2837045b6fa9056a9">Incorrect. Patients undergoing chemotherapy often have difficulty maintaining adequate nutrition this is because the absorptive cells of their digestive system are being killed and sloughed away. Chemotherapy does not alter the cells ability to get nutrients.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="af5bea07b7c86477197094256020715f4">Correct. Chemotherapy kills rapidly dividing cells. The immune system relies of the integrity of the epithelial membranes and the ability of the lymphocytes to reproduce and clonally expand.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aef661b7d8fcc4a3aa82f29467c8b8c14">Incorrect. Chemotherapy kills cells by attacking the machinery the cell needs to replicate its DNA and keep its membrane intact. If chemotherapy doesn&apos;t kill a cell, the cell is likely to carry out its normal growth pattern.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="ace78151cc4ea45a5a7d322b77f258c2d">When lymph passes through the lymph nodes the velocity of the flow decreases in comparison to that in the lymphatic vessels. Which of the following physical or chemical principle would best explain this?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="c6356785bd234d02aaa2ef17a9b351dd" labels="false"><choice value="A">Electrochemical binding such as hydrogen bonding or Van der Waal forces of the molecules in the fluid with the molecules on the surface of the the lymphocytes creates an increase in resistance that slows the velocity of flow.</choice><choice value="B">The increased cross-sectional area of the lymph node leads to a decrease in the velocity of flow. </choice><choice value="C">There is a concentration gradient created when the molecules in the lymph enter the lymph node compared to the lymph in the lymph capillaries. This retards lymph flow.</choice><choice value="D">The oxygen and other gasses dissolved in the lymph undergo a change in partial pressures because of the increase in the volume of the lymph node compared to the volume of the incoming vessel. This expansion slows the lymph fluid flow.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_bp_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad1c18e779d564b78823380a054f9df10">Incorrect. The electrical and chemical balance of the molecules in the lymph are essentially the same as the molecules in the interstitial fluids and spaces. The lymph node is a biological structure without any unusual electrical or chemical properties so this is not a good explanation for why lymph experiences a change in velocity when it enters a node.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab6daf3b07eb34431b157e6c42f82369e">Correct. The laws of fluid flow indicate that the cross-sectional area of flow increases, the velocity will decrease.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af095ad704e6543ed9c728ca0a4c870e2">Incorrect. The molecular content of the lymph does not drastically change while it is in the lymph node.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae9a67e9a58c7403db3f29962134cf97c">Incorrect. Although the lymph node has a larger volume than the individual vessels leading into the node, the increased fluid provides added pressure on the node wall so an expansion of the dissolved gasses is not very likely. </p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
