<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousANS_homeo2"><head><title>Dual Innervation</title><objref idref="describe_effectors_LO" /></head><body><p id="c35cf75154664766b0b9edffcef62642">As you might expect, certain organs and tissues receive innervation from both the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems. These organs are said to be “<term>dually innervated</term>.” An example of this is how the parasympathetic division facilitates micturition and defecation, while sympathetic input activates sphincters of the bladder and the rectum, impending micturition and defecation, respectively.</p><example id="f794f7b72f83403dad2cbf45296238ef"><title>Dually Innervated Heart and Lungs</title><p id="f62e8d6736934aacb3e1a254d8caa4b3">The heart and lungs are dually innervated. Alterations of the pace and the force of contraction of heart muscles are influenced by the effect of the vagus nerve on the pacemaker cells of the heart. Parasympathetic input to both right and left vagus (CN X) nerves provide cervical cardiac nerves to the cardiac plexus. The preganglionic sympathetic fibers to the heart originate from the T1-T4/ T5 of the spinal cord. Normal heart rhythm is in the 60-100 beats per minute range. During restful conditions, the vagus nerve (CN X), through parasympathetic input, has the dominant influence that maintains the heart rate in the 60-80 beats per min (bpm) range. Under stress, excitement, or exertion, sympathetic stimulation can shift the heart rate to greater than 100 bpm. A slower than normal heart rate, less than 60 bpm, mediated by vagus nerve and the parasympathetic nervous system or an illness, is referred to as bradycardia. A faster than normal heart rate can be mediated by sympathetic nervous systems or can be due to illness, and is referred to as tachycardia.</p><p id="b05ef1dda3f3438a9107b67af4960746">For lung innervation, the sympathetic and parasympathetic divisions of the autonomic nervous system nerves are arranged as the <term>pulmonary plexi</term> and innervate the smooth muscle and glands of the bronchi and pulmonary blood vessels. The sympathetic preganglionic fibers to the lungs arise from T1-T4. The sympathetic stimulation of the bronchial smooth muscles is achieved by the epinephrine released from adrenal glands. Overall, the sympathetic stimulation causes vasoconstriction and bronchodilation in the lungs. Stimulation by parasympathetic input causes vasodilation and bronchoconstriction in the lungs.</p><image id="ca147d06519143ca812e250e72364bdd" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_61.jpg" alt="Dually innervated cardiac nerves." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption><p id="a7af179254a94173bab985f638778e82">Dually innervated cardiac nerves. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="fd1a5c1a8d0a476f992c884dab50bc1a">Everybody is familiar with asthma. Whatever the causality, asthma is characterized by bronchoconstriction due to increased sensitivity to irritating stimuli (which could be due to allergic response to certain antigens or due to irritants in the environment like coal dust, exhaust fumes, etc.). Increased mucus secretions rapid bronchoconstriction leads to labored breathing which we know as “asthma.”</p></example><wb:inline idref="describe_effectors_DIGT1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="autonomic_asthma_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
