<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousANS_structure7"><head><title>ANS Neurotransmitters</title><objref idref="describe_para_symp_effects_LO" /><objref idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LO" /></head><body><p id="e7f963727fcd4f98b44d23a7d9edee56">Before we discuss the neurotransmitters for autonomic nervous system, let us refresh our memory about these molecules. Neurotransmitters are chemical “signals” that travel from a neuron (presynaptic cell) to the next cell (neuron, muscle, glands, etc.) to relay information necessary for the task that this “next” cell should perform. Chemically, these molecules are quite varied, ranging from a simple gaseous molecule (nitric oxide) to peptides (endorphin). The most widespread of all neurotransmitters in your body is <term>acetylcholine (ACh)</term>. This is the neurotransmitter we came across in an earlier chapter on skeletal muscles. In the somatic nervous system, which is a <term>“one neuron system”</term> where the signal is carried by one neuron from the CNS to the target organ, the neurotransmitter is always ACh which activates skeletal muscles. In the parasympathetic division, this same neurotransmitter is released by both preganglionic neuron (at the ganglionic synapse) as well as postganglionic neuron (at the effector synapse). In the sympathetic division, the preganglionic neuron releases the same ACh as the neurotransmitter, but the postganglionic neurons release <term>norepinephrine</term> (NE; a catecholamine synthesized from phenylalanine). However, if the target organ for the postganglionic sympathetic neuron is a sweat gland, the neurotransmitter is again ACh.</p><wb:inline idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /><p id="e7ebb8f9810d4cf6be0301169e60f2bf">The longest of the preganglionic sympathetic fibers do not synapse in any conventional ganglia but directly onto the <term>chromaffin cells</term> of the <term>adrenal medullae</term>. The chromaffin cells can be thought of as modified postsynaptic neurons that form microganglia. These medullary cells, upon stimulation by ACh released by the sympathetic preganglionic neuron, release <term>epinephrine</term> and, to a lesser extent, <term>norepinephrine</term>. These molecules function as hormones of the sympathetic system, and are released into the bloodstream, which propagates the sympathetic response throughout the body. </p><section id="fc481edc2f4841b29fcfd8a718f1a768" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_DIGT2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LBD3" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><wb:inline idref="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LBD2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
