<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousANS_structure4">
	<head>
		<title>Anatomy of the Parasympathetic (Craniosacral) Division</title>
		<objref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The nerve fibers that constitute the parasympathetic division originate at
			the two anatomical ends of the central nervous system. The cranial nerves, CN III, CN
			VII, CN IX and CN X and the sacral spinal nerves S2, S3 and S4 carry the presynaptic
			(or, pre-ganglionic) parasympathetic outflow. The presynaptic neurons of the sacral part
			of the Craniosacral division lie in the lateral horns of the spinal cord at the
			appropriate level. These neurons extend into the body’s internal organs only and synapse
			at the <term>terminal</term> (that lie close to the organ) or <term>intramural</term>
			(within the target organ) ganglia. The exceptions are the four paired parasympathetic
			ganglia of the head and neck. Of the four cranial nerves mentioned above, CNIII
			supplies the <term>ciliary</term> ganglion; <em>CNVII</em> supplies the
				<term>pterygopalatine</term> and <term>submandibular ganglia</term>; and
				<em>CNIX</em> supplies the <term>otic ganglion</term>. The <term>Vagus nerve
				(CNX)</term>, as you have learned before, gets its name from its “wandering” nature.
			It does wander in the thoracic and abdominopelvic cavities in your body to synapse on
			postsynaptic (or postganglionic) neurons that innervate the heart, bronchi, stomach,
			liver and the intestines. There are no named ganglia for these organs. </p>

		<wb:inline idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT3" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT4" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
