<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousANS_homeo3">
	<head>
		<title>Sympathetic and Parasympathetic Effectors</title>
		<objref idref="name_exclusive_effectors_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="explain_sympathetic_innervation_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>There are certain effectors in your body that are not dually innervated.  
			Sweat glands, arrector pili muscles, adrenal medula, liver, adipocytes, 
			lacrymal glands, radial muscle of the iris, juxtaglomerular apparatus, 
			uterus and most vascular smooth muscles have only sympathetic 
			innervation.  In contrast to the sympathetic system, there are 
			relatively few organs that function only with parasympathetic 
			stimulation.  Examples of such organs are the circular muscle of iris 
			which causes pupillary constriction and the parietal cells of the 
			stomach that secrete gastric acid.  </p>
		
		<p>Most vasculature of smooth muscles receive only sympathetic innervations.  
			The balance of vascular constriction and dilation is mediated by 
			sympathetic tone.  The tone of a single vessel is proportional to the 
			sympathetic stimulation it is receiving.  More stimulation leads to 
			more constriction, and, as sympathetic input to the vessel decreases, 
			the vessel relaxes.  Also, it is important to recognize that the impact 
			of the release of epinephrine or norepinephrine on blood vessels is 
			dependent on the subtype of neurotransmitter receptor on those blood 
			vessels.  For example, sympathetic activation leads to constriction of 
			most vasculature in the body (mediated through stimulation of 
			alpha-type receptors), but leads to dilation of coronary vessels 
			supplying the heart (mediated through stimulation of beta-type 
			receptors).  The difference in how the vessel responds is due to 
			the type of <term>adrenergic</term> receptor, and, ultimately, what type of 
			intracellular signaling pathways are engaged to drive the vascular 
			response.  Adrenergic receptors are stimulated by either 
			norepinephrine or epinephrine. </p>
		<p>Most vessels in the body have the alpha-type receptor for binding 
			norepinephrine, which results in vasoconstriction.  Vasculature of 
			the heart, on the other hand, has beta-type receptors for binding 
			norepinephrine, which results in vasodilation.  Also, recall that 
			sympathetic nervous system activation causes release of epinephrine 
			by chromaffin cells of adrenal medullae.  Epinephrine has a greater 
			effect on stimulating beta receptors than does norepinephrine, which 
			means that epinephrine has a stronger effect on cardiac stimulation 
			and a much weaker effect on blood vessels in muscles.  Stimulation of 
			beta receptors in the heart causes dilation of coronary blood vessels supplying the 
			heart, increase heart rate, and increase in the strength of contraction 
			of cardiac muscle.  Blood vessels in skeletal muscles express alpha 
			and beta adrenergic receptors.  During exercise, blood vessels in 
			skeletal muscle dilate, and, among many possible factors (ATP, lactic 
			acid, carbon dioxide, oxygen, adenosine) that could cause this 
			vasodilation, circulating epinephrine released into the bloodstream 
			by chromaffin cells in the adrenal medullae is one other possible 
			factor.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="name_exclusive_effectors_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
