<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousANS_structure1"><head><title>The Role of ANS</title><objref idref="compare_somatic_autonomic_systems_LO" /><objref idref="explain_autonomic_motor_LO" /></head><body><p id="ab14d1c2bd6c4d979cd6a58478f1163b">The peripheral nervous system is divided into two functional subdivisions:</p><ul id="fe32ddc1bc35418f8d34122365340106"><li><p id="ac00b419519944fee8c8014bfdb62a7c7">Somatic Nervous System (SNS)</p></li><li><p id="ae134339ff5514d59a8c45c7b42fe81cd">Autonomic Nervous System (ANS)</p></li></ul><p id="e860fcf3973a4c539d2acfceec35687d">The autonomic nervous system is further divided into the <term>sympathetic</term> and <term>parasympathetic</term> branches.</p><image id="b114f5db269d45018ee3dd4794fd1051" src="../webcontent/nervous_division2.png" alt="A visual representation of the nervous system, how it is divided into a Peripheral NS and Central NS and from there." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="aae8e9017b138421c855939c71f48d63e">Division of the Nervous System into Peripheral NS and Central NS.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d5c033e379b74944b33143c33847c820">The somatic nervous system <term>(SNS)</term> deals with sensory input and voluntary motor (efferent) activities, while the autonomic nervous system <term>(ANS)</term> deals only with efferent (motor) signals from the CNS to control activities in the body that are distinct from those under conscious voluntary control. The targets of efferents are called <term>effectors</term>, and these are organs, muscles or glands. The autonomic nervous system is also called the visceral nervous system because it controls smooth muscle, cardiac muscle, and glands, which make up the viscera of the body.</p><p id="eea1e4ced39f4bd8b7d9f6eafbf678a4">Sensory information from internal organs (namely, the blood vessels, the heart, and the abdominopelvic organs) reaches the CNS levels of medulla, pons and hypothalamus, often without ever reaching sensory cortex of your cerebrum and, thereby, not reaching conscious awareness. These inputs elicit reflex responses through the efferent autonomic nerves. As necessary, the ANS neurons elicit appropriate reactions of the heart, the vascular system, and all the organs of the body in response to variations in the environment – physical or biochemical (See the <activity_link idref="NervousANS_homeo1" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">Homeostasis and Integrated Function</activity_link> section for more about role of the autonomic nervous system in maintaining the environment of the body). </p><p id="c3c917d6336b48529116773f5adb24af">The following table compares basic structural and functional features of the SNS and the ANS:</p><table id="compare_ans" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><title>Comparison of the Somatic and the Autonomic Divisions of the Nervous System.</title><cite id="i14fe69fba7e74417934a5175f9781719" /><caption><p id="abe5e9b5885b14b4d87ebbbf5983cccf4"></p></caption><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="addf3027caa7747e2a771091775ccc26a">Somatic</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af12c79c45ef049bb80e91a8ae0c5b00b">Autonomic</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa986b5bec85b4de19c12af4976dedb10">Involves both afferent and efferent pathways</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aeb81bfdddc9842f0917be99af5cf29aa">Involves only the efferent pathway</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abe40682fff86452fa1a49ad4209bf165">Voluntary activities, including locomotion (effectors are skeletal muscles)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac345538457a8421aa53c09b7e86463e1">Involuntary activities (effectors are cardiac muscle, smooth muscles, fat cells, and glands)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab811dfd44cfd4b94af929127198db77b">Efferent signals originate at the cerebral cortex as a conscious decision and activate neurons in the brainstem or spinal cord</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac2bd979e10ba4b05ba52a690a0210639">Unconscious signals originate in hypothalamus, brain stem, and spinal cord and activate target neurons that lie in the peripheral nervous system</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa887aec450bd46a2a45d81b06dbcea9a">Brainstem and spinal cord neuron exerts direct control over skeletal muscle (one neuron system, where there are no intermediate synapses between the CNS and the target organs)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af099dadb41434bb2bd93d5df3ce04505">Target neurons in the peripheral nervous system are grouped in ganglia and their axons exert direct control over smooth muscle, cardiac muscle, glands, and fat cells (two neuron system, where the efferent neurons synapse once outside the CNS before the signals reach the target organs.)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad645142d97f54a25b5d5d33346a4c2fe">Efferent axons are myelinated (fast conduction)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="acbe511880c2f46c090676b28d2ce5187">Postsynaptic axons are non-myelinated (slow conduction); presynaptic axons are myelinated</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae26a75b02b8d466c9cf8327a2a2a37da">Neuromuscular junctions are specific and localized</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab549afabcb024efa876fbb969cc8fdc4">Synapses at the target organs for the axons of the ANS may be diffuse (varicosities).</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="acf6adc9acf9549a093928ee2e05aa9fa">Target organs (skeletal muscles) are always stimulated into action</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abc7bbb47a4704f069707aa4a23d8c3d0">ANS used several different neurotransmitter molecules (predominantly ACh and norepinephrine, NE)</p></td></tr></table><wb:inline idref="compare_somatic_autonomic_systems_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
