<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousANS_structure3"><head><title>Anatomy of the Sympathetic (Thoracolumbar) Division</title><objref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LO" /></head><body><p id="c3ffc45e80754cb2b44d0739bd95b764">The cell bodies of the preganglionic neurons in the sympathetic division lie in the lateral horns of the 
spinal cord from the segments T1 through L2. The axon of the preganglionic neuron typically exits at 
the same level to synapse with the cell bodies and dendrites of the postsynaptic sympathetic neurons. 
These postsynaptic neuronal cell bodies make up the <term>paravertebral ganglia</term> that lie close to the spinal 
cord (around- or by the vertebrae) or <term>sympathetic chain ganglia</term> (the ganglia form a chain like structure 
on either side of the vertebral column). As described below, the sympathetic chain has ganglia adjacent 
to the thoracolumbar vertebrae, as well as adjacent to some cranial and sacral vertebrae. </p><p id="f0b98dbd64e446afa5a980f99ce464a1">Adjacent paravertebral ganglia are connected via ascending and descending preganglionic sympathetic fibers 
forming longitudinal cords running parallel to the spinal cord. These connecting branches may be referred to 
as <term>interganglionic rami</term> (ramus = branch). Together with the ganglia, they form the <term>sympathetic trunk</term> on either 
side (<term>bilateral</term>) of the vertebral column. Its cephalic end continues into the skull through the <term>carotid canal</term>, 
while caudally it converges with its counterpart anterior to the coccyx. </p><p id="a7a1048d56304f2ba3a2fb7afcb398a8">As mentioned in a previous <xref idref="compare_ans" target="self" page="NervousANS_structure1">comparison table</xref> (row 4), the ANS has a sequential two-neuron efferent pathway, 
where each autonomic ganglion contains the synapse between the preganglionic neuron (the neuron that exits the CNS) 
and the postganglionic neuron (the neuron that innervates the target organ).</p><p id="e9e83a4ef8654f46a99ed135794a55f8">The <term>presynaptic sympathetic fibers</term> entering the <term>sympathetic chain</term> may:</p><materials id="d869ffed61594ba6afa1a28ad9703373"><material><image id="cbf72d5680e8421e8f986c1f50c26bf3" src="../webcontent/Nerv_60.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption><p id="afb118300dbc6499dbfa446a968b756f6">Three possibilities of what happens when presynaptic sympathetic fibers enter the sympathetic chain. Drawn by Debra McLaughlin.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><ol id="c460e5383a4b45bb92d8d39f1c02a3a3"><li><p id="acd5ede6bbd0145f88f55c67a9dc92e85">synapse immediately on the postsynaptic neuron in the ganglion located at the same level it entered;</p></li><li><p id="aa1c5f83a21644b2d965a785af3190263">ascend or descend down the sympathetic trunk before synapsing in a ganglion located at a different level; </p></li><li><p id="afc127dbe70d04290ad5ffd94088d1399">pass through the sympathetic chain ganglia without synapsing at all, synapsing instead in a prevertebral 
ganglion (also known as the collateral ganglion). </p></li></ol></material></materials><p id="b522b0db7bde4339b6a901d9650607e3">As you will see shortly, the internal organs of the abdomen 
and pelvis are primarily supplied by the fibers of this third pathway, while, generally, structures located 
in the head, neck, body wall, limbs and thoracic cavity are innervated by one the first two pathways.</p><wb:inline idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT2" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
