<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousANS_structure2">
	<head>
		<title>Anatomy of Parasympathetic &amp; Sympathetic Systems</title>
		<objref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The two parts of the autonomic nervous system are organized differently. The
			parasympathetic nervous system is derived from preganglionic neurons in the brainstem
			and from preganglionic neurons in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at sacral levels.
			Preganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system lie in the lateral horn of the
			spinal cord at thoracic and lumbar levels of the spinal cord. This differential
			distribution of the preganglionic neurons of the two systems gives rise to the names
			“craniosacral division” for the parasympathetic nervous system and “thoracolumbar
			division” for the sympathetic division. This is depicted in a generalized manner and will be discussed in detail below.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/as_general_org.png" alt="Generalized organization of the ANS showing that each part of the ANS is bilateral." width="500"><caption>Image drawn by Debra McLaughlin.</caption></image>

		<p>Parasympathetic preganglionic neurons originate from midbrain, pons, medulla oblongata,
			and lateral horn of the spinal cord at sacral levels S2-S4. Axons of parasympathetic
			preganglionic neurons travel to synapse at or within their target tissue.</p>

		<p>Sympathetic preganglionic neurons originate from the lateral horn of spinal cord segment
			levels thoracic T1 -T12 and lumbar L1-L2.</p>

		<p>At the cervical and upper thoracic levels, axons of preganglionic sympathetic neurons
			synapse onto postganglionic neurons that originate at the sympathetic chain ganglia
			which lies to the side of the spinal cord and vertebral column, i.e., paravertebral. At
			spinal cord levels T1-L2, axons of preganglionic neurons pass through the sympathetic
			chain and synapse onto postganglionic neurons in one of the three midline collateral
			(prevertebral, i.e., lying anterior to the vertebral column) ganglia.</p>

		<p>Postganglionic neurons release neurotransmitter onto the target tissue, resulting in
			either excitation or inhibition of cells in the target gland, muscle, or tissue.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/ans_diagram4.png" id="sympathetic_anatomy">
			<caption><link href="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/File:Autonomic_nervous_system_main_figure_Blessing.gif">
				http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/File:Autonomic_nervous_system_main_figure_Blessing.gif</link></caption>
		</image>
		
	<section purpose="learnbydoing">
		<title/>
		<body>
			<wb:inline idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			<wb:inline idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LBD2" purpose="learnbydoing"/></body>
	</section>
		
		
		
		

	</body>
</workbook_page>
