<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_system_homeostasis"><title>Tutor</title><page><question id="more_oxygen"><body><p>As a person exercises their muscles require more energy. To produce energy, the muscles require more oxygen. The respiratory system responds to this need by increasing the rate of respiration. </p><p>Additionally in response to the epinephrine produced during exercise the <input_ref input="A" /> will <input_ref input="B" /> making it easier to move an increased volume in and out of the lungs.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">trachea</choice><choice value="two">bronchioles</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">dilate</choice><choice value="two">constrict</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="describe_oxygen_homestasis" /><response name="trachea" input="A" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The trachea is composed of C-shaped cartilage rings that remain open to allow air in and out. </feedback></response><response name="bronchioles" input="A" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The smooth muscle of the bronchioles can change the diameter of these smaller tubes. </feedback></response><hint>The higher volume of air we can move into the respiratory system the more oxygen.</hint></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="describe_oxygen_homestasis" /><response name="dilate" input="B" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Dilating the airways will increase the diameter and allow for air to flow more readily through the respiratory system.</feedback></response><response name="constrict" input="B" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Constricting the airways will decrease the diameter and inhibit air flow which will not help the body receive more oxygen. </feedback></response><hint>The walls of the alveoli are so thin that the hydrogen bonds between water molecules need to be disrupted so the alveoli can open and close properly.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="blood_ph"><body><p>In addition to providing the body with an increased supply of oxygen the respiratory system must also maintain the homeostasis of blood pH. If the pH of the blood rises above 7.45 it can result in respiratory alkalosis. If the pH of the blood falls lower than 7.35 the result is respiratory alkalosis. If the level of carbon dioxide in the blood increases with no homeostatic influence from the respiratory system it could result in <input_ref input="C" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">respiratory alkalosis</choice><choice value="two">respiratory acidosis</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="blood_ph_p1"><skillref idref="describe_role_blood_pH_oxygen_homestasis" /><response name="respiratory_alkalosis" input="C" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Alkalosis occurs when the blood becomes too basic. When carbon dioxide reacts with water it forms carbonic acid, which would cause the blood to become more acidic not basic.</feedback></response><response name="respiratory_acidosis" input="C" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Acidosis occurs when the blood becomes too acidic. Carbon dioxide combines with water to form carbonic acid which will result in raising the acidity which lowers the pH. </feedback></response><hint>On the pH scale 7.1 and above is basic and 6.9 and below is acidic.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="hyperventilation"><body><p>Hyperventilating occurs when a person is breathing too fast. This results in the release of too much carbon dioxide. The release of too much carbon dioxide would result in <input_ref input="D" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="D" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">respiratory alkalosis</choice><choice value="two">respiratory acidosis</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="hyperventilation_p1"><skillref idref="describe_role_blood_pH_oxygen_homestasis" /><response name="respiratory_alkalosis" input="D" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Alkalosis occurs when the blood becomes too basic. When carbon dioxide normally reacts with water to create carbonic acid in the blood. If too much carbon dioxide is released it can lower the acidity of the blood and increase the pH resulting in alkalosis.</feedback></response><response name="respiratory_acidosis" input="D" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Acidosis occurs when the blood becomes too acidic. Carbon dioxide combines with water to form carbonic acid which will result in raising the acidity which lowers the pH. Breathing out too much carbon dioxide would increase the pH.</feedback></response><hint>On the pH scale 7.1 and above is basic and 6.9 and below is acidic.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="paper_bag"><body>A common treatment for hyperventilation has been to breath into a paper bag. Based on what you know about how the respiratory system functions to maintain homeostasis. Explain why this may help hyperventilation but may also cause serious problems. </body><short_answer id="E" /><part><response input="E" match="*" score="10" /><hint>What are the two gasses that the respiratory system works to exchange?</hint><explanation>By breathing out into a paper bag a person creates air that is rich in carbon dioxide. Hyperventilation lowers the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood by inhaling air that is rich in carbon dioxide a person can restore some of that carbon dioxide. If the carbon dioxide levels in the blood fall too far it can result in hypocapnia which can result in the dilation of blood vessels and an increased affinity of hemoglobin for oxygen. These two things can cause a lack of oxygen being supplied to the brain. The other issue can occur when a person is breathing the air from the bag, they are breathing air with a lower concentration of oxygen which lowers the amount of oxygen available to the person. </explanation></part></question></page></assessment>
