<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u11_m2_structures_wrapup"><head><title>Respiratory Structures and Functions Review and Assessment</title></head><body><section id="c7fa96d17e1a45efa0cb93bfdba24dca"><title>Let’s Summarize</title><body><p id="bc50e822dfbe4b489060d32b97bf88c3">Structure determines function. To understand how the respiratory system performs its function it is essential to examine the anatomical structures of the system. Previously we examined the microscopic components of the respiratory system. Now we will place those components into the gross anatomy of the upper and lower respiratory tracts. After examining the structure we discussed how these structures perform the functions of the respiratory system and how the efficiency of these functions is measured.</p><ul id="e540e19ec32944d6a4c486d817bc374a"><li><p id="ad7cd1843b3544b208f997e874cc63c19">Entrance to the upper respiratory tract is through the nose or the mouth. </p><ul id="a0e6c62ae01f494dbb63dc5ca79181de"><li><p id="abfa25a754a944e97a8c9d7b3b85bbff5">The nasal cavity contains structures such as hair, sebaceous glands and mucus that aid in preventing microorganisms from entering.</p></li><li><p id="ac7730e3fa2f94f3083e9a6500491380b">The nasal cavity also contains olfactory epithelium for the sense of smell.</p></li><li><p id="ad094b7667af84b30a8183dad96109b18">The conchae of the nose contain mucus glands and blood vessels to aid in humidifying and warming the air.</p></li><li><p id="ae3be81d9e3b04c658af972416387d89b">The paranasal sinuses are hollow areas that make the skull lighter and also moisten and warm incoming air.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="ac97885c6d58b4dc78d37f7e6aa381567">Next the air passes into the pharynx which is divided into three areas and connects to the larynx. </p><ul id="a14f462a962d42cc95b150f0a34e78c0"><li><p id="ad9458e004145454a89fdcbf55510e673">The nasopharynx is the superior portion of the pharynx and only acts as a passageway for air.</p></li><li><p id="ae55ed2f2912c4356a8f5ea34bb82273e">The oropharynx extends from the soft palate to the epiglottis, and is covered in stratified squamous epithelia to protect it from the friction of food as it is swallowed.</p></li><li><p id="aef460f04ad7847a5aecd16c986e2ac82">The laryngopharynx is the third and shortest portion of the pharynx. It extends from the epiglottis and ends above the esophagus. It is lined with stratified squamous epithelia to protect it from the friction of food as it is swallowed. Both the oropharynx and the laryngopharynx are passageways used to transport both air and food.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="ac83a7e59b3fb40dea87e03fb8574a248">The tonsils are patches of lymphatic tissue that help protect the body against pathogens by filtering them from the air. </p><ul id="dd8d83fcb7f94a81a8233e4498a1ee55"><li><p id="af5df488b43c24e7284f4dbba4f754145">Pharyngeal tonsils (adenoids) are located in the nasopharynx</p></li><li><p id="ab751ff5412924ab48fe5f7f63fc4db47">Tubal tonsils protect the auditory tubes and middle ear.</p></li><li><p id="aa415103a3bae460cb8e1c04f5e63160e">Palatine tonsils are located in the oropharynx</p></li><li><p id="adbec8cd64e4b4cb6933f2252642fb792">Lingual tonsils are located under the tongue.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="afdcacbe09e124c3ca2c47854313c95eb">The path of air then continues from the pharynx to the larynx which extends from hyoid bone to the trachea. At the juncture of the pharynx and the larynx air and food are directed into the larynx (and then trachea)and esophagus respectively. </p><ul id="ce96932fb7254df7bf64637eb757d4af"><li><p id="ad920e54502f1472389a98c628833ef7a">The glottis or opening to the larynx and thus the passageway to the trachea is blocked by the epiglottis when swallowing.</p></li><li><p id="ac7122a83f8534c3695f5b4cdfa5633b0">The vocal cords are located in the larynx and used for speech</p></li><li><p id="ad5fa852ff0fc4dcdbe6ec2d08fb46eec">The larynx also consists of nine cartilage structures that we use as anatomical landmarks. They function to maintain an open airway. The cartilages include the thyroid cartilage sometimes known as the Adam’s apple, the inferior thyroid cartilage (punctured when a tracheostomy is performed). The paired arytenoid, cuneiform, and corniculate cartilages.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="ad806bbd8f15f4cf9ba27211334d157aa">Although the lower respiratory tract begins at the larynx, most of the tract consists of the trachea, the bronchi and bronchioles, the alveoli and the lungs. </p><ul id="e2f914a052fa449ab1a5b5e432374563"><li><p id="abf5fa80335394496b2eb7a7232a3ae12">The trachea, known as the windpipe, extends from the larynx to the fifth thoracic vertebrae. It is composed of C-shaped cartilage that maintains an open airway. The trachea consists of three layers of tissue the mucosa, submucosa and adventitia.</p></li><li><p id="ab6efb5c0a01645c8928e86bbc9f285d5">The bronchial tree is next and is a series of passageways that grow smaller and smaller as they extend into the lungs. The cartilage plates are not present in the bronchioles. Plates of cartilage help maintain the opening of the passageways. As the size of the passageway decreases so does the number of plates. The respiratory bronchioles are the smallest and end in the alveolar sacs where gas exchange will occur.</p></li><li><p id="ab83bac00eda2405dbe85507829cbae77">The lungs contain elastic connective tissue that allow them to expand and recoil during ventilation.</p></li><li><p id="ac69611e7e34642319e43effd81733ddd">Anatomical reference points of the lungs include 1) the hilus, the entry point for blood vessels, the primary bronchi and nerves 2) the apex of the lung, the most superior portion of the lung, and 3)the base of the lungs, located above the diaphragm.</p></li><li><p id="ac4b016280feb425f8c7de14a5a11019a">There is a right and a left lung. The right lung consists of three lobes while the left lung only has two lobes because of the location of the heart.</p></li><li><p id="afe7d30b796fb4e0da59aad90780e378a">Each lobe is divided into many lobules each of which contains a terminal bronchiole and its respiratory bronchioles and associated alveoli.</p></li><li><p id="ad7d65fbe739d4746b3faa38e3da01a3a">The lungs have a dual blood supply. The pulmonary circuit brings deoxygenated blood to the lungs to release carbon dioxide and pick up oxygen to return to the heart. The systemic circuit brings oxygenated blood to feed the tissue of the lungs.</p></li><li><p id="afda4b83dcd7a42c1a8f95bdabaa79d7e">The lungs are surrounded by the visceral pleural which is a mucus membrane and then the parietal pleural that attaches to the walls of the thoracic cavity.</p></li><li><p id="aef2ce341848d41259f6831817cb0ee62">The space between the membranes is the pleural space and contains pleural fluid that can be examined for signs of infection.</p></li><li><p id="ac74c3f19f0a443a1b9d111ac95ef353d">Pleural effusion can be caused by different conditions so the fluid is checked to see if it is exudate with increased proteins or transudate with normal protein levels.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="aedd15f15f2784638b2cb9799329ebf7f">The primary function of the respiratory system is the movement of gases from the atmosphere into the lungs and to provide oxygen to the body while ridding the body of carbon dioxide. </p><ul id="d74c00a2c5004240bf7a5fbfc5bb8bbd"><li><p id="ad6d06f867dd44f1dbab77864516ff8a8">External respiration includes ventilation and the movement of gases between the lungs and the blood and between the blood and the systemic tissues.</p></li><li><p id="ace0433c4aa3841d79467445630f5b2c0">The passageway for air moving into and out of the body can be divided functionally into two divisions: the conducting zone and the respiratory zone which allows for air to diffuse from the lungs into the blood.</p></li><li><p id="aa0f1deeef8484d3caa017487d51c35fa">The conducting zone brings air into and out of the lungs. As the air passes through the conducting zone it is warmed to body temperature, humidified and microorganisms are filtered out.</p></li><li><p id="ab686750e1a4f412092ddb133033ddbbb">The temperature and humidity must be correct so the delicate respiratory zone is not damaged.</p></li><li><p id="af211a09624db4dd4a8a547b15fa37494">The respiratory zone consists of the respiratory bronchioles and the alveolar sacs and is the location of gas exchange between the lungs and the blood.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="aee0621eab514432d9ad3f0a7f242e469">Pulmonary ventilation is the act of moving air into and out of the lungs and is the first step of external respiration. </p><ul id="deb6e1cb590346e8a0de75a1174d5205"><li><p id="abc1349c7798c4369b37a1e28f9cc39c2">Pressure plays a huge role in moving air into and out of the lungs. Air follows pressure gradients moving from an area of high pressure to an area of low pressure.</p></li><li><p id="acdb7c83d6cc44aca930d098080029819">Air will move into the lungs if the alveolar pressure is less than the atmospheric pressure and air will move out of the lungs if the alveolar pressure is higher than the atmospheric pressure.</p></li><li><p id="aa3294d48581643f4bed5bbd60efbb712">Intrapleural pressure is the pressure within the pleural space and it will help keep the lungs slightly inflated to prevent collapse during exhalation.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="af5f09cb0e95d4ec8895d97de4866d08f">Pulmonary ventilation includes both inspiration and expiration. To understand how air moves into and out of the lungs, it is important to understand the physical laws that govern molecular movement. </p><ul id="b07374282fe24bc28ad6f64514b19cf2"><li><p id="acd7c17d5d810445c9a8564497947b908">Boyle’s law states that initial pressure times initial volume is equal to the resulting pressure times the resulting volume.</p></li><li><p id="ab6811772e5914f92a8615d11c62a77e2">This means as volume goes up pressure goes down and as volume goes down pressure goes up.</p></li><li><p id="acb7b20ed114b484fb4a3990fcae92aed">During inhalation the diaphragm and the external intercostal muscles of the ribs contract and move to increase the volume of the thorax resulting in a decrease the intrapulmonary pressure and causing air to move in.</p></li><li><p id="ab92bf5a56bcc4042b183d0c9a23e0bc2">During exhalation the diaphragm and the external intercostal muscles of the ribs relax and decrease the volume of the thorax resulting in an increase in the intrapulmonary pressure and causing air to move out.</p></li><li><p id="aed961282ca9a4079bee757e49a2d2a23">During forced inspiration contraction of additional muscles of the neck will allow more air to enter.</p></li><li><p id="aeec22a924b26460bbe07e01a7166d69b">During forced expiration muscles of the abdomen help force the diaphragm up further decreasing the volume of the thoracic cavity and increasing the volume of air exhaled.</p></li><li><p id="ae2529baab1df451c8e11273b6632ece1">Additional factors that affect the pressure gradient include airway resistance, alveolar surface tension and lung compliance. </p><ul id="c3af196be58c48aebde881ca47d1272f"><li><p id="ad5e7990062ee4ea782167e3891dcee9a">Smooth muscle of the bronchial tubes can constrict or dilate to alter the airway resistance.</p></li><li><p id="ab3f1b198c79a49d28d8a5a13e3088b3a">Conditions such as asthma can cause an increase in resistance that will result in a person needing to use accessory muscles to maintain adequate air flow.</p></li><li><p id="ac44892dee6e445a0be73e4ab48cc46a4">Compliance will also affect the amount of effort required for breathing. Compliance depends on the elasticity of the connective tissue in the lungs as well as the alveolar surface tension.</p></li><li><p id="abcfef8a3e1a54b8caa333e7142477646">Compliance can be decreased by fibrosis of the lung tissue or by the lack of surfactant.</p></li></ul></li></ul></li><li><p id="aab81b60ba9bb420096a12be3bbad3f63">To evaluate the efficiency of a person&apos;s inhalations and exhalations the process of spirometry is used. </p><ul id="d825a6dfde164d34add74b3fe38c514a"><li><p id="acb396d2f6dff4bac90c4103d676773e1">A person breathes in and out under controlled conditions and the amount of air and the flow rate can be measured.</p></li><li><p id="aaec64ace11104c01ac272f05cbbd3f02">The respiratory volumes include: Tidal Volume, Inspiratory Reserve Volume, Expiratory Reserve Volume, Residual Volume, and Dead Space.</p></li><li><p id="ae2d2e14dc951491dbca8696b4884757c">The Respiratory Capacities are two or more respiratory volumes added together. They include: Inspiratory Capacity, Functional Residual Capacity, Vital Capacity, Total Lung Capacity</p></li><li><p id="aca28e62721734819817a7ba2df85e6b2">Flow rates can also be used to assess a person’s lung function because there can be changes in the air flow that do not affect the volumes.</p></li></ul></li></ul><p id="bf841dbb8fb34aa2bcaa16f3637fe517">The lungs function to provide the entire body with the oxygen required to convert nutrients to energy. The lungs also need to be able to remove excess carbon dioxide from the body. To assess a person’s lung function, a person can breathe into a spirometer. The patient’s Respiratory Volumes and Capacities and flow rate can be measured. These measurements will vary based on a person’s size, age and gender. Restrictive lung disorders such as tuberculosis and obstructive disorders such as bronchitis can impede normal airflow and can be differentiated using spirometry.</p></body></section><section id="c99e7d1e39724ca2a73980768315fc4c"><title>Quiz</title><body><p id="a2e37134aba7419b9fa017f6d415a5e6">If you do not feel ready for the quiz, identify the objectives you need to review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of questions that will be in the quiz.</p><activity idref="respiratory_structures_functions_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
