<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m2_structures_wrapup_openfree">
	<head>
		<title>Respiratory Structures and Functions Summary</title>


	</head>



	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Let’s summarize</title>

			<body>
				<p>Structure determines function. To understand how the respiratory system performs
					its function it is essential to examine the anatomical structures of the system.
					Previously we examined the microscopic components of the respiratory system. Now
					we will places those components into the gross anatomy of the upper and lower
					respiratory tracts. After examining the structure we discussed how these
					structures perform the functions of the respiratory system and how the
					efficiency of these functions is measured.</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Entrance to the upper respiratory tract is through the nose or the mouth. <ul>
							<li>The nasal cavity contains structures such as hair, sebaceous glands
								and mucus that aid in preventing microorganisms from entering.</li>
							<li>The nasal cavity also contains olfactory epithelium for the sense of
								smell.</li>
							<li>The conchae of the nose contain mucus glands and blood vessels to
								aid in humidifying and warming the air.</li>
							<li>The paranasal sinuses are hollow areas that make the skull lighter
								and also moisten and warm incoming air.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>Next the air passes into the pharynx which is divided into three areas and
						connects to the larynx. <ul>
							<li>The nasopharynx is the superior portion of the pharynx and only acts
								as a passageway for air.</li>
							<li>The oropharynx extends from the soft palate to the epiglottis, and
								is covered in stratified squamous epithelia to protect it from the
								friction of food as it is swallowed.</li>
							<li>The laryngopharynx is the third and shortest portion of the pharynx.
								It extends from the epiglottis and ends above the esophagus. It is
								lined with stratified squamous epithelia to protect it from the
								friction of food as it is swallowed. Both the oropharynx and the
								laryngopharynx are passageways used to transport both air and
								food.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>The tonsils are patches of lymphatic tissue that help protect the body
						against pathogens by filtering them from the air. <ul>
							<li>Pharyngeal tonsils (adenoids) are located in the nasopharynx</li>
							<li>Tubal tonsils protect the auditory tubes and middle ear.</li>
							<li>Palatine tonsils are located in the oropharynx</li>
							<li>Lingual tonsils are located under the tongue.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>The path of air then continues from the pharynx to the larynx which extends
						from hyoid bone to the trachea. At the juncture of the pharynx and the
						larynx air and food are directed into the larynx (and then trachea)and
						esophagus respectively. <ul>
							<li>The glottis or opening to the larynx and thus the passageway to the
								trachea is blocked by the epiglottis when swallowing.</li>
							<li>The vocal cords are located in the larynx and used for speech</li>
							<li>The larynx also consists of nine cartilage structures that we use as
								anatomical landmarks. They function to maintain an open airway. The
								cartilages include the thyroid cartilage sometimes known as the
								Adam’s apple, the inferior thyroid cartilage (punctured when a
								tracheostomy is performed). The paired arytenoid, cuneiform, and
								corniculate cartilages.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>Although the lower respiratory tract begins at the larynx, most of the tract
						consists of the trachea, the bronchi and bronchioles, the alveoli and the
						lungs. <ul>
							<li>The trachea, known as the windpipe, extends from the larynx to the
								fifth thoracic vertebrae. It is composed of C-shaped cartilage that
								maintain an open airway. The trachea consists of three layers of
								tissue the mucosa, submucosa and adventitia.</li>
							<li>The bronchial tree is next and is a series of passageways that grow
								smaller and smaller as they extend into the lungs. The cartilage
								plates are not present in the bronchioles. Plates of cartilage help
								maintain the opening of the passageways. As the size of the
								passageway decreases so does the number of plates. The respiratory
								bronchioles are the smallest and end in the alveolar sacs where gas
								exchange will occur.</li>
							<li>The lungs contain elastic connective tissue that allow them to
								expand and recoil during ventilation.</li>
							<li>Anatomical reference points of the lungs include 1) the hilus, the
								entry point for blood vessels, the primary bronchi and nerves 2) the
								apex of the lung, the most superior portion of the lung, and 3)the
								base of the lungs, located above the diaphragm.</li>
							<li>There is a right and a left lung. The right lung consists of three
								lobes while the left lung only has two lobes because of the location
								of the heart.</li>
							<li>Each lobe is divided into many lobules each of which contains a
								terminal bronchiole and its respiratory bronchioles and associated
								alveoli.</li>
							<li>The lungs have a dual blood supply. The pulmonary circuit brings
								deoxygenated blood to the lungs to release carbon dioxide and pick
								up oxygen to return to the heart. The systemic circuit brings
								oxygenated blood to feed the tissue of the lungs.</li>
							<li>The lungs are surrounded by the visceral pleural which is a mucus
								membrane and then the parietal pleural that attaches to the walls of
								the thoracic cavity.</li>
							<li>The space between the membranes is the pleural space and contains
								pleural fluid that can be examined for signs of infection.</li>
							<li>Pleural effusion can be caused by different conditions so the fluid
								is checked to see if it is exudate with increased proteins or
								transudate with normal protein levels.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>The primary function of the respiratory system is the movement of gases from
						the atmosphere into the lungs and to provide oxygen to the body while
						ridding the body of carbon dioxide. <ul>
							<li>External respiration includes ventilation and the movement of gases
								between the lungs and the blood and between the blood and the
								systemic tissues.</li>
							<li>The passageway for air moving into and out of the body can be
								divided functionally into two divisions: the conducting zone and the
								respiratory zone which allows for air to diffuse from the lungs into
								the blood.</li>
							<li>The conducting zone brings air into and out of the lungs. As the air
								passes through the conducting zone it is warmed to body temperature,
								humidified and microorganisms are filtered out.</li>
							<li>The temperature and humidity must be correct so the delicate
								respiratory zone is not damaged.</li>
							<li>The respiratory zone consists of the respiratory bronchioles and the
								alveolar sacs and is the location of gas exchange between the lungs
								and the blood.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>Pulmonary ventilation is the act of moving air into and out of the lungs and
						is the first step of external respiration. <ul>
							<li>Pressure plays a huge role in moving air into and out of the lungs.
								Air follows pressure gradients moving from an area of high pressure
								to an area of low pressure.</li>
							<li>Air will move into the lungs if the alveolar pressure is less than
								the atmospheric pressure and air will move out of the lungs if the
								alveolar pressure is higher than the atmospheric pressure.</li>
							<li>Intrapleural pressure is the pressure within the pleural space and
								it will help keep the lungs slightly inflated to prevent collapse
								during exhalation.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>Pulmonary ventilation includes both inspiration and expiration. To
						understand how air moves into and out of the lungs, it is important to
						understand the physical laws that govern molecular movement. <ul>
							<li>Boyle’s law states that initial pressure times initial volume is
								equal to the resulting pressure times the resulting volume.</li>
							<li>This means as volume goes up pressure goes down and as volume goes
								down pressure goes up.</li>
							<li>During inhalation the diaphragm and the external intercostal muscles
								of the ribs contract and move to increase the volume of the thorax
								resulting in a decrease the intrapulmonary pressure and causing air
								to move in.</li>
							<li>During exhalation the diaphragm and the external intercostal muscles
								of the ribs relax and decrease the volume of the thorax resulting in
								an increase in the intrapulmonary pressure and causing air to move
								out.</li>
							<li>During forced inspiration contraction of additional muscles of the
								neck will allow more air to enter.</li>
							<li>During forced expiration muscles of the abdomen help force the
								diaphragm up further decreasing the volume of the thoracic cavity
								and increasing the volume of air exhaled.</li>
							<li>Additional factors that affect the pressure gradient include airway
								resistance, alveolar surface tension and lung compliance. <ul>
									<li>Smooth muscle of the bronchial tubes can constrict or dilate
										to alter the airway resistance.</li>
									<li>Conditions such as asthma can cause an increase in
										resistance that will result in a person needing to use
										accessory muscles to maintain adequate air flow.</li>
									<li>Compliance will also affect the amount of effort required
										for breathing. Compliance depends on the elasticity of the
										connective tissue in the lungs as well as the alveolar
										surface tension.</li>
									<li>Compliance can be decreased by fibrosis of the lung tissue
										or by the lack of surfactant.</li>
								</ul>
							</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>To evaluate the efficiency of a person's inhalations and exhalations the
						process of spirometry is used. <ul>
							<li>A person breathes in and out under controlled conditions and the
								amount of air and the flow rate can be measured.</li>
							<li>The respiratory volumes include: Tidal Volume, Inspiratory Reserve
								Volume, Expiratory Reserve Volume, Residual Volume, and Dead
								Space.</li>
							<li>The Respiratory Capacities are two or more respiratory volumes added
								together. They include: Inspiratory Capacity, Functional Residual
								Capacity, Vital Capacity, Total Lung Capacity</li>
							<li>Flow rates can also be used to assess a person’s lung function
								because there can be changes in the air flow that do not affect
								the volumes.</li>

						</ul>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>The lungs function to provide the entire body with the oxygen required to convert
					nutrients to energy. The lungs also need to be able to remove excess carbon
					dioxide from the body. To assess a person’s lung function, a person can
					breathe into a spirometer. The patient’s Respiratory Volumes and Capacities and
					flow rate can be measured. These measurements will vary based on a person’s
					size, age and gender. Restrictive lung disorders such as tuberculosis and
					obstructive disorders such as bronchitis can impede normal airflow and can be
					differentiated using spirometry.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<!--	<section>
			
			<title><em style="bold">End Questions</em></title>
			
			<body>
				
				
				
				  <p>Before you do the quiz activity, please evaluate your understanding of the
					learning objectives for the Respiratory Sturctures and Functions and use the first My Response
					link below to ask any questions you might have about the material that you would
					like the instructor to address. Your questions can be for clarification of the
					material or further insight. Your self-evaluation will not be graded, but will
					be available for your instructor to read. Answering these questions may also
					shape the discussions in class. </p>
				
				  <activity idref="_u11_m2_respiratory_structures_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>
				
			 <p> If you do not feel ready for the quiz, identify the objectives you need to
					review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t
					just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of
					questions that will be in the quiz.</p>
			
				
				 <activity idref="u2_m3_checkpoint" purpose="checkpoint"/>
				
				<p> Now that you have finished the quiz, do you have any questions? Your
					instructor will be able to read the questions and comments that you submit. </p>
				<activity idref="_u11_m2_respiratory_structures_feedback_post_quiz" purpose="myresponse"/>
				
				
				
			</body>
			
		</section>-->



	</body>
</workbook_page>
