<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m2_structures_03">
	<head>
		<title>Respiratory Functions</title>

		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_conducting_respiratory_zone"/>
	</head>


	<body>

		<!-- <p>Describe and distinguish between the conducting and respiratory zones of the respiratory
		tract.</p> -->


		<section>
			<title>Respiratory Function</title>
			<body>

				<p>The movement of gases from the atmosphere into the lungs and the cells of the
					body and back out again is called <term>external respiration</term>. External
					respiration includes ventilation, the bulk flow of air from outside the body
					into the repiratory system (inhalation) and the bulk flow of air from the
					respiratory system back to the outside (exhalation). Also included under the
					processes described as external respiration are the exchange of oxygen and
					carbon dioxide between the lungs and the blood, the transport of oxygen and
					carbon dioxide by the blood, and the exchange of gasses between the cells and
					the blood. The conduit for moving air into the lungs and then returning it to
					the external environment is referred to as the <term>conducting zone</term>
					(division). Gas exchange does not take place in the structures that make up the
					conductiong zone. The conducting zone consists of a system of tubes that connect
					the nose and mouth to the alveoli. Air movement starts at the nose or mouth and
					continues through the pharynx, larynx, trachea, and bronchial tree, terminating
					at the structures of the <term>respiratory zone</term> (division) where gas
					exchange will occur.</p>

				<p>The respiratory zone includes the very small respiratory bronchioles, the alveoli
					and the blood capillaries. It is critical that both the conducting and
					respiratory zones function adequately for the body to maintain homeostasis.
					Organization of conducting and respiratory zones will be the focus of this
					discussion.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_conducting_respiratory_zone" purpose="didigetthis"/>

				<section>
					<title>The Conducting Zone</title>
					<body>
						<p>The conducting zone of the respiratory system brings gases into and out
							of the respiratory system. In addition, the organs and tissues along
							this path warm the incoming air to approximately body temperature,
							moisten the air to about 100 percent humidity, and begin filtering out
							any harmful microorganisms or particles that may be suspended in the
							inhaled air.</p>

						<p>Temperatures too far below 37°C (98.6°F) can harm the delicate alveoli
							and inhibit enzyme function. Damaged aveoli, or improperly functioning
							enzymes could lead to decreased gas diffusion and subsequent homeostatic
							imbalances. For example, the inter-conversion of carbon dioxide and
							carbonic acid is catalyzed by the enzyme carbonic anhydrase. Similar to
							most other body enzymes, it loses efficiency at lower temperatures. If
							carbonic anhydrase is not functioning properly there could be an
							increase in carbonic acid levels. Since carbonic acid breaks down into
							bicarbonate ions and free hydrogen ions, there would be resulting
							decrease in pH leading to acidosis. The temperature in the respiratory
							zone is so important that a person who runs in cold weather is advised
							to put a scarf across their nose and mouth to help pre-warm the air.
							Otherwise, the tissues in the conducting zone may not be able to warm
							the air sufficiently to prevent damage to the system.</p>

						<p>If the air in the respiratory zone is not near 100 percent humidity, the
							thin-walled alveoli can become dehydrated and may deteriorate. The
							alveoli are lined with a very thin layer of water and chemicals that
							prevent damage to the tissues and help to keep the alveoli open. If the
							air taken to the respiratory zone doesn’t have sufficient humidity
							(water vapor), the water layer lining the aveoli will evaporate
							resulting in damage to the structures and interference with
							respiration.</p>

						<p>The hairs found at the entrance to the nose, along with the mucus and
							cilia found inside the nose help to trap and remove pathogens and
							particles taken in with air. Large particles can build up at the
							entrance of the nose where the hairs trap them. Coal miners, for
							example, will accumulate coal dust at the opening of their nostrils due
							to the action of these hairs. Smaller particles, such as some viruses
							and bacteria will be trapped in the mucus in the nose and the cilia on
							the epithelial cells will sweep them to the back of the pharynx. The
							combined action of the mucus and the cilia is referred to as the
							mucociliary escalator. Ultimately the mixture of mucus and particles
							will be swallowed and destroyed by the acid and digestive enzymes in the
							stomach. This process of trapping and removal of particles and
							microorganisms occurs throughout the conducting zone and through the
							first part of the respiratory zone.</p>


					</body>
				</section>

				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_low_temp_breath_nose" purpose="didigetthis"/>

				<section>
					<title>The Respiratory Zone</title>
					<body>
						<p>A transition occurs in the composition of the epithelial lining at the
							end of the terminal bronchioles. The epithelial lining changes to simple
							cuboidal cells without any intermixed goblet cells. The walls of the
							tubes at this point become very thin and are called <term>respiratory</term>
							bronchioles. The loss of the goblet cells means that no mucus is
							secreted into the bronchioles at this point, but the cilia are still
							present to sweep away any mucus that should come down into them. Some
							portions of the respiratory bronchioles are not completely covered by
							cilia, and a number of phagocytic macrophages are found in this area to
							compensate for the loss of the cilia. Some gas exchange can occur
							through the walls of the respiratory bronchioles.</p>
						<p>Respiratory bronchioles lead into the alveolar ducts, which still have
							smooth muscle and some elastic fibers in the walls. Alveolar sacs occur
							as clusters of aveoli (singular alveolus) sharing a common chamber along
							the alveolar ducts. It has been estimated that there are 300 million
							alveoli in the lungs. These alveoli provide a surface area of 27 square
							meters, or an area 25 feet by 30 feet, which is roughly the size of a
							three-car garage. Adjacent alveoli are interconnected through alveolar
							pores.</p>
					</body>
				</section>


			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="respiratory_tract_which_zone" purpose="didigetthis"/>




	</body>
</workbook_page>
