<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m2_structures_05">
	<head>
		<title>Respiratory Volumes, Capacities, and Function Tests</title>

		<objref idref="define_identify_values_of_respiratory_volumes_capacities"/>
	</head>


	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Respiratory Volumes, Capacities, and Function Tests</title>
			<body>
				<p>Various lung volumes, capacities (capacities are combinations of lung volumes)
					and flow rates can be evaluated through a process called <term>spirometry</term>. The patient
					breathes in and out under controlled conditions, and the amount of air passing
					through the system, as well as the time it takes for air passage is measured.
					The values for these measurements depend on lung function and the size of the
					patient.</p>
				<table rowstyle="alternating">
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Respiratory Volumes</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Description</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Normal adult values</em></td>
						<!--slewando00:Do we want this box here or do we want to break up the text beneath by splitting this box into two the volumes and the capacities and using them as drop in LBDKim Larson:yes, I think splitting them is a good idea. If you want to create a drop and drag for each that would be great. tx-->
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Tidal Volume (TV)</td>
						<td>Volume of a resting breath</td>
						<td>500 mL/breath</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Inspiratory Reserve Volume (IRV)</td>
						<td>Maximum volume that can be inhaled after a normal inhale</td>
						<td>1900 – 3300 mL</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Expiratory Reserve Volume (ERV)</td>
						<td>Maximum volume that can be exhaled after a normal exhale</td>
						<td>700 – 1200 mL</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Residual Volume (RV)</td>
						<td>Air left in the lungs after exhaling completely (i.e. after an ERV)</td>
						<td>1200 mL</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Dead Space</td>
						<td>Air inhaled during breathing that stays in the conducting zone</td>
						<td>150 mL</td>
					</tr>
				</table>



				<p>A normal, resting respiration is called the <term>tidal volume (TV)</term>, and
					is typically about 500 ml per breath. <term>Inspiratory reserve volume (IRV)
					</term>is the amount of air that can be taken in “on top of” the tidal volume,
					with a deep breath. This ranges from 2,100 to 3,200 ml. The reverse of the IRV
					is the <term>expiratory reserve volume (ERV)</term>, the amount of air that can
					be forcefully expelled after the tidal volume. The ERV range is from 1,000 to
					1,200 ml. The conducting zone organs contain a volume of air that does not enter
					the respiratory zone (and therefore does not participate in gas exchange) called
					the dead space air. The amount of dead space air is typically 150 ml. The actual
					air will be moved during the next inspiration or expiration, but the volume of
					dead space air does not enter into the volumes involved in internal
					respiration.</p>
				<p>The final normal respiratory volume is the <term>residual volume (RV)</term>.
					This is the amount that is left in the lungs after the ERV is expelled. The RV
					is about 1,200 ml of air. The residual volume helps maintain open alveoli and is
					the air that the newly inhaled air is mixed with. No matter how hard a person
					exhales, there is always air left in the lungs. This remains true even after
					death. The only way to remove the residual air from the lungs is to replace it
					with something else.</p>

				<p>Essentially this is what happens when a person drowns, water replaces residual
					air. If a pathologist needs to determine if a deceased person recovered from a
					body of water drowned or was dead before going into the water, he or she clamps
					off the trachea, removes the lungs, and places them in a bucket of water. If the
					person drowned, the lungs will sink because the residual air was replaced by the
					water. If the person was dead before going into the water, the lungs will float
					because the residual air is still there.</p>
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<p>Spirometry is the measuring of breath and is one of the most common tests
							of pulmonary function. These tests are collectively known as PFTs
							(pulmonary function tests) and are used to measure and assess the
							ventilation of the lungs. Spirometry can measure the volume of air
							moving in and out of lungs and the speed of airflow in and out of the
							lungs. The picture below is an example of a spirogram that is showing a
							volume vs time curve. The most common features measured in spirometry
							are the vital capacity, the forced vital capacity, and forced expiratory
							volume.</p>
						<!--  <image src="../webcontent/spirometry_results.jpg" height="500" width="600" alt="spirometry"/>-->

						<image src="../webcontent/spirometry_results.jpg" height="500" width="600"
							alt="spirometry graph">
							<caption>By Vihsadas at en.wikipedia derivative work (<link
									href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/3b/Lungvolumes.svg"
									>Lung Volumes</link>) <link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" target="new"
									>CC-BY-SA-3.0</link>
							</caption>
						</image>

						<wb:inline idref="respiratory_pulmonary_function"/>
					</body>
				</section>


				<p>Several respiratory capacities can be calculated from the volumes listed above.
					The <term>inspiratory capacity (IC) </term>is the total amount of air that can
					be inhaled and is calculated by adding the tidal volume and inspiratory reserve
					volume. The <term>functional residual capacity (FRC) </term>is the amount of air
					remaining in the lungs at the end of a normal exhalation. This air continues to
					participate in gas exchange even after the person has exhaled. Functional
					residual capacity is calculated by adding together residual and expiratory
					reserve volumes. The <term>vital capacity (VC) </term>is the total exchangeable
					air in the system and is calculated by adding together tidal volume, inspiratory
					reserve volume, and expiratory reserve volume. Typically vital capacity is about
					4,800ml of air. The <term>total lung capacity (TLC) </term>is the total of all
					lung volumes and is about 6,000 ml.</p>

				<table rowstyle="alternating">


					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Respiratory Capacities</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Description</em></td>
						<td><em style="bold">Normal adult values</em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Inspiratory Capacity (IC)</td>
						<td>TV + IRV</td>
						<td>2400 – 3800 mL</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Functional Residual Capacity (FRC)</td>
						<td>RV + ERV</td>
						<td>1800 – 2200 mL</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Vital Capacity (VC)</td>
						<td>TV + IRV + ERV</td>
						<td>3000 – 4600 mL</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Total Lung Capacity (TLC)</td>
						<td>TV + IRV + ERV + RV</td>
						<td>4200 – 6000 mL</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<p>Besides volumes and capacities, flow rates are often measured to assess a
					person’s lung function. Flow rates are important because although changes in airway
					resistance will not usually change volumes, they will affect the rate of
					air movement through the system. To assess flow rates, the individual takes as deep
					a breath as possible (gets to VC) and then exhales maximally and as quickly as possible. The
					time it takes to bring the lung volume down to RV provides information about
					airway resistance. Flow rates are used to assess asthma and related
					conditions.</p>

				<section purpose="didigetthis">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<p>Another common pulmonary function test measured by spirometry is the
							speed of airflow in and out of the lungs. The FEV1/FVC ratio is commonly
							used in the diagnosis of obstructive and restrictive lung diseases. This
							ratio is the forced expiratory volume in one second divided by the
							forced vital capacity. In healthy adults this ratio should be between
							75-80%. Please examine the chart provided to assist you in answering
							the following questions. </p>
						<!-- <image src="../webcontent/normal_values.jpg" alt="normal values, fvc, fev1 and fev 25-75%"
						/> -->

						<image src="../webcontent/normal_values.jpg"
							alt="normal values, fvc, fev1 and fev 25-75%">
							<caption>By Mikael Häggström (<link
									href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/39/Normal_values_for_FVC%2C_FEV1_and_FEF_25-75.png"
									>Lung Volumes</link>) </caption>
						</image>
						<wb:inline idref="respiratory_spirometry_airflow_lungs"
							purpose="didigetthis"/>
					</body>
				</section>

				<p>Lung volumes and flow rates can be used to differentiate between obstructive and
					restrictive pulmonary diseases. Obstructive pulmonary disorders are those that increase
					the resistance to airflow, thus increasing the time it takes to move air in and
					out of the lungs. Examples of obstructive disorders include bronchitis and
					asthma. Restrictive pulmonary disorders are those that affect the compliance of the lung
					or affect the ability of the chest wall to expand and relax normally. Such
					disorders lead to lower lung volumes than would be expected based upon a
					person’s size. Examples of restrictive pulmonary disorders include those that lead to
					structural or functional changes in the lung tissue (tuberculosis, fibrosis) or
					those that impede normal muscular function (such as muscular dystrophy) or
					function of motor nerves (such as multiple sclerosis and ALS).</p>

			</body>
		</section>









	</body>

</workbook_page>
