<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u11_m2_structures_04">
	<head>
		<title>Respiratory Pulmonary Ventilation</title>

		<objref idref="describe_mechanisms_pulmonary_ventilation"/>
	</head>


	<body>
		<!--  	<p>Hi Susan, here are the sub ojectives. </p>

		<p>Define pulmonary ventilation, inspiration, and expiration. </p>
		<p>Identify the muscles used during quiet inspiration, during forced inspiration, and during
			forced expiration, as well as the nerves responsible for stimulating those muscles.</p>
		<p>Define and state relative values for atmospheric pressure, intrapulmonary pressure,
			intrapleural pressure, and transpulmonary pressure. </p>
		<p>State Boyle’s Law and relate this law to the specific sequence of events (muscle
			contractions/relaxations and pressure/volume changes) causing inspiration and
			expiration.</p>
		<p>Explain how each of the following affect pulmonary ventilation: bronchiolar smooth muscle
			contractions, lung and thoracic wall compliance and recoil, and pulmonary surfactant and
			alveolar surface tension.</p>
		<p>Describe the forces that tend to collapse the lungs and those that normally oppose or
			prevent collapse.</p>-->



		<section>
			<title>Pulmonary Ventilation</title>
			<body>

				<p><term>Pulmonary ventilation </term>is the act of breathing and the first step in
					the respiratory process. Pulmonary ventilation brings in air with a new supply
					of oxygen and a very small amount of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere into the
					alveoli. This mixture then participates in <term>external respiration</term>,
					the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide between the alveoli and pulmonary
					capillary blood across the respiratory membrane. <term>Internal respiration
					</term>is the exchange of gasses between the tissues of the body and the blood,
					which provides oxygen for aerobic cellular respiration and removes carbon
					dioxide. Aerobic <term>Cellular respiration </term>refers to the intracellular
					use of oxygen and the generation of carbon dioxide waste through metabolic
					pathways.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="respiratory_pulmonary_ventilation_disruption"
					purpose="didigetthis"/>

				<section>
					<title>Pressure</title>
					<body>
						<p>Breathing or ventilation, involves changes in pressure as a result of
							mechanical work.</p>
						<p> The physical movement of air into the lungs is a result of the
							production of differences in total pressure between the interior
							(alveolar pressure) and exterior (atmospheric pressure) of the
							respiratory zone. Atmospheric pressure at sea level is typically 1
							atmosphere or 760 mmHg, and this value will be used as the reference
							atmospheric pressure here. 
							One atmosphere is the air pressure that would push a column of the
							mercury up in a thin tube a distance of 760 mm. Mercury is used because
							it is a liquid at room temperature, and its density changes very little
							over pressure and temperature ranges. In the process of ventilation, air
							moves down pressure gradients going from an area of higher pressure to
							an area of lower pressure. Assuming a person is at sea level, if his or her
							intrapulmonary pressure, the pressure in the alveoli, is less than 1
							atm, air enters the lungs and fills the alveoli. If his or her intrapulmonary
							pressure is greater than 1 atm, then air moves out of the lungs into the
							environment.</p>

						<p>There is another pressure often discussed in the mechanics of
							ventilation, intrapleural (sometimes just pleural) pressure. This is the
							pressure within the pleural sac (space). Intrapleural pressure is
							maintained slightly less than the pressure in the alveoli. This pressure
							difference aids in keeping the lungs slightly inflated at all times and
							ensures that they do not collapse when exhaling.</p>

						<wb:inline idref="respiratory_pressure_lungs_inflated" purpose="didigetthis"/>




						<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_18.jpg" width="400"
							alt="lungs, close up intercostal muscle">
							<caption>Close up intercostal muscle. This work by Cenveo is licensed
								under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
									>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
						</image>

					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Inspiration and Expiration</title>
					<body>
						<p>Gases have a property of distributing to fill whatever size and shape
							container they occupy. If a closed container is made larger (an increase
							in volume), the total number of gas molecules will stay the same, but
							they will redistribute to fill the larger space. In doing so, they
							decrease their concentration (remember that concentration is a property
							of mass and volume). This increase in volume but not number of molecules
							of the gas leads to a corresponding decrease in the pressure exerted by
							that gas on the walls of the container. If the same closed container is
							made smaller, the concentration of gases increases( even though the
							actual number of gas molecules has not changed) and the pressure
							increases. This is an example of a physical law called <term>Boyle’s
								Law</term>. </p>
						<p>The law is expressed mathematically as:</p>
						<formula>P<sub>1</sub>V<sub>1</sub> = P<sub>2</sub>V<sub>2</sub></formula>
						<p>where P = pressure, V = volume, 1 is the initial pressure and volume, and
							2 is the resulting pressure and volume.</p>
						<p>Boyle’s Law states that, at a constant temperature, the pressure of a gas
							is inversely proportional with the volume of its container. Very simply,
							as volume goes up, pressure goes down, and as volume goes down, pressure
							goes up. These properties become important for ventilation because the
							passage of air into and out of the lungs is controlled by the size of
							the lungs’ container, the thorax. The difference between the example
							above and the lungs is that the lungs are not a closed system (unless
							you have a closed glottis), with the opening to the lungs maintained
							through the conducting zone. But over very short periods of time Boyle’s
							law still applies. In this case, when we inhale, the movement of the
							diaphragm and the ribs increases the volume of the thorax. This
							immediately decreases the air pressure within the thorax, creating a
							pressure gradient between the atmosphere and the alveoli (the latter is
							called intrapulmonary pressure), and drawing air into the lungs. Air
							will enter until the atmospheric and intrapulmonary pressures are equal.
							However, the volume of the thorax remains larger than before the start
							of inhalation. To exhale, the thorax is allowed to decrease in volume
							(the ribs and diaphragm return to their original positions), increasing
							the intrapulmonary pressure and creating a gradient in the opposite
							direction resulting in the flow of air out to the atmosphere. Changing
							the size of the thoracic cavity would be impossible if the ribs were
							solidly attached to the sternum. If they were solidly attached, it would
							be like trying to move the sides of a birdcage. The costal cartilage
							allows the ribs to move and expand or contract the chest wall.</p>

						<wb:inline idref="respiratory_boyles_law" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						<section>
							<title>Inspiration</title>
							<body>
								<p>Inspiration is the act of inhaling. As stated above, inspiration
									occurs by increasing the volume of the thorax. This active
									process involves the use of chest and neck muscles. Resting
									inspiration is achieved mostly by movement of the diaphragm. The
									relaxed shape of the diaphragm resembles a shallow dome with the
									apex pointing toward the lungs, similar to the shape of an open
									umbrella. When the diaphragm contracts, it tends to flatten out,
									expanding the volume of the thorax in an inferior direction.
									Consequently, the intrapleural and intrapulmonary pressures
									decrease below atmospheric pressure resulting in air being
									pulled through the conducting zone and into the lungs. The
									external intercostal muscles work in conjunction with the
									diaphragm. The normal orientation of the ribs is around the side
									of the thorax and angled inferiorly to the sternum. When the
									external intercostal muscles contract, the ribs are pulled up,
									also expanding the thoracic cavity in a horizontal direction. In
									adults, ventilation occurs about 12 times a minute and moves
									roughly 500 ml of air during each breath.</p>
								<!-- <table>
									<tr>
										<td><image src="../webcontent/r_m1_18.jpg" height="300"
												width="300" alt="lungs"/></td>
										<td><image src="../webcontent/r_m1_19.jpg" height="300"
												width="300" alt="lungs, inhalation and exhalation"/></td>
									</tr>
								</table> -->

								<section purpose="learnbydoing">
									<title>Inhalation</title>
									<body>

										<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_19a.jpg" height="300"
											width="300" alt="lungs, inhalation">
											<caption>Lungs, inhalation. This work by Cenveo is
												licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0
												United States (<link
												href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
												>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
										</image>

										<wb:inline idref="respiratory_inhalation"
											purpose="learnbydoing"/>
									</body>
								</section>

								<p>A deep breath involves a greater shortening of the diaphragm and
									the external intercostal muscles plus additional contractions of
									other neck and chest muscles. The scalene muscles elevate the
									first two ribs. The sternocleidomastoid muscles elevate the
									sternum, and the pectoralis minor muscles help to elevate the
									third, fourth, and fifth ribs. Two physical conditions that
									interfere with inspiration are obesity and advanced pregnancy.
									In both cases, the abdominal organs are pushed against the
									diaphragm, restricting its downward movement and hindering the
									expansion of the thoracic cavity.</p>
							</body>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>Expiration</title>
							<body>
								<p>Expiration is the act of exhaling. Resting expiration is a
									passive process. The muscles used during inspiration relax, and
									allow the chest wall and the diaphragm to move back to their
									original position, thus decreasing the volume of the thorax and
									forcing air from the lungs. The compression of the chest wall
									also aids in moving blood and lymph through the vessels that
									drain the lungs. Expiration becomes an active process when a
									more forceful exhale is required. The internal intercostal
									muscles pull the ribs down, helping to compress the chest. The
									external and internal oblique and transverse abdominal muscles
									press on the abdominal organs, which move them up against the
									diaphragm and force the diaphragm higher than it would normally
									go on relaxation, further decreasing the volume of the thoracic
									cavity.</p>

								<section purpose="learnbydoing">
									<title>Exhalation</title>
									<body>
										<!--  <image src="../webcontent/r_m1_19b.jpg" height="300"
											width="300" alt="lungs, exhalation"/>-->

										<image src="../webcontent/r_m1_19b.jpg" height="300"
											width="300" alt="lungs, exhalation">
											<caption>Lungs, exhalation. This work by Cenveo is
												licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0
												United States (<link
												href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
												>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
										</image>

										<wb:inline idref="respiratory_exhalation"
											purpose="learnbydoing"/>
									</body>
								</section>
							</body>
						</section>




					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Airway resistance, alveolar surface tension, and lung compliance</title>
					<body>
						<p>One thing that works against the pressure gradient created by the
							expansion of the thorax is the resistance found within the conducting
							zone. Under normal conditions this resistance is quite low, and the
							airways have little trouble passing air between the atmosphere and the
							alveoli. The small amount of resistance found in the system stems mainly
							from the bronchioles, which are analogous to the arterioles of the
							vascular system. Both the bronchioles and the arterioles contribute a
							large portion of the resistance of their entire system, and both have
							smooth muscles in their walls that allow them to constrict or dilate.
							Under conditions of bronchiolar constriction (bronchoconstriction),
							resistance to airflow can increase dramatically. When this happens
							rapidly, it is classified as an acute asthma attack. The afflicted
							individual will need to generate much larger changes in intrapulmonary
							pressure to maintain a normal flow rate of air during breathing. Recall
							that if resistance increases an increased pressure gradient is necessary
							to maintain the same flow. To achieve this, the person uses the accessory
							muscles to breathe, and will appear to be “straining” as he or she does so.
							Treatment usually involves an inhaler containing a bronchodilator.
							Resistance will also be affected if the airways become narrowed by mucus
							(chronic asthma) or aspirated substances.</p>
						<p>Along with the resistance of the airways, the compliance of the lung
							tissue also determines how much effort breathing requires. Compliance is
							a property that explains the relationship between a volume change and
							pressure change. Typically it takes a 2-3 cm of water change in pleural
							pressure to change volume in the lungs by 500 ml. This is a compliance
							of about 200 ml/cm H<sub>2</sub>O. The compliance of the lungs is
							dependent on the elasticity of the connective tissues of the lung as
							well as the alveolar surface tension. Remember that a thin liquid layer
							containing water as well as other molecules lines the interior lung
							surface. Because of its polar nature, water exhibits cohesion, such that
							it takes some effort to separate water molecules (you may have
							experienced the force of this cohesion if you ever belly flopped into
							the water). This surface tension is actually enough to collapse the
							alveoli each time a person exhales. In order to prevent this from
							happening, the type II alveolar cells make a combination of lipids and
							proteins that serves as a surfactant in the alveoli. A surfactant is a
							chemical that acts like a detergent breaking the surface tension of the water
							lining the alveoli. This action allows the alveoli to remain open when exhaling.</p>
						<p>Compliance of the lung can be decreased either by fibrosis of the lung
							tissue creating a stiffening of the tissue (this can occur with
							conditions such as tuberculosis) or lack of surfactant (common in
							premature infants). Either way breathing becomes much more difficult,
							requiring more effort and sometimes mechanical ventilation.</p>

					</body>
				</section>

			</body>
		</section>


		<wb:inline idref="respiratory_affects_on_pulmonary_ventilation" purpose="didigetthis"/>





	</body>
</workbook_page>
