<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment 2.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_2_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_assessment_2_3.css"?>
<assessment id="_u2_m2_checkpoint2" max_attempts="3" recommended_attempts="1">
    <title>Examining Relationships Checkpoint 2</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you
            are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window
            will ask "This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?",
            click "OK" if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p>
        <p>If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost.
            After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to
            be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p>
    </introduction>
    <!--<content available="instructor_only">
        <p><em>Instructors: you can download the solution set for this checkpoint by clicking on the
                following link:</em>
            <link href="../webcontent/_u2_m2_checkpoint2.pdf">Solution Set</link>.</p>
    </content>-->
    <multiple_choice id="two_way_table" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>High blood pressure is unhealthy. Here are the results of one of the studies that
                link high blood pressure to death from cardiovascular disease. The researchers
                classified a group of white males aged 35 to 64 as having low blood pressure or high
                blood pressure, then followed the subjects for 5 years. The following two-way table
                gives the results of the study:</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment2q9.gif"/>
            <p>In this example, which of the following would be appropriate to calculate?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Conditional row percentages </choice>
            <choice value="B">Conditional column percentages </choice>
            <choice value="C">The correlation coefficient r </choice>
            <choice value="D">The five-number summary of both variables </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. To explore a categorical relationship, the most appropriate
                    summary is the outcome percentages within each <em>explanatory</em> group. For
                    the table shown, think about whether the row variable (cardiovascular death) or
                    the column variable (blood pressure) would be the <em>explanatory</em>
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. To explore a categorical relationship, the most appropriate
                    summary is the outcome percentages within each <em>explanatory</em> group. In
                    this case, the column variable (blood pressure) would be the explanatory
                    variable, so the appropriate percentages are the death percentages from each
                    blood pressure group. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient is a summary value for a
                    scatterplot, not for a two-way table. To explore a categorical relationship, the
                    most appropriate summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory
                    group.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Five-number summaries are only appropriate for lists of
                    quantitative measurements. But a two-way table summarizes categorical variables,
                    not quantitative variables. To explore a categorical relationship, the most
                    appropriate summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory
                    group.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="scatterplot_correlation_outlier" select="single">
        <body> A local ice cream shop kept track of the number of cans of cold soda it sold each
            day, and the temperature that day, for two months during the summer. The data are
            displayed in the scatterplot below: <image style="block"
                src="../webcontent/assessment2q3.gif"/> The one outlier corresponds to a day on
            which the refrigerator for the soda was broken. Which of the following is true? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> A reasonable value of the correlation coefficient r for these data is
                1.2. </choice>
            <choice value="B"> If the temperature were measured in degrees Celsius (C = 5/9*(F-32)),
                the value of r would change accordingly. </choice>
            <choice value="C"> If the outlier were removed, r would increase. </choice>
            <choice value="D"> If the outlier were removed, r would decrease. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient r must be between –1 and 1. It
                    cannot be larger than 1.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient r is a unitless number, so it’s not
                    affected by a change of units.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The outlier makes the data less "tightly clustered" around the
                    linear trend. Removing the outlier will increase the overall tightness of the
                    points around their straight-line trend, so the correlation coefficient would be
                    closer to 1. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. For a scatterplot where the trend is generally rising, the
                        <em>more</em> linear the scatterplot is, the <em>closer to 1</em> the
                    correlation coefficient r will be. Notice that removing the outlier will
                        <em>increase</em> the overall tightness of the points around their
                    straight-line trend.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="scatterplot_correlation_1" select="single">
        <body>Suppose that the correlation r between two quantitative variables was found to be r =
            0. Which of the following is the best interpretation of this correlation value?</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">There is a strong linear relationship between the two variables. </choice>
            <choice value="B">There is no linear relationship between the two variables. </choice>
            <choice value="C">There is a strong relationship between the two variables. </choice>
            <choice value="D">There is no relationship between the two variables. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A correlation coefficient <em style="italic">far</em> from zero
                    would indicate a strong linear relationship. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The correlation coefficient indicates the strength of the
                    linearity of a scatterplot relationship, and a correlation coefficient that is
                    zero indicates no linear relationship. However, that there might still be some
                    other (non-straight-line) kind of relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A correlation coefficient <em style="italic">far</em> from zero
                    would indicate a strong linear relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient only measures <em style="italic"
                        >linear</em> relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="scatterplot_correlation_2" select="multiple">
        <body> A correlation of r = 0.85 is found between weekly sales of firewood and cough drops
            over a 1-year period. Check all that apply.</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">There is a pretty strong positive linear relationship between sales of
                firewood and cough drops. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Fire must be the cause of coughing. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Temperature is a possible lurking variable that is behind this
                relationship. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient by itself isn’t enough to determine
                    whether the relationship was linear. You would need to look at the scatterplot
                    to determine if the relationship was a straight-line trend. Also, there is at
                    least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You can’t determine causation merely from the nature of a
                    display. Just because there might be an association, that doesn’t (by itself)
                    indicate anything about causation. Causation can only be determined by knowing
                    the nature of the study design. Also, there is at least one true
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Temperature is a possible lurking variable since the sales of
                    both items will tend to be low in the warm parts of the year, and tend to be
                    high in the cold parts of the year. So the sales would tend to be positively
                    associated (both low at the same time, both high at the same time), which would
                    explain the strong positive correlation coefficient.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient by itself isn’t enough to determine
                    whether the relationship was linear. You would need to look at the scatterplot
                    to determine if the relationship was a straight-line trend. Also, you can’t
                    determine causation merely from the nature of a display. Just because there
                    might be an association, that doesn’t (by itself) indicate anything about
                    causation. Causation can only be determined by knowing the nature of the study
                    design.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that temperature is a possible lurking variable
                    since the sales of both items will tend to be low in the warm parts of the year,
                    and tend to be high in the cold parts of the year. So the sales would tend to be
                    positively associated (both low at the same time, both high at the same time),
                    which would explain the strong positive correlation coefficient. However, the
                    correlation coefficient by itself isn’t enough to determine whether the
                    relationship was linear. You would need to look at the scatterplot to determine
                    if the relationship was a straight-line trend.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that temperature is a possible lurking variable
                    since the sales of both items will tend to be low in the warm parts of the year,
                    and tend to be high in the cold parts of the year. So the sales would tend to be
                    positively associated (both low at the same time, both high at the same time),
                    which would explain the strong positive correlation coefficient. However, you
                    can’t determine causation merely from the nature of a display. Just because
                    there might be an association, that doesn’t (by itself) indicate anything about
                    causation. Causation can only be determined by knowing the nature of the study
                    design.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that temperature is a possible lurking variable
                    since the sales of both items will tend to be low in the warm parts of the year,
                    and tend to be high in the cold parts of the year. So the sales would tend to be
                    positively associated (both low at the same time, both high at the same time),
                    which would explain the strong positive correlation coefficient. However, the
                    correlation coefficient by itself isn’t enough to determine whether the
                    relationship was linear. You would need to look at the scatterplot to determine
                    if the relationship was a straight-line trend. Also, you can’t determine
                    causation merely from the nature of a display. Just because there might be an
                    association, that doesn’t (by itself) indicate anything about causation.
                    Causation can only be determined by knowing the nature of the study
                    design.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="scatterplot_correlation_3" select="single">
        <body> The data in the scatterplot below are an individual's weight and the time it takes
            (in seconds) on a treadmill to raise his or her pulse rate to 140 beats per minute. The
            o's correspond to females and the +'s to males. Which of the following conclusions is
            most accurate?<image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment2q8.gif"/>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">There is a positive correlation between gender and weight. </choice>
            <choice value="B">There is a negative correlation between time and weight for males and
                for females. </choice>
            <choice value="C">There is a positive correlation between time and weight for males and
                for females. </choice>
            <choice value="D">There is a negative correlation between gender and weight.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There can only be a <em style="italic">correlation</em> between
                    two quantitative variables. But notice that "gender" is categorical. Also, the
                    correlation coefficient would be positive only when the points tend to rise from
                    left to right.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. For each separate gender, we see that the points on the
                    scatterplot tend to <em style="italic">fall</em> from left to right. This
                    indicates a <em style="italic">negative</em> relationship. So the correlation
                    coefficient would be negative for males, and would also be negative for females.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient would be positive only when the
                    points tend to rise from left to right. But on the scatterplot, we see that, for
                    both males and females, the points tend to fall from left to right. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The scatterplot does show a negative correlation pattern, but
                    there can only be a <em style="italic">correlation</em> between two quantitative
                    variables. But notice that "gender" is categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="scatterplot_correlation_4" select="single">
        <body> What can we say about the relationship between the correlation r and the slope b of
            the least-squares line for the same set of data? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Both r and b always have values between -1 and 1. </choice>
            <choice value="B">r is always larger than b. </choice>
            <choice value="C">r and b have the same sign (+ or -). </choice>
            <choice value="D">the slope b is always equal to the square of the correlation r. </choice>
            <choice value="E">b is always larger than r. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It’s true that the correlation r always has a value between –1
                    and 1, but there is no such restriction on slope. The slope of a line can exceed
                    1 or –1.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the correlation r always has value between -1 and
                    1, but a regression line could have a slope larger than 1. So it’s possible for
                    b to be larger than r.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Although the correlation r isn’t the same as the slope b, the
                    thing they always have in common is their <em style="italic">sign</em>.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is no such relationship between slope and correlation.
                    Remember that the correlation r always has a value between 0 and 1, so the
                    square of the correlation will also be between –1 and 1. But there is no such
                    restriction on slope.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that for points that tend to rise from left to right,
                    the correlation is close to 1 when the points are tightly clustered around the
                    regression line. But if the regression line is shallow, the slope could be close
                    to zero. So it’s possible for b to be <em style="italic">less</em> than
                    r.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="simpsons_paradox_lurking_variable" select="multiple">
        <body>
            <p>A study was done on the timeliness of flights categorized as either "on-time" or
                "delayed" of two major airlines: StatsAir and AirMedian. Data were collected over a
                period of time from five major cities and it was found that StatsAir does better
                overall (i.e., has a smaller percentage of flights categorized as delayed. However,
                in each of the five cities separately, AirMedian does better (i.e. has a smaller
                percentage of flights categorized as delayed in each city).</p>
            <p>Which of the following is correct? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">This is an example of Simpson's paradox.</choice>
            <choice value="B">"City" is a lurking variable in this example.</choice>
            <choice value="C">This is an example of a negative association between
                variables.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but "reverses" when the groups are combined. However,
                    there is at least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that "city" is a lurking variable, because
                    there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups
                    separately but "reverses" when the groups are combined. However, there is at
                    least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is only appropriate to call an association "positive" or
                    "negative" when the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables
                    ("timeliness" and "city") are categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is an example of Simpson’s paradox, because there is an
                    association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups separately
                    but "reverses" when the groups are combined. Such reversal typically indicates a
                    lurking variable, which in this case is "city."</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but "reverses" when the groups are combined. However,
                    it is only appropriate to call an association "positive" or "negative" when the
                    variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("timeliness" and
                    "city") are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that "city" is a lurking variable, because
                    there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups
                    separately but "reverses" when the groups are combined. However, it is only
                    appropriate to call an association "positive" or "negative" when the variables
                    are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("timeliness" and "city") are
                    categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s Paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but "reverses" when the groups are combined. Such
                    reversal typically indicates a lurking variable, which in this case is "city."
                    However, it is only appropriate to call an association "positive" or "negative"
                    when the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables
                    ("timeliness" and "city") are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <section id="myresponse">
        <short_answer id="short_answer_appropriate_display_numerical_measures" grading="automatic">
            <body>
                <p> Please answer the question below. Your response will not be graded, but it will
                    be available for your instructor to read.</p>
                <p>When faced with a data analysis problem that involves two variables, explain how
                    you would decide which graphical display and numerical measures to use.</p>
            </body>
            <part>
                <response match="*" score="0">
                    <feedback>Thank you for your response. It has been recorded and will be
                        available for your instructor to read.</feedback>
                </response>
                <no_response>
                    <feedback>You did not enter a response for this question.</feedback>
                </no_response>
            </part>
        </short_answer>
    </section>
</assessment>
