<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment 2.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_2_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_assessment_2_3.css"?>
<assessment id="_u2_m2_checkpoint1" max_attempts="3" recommended_attempts="1">
    <title>Examining Relationships Checkpoint 1</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you
            are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window
            will ask "This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?",
            click "OK" if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p>
        <p>If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost.
            After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to
            be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p>
    </introduction>
    <!--<content available="instructor_only">
        <p><em>Instructors: you can download the solution set for this checkpoint by clicking on the
                following link:</em>
            <link href="../webcontent/_u2_m2_checkpoint1.pdf">Solution Set</link>.</p>
    </content>-->
    <multiple_choice id="appropriate_display_1" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>A store asked 250 of its customers whether or not they were satisfied with the service.
                The responses were also classified according to the gender of the customers. We
                want to study whether there is a relationship between satisfaction and gender. </p>
            <p>Which of the following would be a meaningful display of the data from this study?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Side-by-side boxplots </choice>
            <choice value="B">A pie chart </choice>
            <choice value="C">A histogram </choice>
            <choice value="D">A scatterplot </choice>
            <choice value="E">A two-way table </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Side-by-side boxplots are a display for comparing several
                    groups of quantitative data (that is, for the relationship between a
                    categorical explanatory variable and a quantitative response variable).
                    In this scenario, both variables are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A pie chart is a display of a single variable. In this
                    scenario, there were two variables measured.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that a histogram is a display of a single
                    variable. In this scenario, there were two variables measured.
                    Furthermore, a histogram would display a set of quantitative data, but
                    in this scenario, both variables are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that a scatterplot is a display of
                        quantitative relationship (in other words, for the relationship
                    between a quantitative explanatory variable and a quantitative
                    response variable). In this scenario, both variables are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. A two-way table is the appropriate display of categorical
                    relationship (in other words, to display the relationship between a categorical
                    explanatory variable and a categorical response variable). </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="appropriate_display_2" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>A survey was conducted to study the relationship between the annual income of a
                family and the amount of money the family spends on entertainment. Data were
                collected from a random sample of 280 families from a certain metropolitan area. </p>
            <p>Which of the following would be a meaningful display of the data from this study?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Side-by-side boxplots </choice>
            <choice value="B">A pie chart </choice>
            <choice value="C">A histogram </choice>
            <choice value="D">A scatterplot </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Side-by-side boxplots are a display for comparing quantitative
                    data for several categories or groups (in other words, for the
                    relationship between a categorical explanatory variable and a
                    quantitative response variable). In this scenario, both variables are
                        quantitative.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A pie chart is a display of a single variable. In this
                    scenario, there were two variables measured. Furthermore, a pie chart
                    would display categorical data, but in this scenario, both variables
                    are quantitative.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A stemplot is a display of a single variable. In this
                    scenario, there were two variables measured.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. A scatterplot is the appropriate display of quantitative
                    relationship (in other words, to display the relationship between a quantitative
                    explanatory variable and a quantitative response variable). </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="appropriate_display_3" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>In order to study whether IQ level is related to birth order, data were collected
                from a sample of 540 students on their birth order (Oldest/In Between/Youngest) and
                their score on an IQ test.</p>
            <p>Which of the following would be a meaningful display of the data from this study?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">A pie chart </choice>
            <choice value="B">A histogram </choice>
            <choice value="C">A scatterplot </choice>
            <choice value="D">A two-way table </choice>
            <choice value="E">Side-by-side boxplots </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A pie graph is a display of a single variable. In this
                    scenario, there were <em style="italic">two</em> variables measured.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A histogram is a display of a single variable. In this
                    scenario, <em style="italic">two</em> variables were measured.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A scatterplot is a display of relationship between two
                    variables which are both quantitative. In this scenario, only one of
                    the two variables is quantitative.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A two-way table is a display of relationship between two
                    variables which are both categorical. In this scenario, only one of the
                    two variables is categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Side-by-side boxplots are the appropriate display for comparing
                    several groups of quantitative data (in other words, for displaying the
                    relationship between a categorical explanatory variable, in this case,
                    birth order, and a quantitative response variable, in this case, IQ
                    score). </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="scatterplot_relationship" select="single">
        <body> A local ice cream shop kept track of the number of cans of cold soda it sold each
            day, and the temperature that day, for 2 months during the summer. The data are
            displayed in the scatterplot below: <image style="block"
                src="../webcontent/assessment2q3.gif"/>Which of the following is the best
            description of the relationship between X and Y as it appears in the scatterplot?</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Positive linear relationship with outlier(s)</choice>
            <choice value="B">Positive linear relationship with no outlier(s) </choice>
            <choice value="C">Positive nonlinear relationship with outlier(s)</choice>
            <choice value="D">Negative linear relationship with no outlier(s)</choice>
            <choice value="E">Negative nonlinear relationship with outlier(s)</choice>
            <choice value="F">Negative nonlinear relationship with no outlier(s)</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The graph displays a positive relationship: an increase in X is
                    associated with an increase in Y. The relationship is linear because it can be
                    described as points scattered about a line. Finally, it has one point that
                    deviates from the pattern of the relationship, which is considered an
                    outlier.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While the relationship is positive and linear, it does have one
                    outlier&#8212;the point on the lower right that deviates from the pattern of the
                    relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you're correct that the relationship is positive and has
                    an outlier, the relationship is linear, because it can be described as points
                    scattered about a line.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While the relationship is linear, it is positive, because an
                    increase in X is associated with an increase in Y. It also does have one
                    outlier&#8212;the point on the lower right that deviates from the pattern of the
                    relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you're correct that the relationship has an outlier, it
                    is positive, because an increase in X is associated with an increase in Y, and
                    it is linear, because it can be described as points scattered about a
                    line.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="F" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The graph displays a positive relationship: an increase in X is
                    associated with an increase in Y. The relationship is linear, because it can be
                    described as points scattered about a line. Finally, it has one point that
                    deviates from the pattern of the relationship, which is considered an
                    outlier.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="conditional_percents" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Which of the tables is the appropriate table of conditional percentages to discover if
                the region where one lives affects whether or not one has health insurance?</p>
            <image src="../../webcontent/flash/didigetthis_caseii2_02q3image1.gif"/>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Table A</choice>
            <choice value="B">Table B</choice>
            <choice value="C">Table C</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This table reports the conditional percentages for each value of the
                    explanatory variable (region) displayed in the rows: northeast, midwest, south,
                    and west.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This table reports percentages each cell contributes to the
                    whole rather than conditional percentages for each value of the explanatory
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. We need to find the conditional percentages for each value of the
                    explanatory variable. This table displays the conditional percentages for health
                    insurance, which is not the explanatory variable.</feedback>
            </response>

        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</assessment>
