<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_introduction3">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction to Probability (3 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="relate_probability_to_likelihood"/>
    </head>
<body>
 
        <section>
            <title>What is Probability?</title>
            <body>
                <p>Probability is a mathematical description of randomness and uncertainty. It is a
                    way to measure or quantify uncertainty. Another way to think about probability
                    is that it is the official name for "chance."</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Probability is the Likelihood of Something Happening</title>
            <body>
                <p>One way to think of probability is that it is the <em>likelihood</em> that
                    something will occur. </p>
                <p>Probability is used to answer the following types of questions: </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><p>What is the chance that it will rain tomorrow?</p></li>
                    <li><p>What is the chance that a stock will go up in price?</p></li>
                    <li><p>What is the chance that I will have a heart attack?</p></li>
                    <li><p>What is the chance that I will live longer than 70 years?</p></li>
                    <li><p>What is the likelihood that when rolling a pair of dice, I will roll doubles?</p></li>
                    <li><p>What is the probability that I will win the lottery?</p></li>
                </ul>
                <p>Each of these examples has some uncertainty. For some, the chances are quite
                    good, so the probability would be quite high. For others, the chances are not
                    very good, so the probability is quite low (especially winning the lottery).</p>
                <p>Certainly, the chance of rain is different each day, and is higher during some
                    seasons. Your chance of having a heart attack, or of living longer than 70
                    years, depends on things like your current age, your family history, and your
                    lifestyle. However, you could use your intuition to predict some of those
                    probabilities fairly accurately, while others you might have no hunches about at
                    all.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Notation</title>
            <body>
                <p>We think you will agree that the word <em>probability</em> is a bit long to
                    include in equations, graphs and charts, so it is customary to use some
                    simplified notation instead of the entire word.</p>
                <p>If we wish to indicate "the probability it will rain tomorrow," we use the
                    notation "P(rain tomorrow)." We can abbreviate the probability of anything. If
                    we let <em>A </em> represent what we wish to find the probability of, then
                        <em>P(A)</em> would represent that probability.</p>
                <p>We can think of "<em>A</em>" as an "<em>event</em>." </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>NOTATION</th>
                        <th>MEANING</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>P(win lottery)</td>
                        <td>the probability that a person who has a lottery ticket will win that
                            lottery</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>P(A)</td>
                        <td>the probability that event A will occur</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>P(B)</td>
                        <td>the probability that event B will occur</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </body>
        </section>
        <theorem type="principle">
            <statement>
                <p><em>The "probability" of an event tells us how likely it is that the event will
                        occur.</em></p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>
        <p>What values can the probability of an event take, and what does the value tell us about
            the likelihood of the event
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T143648-0400" comment="I think the mathematical explanation of probability given in the walkthrough below provides an excellent &quot;turning point&quot; -- from here on out, probablity will be referred to as fractions or decimal values between 0 and 1 ...  not as &quot;2 out of three,&quot; but as 2/3 or .67. This explanation will proved for students the transition between thinking in terms of &quot;2 out of 3&quot; and thinking in terms of &quot;two-thirds.&quot;"?>occurring?<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
    <youtube src="J2KibEm5f04"></youtube>  
  <!--   <flash src="../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="405" height="238"
            purpose="walkthrough">
            <param name="movieURL">../webcontent/flash/_u4_voiceover3.swf</param>
            <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
            <param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
        </flash> -->
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_intro3_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <theorem type="principle">
            <statement>
                <p>
                    <em>The probability that an event will occur is between 0 and 1 or 0 ≤ P(A) ≤ 1.
                    </em></p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>
        <p>Many people prefer to express probability in percentages. Since all probabilities are
            decimals, each can be changed to an equivalent percentage. Thus, the latest principle is
            equivalent to saying, <em>"The chance that an event will occur is between 0% and
                100%</em>."</p>
        <p>Probabilities can be determined in two fundamental ways. Keep reading to find out what
            they are.</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
