<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_introduction2">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T124518-0400"?> to
            <?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T124523-0400" content=" ("?>Probability<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T124526-0400" content=")"?>
            (2 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="relate_probability_to_likelihood"/>
    </head>
<body>
 
        <example>
            <title>The Birthday Problem</title>
            <p>Suppose that you are at a party with 59 other people (for a total of 60). What are
                the chances (or, what is the probability) that at least 2 of the 60 guests share the
                same birthday?</p>
            <p>To clarify, by "share the same birthday," we mean that 2 people were born on the same
                date, not necessarily in the same year. Also, for the sake of simplicity, ignore
                leap years, and assume that there are 365 days in each year.</p>
            <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_intro2_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            <!--<flash src="../webcontent/flash/MultipleChoiceTutor.swf" width="505" height="341" purpose="learnbydoing">
<param name="question_file">../webcontent/flash/_u4_m0_inlinetutor2.xml</param>
<param name="problem_name">_u4_m0_inlinetutor2</param>
</flash>-->
            <p>Indeed, there is a 99.4% chance that at least 2 of the 60 guests share the same
                birthday. In other words, it is <em style="italic">almost certain</em> that at least
                2 of the guests share the same birthday. This is very counterintuitive.</p>
            <p>Unlike the <em style="italic">Let's Make a Deal</em> example, for this scenario, we
                don't really have a good step-by-step explanation that will give you insight into
                this surprising answer. Later in this section, we will revisit this example and
                explain the solution.</p>
        </example>
        <p>From these two examples, you have seen that your original hunches cannot always be
            counted upon to give you correct predictions of probabilities. </p>
        <p>In general, <em style="italic">probability is not always intuitive</em>. </p>
        <p>Even though these two examples are definitely from the
            <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T141116-0400"?>"<?oxy_insert_end?>harder<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T141118-0400"?>"<?oxy_insert_end?>
            end of the complexity spectrum, hopefully they have motivated you to learn more about
            probability. We will need to further expand and extend our understanding of probability.
            Eventually we will need to develop a more formal approach to probability, but we will
            begin with an informal discussion of what probability is.</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
