<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_relative_frequency1">
    <head>
        <title>Relative Frequency (1 of 2)</title>
        <objref idref="explain_how_relative_frequency_is_used"/>
    </head>
<body>
   
        <p>If we toss a coin, roll a die, or spin a spinner many times, we hardly ever achieve the
            exact <em>theoretical</em> probabilities that we know we should get, but we can get
            pretty close. When we run a simulation or when we use a random sample and record the
            results, we are using <em>empirical</em> probability. This is often called the
                <em>Relative Frequency</em> definition of probability.</p>
        <p>Here is a realistic example where the relative frequency method was used to find the
            probabilities:</p>
        <example>
            <title>Blood Type</title>
            <p>Researchers discovered at the beginning of the 20th century that human blood comes in
                various types (A, B, AB, and O), and that some types are more common than others.
                How could researchers determine the probability of a particular blood type, say O?
                Just looking at one or two or a handful of people would not be very helpful in
                determining the overall chance that a randomly chosen person would have blood type
                O. But sampling many people at random, and finding the relative frequency of blood
                type O occurring, provides an adequate estimate. For example, it is now well known
                that the probability of blood type O among white people in the United States is
                0.45. This was found by sampling many (say, 100,000) white people in the country,
                finding that roughly 45,000 of them had blood type O, and then using the relative
                frequency: 45,000 / 100,000 = 0.45 as the estimate for the probability for the event
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T165330-0400" comment="remove bold (no emphasis needed)"?><em>"having
                    blood type O."</em><?oxy_comment_end?></p>
            <p>(Comment: Note that there are racial and ethnic differences in the probabilities of
                blood types. For example, the probability of blood type O among black people in the
                United States is 0.49, and the probability that a randomly chosen Japanese person
                has blood type O is only 0.3). </p>
        </example>
        <p>Let's review the relative frequency method for finding probabilities:</p>
        <p>To estimate the probability of event A, written P(A), we may repeat the random experiment
            many times and count the number of times event A occurs. Then P(A) is estimated by the
            ratio of the number of times A occurs to the number of repetitions, which is called the
                <em>relative frequency of event A</em>.</p>
        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image005a.gif" alt="Relative Frequency of Event
A = (number of times A occurred)/(total number of repetitions)."/>
        <!--<activity idref="_u4_m0_relative_frequency1_dig1" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title>Did I Get This?</title>
            <body>
                <p>What are the breakfast-eating habits of college students?</p>
                <p>A group of 460 college students was surveyed over several typical weekdays, and
                    253 of them reported that they had eaten breakfast that day. Let B be the event
                    of interest&#8212;that a college student eats breakfast.</p>
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_relfreq1_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_relfreq1_tutor2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            </body>
        </section>
         <activity idref="_u4_m0_relative_frequency1_lbd1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
