<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u4_introduction1">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction to Probability (1 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="relate_probability_to_likelihood"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Now that we understand how probability fits into the Big Picture as a key element behind
            statistical inference, we are ready to learn more about it. Our first goal is to
            introduce some fundamental terminology (the language) and notation that is used when
            discussing probability. Before we do that, though, let's start with two fun examples
            that explain the reasons for the careful treatment that we give probability in this
            course.</p>
        <!--  <p>What are the chances that it will rain tomorrow? What is the probability that I will win the lottery? 
    What are the chances that a certain stock will go up? We often talk, hear, or think about probability, and therefore we've all developed some level of intuition about the concept of chance. For example, suppose I asked you
    "What is the probability (or what are the chances) of getting 'heads' when a fair coin is tossed?"  I believe that most, if not all, of you would be able to give me the correct answer (1/2) even without learning anything about probability. In general, though,</p>
-->
        <p>Often, relying only on our intuition is not sufficient to determine probability, so we
            need some tools to work with, which is exactly what we study in this section.</p>
        <p>Here are two examples:</p>
        <example>
            <title>The <em style="italic">Let's Make a Deal</em> Paradox</title>
            <p><em style="italic">Let's Make a Deal</em> was a popular television game show, which
                first aired in the 1960s. The <em style="italic">Let's Make a Deal</em> paradox is
                named after that show. In the show, the contestant had to choose between three
                doors. One of the doors had a big prize behind it such as a car or a lot of cash,
                and the other two were empty. (Actually, for entertainment's sake, each of the other
                two doors had some stupid gift behind it, like a goat or a chicken, but we'll refer
                to them here as empty.)</p>
            <p>The contestant had to choose one of the three doors, but instead of revealing the
                chosen door, the host revealed one of the two unchosen doors to be empty. At this
                point in the game, there were two unopened doors: the door that the contestant had
                originally chosen and the remaining unchosen door. One of them had the prize behind
                it.</p>
            <p>The contestant was given the option either to <em style="italic">stay</em> with the
                door that he or she had initially chosen or <em style="italic">switch</em> to the
                other door. </p>
            <p>What do you think the contestant should do, stay or switch? What do you think is the
                probability that you will win the big prize if you stay? What about if you
                switch?</p>
            <p>In order for you to gain a feel for this game, you can play it a few times using an
                activity below.</p>
            <iframe src="../../webcontent/html_activities/letsmakeadeal/letsMakeADeal.html"
                height="700" width="750"/>

            <!-- <p>In order for you to gain a feel for this game, you can play it a few times using an
                applet. Click <link href="http://nlvm.usu.edu/en/nav/frames_asid_117_g_4_t_5.html"
                    target="new">here</link> to launch the applet in a separate window. </p>
               Click <link href="http://www.stat.tamu.edu/~west/applets/LetsMakeaDeal.html"
                    target="new">here</link> to launch the applet in a separate window. </p>-->
            <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_intro1_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            <!--<flash src="../webcontent/flash/MultipleChoiceTutor.swf" width="505" height="285" purpose="learnbydoing">
<param name="question_file">../webcontent/flash/_u4_m0_inlinetutor1.xml</param>
<param name="problem_name">_u4_m0_inlinetutor1</param>
</flash>-->
            <p>The intuition of most people is that each of the two doors is equally likely to
                contain the prize&#8212;that there is a 50-50 chance of winning with either
                selection. This, however, is not the case. Actually, there is a 67% chance&#8212;or
                a probability of 2/3 (2 out of 3)&#8212;of winning by switching, and only a 33%
                chance&#8212;or a probability of 1/3 (1 out of 3)&#8212;of winning by staying with
                the door that was originally chosen. This means that a contestant is twice as likely
                to win if he or she switches to the unchosen door. Isn't this a bit counterintuitive
                and confusing? Most people think so when they are first faced with this problem. We
                will now try to explain this paradox to you in two different ways:</p>
          
            <youtube src="e7c6_h0Zf6U"></youtube>
            <!--    <flash src="../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="405" height="329"
                purpose="walkthrough">
                <param name="movieURL">../webcontent/flash/_u4_voiceover1.swf</param>
                <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
                <param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
            </flash>-->
            <p>If you are still not convinced (or even if you are), here is a different way of
                explaining the paradox:</p>
            <youtube src="e3cCUAGHIOI"></youtube>
            <!--    <flash src="../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="405" height="265"
                purpose="walkthrough">
                <param name="movieURL">../webcontent/flash/_u4_voiceover2.swf</param>
                <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
                <param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
            </flash>-->
        </example>
        <p>If this example still did not persuade you that probability is not always intuitive, the
            next example should definitely do the trick.</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
