<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_introduction5">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction to Probability (5 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="relate_probability_to_likelihood"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>We will now shift our discussion to
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101105T155016-0400" comment="make bold to indicate new terminiology"?>empirical<?oxy_comment_end?>
            ways to determine probabilities.</p>
        <section>
            <title>A Question</title>
            <body>
                <p>A single flip of a coin has an uncertain outcome. So, every time a coin is
                    flipped, the outcome of that flip is unknown until the flip occurs.</p>
                <p><em>However, if you flip a fair coin over and over again, would you expect P(H)
                        to be exactly 0.5?</em> In other words, would you expect there to be the
                    same number of results of "heads" as there are "tails"?</p>
                <p>The following activity will allow you to discover the answer.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <activity idref="_u4_m0_introduction5_lbd1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <p>The above Learn by Doing activity was our first example of the second way of determining
            probability: Empirical (Observational) methods. In the activity, we determined that the
            probability of getting the result "heads" is 0.5 by flipping a fair coin many, many
            times.</p>
        <section>
            <title>A Second Question</title>
            <body>
                <p>After doing this experiment, an important question naturally comes to mind.
                        <em>How would we know if the coin was not fair?</em> Certainly, classical
                    probability methods would never be able to answer this question. In addition,
                    classical methods could never tell us the actual P(H). The only way to answer
                    this question is to perform another experiment.</p>
                <p>The next activity will allow you to do just that.</p>
                <activity idref="_u4_m0_introduction5_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            </body>
        </section>


        <!-- <definition>
            <term>Random Experiment</term>
            <meaning><p>A <em>random experiment</em> is a series of trials that produces
                outcomes that cannot be predicted in advance (hence the uncertainty).</p>
            </meaning>
        </definition> -->
        <p>So, these types of experiments can verify classical probabilities and they can also
            determine when games of chance are not following <em>fair</em> practices. However, their
            real importance is to answer probability questions that arise when we are faced with a
            situation that does not follow any pattern and cannot be predetermined. In reality, most
            of the probabilities of interest to us fit the latter description.</p>
        <section>
            <title>To Summarize</title>
            <body>
                <p><em>1.</em> Probability is a way of quantifying uncertainty.</p>
                <p><em>2.</em> We are interested in the probability of an event&#8212;the likelihood
                    of the event occurring.</p>
                <p><em>3.</em> The probability of an event ranges from 0 to 1. The closer the
                    probability is to 0, the less likely the event is to occur. The closer the
                    probability is to 1, the more likely the event is to occur.</p>
                <p><em>4.</em> There are two ways to determine probability: Theoretical (Classical)
                    and Empirical (Observational).</p>
                <p><em>5.</em> Theoretical methods use the nature of the situation to determine
                    probabilities.</p>
                <p><em>6.</em> Empirical methods use a series of trials that produce outcomes that
                    cannot be predicted in advance (hence the uncertainty).</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <p/>
        <activity purpose="myresponse" idref="_u4_introduction5_feedback"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
