<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_probability1">
    <head>
        <title>Probability</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Recall the Big Picture—the four-step process that encompasses statistics (as it is
            presented in this course):</p>
        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/big_picture_probability.gif" alt="The Big Picture
of Statistics. First, a set of data was created from subset of the population. This is the Producing
Data step. Then, we perform exploratory data analysis on the data. With these results, we apply
probability which is our first step in drawing conclusions about the population from the data. After
we have applied probability to the data, we can draw conclusions. This is called inference, the second
step in drawing conclusions. In this unit we will be looking at the Probability step."/>
        <p>So far, we've discussed the first two steps:</p>
        <p>
            <em>Producing data</em>—how data are obtained and what considerations affect the data
            production process.</p>
        <p>
            <em>Exploratory data analysis</em>—tools that help us get a first feel for the data, by
            exposing their features using graphs and numbers.</p>
        <p>(Recall that the structure of this course is such that exploratory data analysis was
            covered first, followed by producing data.)</p>
        <p>Our eventual goal is <em>inference</em>—drawing reliable conclusions about the population
            based on what we've discovered in our sample. In order to really understand how
            inference works, though, we first need to talk about <em>probability</em>, because it is
            the underlying foundation for the methods of statistical inference. We use an example to
            explain why probability is so essential to inference.</p>
        <p>First, here is the general idea: As we all know, the way statistics works is that we use
            a sample to learn about the population from which it was drawn. Ideally, the sample
            should be random so that it represents the population well. </p>
        <p>Recall from the Sampling module that when we say a random sample represents the
            population <em style="italic">well</em>, we mean that there is no inherent bias in this
            sampling technique. It is important to acknowledge, though, that this does not mean that
            all random samples are necessarily “perfect.” Random samples are still random, and
            therefore no random sample will be exactly the same as another. One random sample may
            give a fairly accurate representation of the population, while another random sample
            might be “off,” purely due to chance. Unfortunately, when looking at a particular sample
            (which is what happens in practice), we will never know how much it differs from the
            population. This uncertainty is where probability comes into the picture. We use
            probability to quantify how much we expect random samples to vary. This gives us a way
            to draw conclusions about the population in the face of the uncertainty that is
            generated by the use of a random sample. The following example will illustrate this
            important point. </p>
        <example>
            <title>Death Penalty</title>
            <p>Suppose that we are interested in estimating the percentage of U.S. adults who favor
                the death penalty. In order to do so, we choose a random sample of 1,200 U.S. adults
                and ask their opinion: either in favor of or against the death penalty. We find that
                744 out of the 1,200, or 62%, are in favor. (Comment: although this is only an
                example, this figure of 62% is quite realistic, given some recent polls). Here is a
                picture that illustrates what we have done and found in our example:</p>
            <!--:WARNING: Removed paragraph enclosing image element.-->
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image002.gif" alt="We have a large circle
representing the entire population of US Adults. We are interested in the population's opinions
on the death penalty. From this population we take out a random sample of 1200 adults, and find
that within this sample, 62% are in favor of the death penalty."/>
            <p>Our goal here is to do inference&#8212;learn and draw conclusions about the opinions
                of the entire population of U.S. adults regarding the death penalty, based on the
                opinions of only 1,200 of them.</p>
            <p> Can we conclude that 62% of the population favors the death penalty? Another random
                sample could give a very different result. So we are uncertain. But since our sample
                is random, we know that our uncertainty is due to chance, and not due to problems
                with how the sample was collected. So we can use probability to describe the
                likelihood that our sample is within a desired level of accuracy. For example,
                probability can answer the question, "How likely is it that our sample estimate is
                no more than 3% from the true percentage of all U.S. adults who are in favor of the
                death penalty?” </p>
            <p>The answer to this question (which we find using probability) is obviously going to
                have an important impact on the confidence we can attach to the inference step. In
                particular, if we find it quite unlikely that the sample percentage will be very
                different from the population percentage, then we have a lot of confidence that we
                can draw conclusions about the population based on the sample.</p>
        </example>
     <!--     <p>The probability unit starts with an introduction, which will give you some motivating
            examples and an intuitive and informal perspective on probability.</p>-->
    </body>
</workbook_page>
