<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_lbd_01"><title>tutor</title><page><content><p>Leukocytes play major roles in immunity, with some cells having a larger role in nonspecific immunity (can attack a large range of invaders), while others function in specific immunity (only attack specific invaders). Identify whether each of the following is specific or non-specific.</p></content><question id="q1"><body>Neutrophil</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="specific">specific</choice><choice value="nonspecific">non-specific</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="identify_function_each_leukocyte_lymphocyte_SKILL" /><response match="specific" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Neutrophils are non-specific phagocytes, attacking nearly any invader soon after they enter the body&apos;s tissues.</feedback></response><response match="nonspecific" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Neutrophils are non-specific phagocytes, attacking nearly any invader soon after they enter the body&apos;s tissues.</feedback></response><hint>Neutrophils are often the first cells to show up at the site of infection.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>B-lymphocyte</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="specific">specific</choice><choice value="nonspecific">non-specific</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="identify_function_each_leukocyte_lymphocyte_SKILL" /><response match="specific" score="10"><feedback>Correct. These cells produce antibodies, with each B-lymphocyte producing many copies of the same antibody, which will only bind to one antigen, making it specific.</feedback></response><response match="nonspecific" score="0"><feedback>: Incorrect. These cells produce antibodies, with each B-lymphocyte producing many copies of the same antibody, which will only bind to one antigen, making it specific.</feedback></response><hint>Most lymphocytes fall into the same category.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Basophil</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="specific">specific</choice><choice value="nonspecific">non-specific</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="identify_function_each_leukocyte_lymphocyte_SKILL" /><response match="specific" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Basophils play important roles in mediating inflammation, which is a nonspecific response to infection or tissue damage..</feedback></response><response match="nonspecific" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Basophils play important roles in mediating inflammation, which is a nonspecific response to infection or tissue damage.</feedback></response><hint>Consider the process to which basophils contribute.</hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body>T-lymphocyte</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="specific">specific</choice><choice value="nonspecific">non-specific</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="identify_function_each_leukocyte_lymphocyte_SKILL" /><response match="specific" score="10"><feedback>Correct. T-lymphocytes often attack virally infected cells (among other functions). But each T lymphocyte will only attack cells displaying a specific antigen tag on it.</feedback></response><response match="nonspecific" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. T-lymphocytes often attack virally infected cells (among other functions). But each T lymphocyte will only attack cells displaying a specific antigen tag on it.</feedback></response><hint>Most lymphocytes fall into the same category.</hint></part></question><question id="q5"><body>Monocytes</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="specific">specific</choice><choice value="nonspecific">non-specific</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="identify_function_each_leukocyte_lymphocyte_SKILL" /><response match="specific" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Monocytes are nonspecific phagocytes similar to neutrophils, except that they will move into the tissues and mature into large, long-living cells called macrophages, while neutrophils are short-lived cells that only move out of the bloodstream at sites of infections.</feedback></response><response match="nonspecific" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Monocytes are nonspecific phagocytes similar to neutrophils, except that they will move into the tissues and mature into large, long-living cells called macrophages, while neutrophils are short-lived cells that only move out of the bloodstream at sites of infections.</feedback></response><hint>Moncytes are similar to neutrophils.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
