<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow__LBD_03"><title>DynaDrop Assessment</title><question id="q1"><body><p>Match each characteristic to either the pulmonary circulation, systemic circulation, or both.</p><custom id="dragDrop" src="../../../webcontent/DynaDropHTML.js" type="javascript" width="550" height="200" layout="../webcontent/describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow__LBD_03_layout.xml" logging="true"><param name="showInputs">false</param></custom></body><fill_in_the_blank id="Init_Pul" shuffle="true"><choice value="Location1">Location1</choice><choice value="Location2">Location2</choice><choice value="Location3">Location3</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="Init_Sys" shuffle="true"><choice value="Location1">Location1</choice><choice value="Location2">Location2</choice><choice value="Location3">Location3</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="Init_Both" shuffle="true"><choice value="Location1">Location1</choice><choice value="Location2">Location2</choice><choice value="Location3">Location3</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="identify_classify_major_blood_vessels_heart_SKILL" /><response input="Init_Pul" match="Location1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the pulmonary circulation contains capillary networks for the exchange of gasses, the systemic circulation also participates in exchange.</feedback></response><response input="Init_Pul" match="Location2" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The pulmonary circulation is found in the thoracic cavity along with the heart, making the distance blood has to travel much shorter than most of the pathways found in the systemic circulation.</feedback></response><response input="Init_Pul" match="Location3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pulmonary arteries carry oxygen-poor blood from the heart to the pulmonary capillary beds.</feedback></response><hint>Consider the distance of the pulmonary circulation from the heart.</hint></part><part id="q1_p2"><skillref idref="identify_classify_major_blood_vessels_heart_SKILL" /><response input="Init_Sys" match="Location1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the systemic circulation contains capillary networks for the exchange of gasses and nutrients, the pulmonary circulation also participates in exchange.</feedback></response><response input="Init_Sys" match="Location2" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pulmonary circulation is found in the thoracic cavity along with the heart, making the distance blood has to travel much shorter than most of the pathways found in the systemic circulation.</feedback></response><response input="Init_Sys" match="Location3" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The arteries of the systemic circulation carry oxygen-rich blood from the heart to the systemic capillary beds.</feedback></response><hint>The systemic circulation delivers blood from the heart to organs and tissues.</hint></part><part id="q1_p3"><skillref idref="identify_classify_major_blood_vessels_heart_SKILL" /><response input="Init_Both" match="Location1" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Gas exchange occurs in the capillaries of the pulmonary circulation while gas and nutrient exchange occurs in the capillaries of the systemic circulation.</feedback></response><response input="Init_Both" match="Location2" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. One of these circulations is found in the thoracic cavity along with the heart, making its pathways for blood flow much shorter than in the other pathway.</feedback></response><response input="Init_Both" match="Location3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. One of these circulations carries oxygen-rich blood in their arterial circulation whereas the other carries oxygen-poor blood.</feedback></response><hint>Circulation means “the continuous motion by which blood travels through all parts of the body under the action of the heart.”</hint></part></question></assessment>
