<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_phases_hemostasis_lbd_02"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>The extrinsic pathway for coagulation would begin where?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="surf_contact">surface contact</choice><choice value="tis_dam">tissue damage</choice><choice value="fac_x">factor Xa</choice><choice value="fibrinogen">fibrinogen</choice><choice value="fibrin">fibrin</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_steps_form_fibrin_clot_SKILL" /><response match="surf_contact" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood can still clot outside of the body when exposed to a surface like a glass tube because it contains an intrinsic clotting mechanism.</feedback></response><response match="tis_dam" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The damaged endothelium of the blood vessel releases tissue factor that initiates the clotting process.</feedback></response><response match="fac_x" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Factor Xa is involved in both the extrinsic and intrinsic pathways but it must be stimulated by other factors so it does not begin either pathway.</feedback></response><response match="fibrinogen" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fibrinogen is a protein that is found in both pathways. The goal of both pathways is to convert fibrinogen to its active form fibrin to form clots.</feedback></response><response match="fibrin" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fibrin is the active form of fibrinogen and is the end of the clotting pathway not the beginning.</feedback></response><hint>Extrinsic means the signal comes from outside of the blood itself.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p>The goal of both pathways is to activate which clotting factor which can go on to form stable clots?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="fac_x">factor Xa</choice><choice value="fibrinogen">fibrinogen</choice><choice value="fibrin">fibrin</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="describe_steps_form_fibrin_clot_SKILL" /><response match="fac_x" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Factor Xa is involved in both the extrinsic and intrinsic pathways but it is not directly converted into a protein that results in clots.</feedback></response><response match="fibrinogen" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Fibrinogen is a protein that is found in both pathways. The goal of both pathways is to convert fibrinogen to its active form fibrin to form clots.</feedback></response><response match="fibrin" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fibrin is the active form of fibrinogen and is the end of the clotting pathway. If it were always present it would cause unwanted clots. </feedback></response><hint>This protein has to be inactive until needed or clots would form spontaneously.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p>What is the factor that is shared by both pathways and that is required to activate prothrombin?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="fac_x">factor Xa</choice><choice value="fibrinogen">fibrinogen</choice><choice value="fibrin">fibrin</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="describe_steps_form_fibrin_clot_SKILL" /><response match="fac_x" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Factor Xa is involved in both the extrinsic and intrinsic pathways and leads to the activation of prothrombin.</feedback></response><response match="fibrinogen" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fibrinogen is a protein that is found in both pathways, however prothrombin must be activated to thrombin in order for it to be activated. </feedback></response><response match="fibrin" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fibrin is the active form of fibrinogen and is the end of the clotting pathway. </feedback></response><hint>This factor is activated differently by the two pathways but then leads to the activation of prothrombin to thrombin.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
