<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_composition_plasma_lbd_01"><title>tutor</title><page><content><p>Using the diagram of a sample of blood that has been centrifuged to separate it into its component parts answer the following questions:</p><image src="../webcontent/blood-centrifugation-scheme-lbd.png" /></content><question id="q1"><body>What makes up the largest fraction of blood?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="plasma">plasma</choice><choice value="leukocytes">leukocytes</choice><choice value="platelets">platelets</choice><choice value="erythrocytes">erythrocytes</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="identify_structure_platelets_SKILL" /><response match="plasma" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Plasma is the liquid portion of the blood and makes up about 55% of blood by volume.</feedback></response><response match="leukocytes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Leukocytes are white blood cells and make up less than 1% of the blood.</feedback></response><response match="platelets" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Platelets are part of the buffy coat with the white blood cells and make up less than 1% of the blood.</feedback></response><response match="erythrocytes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The erythrocytes are the red blood cells and make up 45% of the blood which is less than another fraction.</feedback></response><hint>Look for what takes up the most space in the test tube of separated blood.</hint><hint>The plasma does not contain cells so it is the most trasnlucent portion of blood.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Why do erythrocytes appear on the bottom of the tube after it has been centrifuged?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="oxygen">they carry oxygen</choice><choice value="biggest">they are the biggest cells</choice><choice value="less_dense">they are less dense than water</choice><choice value="heme">they contain heme</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="identify_structure_platelets_SKILL" /><response match="oxygen" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The oxygen they carry does not make them the most dense, and density determines where they end up after centrifugation.</feedback></response><response match="biggest" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Erythrocytes are smaller than the white blood cells.</feedback></response><response match="less_dense" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. They are more dense than water.</feedback></response><response match="heme" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The heme group contains iron which makes these cells the most dense so they end up on the bottom.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what element they need to carry oxygen.</hint><hint>They contain iron</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>What is the function(s) of the smallest portion of the blood?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="A">carry oxygen and defend against infection</choice><choice value="B">carry oxygen and regulate temperature</choice><choice value="C">defend against infection and contribute to hemostasis</choice><choice value="D">defended against infection and regulate water homeostasis</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="describe_function_platelets_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The Erythrocytes which make up 45% of the blood are responsible for carrying the oxygen.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The Erythrocytes which make up 45% of the blood are responsible for carrying the oxygen.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The buffy coat contains both the leukocytes, which are responsible for defending against infection, and the platelets, which help prevent blood loss (hemostasis).</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The proteins in the plasma help to regulate water homeostasis and blood pressure. </feedback></response><hint>This portion of blood is called the buffy coat.</hint><hint>This portion contains white blood cells and platelets.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
