<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_structure_function_arterioles_metarterioles_capillaries_venules_digt_01"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Which of the following structure is designed to facilitate the exchange of gasses and nutrients?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">Arterioles</choice><choice value="choice2">Metarterioles</choice><choice value="choice3">Capillaries</choice><choice value="choice4">Venules</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_structure_function_capillaries_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Arterioles determine delivery to tissues by constricting or dilating as necessary.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Metarterioles are associated with precapillary sphincters that can be used to direct the flow of blood into specific capillary networks.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Capillary walls consist of only a tunica interna, which allows for efficient diffusion.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some post capillary venules can participate in gas exchange, but the main function of the venules is to return the blood to the heart.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Arterioles can adjust their diameter in response to __________.</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="choice1">the sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="choice2">hormones</choice><choice value="choice3">local signaling molecules</choice><choice value="choice4">all of the above</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="describe_structure_function_arterioles_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the sympathetic nervous system is an important determinant of arteriolar diameter, it is not the only determinant of arteriolar diameter on this list as well.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although several hormones affect arteriolar diameter, there are other determinants of arteriolar diameter on this list as well.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although local signaling molecules can affect arteriolar diameter, there are other determinants of arteriolar diameter on this list as well.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Arteriolar diameter can be adjusted in response to many signals, including the sympathetic nervous system, hormones and local signaling molecules.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Which of the following type of capillary is <em style="bold">not</em> matched with its correct description?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">Fenestrated capillary: have large openings, making them the most permeable of all the capillary types</choice><choice value="choice2">Sinusoid capillaries: allow for the passage of blood cells and blood proteins and are found in bone marrow and liver</choice><choice value="choice3">Continuous capillary: have the lowest permeability and are found in tissues such as muscle and nervous</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="describe_structure_function_capillaries_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Fenestrated capillaries have openings, but they are not as large as those in sinusoid capillaries. Therefore, they are not the most permeable capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an appropriate description of sinusoid capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an appropriate description of continuous capillaries.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
