<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_changes_circulatory_system_aging_lbd_01"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>As people age, it is common for their arterial pulse pressure (the difference between systolic and diastolic pressures) to increase. For example, a typical pulse pressure in a young adult is 40 mmHg (120 mmHg – 80 mmHg). This tends to increase to 50 mmHg as we get older.</p><p>What cardiovascular change would explain why pulse pressure tends to increase with age?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">Atherosclerosis of the coronary arteries leads to a decrease in cardiac output.</choice><choice value="choice2">Arteriosclerosis of the large arteries prevents them from passively absorbing the blood ejected from the heart (stroke volume) as easily, causing systolic pressure to rise.</choice><choice value="choice3">Congestive heart failure, which leads to larger stroke volumes and therefore more pressure in the arteries with each beat.</choice><choice value="choice4">Increasing LDL levels that lead to plaques in the coronary vessels.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_changes_circulatory_system_aging_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Atherosclerosis of coronary vessels could cause a heart attack, leading to a decrease in cardiac output, but an increased pulse pressure is either associated with an increased stroke volume (and most likely cardiac output) or an increased stiffness of the arteries.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="10"><feedback>Correct. As the vessels become more stiff with age, they don’t passively expand well. This increases the pressure for any given volume of blood in the arteries.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Congestive heart failure leads to a decrease in stroke volumes, which would decrease the pulse pressure.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. LDL can contribute to the development of atherosclerotic plaque in the coronary vessels, ultimately leading to a heart attack. But this would lead to a decrease in cardiac output, while an increased pulse pressure is either associated with an increased stroke volume or stiffer large arteries.</feedback></response><hint>Pulse pressure is determined by the compliance of the large arteries (how easily they passively expand) and the volume entering these same arteries.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
