<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_lbd_01"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Although the SA node can spontaneously depolarize, this rate is partially controlled by the autonomic nervous system. What affect does the parasympathetic nervous system have on the rate of SA node depolarization and what could be a mechanism for this effect?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">increase HR, open potassium channels</choice><choice value="choice2">increase HR, close potassium channels</choice><choice value="choice3">decrease HR, open potassium channels</choice><choice value="choice4">decrease HR, close potassium channels</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_role_nerves_depolarization_pacemaker_cells_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The parasympathetic nervous system is associated with rest, which includes a decrease in HR, not an increase. But opening potassium channels lets positive potassium ions out of the cell, making it more negative inside, bringing it further from threshold potential. This would slow HR.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The parasympathetic nervous system is associated with rest, which includes a decrease in HR, not an increase. Closing potassium channels would keep more positive ions inside of the cell, keeping it closer to threshold. This would increase HR.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The parasympathetic nervous system decreases HR by opening potassium channels. As potassium ions flow out of the cell, it becomes more negative inside, moving it further from threshold.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the parasympthatetic nervous system decreases HR, it does not do so by closing potassium channels. When these channels close, they keep more positive ions inside of the cells, bringing the membrane potential closer to threshold. This would increase HR.</feedback></response><hint>The parasympathetic nervous system is often associated with functions related to “rest and digest”.</hint><hint>In order to depolarize, positive ions must enter the cell.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
