<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_02"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>When RBCs are broken down at the end of their lifespan, most of the hemoglobin components are recycled. Which component is not recycled?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">iron</choice><choice value="choice2">heme group</choice><choice value="choice3">alpha globin</choice><choice value="choice4">beta globin</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Iron is recycled by transporting it on tranferrin back to bone marrow.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The heme group is ultimately broken down into bilirubin and urobilin, which are excreted from the body in urine and feces. These breakdown products are responsible for the yellow color of urine and the brown color of feces.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The globin proteins can be broken down into their amino acids to be re-used in making other proteins.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The globin proteins can be broken down into their amino acids to be re-used in making other proteins.</feedback></response><hint>The body is good at recycling common structures and ions.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Red blood cells have a limited lifespan because __________.</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">they experience apoptosis</choice><choice value="choice2">they cannot “fix” damage that accumulates over time</choice><choice value="choice3">they express self proteins that degrade, causing immune cells to attack them</choice><choice value="choice4">their high mitotic rate causes mutations that accumulate over time</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="describe_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Apoptosis is programmed cell death, which is not what RBC experience.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Because they do not have nuclei, as damage occurs to proteins, they cannot replace them.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The self-proteins (antigens) that determine blood type do not degrade and are not attached by immune cells; they would only cause problems during mismatched transfusion as discussed later.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Mature RBC do not divide.</feedback></response><hint>Most long-living cells would not live as long if they could not do this.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
