<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_03"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>One of the stages of red blood cell production is called the reticulocyte, so named because these cells contain ribosomal RNA strands that when stained look like reticular fibers. Reticulocytes are those cells recently released by the bone marrow and only circulate for about 24 hours before becoming mature RBCs. Normally about 1% of circulating RBCs are reticulocytes.</p><p>In the hours and days after donating blood, what would you expect to happen to both your erythropoietin levels and your reticulocyte count?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="choice1">They will both decrease.</choice><choice value="choice2">They will both increase.</choice><choice value="choice3">Erythropoeitin will increase and reticulocyte count will decrease.</choice><choice value="choice4">Erythropoeitin will decrease and reticulocyte count will increase.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_SKILL" /><response match="choice1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood donation can cause your total volume of RBCs to fall by up to 10%. This would stimulate changes in erythropoietin and reticulocyte count, but not in the directions chosen.</feedback></response><response match="choice2" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Blood donation can cause your total volume of RBCs to fall by up to 10%. This would stimulate an increase in erythropoietin, which would stimulate your bone marrow to increase production of RBCs, causing the release of more reticulocytes.</feedback></response><response match="choice3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood donation can cause your total volume of RBCs to fall by up to 10%. This would stimulate an increase in erythropoietin but not a decrease in reticulocyte count.</feedback></response><response match="choice4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood donation can cause your total volume of RBCs to fall by up to 10%. This would stimulate an increase in erythropoietin.</feedback></response><hint>After donating blood the body would like to rapidly replace the lost cells.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
