<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m2_transmit_dopamine_DIGT"><title>Transport Mechanisms</title><page><question id="_u3_m2_transmit_dopamine_DIGTq1"><body>The chemical transmitter dopamine is released from a vesicle within a neuron when the vesicle fuses with the cell membrane and dumps the chemical into the extracellular space. Which type of transport mechanism is most representative of this process?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="A">diffusion</choice><choice value="B">active transport</choice><choice value="C">exocytosis</choice><choice value="D">endocytosis</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i96a5e6f3c7c44d9b929cdcbdbb591310"><skillref idref="levels_membrane_active2_SKILL" /><skillref idref="levels_cell_number_mitosis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The membranes of the vesicle and of the cell interact with each other. However, the vesicle itself is not carried across the membrane bilayer. The vesicles fuse with the cell membrane, and release the content of their vesicles.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The membranes of the vesicle and of the cell interact with each other. However, the vesicle itself is not carried across the bilayer; it fuses with the cell membrane and releases its contents into the extracellular fluid. </feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Vesicles release their chemical messages which interact with membrane proteins on the target cell, allowing communication from one neuron to the next.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The membranes of the vesicle and of the cell interact with each other and release the content of their vesicles. Neither the vesicle nor its contents pass through the membrane by diffusion.</feedback></response><hint>The vesicle itself is not transported from the intracellular space to the extracellular space.</hint><hint>The vesicle contains chemicals that are released into the extracellular space.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
