<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="inline_m3_anaphase_function_DIGT"><title>Mitosis Anaphase Function</title><page><question id="q1"><body>How are kinetochore and nonkinetochore microtubules defined?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Kinetochore microtubules are attached to chromosomes; nonkinetochore microtubules are not.</choice><choice value="B">Nonkinetochore microtubules are attached to chromosomes; kinetochore microtubules are not.</choice><choice value="C">Kinetochore microtubules are involved in mitosis; nonkinetochore microtubules are involved in meiosis.</choice><choice value="D">Nonkinetochore microtubules are involved in mitosis; kinetochore microtubules are involved in meiosis.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="e536021ba7dc4c4a98f65dbeb03cf984"><skillref idref="levels_cell_number_mitosis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Kinetochore microtubules are attached to the kinetochore proteins on the centromere of the chromosome.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinetochore microtubules are attached to the kinetochore proteins on the centromere of the chromosome.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Both kinetochore and nonkinetochore microtubules are necessary for both processes.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Both kinetochore and nonkinetochore microtubules are necessary for both processes.</feedback></response></part></question></page><page><question id="q2"><body>What are the functions of kinetochore and nonkinetochore microtubules? <em style="italic">(More than one answer is correct.)</em></body><multiple_choice select="multiple" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Kinetochore microtubules move to one pole of the cell; nonkinetochore microtubules move to the other.</choice><choice value="B">Kinetochore microtubules change the shape of the cell; nonkinetochore microtubules help chromosomes move.</choice><choice value="C">Kinetochore microtubules are involved in mitosis; nonkinetochore microtubules are involved in meiosis.</choice><choice value="D">Kinetochore microtubules help chromosomes move; nonkinetochore microtubules change the shape of the cell.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="ce118f0eb5c9441c8e8d1599370e1651"><skillref idref="levels_cell_number_mitosis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinetochore microtubules are broken down to move chromosomes to the opposite poles; nonkinetochore microtubules are elongated, which elongates the cell.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinetochore microtubules are broken down to move chromosomes to the opposite poles; nonkinetochore microtubules are elongated, which elongates the cell.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Kinetochore microtubules are broken down to move chromosomes to the opposite poles; nonkinetochore microtubules are elongated, which elongates the cell.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Kinetochore microtubules are broken down to move chromosomes to the opposite poles; nonkinetochore microtubules are elongated, which elongates the cell.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
