<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="levels_membrane_active_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page id="b837b387d2c1421c8c0de06b348c4538"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="da511e4d7ece43eab71cd64b1360cc33">Which of the following is <em style="bold">not</em> true of active transport processes?</p></body><multiple_choice id="d34f5c4046d3414f92fef45a1983c23f" labels="false" select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">It requires a protein carrier and enzymes.</choice><choice value="B">It moves substances across membranes with their concentration gradients (downhill).</choice><choice value="C">One example is the N+/K+ pump and active transport moves K+ into the cell.</choice><choice value="D">None of the above are true of active transport processes.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="a8cc39ce62d143958153255b19b0a143"><skillref idref="levels_membrane_active_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="acea7a76dc2bb4a968380cf924f7c7827">Incorrect. It does require a protein carrier and enzymes but also requires ATP. Remember it is active transport so it is an active not a passive process.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa5bf3545311c412a932013fca0ecdebd">Correct. Passive processes move molecules downhill, but active processes require energy to move the molecules. It takes energy to move an object uphill or against its concentration gradient.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af0a489eb3d6f4fa281b95dbb50c56d6c">Incorrect. It is true that the Na+/K+ pump is an example of active transport and K+ is moved against its concentration gradient and pumped back into the cell it escaped from.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa2ad821b924a48b5ae2ea2532a07758d">Incorrect. Active transport requires 3 things: protein carriers, enzymes, and ATP and moves molecules against their gradients or uphill. In the cell this means it moves K+ from an area of low to high or pumps it back into the cell it escaped from.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="af3a01f9545c7474d88f4a9a017d1efed">Active transport of the Na+/K+ pump requires energy and 2 other components to work properly.</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
