<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="levels_membrane_osmosis_digt2"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Nemo is a clownfish and clownfish live in the ocean. The salinity of the Nemo’s ocean environment averages around 3.5%. What would happen to Nemo if he became lost and ended up in a fresh water lake?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">Nemo would die because his cells would lose water and he would dehydrate quickly.</choice><choice value="B">Nemo would swell and could pop if he doesn’t get out of there.</choice><choice value="C">Nemo would be fine, there wouldn’t be any water movement.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i6b8145aa60804f45b58243e0a800ea1e"><skillref idref="levels_membrane_osmosis_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Remember Nemo is moving from a salty environment into a low salt environment.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Poor Nemo his body cells are used to the higher salinity and are hypertonic to his fresh water environment.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Water must follow osmotic gradients and there is a gradient between Nemo’scells and the fresh water lake.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what Nemo’s natural habitat is and how his body has adapted to it.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which way does water move when individual is dehydrated. A patient has had a GI bug for 2 days and has complained of vomiting and diarrhea. You are very concerned about dehydration and realize that the patient is actually severly dehydrated. Which type of fluid (water) shifts are occurring in the patient&apos;s tissue cells?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">Water is entering the patient’s cells from the blood.</choice><choice value="B">Water is being pulled out the patient’s cells into the blood.</choice><choice value="C">Dehydration does not affect water movement in or out of cells.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i95539977359b42e0b171141c46b12843"><skillref idref="levels_membrane_osmosis_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The patient has lost water due to the GI bug and therefore the blood is less dilute – contains less water.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The water loss from the patient has created hypertonic blood which pulls water from the cells (and interstitial fluid).</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Water will move – think about the patient’s blood, is it too dilute or too concentrated?</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>If trying to reduce edema what type of IV would be given? Another patient presents with edema due to an acute hepatitis infection. In order to clear the excess fluid what type of IV would you give? Note edema is an increase in water in the interstitial (extracellular fluid) that bathes cells.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">Isotonic</choice><choice value="B">Hypertonic</choice><choice value="C">Hypotonic</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i5b406f789a67428aad092f7b585b68df"><skillref idref="levels_membrane_osmosis_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An isotonic IV solution would maintain the current conditions, not remove the excess water.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hypertonic IV would pull water into the blood from the interstitial space to help clear the edema. This excess water will travel via the blood to the kidneys where it can be excreted as urine.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This could kill your patient! Hypotonic IV solutions will increase water loss from the blood into the interstitial space and cells.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
