<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<!--Created by OLI Author v3.0-->
<assessment id="levels_chem_protein_lbd">
    <title>Protein structure and function</title>
    <page id="page_0">
        <question id="levels_chem_protein_lbd_0">
            <!--LO:levels_chem_protein-->
            <body>If a protein has a quaternary structure, that means it:</body>
            <multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true">
                <choice value="A">Uses all 20 amino acids in its composition</choice>
                <choice value="B">Is most likely coded for by multiple genes</choice>
                <choice value="C">Is a small protein</choice>
                <choice value="D">Has enzymatic activity</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part id="qpart_0">
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Although it is likely that a protein will contain most or all of the amino acids, it is not a necessity.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Quaternary structure indicates multiple amino acid chains combining into a single, larger protein. Each amino acid chain is typically coded by a separate gene. For example, hemoglobin is made of alpha chains and beta chains, which are coded by separate genes.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. In fact, more proteins with quaternary structure are large, although this is not a necessity.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Many proteins with quaternary structure are not enzymes, but function as transport proteins, etc.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>Quaternary means “fourth in rank order” and indicates the most complex version of proteins.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="levels_chem_protein_lbd_1">
            <!--LO:levels_chem_protein_function-->
            <body>Different cell types express different types and concentrations of proteins. You would expect a cell common to connective tissues like ligaments and tendons to produce an abundance of proteins with which of the following functions?</body>
            <multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true">
                <choice value="A">Immune</choice>
                <choice value="B">Enzymatic</choice>
                <choice value="C">Structural</choice>
                <choice value="D">Cell signaling</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part id="qpart_1">
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Some connective tissue does contain an abundance of immune cells the produce immune proteins, but that would not be the case for tendons or ligaments.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Although all cells produce enzymatic proteins, you would not expect a connective tissue cell in ligaments and tendons to produce more of these than the typical cell.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Tendons and ligaments are structural connective tissues. The mast cells of these tissues produce and secrete many structural proteins that maintain the strength of these tissues.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Although all cells produce some proteins that are involved in cell signaling, you would not expect a connective tissue cell in ligaments and tendons to produce more of these than the typical cell.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>Ligaments connect bone to bone and tendons connect muscle to bone to maintain structural support.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>