<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="water_1"><title>Water Properties</title><page><question id="water_1_properties"><body><p>The polar character of water that results in its ability to form extensive hydrogen bonding networks gives rise to several properties of water that are important to sustaining life. The following is a list of a few of these properties. </p><p><em>Explain why each of these properties is important to sustaining life.</em></p><p>1. Water has a high surface tension.</p><p>2. Ice is less dense than water.</p><p>3. High heat is required for vaporization of water (a large amount of heat is required to convert liquid water to a gas).</p><p>4. Water has a high specific heat capacity (a large amount of heat is required to raise the temperature of one gram of water one degree Celsius).</p><p>5. Water has a high dielectric constant (a measure of the polarity of the polar covalent bond).</p></body><short_answer id="water_1_properties" /><part id="i3397ee8274f34fae84afa9d0428c52b2"><skillref idref="levels_chem_water_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="levels_chem_water_properties_SKILL" /><response input="water_1_properties" match="*" score="1" /><hint>You may want to think about what would happen if a certain property were different. </hint><hint>Make sure you write an explanation for each of the properties.</hint><explanation><p>Water&apos;s high surface tension allows it to enter small structures (capillary action), allowing water to be transported in plants.</p><p>If ice were more dense, lakes would freeze from the bottom up, never completely thawing in the summer.</p><p>The high heat required for vaporization of water allows an organism to cool via evaporation of sweat. It also prevents the body from losing too much water due to evaporation (sweating) when you run a fever or are in a hot climate.</p><p>Water&apos;s high specific heat capacity means that heat produced by biochemical reactions within an organism doesn’t raise the temperature of the organism.</p><p>The high dielectric constant of water reduces ionic attraction, allowing salts to dissolve.</p></explanation></part></question></page></assessment>
