<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_review_synthesis_06">
   <head>
      <title>Integration of Systems </title>
      <objref idref="ident_examples_system_integration_LO"/>
      <objref idref="predict_dysfunction_across_systems_LO"/>
      
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>Throughout the course, we considered organ systems as separate systems. However, since the body functions as a single unit, the physiology of organ systems cannot truly be understood in isolation of other systems. Here, we will consider pathological conditions which impact multiple organ systems. We will also highlight how a thorough knowledge of physiology will allow a proper diagnosis of a disease of one organ system caused by another.</p>
    <example>
       <title>Diabeties</title>
          <p>A podiatrist sees unhealed sores on a patient's feet. He inquires if the patient has noticed any problems with vision in the past few months. When the patient says that his eyes have been bad, the podiatrist refers the patient to an endocrine specialist to be checked for diabetes. </p>      
       <wb:inline idref="ident_examples_system_integration_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
    </example>
      <example>
         <title>Lymphatic: Splenic Sequestration Crisis</title>
         <p>One of the main functions of the sinuses of the spleen is to break open senescent (old) red blood cells for processing. In indiviudals with severe sickle cell anemia, the spleen can be affected and vessels become occluded.  Splenic sequestration crises are painful enlargements of the spleen, which causes nausea and abdomen bloating. This condition can cause circulatory failure and be fatal if not treated.</p>
         <wb:inline idref="predict_dysfunction_across_systems_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
      </example>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
