<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_review_synthesis_03">
   <head>
      <title>Levels of Organization: Sickle Cell and Obesity</title>
      <objref idref="predict_disfunction_across_scales_LO"/>
   </head>
   <body>
      <example>
         <title>Sickle Cell's Gene Mutation Across Length Scales</title>
      <p>In sickle cell anemia, there is a mutation in gene for the β-globin protein, which is part of hemoglobin. The altered structure of β-globin causes an aggregation of the proteins. When these proteins aggregate, they distort the shape of the red blood cell and reduces red blood cell elasticity. The abnormal cells get stuck in capillaries, reducing blood flow to tissues and organs. Organ damage may result, permanently affecting body function. Thus, a seemingly tiny error in DNA causes significant changes in the body’s systems at higher levels. </p>
     
      <wb:inline idref="predict_disfunction_across_scales_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
          <param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/predict_disfunction_across_scales_LBD1-layout.xml</param>
      </wb:inline>
      </example>
      <example>
         <title>Obesity Followed Through the Levels of Organization</title>
         <p>Obesity is caused by excessive food intake and reduced physical activity. Genetics and cultural surroundings can also play a part. Let’s examine how levels of organization all have contributing factors on obesity:</p>
         <p>Increased carbohydrates and lipid intake: at the molecular level, excessive food intake can lead to accumulation of fat and altered body chemistry.</p>
         <wb:inline idref="predict_disfunction_across_scales_LBD2" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
         <p>Decreased activity leads to reduced muscle mass: at the cellular and tissue level the inactivity of obesity is associated with decreased activity, muscle tone and muscle mass. </p>
         <wb:inline idref="predict_disfunction_across_scales_LBD3" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
         <p>Obesity is also strongly correlated with the local population demographics.</p>
         <wb:inline idref="predict_disfunction_across_scales_LBD4" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
      </example>
    
   </body>
</workbook_page>
