<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_review_synthesis_01"><head><title>Structure and Function</title><objref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_LO" /><objref idref="predict_disfunction_structure_LO" /></head><body><p id="b077e45d14e242d4bf8086c10159c39e">As you have seen, function relies completely upon structure and altered structure can greatly affect function. The following exercises take a look at one way this relationship plays out in the Urinary system. </p><example id="e650d17da32c4be691b566f297eb6b80"><title>The Bladder</title><p id="cbca15714a0e459e97b34806daeee44d">Within the urinary system, recall that the bladder is the organ that stores urine until elimination by urination. Since urination production is continuous and elimination occurs less frequently, the amount stored changes over time. We will examine how the anatomical structure of the bladder allows its physiological function.</p><p id="cefc60634fa64a4b8f437796a8dc37d4">To permit large volume changes, the lining of the urinary bladder has rugae, similar to the lining of the digestive system. </p><image id="f22d70a98feb417e8b16c3c819bff7b2" src="../webcontent/urinary.jpg" alt="diagram of the male and female urinary system." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="de79570bbfbc4b11a44b4230d634c5c9">The detrusor muscle in the urinary bladder contains multiple layers of smooth muscle cells that align in different directions. These muscles are aligned in the long axis, as well as around the bladder as circles and as spirals. These smooth muscles are able to stretch and signal that voiding is necessary.</p><wb:inline idref="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD2" purpose="learnbydoing" /></example><example id="fb0ade6e89684a6fbeec0f03fd2d6a45"><title>Layers of the Epidermis</title><p id="c5d7f127cbde416c9c73842d4a3cf81b">There are multiple layers of cells in the epidermis of the integumentary system. The function of the collective structural layers is to provide a continuous barrier that also renews. Within the epidermis, each distinct layer has different structures and functions related to their structure. </p><image id="df93f3bcde944b0cbe9d3308f7f70df0" src="../webcontent/IU_M2_7.jpg" alt="diagram detailing all the layers of the epidermis of the inegumentary system." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD3" purpose="learnbydoing" /></example><example id="bb3c7302f9f944b3af27f2abd1ff8261"><title>Gastric Bypass</title><p id="fc4b80e9185a43639fc954f66b4eb82f">Obesity is usually treated with altered lifestyle changes including altered diet and increased exercise. Occasionally, weight loss medication is used to supplement lifestyle changes. However, in severe cases, altering the stomach’s structure can also be used to reduce food intake. Two major types of surgery include adjustable gastric band (Lap-Band) and gastric bypass.</p><p id="a73868b672c246bcb796c0afaac31390">Gastric banding physically restricts the stomach from expanding. Without the band, an adult’s stomach can expand from 50 mL to hold about 1 liter of food, and can distend to hold as much as 4 liters. There are numerous structures which allow this distension function.</p><wb:inline idref="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD4" purpose="learnbydoing" /><image id="e48502b199424c43a21598d03a8a47fc" src="../webcontent/stomach.jpg" alt="diagram of stomach" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="339" width="400"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f67af0fec24a486b913ba63751004436">Less food can fit into a stomach with a gastric band, and individuals feel full sooner. With gastric bypass surgery, stapling the stomach reduces stomach volume. Also, a portion of the small intestine is bypassed.</p><wb:inline idref="predict_disfunction_structure_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /></example><example id="b37f5603a8e44f5baed212bc9aa04fe2"><title>Sickle Cell: Altered Red Blood Cell Shape</title><p id="be60944b188b4982a8c5c5e6f029471b">In sickle cell anemia, low oxygen conditions lead to an altered red blood cell shape and reduced elasticity. Stiffer red blood cells can lead to vessel occlusion and ultimately tissue damage. </p><wb:inline idref="ident_examp_sf_across_LBD5" purpose="learnbydoing" /></example></body></workbook_page>
