<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_review_synthesis_04"><head><title>Homeostasis Considerations with Sickle Cell Anemia</title><objref idref="complete_loops_LO" /><objref idref="predict_dysfunction_homeo_LO" /></head><body><section id="db04f3fd84fd41ec90895139c428c770"><title>Red Blood Cells in Sickle Cell Anemia</title><body><p id="a8e11ab4695649cfb701c9c42c62a2dc">Sickle cell anemia can lead to reduced oxygen delivery to tissues. Also, reduced red blood cell elasticity can lead to cell rupture and anemia. Anaemia is measured by a reduction in iron. It can be caused by iron deficiency, insufficient red cell production or red blood cell dysfunction; in this case dysfunction. When red cells are sickled, they only have a lifespan of 10-20 days whereas normal red blood cells have a lifespan of &gt;100 days.</p><wb:inline idref="predict_dysfunction_homeo_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="b77f0c153f51410cbbf34088617c3d36">If red blood cells are not able to be replenished and the patient becomes anemic then different regions of the body can be deprived of oxygen. The effects of anemia can be compounded by obstruction of blood vessels by sickled cells. When tissues do not have sufficient oxygen, cells die by apoptosis or necrosis. Apoptosis is programmed death, which is a natural part of remodeling: when tissues are remodeled cells invade or proliferate (divide) to perform a function and they are done the apoptose. This type of cell death does not cause disruption to the cells surrounding the dying cell. Necrosis on the other hand triggers uncontrolled release of cell products into intracellular space which in turn initiates an inflammatory response in the surrounding tissue.</p><wb:inline idref="predict_dysfunction_homeo_LBD2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="complete_loops_LBD1" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/complete_loops_LBD1_layout.xml</param></wb:inline></body></section></body></workbook_page>
