<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_lab_obesity"><head><title>Obesity Lab</title></head><body><p id="d88e85dd1b0144618ec959f37d24d79f">Now, let&apos;s look at the condition of obesity in more depth. Below is an activity that provides several sections of content and questions that will help you recall, organize and apply what you have learned in this course to the comprehensive condition of obesity. Explore the following activity to learn how obesity affects each system of the body. </p><p id="d2ed2772bbbf42d8b97268eb449d1ca2">The activity consists of three sections.</p><ul id="f00e7243c39b456ba0150b70138ba8cd"><li><p id="aadea8860ccda4e999d9e61e0b105bc6d">The top left panel contains an image with hotspots. Use this for navigation. Each hotspot connects to a section of unique material and activities.</p></li><li><p id="ad80b9a1c42e04e4bb18396ab3fccb668">The top right panel changes each time you choose a new section to work through. Look to this panel for the information you will need to solve the problems and questions that also appear for that section.</p></li><li><p id="af96ec63252c541d294848a8371d70ec3">The bottom panel changes each time you choose a new section as well. You will find activities and questions here that are unique to that section.</p></li></ul><p id="f4a14f3b7d8b40fa98c9e78c6d6655be">Be sure to click on each hotspot to ensure you complete all of the questions within this activity. </p><multipanel id="multiID" purpose="learnbydoing"><title>Effects of Obesity on the Human Body</title><image_hotspot id="obesity_fig" src="../webcontent/obesity-hotspot2.png" alt="" width="274" height="330"><hotspot shape="circle" coords="68,105,9" title="skin imbalance" panel_ref="two" activity_ref="2" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="104,70,9" title="sleep apnea and shallow breathing" panel_ref="three" activity_ref="3" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="102,94,9" title="acid reflux" panel_ref="four" activity_ref="4" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="102,125,9" title="heart strain" panel_ref="six" activity_ref="5" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="132,114,9" title="breast and other cancers" panel_ref="seven" activity_ref="6" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="108,191,9" title="urinary incontinence" panel_ref="twelve" activity_ref="7" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="119,232,9" title="joint strain" panel_ref="thirteen" activity_ref="8" /><hotspot shape="circle" coords="123,309,10" title="poor circulation" panel_ref="fourteen" activity_ref="9" /></image_hotspot><panels intro_panel_ref="ex_intropanel"><panel id="ex_intropanel" title="Obesity Introduction"><p id="f191312e03e0421c841ce27e8ccb64e9">A woman comes for her annual check-up and is told that she is obese. Her physician strongly urges her to lose weight as obesity is very bad for her overall health.</p><p id="a132a49ee6b946fea77c577653b0613d">Obesity is a condition that affects much of the body - both in ways we can and cannot see.</p><p id="c1ef3e954c3645c28b23193eb3c5fb9d"><em style="italic">Directions:</em> Explore common changes and results that come from obesity by clicking on hotspots found on the line drawing in the left panel. Clicking the questions tab on your right will bring up questions about how this condition is related to other conditions.</p></panel><panel id="two" title="Skin Imbalance"><p id="bb07b6ebcb5b46508cd8e46c12106eb4">Numerous complications in the integumentary system can arise as a result of obesity. For example, obesity can result in insulin resistance, which subsequently leads to larger concentrations of insulin circulating in the bloodstream. Excess insulin impacts the skin causing abnormal growth, referred to as as hyperplasia.The hyperplasia can lead to a disease known as acanthosis nigricans, which presents itself as brown or black hyperpigmentation of the skin. </p><p id="ad3347ba15e04bea8b1ae80467b30ce4">Increased strain on leg veins due to obesity can result in fluid retention and swelling (edema), superficial capillary rupture, and ulcers. The increased weight can also result in corns and calluses on the feet. Most of these conditions can be resolved weight loss. </p></panel><panel id="three" title="Sleep Apnea and Shallow Breathing"><p id="d13f69f2682240b5b19a5ec07437d697">Obesity can hinder respiratory function. With fat accumulation around the waste, the diaphragm muscle becomes distended. The diaphragm is the primary inspiratory muscle for respiration. If the diaphragm&apos;s function is impeded, muscles in the upper chest and throat have more of the mechanical burden for breath. </p><image id="e532c37db4f744c9979f847a79245ae8" src="../webcontent/diaphram.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af59a19908cc543fabd6cb6d5caa74d55"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="e579f94818a044a7b394e10a7b41a619">Sleep apnea is a sleep disorder that presents itself with abnormal pauses in breathing (known as apneas) that can last anywhere from several seconds to a minute. The most common form of sleep apnea, <term>obstructive sleep apnea</term>, can be caused or exacerbated by obesity. The low muscle-tone and excessive amount of soft tissue in the throat area can cause breathing to be obstructed. This subsequently results in temporary episodes of an inability to breath. </p></panel><panel id="four" title="Acid Reflux"><p id="fd3f85cf58e944d293c0df859ea74ab7">Strong acids and enzymes (such as HCl and pepsin, respectively) are generated by the stomach to promote food digestion. The esophagus is protected by this gastric juice by the lower esophageal sphincter, which holds shut the barrier between the bottom of the esophagus and the top of the stomach. When stomach acid manages to make its way through a faulty lower esophageal sphincter and into the esophagus, it results in a condition known as <term>acid reflux</term>. This phenomenon is colloquially known as heartburn because of the burning sensation felt in the general area where the heart is located. </p><image id="e4e3ec81f1214d56804297f742a051af" src="../webcontent/HeartburnBasics_WhatCausesHeartburn.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ac36c1e8a7091435b8c696099c537d8b2"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ce69c0e2c5404d8e98e267cbeba1637b">An adult stomach is designed to expand to allow the intake of food. However, when a person habitually takes in large meals, the stomach grows. In addition to stomach distension, the peritoneal cavity has can gain increased visceral fat. This generally occurs as a result of excess caloric intake. </p><image id="a3fab8e6b56c4d02944ae56ffa876c74" src="../webcontent/visceral-fat-diagram1.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ae791ecd35c2e4f948ef987e48155f6bf"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel><panel id="six" title="Heart Strain"><p id="ff7923693c814d3e8a6b41408505c74d">Obesity results in an increase in body fat and subsequently body mass. This forces the heart to work harder and exert greater force when pumping blood throughout the body. The increase in body fat also results in greater levels of cholesterol in the blood vessels. Blood vessel constriction further increases the strain on the heart. As the heart is forced to work harder and harder, it requires greater quantities of oxygen. Heart failure can result when lack of oxygen results in death of cardiac muscle. This is typically a result of impeded blood flow due to fat-clogged blood vessels. </p><image id="e097986c82ae45978f7b86cd9c838ecb" src="../webcontent/reduced_flow.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="acf92d646b57646af8f401c8138f4ed5d"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel><panel id="seven" title="Breast and/or Other Cancers. . ."><p id="cc3af4c71aae41168bfbea9cdd0c4ce3">Obesity has been found to be correlated with an increased risk of breast cancer. This is speculated to be a result of increased levels of estrogen in obese women. After menopause, the ovaries stop producing hormones, which puts the burden of estrogen production on fat tissue. Since obese women have greater amounts of fat tissue, their estrogen levels are higher. This subsequently results in more rapid growth of estrogen-responsive breast tumors.</p><p id="d3b115ec8eb64e14982e15a57c7dd03a">Obesity is also associated with an increased risk of cancer in the esophagus, pancreas, kidneys, thyroid, gallbladder, endometrium, colon and rectum.</p></panel><panel id="twelve" title="Urinary Incontinence"><p id="b47ab02ff32a4193bf9fe9056748bb8d">Urinary incontinence is the inability to control urine flow. Obesity often presents itself with urinary incontinence because of increased weight in the midsection. This causes extra pressure that makes it more likely that the bladder will leak. This results in stress incontinence, or the tendency for the bladder to leak when performing everyday actions such as laughing or coughing. Obesity is also strongly correlated with diabetes, which can cause damage to the nerves that control bladder muscles. </p></panel><panel id="thirteen" title="Joint Strain"><p id="f5833cbd539c490b98f8211bd61f9a66">Joints are found at the location where two or more bones make contact. Their general purpose is to allow movement, and they also serve to provide mechanical support. Joints essentially carry the weight of our bodies. So, the more weight they are forced to carry, the greater the strain it places on the joints. Small changes in weight can have substantial effects on joint forces in the hips and knees. Research has shown that obese individuals are more likely to develop arthritis.</p></panel><panel id="fourteen" title="Poor Circulation"><p id="eddf834f20624b839dc5345e729c6d6d">Calf muscles rely on a constant supply of fresh blood to the muscle tissues. In a healthy individual, this blood is returned back up to the body against gravity via a pumping system formed by the leg muscles. The main driving force for this pumping system is supplied by the calf muscles as they contract, which takes pressure off the veins, allowing blood to return to the upper body. As blood passes through these veins, one way valves found in the veins shut to prevent blood from returning to the feet. This used blood is subsequently displaced by the same volume of fresh blood. </p><p id="ce327af782d64373b34950dd3b5ec0f0">Because obese individuals tend to lead a life of little movement and activity, the ability of their legs to contribute to circulation decreases substantially. This results in a disruption of the aforementioned cycle, and used blood remains in the lower legs. This causes water from lymph fluid to separate from the blood and fill spaces in tissues, resulting in edema. </p><image id="e7530d692b3a4fc7ba82d5b762fc753c" src="../webcontent/edema.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ac5bfaba1f1d544da860eea57450bc846"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></panel></panels><wb:inline idref="obesity_inline-1" purpose="learnbydoing" /></multipanel></body></workbook_page>
