<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Signaling via G-Protein" >
    <step stepURL="swfs/intro.swf" textURL="text_intro.swf" menustep=" Introduction ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;This animation illustrates how binding of a ligand to its receptor ultimately leads to the production of high levels of cAMP, an important second messenger in the signal transduction pathway.  This process is mediated by a protein called G-Protein.  G-protein is inactive when bound to GDP, but becomes activated by the receptor induced exchange of GDP for GTP.  Many ligand-receptor complexes utilize this method of signal transduction.  The epinephrine receptor is an important example of such a G-coupled receptor.&lt;/html&gt; 
    </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/one.swf"  menustep=" Ligand binding ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The ligand forms a specific complex with its receptor.  The binding of ligand to the receptor causes an allosteric change in the structure of the receptor on the other side of the membrane, inside the cell. This allosteric change produces a binding site for the G-protein/GDP complex.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/two.swf"  menustep=" Ligand + R + G complex ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The G-protein/GDP complex binds to the intra-celluar part of the receptor-ligand complex.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/three.swf" menustep=" GTP/GDP exchange  ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The interaction of the G-protein/GDP complex with the receptor causes a conformational change in the G-protein/GDP complex. This change results in the exchange of GTP for GDP. The G-protein/GTP complex is the active form of the G-protein.   &lt;/html&gt; </text> 
</step>  
    <step stepURL="swfs/four.swf"  menustep="  Dissociation ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The active G-protein/GTP complex dissociates from the receptor and is now competent to bind to Adenylate cyclase, the enzyme that converts ATP to cAMP.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/five.swf"  menustep="  Binding to AC ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The active G-protein/GTP complex dissociates from the receptor and is now competent to bind to Adenylate cyclase, the enzyme that converts ATP to cAMP.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/six.swf" menustep="  Generation of cAMPs ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The G-protein/GTP complex binds to adenylate cyclase.  In doing so it causes an allosteric change in Adenylate cyclase to produce an active enzyme.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/seven.swf"  menustep="  Hydrolysis of GTP ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Eventually, the GTP bound to the G-protein hydrolyzes to GDP.  This event results a change in the structure of the G-protein, causing it to dissociate from adenylate cyclase.  Adenylate cyclase returns to its inactive form, ceasing to produce cAMP.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/eight.swf"  menustep="  Ligand dissociation ">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;The ligand-receptor complex is still competent to activate G-protein/GDP by exchanging the bound GDP with GTP.  The signaling process does not terminate until the ligand leaves the receptor, causing the receptor to return to its original state.   &lt;/html&gt; </text>
</step>
</TUTORIAL>