<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_8.css"?>
<workbook_page id="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_msw">
	<head>
		<title>Scales of Measurement / Types of Variables</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>In the previous section, a simple distinction was made between quantitative and
			categorical variables. However, there is a more precise method of categorizing
			variables: it is called <em style="bold">scale of measurement</em>. The four different
			scales of measurement, from least to most precise, are</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Nominal</li>
			<li>Ordinal</li>
			<li>Interval</li>
			<li>Ratio</li>
		</ul>
		<p>In the following walkthrough video and sections, each one of these types of variables is described with a
			comparison of their properties.</p>
		
	
		<youtube src="dbI8EDP8IxE"/>
		<!-- <iframe
			src="../../webcontent/scale_measurement/index.htm"
			height="600" width="900"/> -->
	

		
		
		<section>
			
			<title>Nominal Scale of Measurement</title>
			<body>
				<p>The <em style="bold">nominal scale of measurement</em> is a qualitative measure that uses
					discrete categories to describe a characteristic of the research participants. For each
					participant, the researcher determines the presence, absence, and type of the attribute.
					Nominal scales of measurement may have two categories, such as citizen status
					(citizen/non-citizen), or they can have more than two categories, like religious
					affiliation (e.g., Agnostic, Buddhist, Jewish, Muslim) or marital status (e.g., divorced,
					married, single). Often, as described here, the categories have names; however,
					researchers code them with numbers for use in statistical analyses. These categories
					are not ordered or ranked in any way. </p>
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title></title>
					<body><wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_question1" purpose="learnbydoing"/></body>
				</section>
				
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Ordinal Scale of Measurement</title>
			<body>
				
				<p>An <em style="bold">ordinal scale of measurement</em> rank-orders participants on some
					scale or attribute, but the difference between numbers does not convey fixed or equal
					differences. Thus, with ordinal data, we know that a one-unit increase in an ordinal
					scales represents “more,” but we don’t know how much more. For example, a group of
					participants can be rank-ordered from least to most politically active. We know that a
					person who is ranked as 5 is more politically active than a person who is ranked as 4,
					but not how much more politically active. The value of the variable is used to order
					participants according to the strength/presence of the attribute and not to calculate
					differences between participants.</p>
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title></title>
					<body>	<wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_question2" purpose="learnbydoing"/></body>
				</section>
				
				
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Interval Scale of Measurement</title>
			<body>
				
				
				<p>The <em style="bold">interval scale of measurement </em>takes numerical form, and the
					distance between pairs of consecutive numbers is assumed to be equal. However, interval
					variables do not have a meaningful zero point; thus, a zero does not mean the absence of
					the attribute, but rather it is a particular (but arbitrary) point on the scale. A good
					example of an interval measure is temperature in the Fahrenheit scale: a temperature of zero degrees Fahrenheit is still a
					temperature, not the absence of temperature. In education, measures like achievement,
					motivation, and self-concept are considered interval measures; a zero on a measure of
					such variables does not mean the absence of the characteristic in the participant. </p>
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title></title>
					<body><wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_question3" purpose="learnbydoing"/></body>
				</section>
				
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Ratio Scale of Measurement</title>
			<body>
				
				
				<p>The <em style="bold">ratio scale of measurement </em>is similar to the interval scale. As
					with the interval scale, a number is assigned to a subject that represents the amount of
					the attribute that the subject has and the difference between consecutive numbers is
					assumed to be equal. The main difference between interval and ratio measurements has
					to do with how we interpret a value of zero. For <em style="italic">ratio</em> measures,
					the zero <em style="italic">is</em> meaningful and tell us that the attribute is not
					present in the participant. Examples of ratio measures include a participant’s number of
					children, number of AP courses taken, or cumulative college credits: for each of these
					variables, a score of zero represents that the participant has none of the
					attribute.</p>
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title></title>
					<body><wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_question4" purpose="learnbydoing"/></body>
				</section>
				
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<p>The next activity will help you to see whether you understand the different scales of
			measurement.</p>
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title>Did I Get This?</title>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_digt1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_digt2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_digt3" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="type_of_var_scales_of_measurement_digt4" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
