<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<!--Created by OLI Author v2.0-->
<assessment id="urinary_track_infection">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
        <question id="uti">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>Why are women for likely to have a urinary tract infection when compared to
                men?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">Women and men are have an equal chance of having a UTI.</choice>
                <choice value="B">Women’s urethras are shorter than those of men; the urethra's
                    external opening in women is closer to the anus than it is in men.</choice>
                <choice value="C">Women’s urethras are longer than those of men; the urethra's
                    external opening in women is closer to the anus than it is in men.</choice>
                <choice value="D">Women’s urethras are shorter than those of men; the urethra's
                    external opening in men is closer to the anus than it is in men.</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Women are more likely than men to have a UTI.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are
                        shorter than those of men. In addition, external opening of the urethra in
                        women is closer to the anus than it is in men.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are
                        actually shorter than those of men. In addition, external opening of the
                        urethra in women is closer to the anus than it is in men.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Women are predisposed to UTIs because their urethras are
                        shorter than those of men. However, external opening of the urethra in women
                        is closer to the anus than it is in men.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>A reason why a specific gender is less likely to have a UTI has to do with
                    distance.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
