<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_collecting_ducts"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="primary_function_collecting_ducts"><body>The primary function of the collecting ducts, located in the kidneys, is to:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Filter plasma, reabsorb what the body would like to keep, and excrete the rest.</choice><choice value="B">Collect any substance not reabsorbed along the nephrons.</choice><choice value="C">Expand the surface area that available for reabsorbing water and solutes.</choice><choice value="D">Facilitate the process of urine traveling through the smooth muscles, otherwise known as parasitosis.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="primary_function_collecting_ducts_p1"><skillref idref="identify_substances_not_reabsorbed_nephrons" /><skillref idref="identify_kidneys" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The primary role of the nephrons is to filter plasma, reabsorb what the body would like to keep, and excrete the rest. The primary function of the collecting ducts, located in the kidneys, is to collect any substance not reabsorbed along the nephrons.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The primary function of the collecting ducts, located in the kidneys, is to collect any substance not reabsorbed along the nephrons.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Microvilli form a brush border and greatly expand the surface area available for reabsorbing water and solutes. The primary function of the collecting ducts, located in the kidneys, is to collect any substance not reabsorbed along the nephrons.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Circular contraction occurs through the smooth muscle, is otherwise known as parasitosis, and is responsible for urine traveling to the bladder. The primary function of the collecting ducts, located in the kidneys, is to collect any substance not reabsorbed along the nephrons.</feedback></response><hint>What do “ducts” do? Filter, collect, expand or facilitate?</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
