<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_histology_renal_tubule_collecting_duct"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="cuboidal_epithelial_cells"><body>When looking at the histology of the renal tubule and collecting ducts, what is a common component between the proximal convoluted tubule, thick ascending limb, most of the distal convoluted tubule, collecting duct, and last part of distal convoluted tubule?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">They all contain simple cuboidal epithelial cells.</choice><choice value="B">They all have conspicuous brush borders of microvilli.</choice><choice value="C">They all contain simple squamous epithelial cells.</choice><choice value="D">They all contain intercalated cells</choice></multiple_choice><part id="cuboidal_epithelial_cells_p1"><skillref idref="recognize_importance_ascending_limbs_Henle" /><skillref idref="identify_role_proximal_convoluted_tubule" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The proximal convoluted tubule, thick ascending limb, most of the distal convoluted tubule, collecting duct, and last part of distal convoluted tubule all contain simple cuboidal epithelial cells.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Proximal convoluted tubule has conspicuous brush borders of microvilli.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Descending limb and thin ascending limb contain simple squamous epithelial cells.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Collecting duct and last part of distal convoluted tubule contain intercalated cells.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="unique_proximal_tubule"><body>In the histology of the renal tubule and collecting duct areas, what is unique about the proximal convoluted tubule?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The proximal convoluted tubule is the only area that contains simple cuboidal epithelial cells.</choice><choice value="B">The proximal convoluted tubule is the only area that contains a conspicuous brush border of microvilli.</choice><choice value="C">The proximal convoluted tubule is the only area that contains simple squamous epithelial cells.</choice><choice value="D">The proximal convoluted tubule is the only area that contains intercalated cells.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="unique_proximal_tubule_p1"><skillref idref="recognize_importance_ascending_limbs_Henle" /><skillref idref="identify_role_proximal_convoluted_tubule" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The proximal convoluted tubule, thick ascending limb, most of the distal convoluted tubule, collecting duct, and last part of distal convoluted tubule all contain simple cuboidal epithelial cells.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Proximal convoluted tubule has conspicuous brush borders of microvilli.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Descending limb and thin ascending limb contain simple squamous epithelial cells.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Collecting duct and last part of distal convoluted tubule contain intercalated cells.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
