<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_m04_behavior_of_mean2">
    <head>
        <title>Behavior of Sample Mean (2 of 3)</title>
        <objref idref="apply_sampling_distribution_of_sample_mean"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The results we got in our simulations are not surprising. Advanced probability theory
            confirms that by asserting the following:</p>
        <section>
            <title>The Sampling Distribution of the Sample Mean</title>
            <body>
                <p>If repeated random samples of a given size n are taken from a population of
                    values for a quantitative variable, where the population mean is <m:math
                        overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mi>μ</m:mi>
                    </m:math> and the population standard deviation is <m:math overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mi>σ</m:mi>
                    </m:math>, then the mean of all sample means (<m:math overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mover accent="true">
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>x</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mo>¯</m:mo>
                        </m:mover>
                    </m:math>) is population mean <m:math overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mi>μ</m:mi>
                    </m:math>. As for the spread of all sample means, theory dictates the behavior
                    much more precisely than saying that there is less spread for larger samples. In
                    fact, the standard deviation of all sample means (<m:math overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mover accent="true">
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>x</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mo>¯</m:mo>
                        </m:mover>
                    </m:math>) is exactly <m:math overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mfrac>
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>σ</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:msqrt>
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:mi>n</m:mi>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                </m:msqrt>
                            </m:mrow>
                        </m:mfrac>
                    </m:math>. Since the square root of sample size n appears in the denominator,
                    the standard deviation does decrease as sample size increases. </p>

                <section purpose="learnbydoing">
                    <title>Learn By Doing</title>
                    <body>
                        <p>The Federal Pell Grant Program provides need-based grants to low-income
                            undergraduate and certain postbaccalaureate students to promote access
                            to postsecondary education. According to the National Postsecondary
                            Student Aid Study conducted by the U.S. Department of Education in 2008,
                            the average Pell grant award for 2007-2008 was $2,600. Assume that the
                            standard deviation in Pell grant awards was $500.</p>
                        <wb:inline idref="u3_m4_mean2_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
                    </body>
                </section>
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m4_mean2_tutor1_1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <p>Let's compare and contrast what we now know about the sampling distributions for
                    sample means and sample proportions. </p>


                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th/>
                        <th/>
                        <th/>
                        <th colspan="3">Sampling Distribution</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Variable</th>
                        <th>Parameter</th>
                        <th>Statistic</th>
                        <th>Center</th>
                        <th>Spread</th>
                        <th>Shape</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Categorical (example: left-handed or not)</td>
                        <td>p = population proportion</td>
                        <td><m:math overflow="scroll">
                                <m:mover accent="true">
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                    <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                                </m:mover>
                            </m:math> = sample proportion</td>
                        <td>p</td>
                        <td><m:math overflow="scroll">
                                <m:msqrt>
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:mfrac>
                                            <m:mrow>
                                                <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                                                <m:mo>(</m:mo>
                                                <m:mn>1</m:mn>
                                                <m:mo>-</m:mo>
                                                <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                                                <m:mo>)</m:mo>
                                            </m:mrow>
                                            <m:mrow>
                                                <m:mi>n</m:mi>
                                            </m:mrow>
                                        </m:mfrac>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                </m:msqrt>
                            </m:math></td>
                        <td>Normal IF np ≥ 10 and n(1 - p) ≥ 10</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Quantitative (example: age)</td>
                        <td>&#956; = population mean, &#963; = population standard deviation</td>
                        <td><m:math overflow="scroll">
                                <m:mover accent="true">
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:mi>x</m:mi>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                    <m:mo>¯</m:mo>
                                </m:mover>
                            </m:math> = sample mean</td>
                        <td>&#956;</td>
                        <td><m:math overflow="scroll">
                                <m:mfrac>
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:mi>σ</m:mi>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:msqrt>
                                            <m:mrow>
                                                <m:mi>n</m:mi>
                                            </m:mrow>
                                        </m:msqrt>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                </m:mfrac>
                            </m:math></td>
                        <td><em>When will the distribution of sample means be approximately normal
                                ?</em></td>
                    </tr>
                </table>



                <p>Now we will investigate the shape of the sampling distribution of sample means.
                    When we were discussing the sampling distribution of sample proportions, we said
                    that this distribution is approximately normal if np ≥ 10 and n(1 - p) ≥ 10. In
                    other words, we had a guideline based on sample size for determining the
                    conditions under which we could use normal probability calculations for sample
                    proportions. </p>
                <p> When will the distribution of sample means be approximately normal? Does this
                    depend on the size of the sample? </p>
                <p> It seems reasonable that a population with a normal distribution will have
                    sample means that are normally distributed even for very small samples. We saw
                    this illustrated in the previous simulation with samples of size 9. </p>
                <p> What happens if the distribution of the variable in the population is heavily
                    skewed? Do sample means have a skewed distribution also? If we take really large
                    samples, will the sample means become more normally distributed? </p>
                <p> In the next simulation, we will investigate these questions. </p>
             
                <youtube src="cyNqdostWzk"></youtube>
                <!--  <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="592" height="552"
                    purpose="simulation">
                    <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/walkthrough4.swf</param>
                    <param name="movieFPS">15</param>
                    <param name="LoggingLibraryPath"
                        >../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
                </flash>-->
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m4_mean2_tutor2" purpose="didigetthis"/>

            </body>
        </section>
        <p> To summarize, the distribution of sample means will be approximately normal as long as
            the sample size is large enough. This discovery is probably the single most important
            result presented in introductory statistics courses. It is stated formally as the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T192936-0500" comment="Make bold to indicate new terminology"?>Central
            Limit Theorem.<?oxy_comment_end?>
        </p>
        <p> We will depend on the Central Limit Theorem again and again in order to do normal
            probability calculations when we use sample means to draw conclusions about a population
            mean. We now know that we can do this even if the population distribution is not normal. </p>
        <p> How large a sample size do we need in order to assume that sample means will be normally
            distributed? Well, it really depends on the population distribution, as we saw in the
            simulation. The general rule of thumb is that samples of size 30 or greater will have a
            fairly normal distribution regardless of the shape of the distribution of the variable
            in the population. </p>
        <p> Comment: For categorical variables, our claim that sample proportions are approximately
            normal for large enough n is actually a special case of the Central Limit Theorem. </p>


    </body>
</workbook_page>
