<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>

<workbook_page id="_u4_m04_behavior_of_proportion1">

    <head>
        <title>Behavior of Sample Proportion (1 of 3)</title>
        <objref idref="apply_sampling_distribution_of_sample_proportion"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>The first step to drawing conclusions about parameters based on the accompanying
            statistics is to understand how sample statistics behave relative to the parameter that
            summarizes the entire population. We begin with the behavior of sample proportion
            relative to population proportion (when the variable of interest is categorical). After
            that, we will explore the behavior of sample mean relative to population mean (when the
            variable of interest is quantitative).</p>
        <section>
            <title>Behavior of Sample Proportion p&#770;
                <!--  <formula><m:math overflow="scroll">
                <m:mover accent="true">
                    <m:mrow>
                        <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                    </m:mrow>
                    <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                </m:mover>
            </m:math></formula> -->
            </title>
            <body>
                <example>
                    <p>Approximately 60% of all part-time college students in the United States are
                        female. (In other words, the population proportion of females among
                        part-time college students is p = .6.) What would you expect to see in terms
                        of the behavior of sample proportion of females (<m:math overflow="scroll">
                            <m:mover accent="true">
                                <m:mrow>
                                    <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                                </m:mrow>
                                <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                            </m:mover>
                        </m:math>) if random samples of size 100 were taken from the population of
                        all part-time college students?</p>
                    <p>As we saw before, due to sampling variability, sample proportion in random
                        samples of size 100 will take numerical values which vary according to the
                        laws of chance: in other words, sample proportion is a<em> random
                            variable</em>. To summarize the behavior of any random variable, we
                        focus on three features of its distribution: the center, the spread, and the
                        shape.</p>
                    <p>Based only on our intuition, we would expect the following:
                        <!--  (<em>Comment</em>:  obviously, we know what to expect, so it's not really
                             fair, but Read along and try to see if the following makes intuitive sense
                        to you.)--></p>
                    <p><em>Center</em>: Some sample proportions will be on the low sidesay, .55 or
                        .58&#8212; while others will be on the high side&#8212; say, .61 or .66. It
                        is reasonable to expect all the sample proportions in repeated random
                        samples to average out to the underlying population proportion, .6. In other
                        words, the mean of the distribution of 
                            <m:math overflow="scroll">
                                <m:mover accent="true">
                                    <m:mrow>
                                        <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                                    </m:mrow>
                                    <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                                </m:mover>
                            </m:math> should be p.</p>
                    <p><em>Spread</em>: For samples of 100, we would expect sample proportions of
                        females not to stray too far from the population proportion .6. Sample
                        proportions lower than .5 or higher than .7 would be rather surprising. On
                        the other hand, if we were only taking samples of size 10, we would not be
                        at all surprised by a sample proportion of females even as low as 4/10 = .4,
                        or as high as 8/10 = .8. Thus, sample size plays a role in the spread of the
                        distribution of sample proportion: there should be less spread for larger
                        samples, more spread for smaller samples.</p>
                    <p><em>Shape</em>: Sample proportions closest to .6 would be most common, and
                        sample proportions far from .6 in either direction would be progressively
                        less likely. In other words, the shape of the distribution of sample
                        proportion should bulge in the middle and taper at the ends: it should be
                        somewhat <em>normal.</em>
                    </p>
                </example>
                <p> </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>The <em>distribution</em> of the values of the sample proportions (<m:math
                        overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mover accent="true">
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                        </m:mover>
                    </m:math>) in repeated <em>samples</em> is called the <em>sampling distribution
                        of </em>
                    <m:math overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mover accent="true">
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                        </m:mover>
                    </m:math>. </p>
                <!--<activity idref="_u4_m4_lbd1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>-->
                <p>The purpose of the next activity is to check whether our intuition about the
                    center, spread and shape of the sampling distribution of <m:math
                        overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mover accent="true">
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>p</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mo>ˆ</m:mo>
                        </m:mover>
                    </m:math> was right via simulations.</p>
                <youtube src="2bIC4EmejkQ"/>
                <!--     <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="552" height="472"
                    purpose="simulation">
                    <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/walkthrough1.swf</param>
                    <param name="movieFPS">15</param>
                    <param name="LoggingLibraryPath"
                        >../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
                </flash>-->
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m4_proportion1_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m4_proportion1_tutor2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <p>At this point, we have a good sense of what happens as we take random samples
                    from a population. Our simulation suggests that our initial intuition about the
                    shape and center of the sampling distribution is correct. If the population has
                    a proportion of p, then random samples of the same size drawn from the
                    population will have sample proportions close to p. More specifically, the
                    distribution of sample proportions will have a mean of p. We also observed that
                    for this situation, the sample proportions are approximately normal. We will see
                    later that this is not always the case. But if sample proportions are normally
                    distributed, then the distribution is centered at p. Now we want to use
                    simulation to help us think more about the variability we expect to see in the
                    sample proportions. Our intuition tells us that larger samples will better
                    approximate the population, so we might expect less variability in large
                    samples. In the next walk-through we will use simulations to investigate this
                    idea. After that walk-through, we will tie these ideas to more formal theory. </p>

                <youtube src="tUvXeJ3A3_s"/>

                <!--  <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="596" height="508"
                    purpose="simulation">
                    <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/walkthrough2.swf</param>
                    <param name="movieFPS">15</param>
                    <param name="LoggingLibraryPath"
                        >../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
                </flash>-->
                <wb:inline idref="u3_m4_proportion1_tutor3" purpose="didigetthis"/>

            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
