<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u4_m04_sampling_distributions1">
<head>
<title>Sampling Distributions</title>

</head>
<body>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>
<p>Already on several occasions we have pointed out the important distinction between a
                        <em>population</em> and a <em>sample</em>. In Exploratory Data Analysis, we
                    learned to summarize and display values of a variable for a <em>sample</em>,
                    such as displaying the blood types of 100 randomly chosen U.S. adults using a
                    pie chart, or displaying the heights of 150 males using a histogram and
                    supplementing it with the sample mean
                        <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150247-0500"?>(<?oxy_insert_end?><m:math
                        overflow="scroll">
                        <m:mover accent="true">
                            <m:mrow>
                                <m:mi>X</m:mi>
                            </m:mrow>
                            <m:mo>¯</m:mo>
                        </m:mover>
                    </m:math><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150249-0500"?>)
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>and sample standard deviation
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150252-0500"?>(<?oxy_insert_end?>S<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150253-0500"?>)<?oxy_insert_end?>.</p>
<p>In our study of Probability and Random Variables, we discussed the long-run behavior of a
                    variable, considering the <em>population</em> of all possible values taken by
                    that variable. For example, we talked about the distribution of blood types
                    among all U.S. adults and the distribution of
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150401-0500" content="X, "?>the
                    random variable
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150412-0500"?>X,
                    representing a <?oxy_insert_end?>male's height. In this module, we focus
                    directly on the relationship between
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150426-0500"?>the
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>values of a variable for a <em>sample</em> and its values for
                    the entire <em>population</em> from which the sample was taken. This module is
                    the bridge between probability and our ultimate goal of the course, statistical
                    inference. In
                    inference<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150439-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    we look at a sample and ask what we can say about the population from which it
                    was drawn. In this
                    module<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150445-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    we'll pose the reverse question: If I know what the population looks like, what
                    can I expect the sample to look like? Clearly, inference poses the more
                    practical question, since in practice we can look at a sample, but rarely do we
                    know what the whole population looks like. This module will be more theoretical
                    in
                    nature<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T150506-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    since it poses a problem which is not really practical, but will present
                    important ideas which are the underpinnings for statistical inference.</p>
<p> </p>
</body>
</section>
</body>
</workbook_page>
