<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="muscularintro_3"><head><title>The Components of the Muscular System</title><objref idref="_u6_components" /></head><body><p id="d5c7ea9d125541a6ba58589bbf898551">The muscular system consists of skeletal muscle connected to bones via tendons. Tendons are a type of dense regular connective tissue that joins muscles to bone. The abdominal muscles are also held with broad tendon sheaths termed aponeuroses. In Seymour’s case either the muscle separated or pulled away from its aponeurosis that helped to anchor the muscle fibers together.</p><p id="fa2b297d999b41b09385c79fbb9cd5c1">As mentioned, there are three types of muscle tissue. Skeletal muscle attaches to bones, is voluntary, and has a striped (striated) appearance. Cardiac muscle is found in the heart, is involuntary and is striated. Smooth, sometimes known as visceral muscle, is found in many organs and blood vessels, is not striated but is involuntary.</p><p id="e0c022c3faf74a6eb0c5bb8a81e3cf42">All muscle tissue is composed of muscle cells known as muscle fibers. These fibers are bundled and held together with connective tissue. The basic unit of the muscle cell is the sarcomere. Muscles contract because sarcomeres shorten. Calcium is essential for all types of muscle tissue to function properly. You will investigate the role of calcium in muscle contraction in this module.</p><p id="e863a902c7944e6fbbfc1931c6a9990d">Muscle contains many proteins, mainly myosin and actin. Skeletal muscle is under control of the nervous system and will not contract unless a neural command reaches the muscle and instructs it to do so. The nervous system communicates with skeletal muscle via chemical messengers known as neurotransmitters. The neurotransmitter, acetylcholine, is responsible to stimulating skeletal muscle so it contracts. The process of muscle contraction occurs at the cellular level and will be studied in this unit.</p><p id="b0f5c14f9f2441ffbb42e73f4c684e85">Muscle fibers or cells are not all alike. There are cells that are specialized for endurance events, these are known as slow-twitch fibers. There are also cells or fibers that are better suited for power and sprinting. These fatigue a lot faster and are known as fast-twitch fibers.</p><p id="ed402bffb91f4d6daa191a2dfbc52632">When you study the muscular system you will need to understand the microscopic anatomy and physiology so you can learn how muscle contracts. You will also study the gross anatomy of muscles, their names, locations, and functions in the human body. The muscular system is a fascinating system. Enjoy your journey as you discover it!</p><wb:inline idref="_u6_components" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></workbook_page>
