<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="MuscularSystemIntroduction_1">
	<head>
		<title>Muscles and the Skeletal Muscular System</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Think about the things you do during the day. Talking, walking, sitting, standing, shopping,
			cooking; all of these activities require movement of skeletal muscles. You even use
			skeletal muscles when you sleep: your diaphragm has to contract and relax for you to
			breathe. Think back to your study of the skeletal system and joints and remember that
			body movement occurs around the joints in the body when skeletal muscles pull on the
			bones making up the joints.</p>
		<p>Of the <activity_link idref="levels_m3_tissues" title="title" target="new">four basic types of
				tissues</activity_link><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T191734-0500" content=" "?>,
			muscle is among the most abundant in animals. Muscle contractions are among the largest
			energy-consuming processes in the body, which is not surprising considering the work
			that muscles constantly do. The structure of muscles at the microscopic level allows
			them to convert the chemical energy found in ATP into the mechanical energy of
			movement.</p>
		<p>The body contains three types of muscle tissue: <extra><anchor><term>skeletal muscle</term></anchor><meaning>
			<material><p>muscle that moves bones and produces movement</p></material>
		</meaning></extra>, <extra><anchor><term>cardiac muscle</term></anchor><meaning>
			<material><p>muscle found in the heart</p></material>
		</meaning></extra>, and <extra><anchor><term>smooth muscle</term></anchor><meaning>
			<material><p>involuntary muscle of blood vessels and other internal organs, such as stomach and bladder</p></material>
		</meaning></extra>
			. As already mentioned, skeletal muscle is responsible for lifting, walking, and
			many other forms of movement. Cardiac muscle in your heart beats day and night every day
			of your life. Smooth muscles help regulate constriction or dilation of the blood vessels
			in the cardiovascular system, the bronchioles in the respiratory system and the
			intestines in the digestive system. All of these muscles have some properties in common,
			including the ability to contract, to be electrically excited, and to regain their forms
			after being stretched or contracted. At the molecular level, all muscles generate force
			as a result of interactions between <extra><anchor><term>myosin</term></anchor><meaning>
				<material><p>protein that makes up thick filaments</p></material>
			</meaning></extra> and <extra><anchor><term>actin</term></anchor><meaning>
				<material><p>protein that makes up thin filaments</p></material>
			</meaning></extra> filaments. However, the different
			muscle types have slightly different microscopic structures, and the differences in
			structure relate to their different functions. Their locations in the body reflect their
			different roles in body function. <activity_link idref="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_11"
				title="title" target="new">Click here to see the introductory overview of the
				muscular system from unit 1.</activity_link></p>
		
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
