<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="muscularintro_2"><head><title>The Muscular System and Homeostasis</title><objref idref="_u6_homeo" /></head><body><p id="ec986d4e1cb24f10b3da9d078f52be39">Let’s check out the muscular system in action in the following case study.</p><p id="a310b14854a244b2bb1c655fe7503ec5">Seymour is a nineteen year old power lifter and college student. You sit next to Seymour in psychology class and have gotten to know him this semester. On Monday, he sits down next to you and lets out a wince of pain as he takes his seat. You ask him, “What’s wrong?”</p><p id="c964454d10884bac9063e5d969a9fee7">He replies, “Oh, it’s probably nothing, but my stomach has been hurting especially when I lift something heavy.”</p><p id="a8b1b4b163a84f75a880517e457b9459">“Don’t you work at The Dark Horse Tavern? And work out a lot? I bet that must be tough on you. Do you think you pulled a muscle?” you ask him.</p><p id="f7e33dc4e57e44a98e2016338984a3b2">Seymour answers, “I don’t know, I’ve never felt this kind of pain before, it hurt a lot at work and I haven’t been able to lift as much at the gym.”</p><p id="daf3fbc9dfad40b7a58d3a83d0cd8950">“Why don’t we check this out on my iPhone, we still have 5 minutes before class begins” you reply.</p><p id="f9b761de9d2a4529b7d75cc497779ece">Seymour suggests going to WebMD.com for a quick look. “Hmm, I don’t see anything specific for stomach pain while exercising,” you tell him. “What other symptoms do you have?”</p><p id="d9cfa7df7cc2412d96517dfe26ade703">“Well, it’s kind of embarrassing but I have noticed this lump in my navel especially while lifting.”</p><p id="c8f378e225ed4df79778389d9f175222">“My cousin had something like that before, I think it was called a hernia, let’s Google that. Oh – man, it sounds like something called an umbilical hernia, it says that the bulge might be your intestines!” you whisper to him. “Seymour, you better get to your doctor right away, this can’t be good.”</p><p id="e7c06292aedc4fffac66e0c1f3a41a45">Seymour goes a little pale and says, “I’m going to call my mom right after class.”</p><wb:inline idref="_u6_homeo_digt" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="a454b6b95bf04268a4822de7681f0fc1">The muscular system is mainly composed of skeletal muscle, such as those that cover the anterior portion of your abdomen and help compress the abdominopelvic cavity and digestive organs. As we saw with Seymour, if these muscles are weakened, they might separate and allow the underlying organs to protrude. Seymour’s constant exposure to high intra-abdominal pressure has weakened the muscle. If a piece of Seymour’s intestine is bulging through his abdominal muscles this can have serious consequences. The small intestine is a critical component of the digestive system and if it is pinched off that section could become necrotic and die.</p><p id="ecbd8b6ec5384e4f89e9f59fbfd96b1e">There are two other types of muscle tissue that are necessary for life: cardiac and smooth muscle. Cardiac muscle is found in the heart and its rhythmic contraction is responsible for your heart beat, while smooth muscle is found in many organs and blood vessels. Smooth muscle is a significant part of your cardiovascular system (blood vessels), respiratory system (bronchioles), digestive system (esophagus, stomach, small and large intestines), urinary system (ureters and urinary bladder), and your reproductive system (uterus, vas deferens).</p><p id="e0746e299ead433587544c580f68183b">As stated earlier, skeletal muscle has many important functions in maintaining our homeostasis. Skeletal muscle contractions are critical in producing heat for our body. In fact, when you are very cold your skeletal muscles increase contractions to generate more heat to warm you – this is known as shivering. When you exercise and your skeletal muscles are more active you produce more body heat and your body temperature increases. Your body will sweat to help cool itself.</p><p id="c69a34e5e1014f1f9032ef309be90485">The diaphragm is a skeletal muscle that contracts to allow us to inhale, we exhale when it relaxes. Any disruption in this important muscle’s function can be fatal. The diaphragm is a critical organ of the respiratory system.</p><p id="eaa55724ec61439c8be968914c8d48f2">Clearly, skeletal muscle and muscle tissue is much more important than just giving us a “buff” body!</p><wb:inline idref="_u6_homeo_digt2" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></workbook_page>
