<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u7_components_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The dermis layer is the most superficial layer of the skin.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A"><p>True</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>False</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The dermis is not the superficial (top) layer of the skin.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The epidermis is the most superficial layer of the skin.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which of the following is not part of the integumentary system?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A"><p>dermis</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>hair</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>sebaceous glands</p></choice><choice value="D"><p>hypodermis</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The dermis is one of the main structures of the skin. It contains the blood vessels which provide nutrients to the cells of the epidermis.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hairs are located all over our body and are structures in the integumentary system.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sebaceous glands produce sebum or oil which helps to lubricate hair and form a chemical barrier on our epidermis.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hypodermis is below the dermis and not considered part of the integumentary system.</feedback></response><hint>This question is a little tricky, but only one structure below is not technically part of the integumentary system.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Which of the following functions to prevent water loss from the skin?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A"><p>collagen</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>keratin</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>melanin</p></choice><choice value="D"><p>vitamin D</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Collagen is a structurally important component of the skin and maintains the integrity of the skin.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Keratin is made and released from cells of the epidermis and forms a barrier to decrease water loss from the skin.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Melanin is an important pigment that protects the cells from UV radiation.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Vitamin D is made in the skin but functions for calcium absorption and protects us from various cancers.</feedback></response><hint>This protein is a main ingredient in body lotions.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
