<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="integ_factmyth_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>The skin can regenerate. </p><input_ref input="one" /></body><fill_in_the_blank id="one" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_factmyth_SKILL" /><response input="one" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The skin is made up of both connective and epithelial tissue. The epithelial tissue regenerates quickly. You have a brand new epidermis approximately every 30 days.</feedback></response><response input="one" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The skin does regenerate, the epithelial layer is quickly replaced.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p>A bald person will get colder faster than a person with a full head of hair.</p><input_ref input="two" /></body><fill_in_the_blank id="two" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_factmyth_SKILL" /><response input="two" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Any exposed area of the body will lose heat faster. The surface area of the head is much smaller compared to the rest of the body so a bald individual will lose more heat but not significantly more. Approximately 7 – 10% of body heat is lost from the head.</feedback></response><response input="two" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A full head of hair insulates and decreases heat loss from the body. An exposed surface, such as a bald head will increase heat loss and make one colder.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p>Shaving makes hair grow back faster.</p><input_ref input="three" /></body><fill_in_the_blank id="three" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_factmyth_SKILL" /><response input="three" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Hair grows from below the skin known as the follicle. Hair growth is not affected by cutting the hair.</feedback></response><response input="three" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hair grows from the follicle which is below the skin. Hair might appear to be thicker and growing faster because the tips of the hair are more blunt from the razor.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p>Squinting or frowning a lot can form wrinkles.</p><input_ref input="four" /></body><fill_in_the_blank id="four" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_factmyth_SKILL" /><response input="four" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Wrinkles form from skin creases or bends and the skin loses flexibility so the creases remain permanent. If you are constantly bending your skin the same way (frowning or squinting) you are more likely to develop wrinkles in that area.</feedback></response><response input="four" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Wrinkles occur with aging and a loss of skin flexibility. Making the same facial expressions increases the likelihood of developing wrinkles in those areas.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q5"><body><p>Sunlight has some important health benefits.</p><input_ref input="five" /></body><fill_in_the_blank id="five" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_factmyth_SKILL" /><response input="five" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The skin makes vitamin D in response to UV radiation or sunlight. You only need about 20 minutes of sunlight exposure per day.</feedback></response><response input="five" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Actually sunlight or UV radiation allows cells in your skin to make vitamin D. </feedback></response></part></question><question id="q6"><body><p>Tanning from a tanning bed is less dangerous than sun tanning.</p><input_ref input="six" /></body><fill_in_the_blank id="six" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">Fact</choice><choice value="b">Myth</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q6_p1"><skillref idref="_u7_factmyth_SKILL" /><response input="six" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Tanning beds are actually more dangerous than getting natural exposure to sunlight. Exposure to UVA radiation is up to 3X higher from a tanning bed.</feedback></response><response input="six" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. No matter what the source UV radiation is dangerous to the skin. There are two main types of UV radiation that make it to earth – UVA and UVB. UVA waves have a longer wavelength and penetrate deeper into the skin. Tanning beds specifically use more UVA light which is more dangerous. </feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
