<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u3_m1_feedback_02"><head><title>Positive Feedback</title><objref idref="_u3_describe_positive_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="f5fe28b277a74f21a73560da76b5dc75">In a positive feedback mechanism, the output of the system stimulates the system in such a way as to further increase the output. Common terms that could describe positive feedback loops or cycles include &quot;snowballing&quot; and &quot;chain reaction&quot;. Without a counter-balancing or &quot;shut-down&quot; reaction or process, a positive feedback mechanism has the potential to produce a runaway process. As noted, there are some physiologic processes that are commonly considered to be positive feedback, although they may not all have identifiable components of a feedback loop. In these cases, the positive feedback loop always ends with counter-signaling that suppresses the original stimulus. </p><image id="a74b71884e424ed6bb6b333d0cc6e499" src="../../webcontent/feedback_pos.jpg" alt="generic feedback loop that shows the input entering the system arrow to a receptor arrow to the system checking against references and arrow moving to an effector and then back to input." style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="600"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><example id="c56f5c69521044309fc7c25220f6ecca"><title>Birth Contractions</title><p id="ac9344afa4984328925ff995505f7519">A good example of positive feedback involves the amplification of labor contractions. The contractions are initiated as the baby moves into position, stretching the cervix beyond its normal position. The feedback increases the strength and frequency of the contractions until the baby is born. After birth, the stretching stops and the loop is interrupted. </p><image id="e0a0d01d87144abfac73cf6edc04b45d" src="../../webcontent/feedback_birth.jpg" alt="graphical represention of the birth contractionsfeedback loop." style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></example><example id="a60893fd24274c2a836a14e74afa8764"><title>Lactation</title><p id="dc36ba3024864f9da61a840b4677380a">Another example of positive feedback occurs in lactation, during which a mother produces milk for her infant. During pregnancy, levels of the hormone prolactin increase. Prolactin normally stimulates milk production, but during pregnancy, progesterone inhibits milk production. At birth, when the placenta is released from the uterus, progesterone levels drop. As a result, milk production surges. As the baby feeds, its suckling stimulates the breast, promoting further release of prolactin, resulting in yet more milk production. This positive feedback ensures the baby has sufficient milk during feeding. When the baby is weaned and no longer nurses from the mother, stimulation ceases and prolactin in the mother’s blood reverts to pre-breastfeeding levels. </p><wb:inline idref="_u3_m1_lactation" purpose="learnbydoing" /></example><section id="a2e81f7c266349229c492779a714e704" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u3_m1_lactation2" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="meta4_pos" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><p id="b3f4adde451647f9a2e600a1a8a4d8be">The above provide examples of beneficial positive feedback mechanisms. However, in many instances, positive feedback can be potentially damaging to life processes. For example, blood pressure can fall significantly if a person loses a lot of blood due to trauma.</p><example id="ed0de8ed231f4450817e7c63ab87bf94"><title>Heart Failure</title><p id="a94613cab1d64985a496493ff59332ff">Blood pressure is a regulated variable that leads to the heart increasing its rate (i.e. heart rate increases) and contracting more strongly. These changes to the heart cause it to need more oxygen and nutrients, but if the blood volume in the body is too low, the heart tissue itself will not receive enough blood flow to meet these increased needs. The imbalance between oxygen demands of the heart and oxygen supply can lead to further heart damage, which actually lowers blood pressure, providing a larger change in the variable (blood pressure). The loop responds by trying to stimulate the heart even more strongly, leading to further heart damage...and the loop goes on until death ensues. </p></example></body></workbook_page>
