<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m1_feedback_03">
    <head>
        <title>Negative Feedback</title>
        <objref idref="_u3_describe_negative_OBJ"/>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>Most biological feedback systems are negative feedback systems. Negative
            feedback occurs when a system's output acts to reduce or dampen the processes that lead
            to the output of that system, resulting in less output. In general, negative feedback
            loops allow systems to self-stabilize. Negative feedback is a vital control mechanism
            for the body’s homeostasis.</p>
        <image style="block" src="../../webcontent/feedback_neg.jpg"
            alt="generic feedback loop that shows the input entering the system arrow to a receptor arrow to the system checking against references and arrow moving to an effector and then back to input." width="600"/>

        <example>
            <title>Temperature Homeostasis</title>
            <p>You saw an example of a feedback loop applied to <activity_link
                    idref="_u3_m1_terms_04" target="new">temperature</activity_link> and identified the
                components involved. This is an important example of how a negative feedback loop
                maintains homeostasis is the body’s thermoregulation mechanism. The body maintains a
                relatively constant internal temperature to optimize chemical processes. Neural
                impulses from heat-sensitive thermoreceptors in the body signal the hypothalamus.
                The hypothalamus, located in the brain, compares the body temperature to a set point
                value.</p>

            <p>When body temperature drops, the hypothalamus initiates several physiological
                responses to increase heat production and conserve heat: </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Narrowing of surface blood vessels (vasoconstriction) decreases the flow of heat
                    to the skin.</li>
                <li>Shivering commences, increasing production of heat by the muscles.</li>
                <li>Adrenal glands secrete stimulatory hormones such as norepinephrine and
                    epinephrine to increase metabolic rates and hence heat production.</li>
            </ul>

            <p>These effects cause body temperature to increase. When it returns to normal, the
                hypothalamus is no longer stimulated, and these effects cease.</p>

            <image src="../../webcontent/feedback_lowtemp.jpg" width="600"
                alt="graphical display of the high body temperature feedback loop" style="block"/>

            <p> When body temperature rises, the hypothalamus initiates several physiological
                responses to decrease heat production and lose heat:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Widening of surface blood vessels (vasodilation) increases the flow of heat to
                    the skin and get flushed.</li>
                <li>Sweat glands release water (sweat) and evaporation cools the skin.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>These effects cause body temperature to decrease. When it returns to normal, the
                hypothalamus is no longer stimulated, and these effects cease.</p>
            <image src="../../webcontent/feedback_hightemp.jpg" width="600"
                alt="graphical display of the low body temperature feedback loop" style="block"/>
        </example>

        <p>Many homeostatic mechanisms, like temperature, have different responses if the variable
            is above or below the set point. When temperature increases, we sweat, when it
            decreases, we shiver. These responses use different effectors to adjust the variable. In
            other cases, a feedback loop will use the same effector to adjust the variable back
            toward the set point, whether the initial change of the variable was either above or
            below the set point. For example, pupillary diameter is adjusted to make sure an
            appropriate amount of light is entering the eye. If the amount of light is too low, the
            pupil dilates, if it is too high, the pupil constricts.</p>

        <p>This might be compared to driving. If your speed is above the set point (the value you
            want it to be), you can either just decrease the level of the accelerator (i.e. coast),
            or you can active a second system -- the brake. In both cases you slow, but it can be
            done by either just "backing" off on one system, or adding a second system.</p>


        <p>Let’s look at how these two examples work related to normal blood pressure
            homeostasis.</p>

        <example>
            <title>Blood Pressure Homeostasis</title>
            <p>Blood pressure is measured as the circulating blood puts pressure on the walls of the
                body’s arteries. Blood pressure is created initially by the contraction of the
                heart. Changes in the strength and rate of contraction will be directly related to
                changes in blood pressure. Changes in the volume of blood would also be directly
                related to changes in blood pressure. Changes in the diameter of the vessels that
                blood travels through will change resistance and have an opposite change on blood
                pressure. Blood pressure homeostasis involves receptors monitoring blood pressure
                and control centers initiating changes in the effectors to keep it within a normal
                range.</p>
            <wb:inline idref="_u3_control_lbd_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            <wb:inline idref="_u3_control_digt_inline" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        </example>

                
            
       
        
    </body>
</workbook_page>
