<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m1_tech_05-DONOTUSE">
    <head>
        <title>Homeostasis in Technology</title>
        <objref idref="_u3_compare_tech_OBJ"/>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Air Conditioning</title>
            <body>
                <p>Air conditioning is a technological systems that uses feedback. The thermostat senses the temperature, 
                    an electronic interface compares the temperature against a set-point (the temperature that you want 
                    it to be). If the temperature matches or is cooler, then nothing happens. If the tempature is too hot 
                    then the electronic interface triggers the air-conditioning unit to turn on. Once the temperature is 
                    lowered sufficiently to reach the set-point, the electronic interface shuts the air-conditioning off. 
                    For this example, identify the steps of the feedback loop.</p>
                <wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_tech_airconditioning_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
            </body>
        </section> 
      
        <section>
            <title>Cruise Control</title>
            <body>
                <p>Cruise control is another technological feedback system. The idea of cruise control is to maintain a 
                    constant speed in your car. The car's speed is determined by the speedometer and an electronic interface 
                    measures the car's speed against a set-point set by the driver. If the speed is too slow, the interface 
                    stimulates the engine; if the speed is too fast, the interface reduces the power to the tires. For this 
                    example, identify the steps of the feedback loop.  </p>
                <wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_tech_cruise_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
            </body>
        </section>  
    </body>

</workbook_page>