<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u3_m1_feedback_01"><head><title>Feedback Loops</title><objref idref="_u3_compare_pos_neg_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="f870d2fe8bb9481d95ec34f48e451bc4">Remember that homeostasis is the maintenance of a relatively stable internal environment. When a <term>stimulus</term>, or change in the environment, is present, feedback loops respond to keep systems functioning near a <term>set point</term>, or ideal level.</p><definition id="ade53ce04f63465bad5b9c59a89338db"><term>feedback</term><meaning id="aafe537a189f46419938d2c3de039004"><material><p id="b233f1d74b914a05b64e81ae4351070b">Feedback is a situation when the output or response of a loop impacts or influences the input or stimulus. </p></material></meaning></definition><image id="c112d0cf99c94551be28aaa2e6dbaaf4" src="../../webcontent/feedback_1-color.jpg" alt="generic feedback loop that shows the input entering the system arrow to a receptor arrow to the system checking against references and arrow moving to an effector and then back to input." style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="600"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a81daa03c17b43768d4be861b95bb69c">Typically, we divide feedback loops into two main types:</p><ol id="fadf8cc5b373497dbdc549b23688b0d3"><li><p id="be1728e737cf47b9a58fdabdb569d183"><term>positive feedback</term></p><p id="af0bf127bb5bf419fb905b9226a3ad77d"> loops, in which a change in a given direction causes additional change in the same direction. </p><p id="d9cf2c2c3ff847e58bab0844a22c88bb">For example, an increase in the concentration of a substance causes feedback that produces continued increases in concentration.</p></li><li><p id="dfc8175aaee44bddbe891ea5e3857240"><term>negative feedback</term></p><p id="ac9de02f8e0644a289463e15be7923d36"> loops, in which a change in a given direction causes change in the opposite direction. </p><p id="deb19538e383464c90f782215fa0475c">For example, an increase in the concentration of a substance causes feedback that ultimately causes the concentration of the substance to decrease.</p></li></ol><p id="f4dab0c4d80e47b385dfd32b739a4ce8">Positive feedback loops are inherently unstable systems. Because a change in an input causes responses that produce continued changes in the same direction, positive feedback loops can lead to runaway conditions. The term positive feedback is typically used as long as a variable has an ability to amplify itself, even if the components of a loop (receptor, control center and effector) are not easily identifiable. In most cases, positive feedback is harmful, but there are a few instances where positive feedback, when used in limited fashion, contributes to normal function. For example, during blood clotting, a cascade of enzymatic proteins activates each other, leading to the formation of a fibrin clot that prevents blood loss. One of the enzymes in the pathway, called thrombin, not only acts on the next protein in the pathway but also has an ability to activate a protein that preceded it in the cascade. This latter step leads to a positive feedback cycle, where an increase in thrombin leads to further increases in thrombin. It should be noted that there are other aspects of blood clotting that keep the overall process in check, such that thrombin levels don’t rise without limit. But if we just consider the effects of thrombin on itself, it is considered a positive feedback cycle. Although some may consider this a positive feedback loop, such terminology is not universally accepted. </p><p id="d3b7bc9f80a74fad92f3b3c2956fddf3">Negative feedback loops are inherently stable systems. Negative feedback loops, in conjunction with the various stimuli that can affect a variable, typically produce a condition in which the variable oscillates around the set point. For example, negative feedback loops involving insulin and glucagon help to keep blood glucose levels within a narrow concentration range. If glucose levels get too high, the body releases insulin into the bloodstream. Insulin causes the body&apos;s cells to take in and store glucose, lowering the blood glucose concentration. If blood glucose gets too low, the body releases glucagon, which causes the release of glucose from some of the body&apos;s cells.</p><wb:inline idref="_u3_m1_homestasis-posneg1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="b7d82667669840e19c485f5e500d300c" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u3_m1_homestasis-posneg2" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="meta3_compare" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
