<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_disrupt_tt_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Malignant cancer that invades the bone is the second most common cause of hypercalcemia (excess plasma calcium concentration). As it destroys the bone cells, it releases a substance that mimics the action of which hormone?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">thyroid hormones T3 &amp; T 4</choice><choice value="B">calcitonin</choice><choice value="C">thyroid releasing hormone</choice><choice value="D">parathyroid hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i628358f05fd845179ec93a3804509c4b"><skillref idref="endo_disrupt_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These would not directly impact the calcium level.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would decrease not increase plasma calcium concentration.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.This would stimulate release of T3 &amp; T 4 that would not directly impact the calcium level.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This would normally stimulate release of calcium from bone matrix only when blood calcium levels are low and be inhibited by negative feedback when levels return to normal.</feedback></response><hint>The cancer side effect would be inappropriate increased plasma calcium, while the hormone would be stimulating this increase within a negative feedback mechanism to maintain normal homeostatic levels.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Alcoholics typically have poor nutrition intake that can affect their intake of nutrients and often have reduced calcium and magnesium intake. The low magnesium decreases the body’s ability to secrete parathyroid hormone. This combined condition would put them at greater risk of developing which condition?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">hyperkalemia</choice><choice value="B">hypercalcemia</choice><choice value="C">hypokalemia</choice><choice value="D">hypocalcemia</choice></multiple_choice><part id="c7779f3908df47db9a1914df8c79a926"><skillref idref="endo_disrupt_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would not affect the level of potassium (K+) in the blood.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would suppress the release of PTH and decrease plasma calcium, not increase it.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would not affect the level of potassium (K+) in the blood.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. In addition to less calcium in the diet itself, the decreased PTH would prevent the body from maintaining sufficient plasma calcium by stimulating resorption from bone, improving absorption from intestines, and conserving loss of calcium from urine.</feedback></response><hint>The suffix -calcemia refers to calcium while the suffix –kalemia refers to potassium.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
