<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_calcium_tt_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Which of the following would <em>not</em> be stimulated by calcitonin?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">osteoporosis</choice><choice value="B">decreased intestinal absorption</choice><choice value="C">increased calcium in urine</choice><choice value="D">decreased parathyroid hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part id="ce034d5292664bc0bfb2affdf802ec14"><skillref idref="endo_calcium_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Calcitonin would inhibit osteoclast resorption from bone and is being investigated for its possible use in treating osteoporosis and other bone diseases.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would still happen and could cause diarrhea associated with this cancer.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would still happen, but not directly impact the plasma calcium homeostasis.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because it doesn’t affect the plasma calcium level significantly its increase would not necessarily inhibit production of the hormone with opposite effect.</feedback></response><hint>While its role in adult plasma calcium homeostasis is minor, its effect is still opposite to PTH. As a result, excess production of calcitonin from a thyroid medulla tumor does not seem to cause hypocalcemia but still creates effects related to its mechanism of action.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What other ion’s homeostasis would be linked to the calcium homeostasis regulated by these hormones?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">potassium</choice><choice value="B">sodium</choice><choice value="C">phosphate</choice><choice value="D">chloride</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i0b1e6376915d4805a5110ad75707de41"><skillref idref="endo_calcium_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would not be directly linked to the release or deposition of calcium in bone matrix.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would not be directly linked to the release or deposition of calcium in bone matrix.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. As the calcium is released from or deposited into the bony matrix, phosphate plasma levels also will also be affected.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would not be directly linked to the release or deposition of calcium in bone matrix.</feedback></response><hint>Bone matrix, the major storage site for calcium is made of hydroxyapatite that is a calcium-phosphate mineral crystal.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
