<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_metabolism_tt_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Which of the following statements is correct:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Hyperglycemia is associated with too much insulin.</choice><choice value="B">Hypoglycemia is associated with reduced urine production.</choice><choice value="C">Hyperthyroidism would be associated with too much iodine.</choice><choice value="D">Hypothyroidism is associated with weight gain, cold-intolerance and fatigue.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i04d22ecd8f614897b0cbb30fd6919589"><skillref idref="endo_metabolism_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While the pancreas may initially react to produce excess insulin when the body cells become resistant to insulin, the excess insulin is not the cause of the high blood glucose; eventually the pancreas typically stops producing insulin.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While hyperglycemia causes excess urination, hypoglycemia would not have opposite effect on body.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Too much iodine would not cause excess thyroid production; in fact recent studies have shown that significantly excess iodine can have the same effect as too little iodine by damaging the thyroid tissue and causing a mild form of hypothyroidism.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Thyroid hormones stimulate proper metabolic rates, producing enough energy to maintain body temperature and body functions.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>In addition to insulin and thyroid hormones, several other hormones affecting growth, repair and stress will directly or indirectly affect glucose levels in the blood. You will learn more about some of these effects in the next sections. Which of the following would NOT be involved in this glucose regulation?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">growth hormone</choice><choice value="B">cortisol</choice><choice value="C">calcitonin</choice><choice value="D">glucocorticoids</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i921b4e1f34c842bc96fa0d65431ea4ec"><skillref idref="endo_metabolism_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This works both directly and indirectly with IGF to increase glucose levels to support the stimulated cell growth.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Cortisol is an example of a glucocorticoid, and it does stimulate glucose synthesis in response to stress.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This regulates the level of blood calcium ion, not glucose.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. As the name implies, this group of hormones it does stimulate glucose synthesis in response to stress.</feedback></response><hint>These hormones would have receptors on most body cells because they are involved in glucose regulation related to growth and stress.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
