<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_growth_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What is the effect of an overproduction of growth hormone in children and in adults?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">It has the same effect of causing excessive growth of all bones in both children and adults.</choice><choice value="B">In children it can cause pituitary dwarfism; in adults it primarily affects the bones of the face, hands and feet.</choice><choice value="C">In children it primarily affects the bones of the face, hands and feet; in adults it can cause excessive proportional growth</choice><choice value="D">In children it can cause excessive proportional growth; in adults it primarily affects the bones of the face, hands and feet.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i97d0e56481fd46a598e07690d8c9e823"><skillref idref="endo_growth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In children the growth plates of the long bones can still grow so the overproduction of GH results in gigantism. In adults the growth plates of the long bones have calcified and only the short bones of the face, hands and feet can continue to grow resulting in acromegaly.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An under production of GH could cause pituitary dwarfism.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In children the growth plates of the long bones can still grow so the over production of GH results in gigantism. In adults the growth plates of the long bones have calcified and only the short bones of the face, hands and feet can continue to grow resulting in acromegaly.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. In children the growth plates of the long bones can still grow so the over production of GH results in gigantism. In adults the growth plates of the long bones have calcified and only the short bones of the face, hands and feet can continue to grow resulting in acromegaly.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
