<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_repro_female_tt_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>FSH and LH from the anterior pituitary regulate the release of hormones from the gonads. Which classification is correct for these two hormones?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">steroid</choice><choice value="B">trophic</choice><choice value="C">tropic</choice><choice value="D">neurosecretory</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i3aa1c44518504ce9927ad64e17f6e009"><skillref idref="endo_repro_female_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are both peptide hormones.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These are hormones that affect the growth of non-endocrine cells.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. These stimulate the release of testosterone from testes and estrogen and progesterone from ovary.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The hypothalamus hormones controlling their release are carried in the hypophyseal portal vein, not directly by neurons.</feedback></response><hint>These “master gland” hormones are themselves controlled by hormones from the hypothalamus.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Testosterone and estrogen from the gonads regulate the production of gametes. Which classification is correct for these two hormones?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">peptide</choice><choice value="B">trophic</choice><choice value="C">tropic</choice><choice value="D">neurosecretory</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i09ebcc2596ce4c0ab1544913702e278d"><skillref idref="endo_repro_female_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Both of these hormones are steroid.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. In addition to gamete production, testosterone affects the growth of muscle and other tissues while estrogen influences the distribution of adipose and development of uterus lining in preparation for implantation of fertilized ovum.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Tropic hormones, like FSH and LH, stimulate the release of of hormones from the gonads.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Testosterone and estrogen are released by the gonads, not by neurons.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Two hormones are involved in the combined production and release of milk. Which of them are involved in a positive feedback mechanism?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">oxytocin alone</choice><choice value="B">prolactin alone</choice><choice value="C">both oxytocin and prolactin</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i76808023f23c42799877ad3371b9b6cf"><skillref idref="endo_repro_female_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. As with the birth process, plasma levels of oxytocin stimulate more oxytocin to be released; in this case it stimulates stronger contractions for release of more milk as the baby grows.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While milk production increases as the baby grows, it is not the level of prolactin in the hormone stimulating this, but the effect of other stimuli on the hypothalamus and anterior pituitary that prevent the inhibition of its release.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While milk production increases as the baby grows, it is not the level of prolactin in the hormone stimulating this, but the effect of other stimuli on the hypothalamus and anterior pituitary that prevent the inhibition of its release.</feedback></response><hint>Positive feedback involves continued increase in hormone, not just increased effect, which is milk production in this case.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
