<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="endocrine_unit_review"><head><title>Endocrine System Unit Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="c2c5e6ed191f4194a3ffde34a222ae83">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="c204f66a40074af4899e8d30021ee08d"><li><p id="aa611f852badc44b5bcfa4e1593e10bad">Describe the major functions of the endocrine system.</p></li><li><p id="aacdedbf485ad48b4a30c9766c0671602">Identify major diseases associated with the endocrine system and their causes.</p></li><li><p id="abd7dcd1ba0ba49639cfc7c1803df4626">Define hormone and list the three hormone types.</p></li><li><p id="ac806ae4bb7fd4b06adcc24989533ee15">Describe the precursor molecules and identify how lipid-derived hormones are transported.</p></li><li><p id="af2102183e0b2475f80bb2c25e36618c8">Describe the precursor molecules of amino acid hormones.</p></li><li><p id="ac62724bbc0f8481380f31a9dd09c7e22">Describe the precursor molecules of peptide-derived hormones.</p></li><li><p id="afbe044964cfd481284f38cc700ecbdf9">Describe how hormones are involved in loops of homeostasis including positive feedback and negative feedback.</p></li><li><p id="ad16eaa92277d457381a2cf59862a1337">List and compare the mechanisms of hormonal stimulation.</p></li><li><p id="adc7e4f95d48249889e26e44c016c265b">Discuss how hormone receptors maintain specificity in endocrine regulation.</p></li><li><p id="ab46fcbd2762f4e8d845f1e27ea063c1b">List the different locations for hormone receptors. </p></li><li><p id="aa2a94d71cd194d51ab9bc5a032af32a8">Define intracellular and plasma membrane hormone receptors and describe how they impact cellular gene expression.</p></li><li><p id="ae5a9e5b0936d46ebb46f18031fa66346">Define G-protein-coupled hormone receptors and describe how they are messengers for signal transduction.</p></li><li><p id="ae939b1d331a948a3a8785cb7e8cdcfcc">List the hormones secreted by the hypothalamus and describe the functions that these hormones regulate.</p></li><li><p id="af6ac384be4464627a329f48269a366a0">Describe the structure of the anterior pituitary and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="acf8539366e084c10ab6585acd6b3d5aa">Describe the structure of the posterior pituitary and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="ade8ec6cb0d454603b1624869d3157b87">Describe the structure of the thyroid gland and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="abe70d6cf12fb4ab5908dbc6b52932db6">Compare the production of hormones in the thyroid to other endocrine glands.</p></li><li><p id="ae321c8f333d34f9cafb3f5db8db1afeb">Describe the structure of the parathyroid glands and what hormones these glands produce.</p></li><li><p id="af148d874f54a47278bdbbe47e41351d5">Use anatomical terms to describe the location of the adrenal glands and the layers of the adrenal glands.</p></li><li><p id="ab73bf152e0924d998695f2234082e8d9">Describe the structure of the adrenal cortex and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="afa7d560577db43888bc6e770188d6107">Describe the structure of the adrenal medulla and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="ab4d4ae441d4d4c06b2327b2ea74408c5">Describe the structure of the pineal gland and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="ab15fcda0a7464bc7951d0dda5cd1b67e">Describe the structure of the pancreas and what hormones it produces.</p></li><li><p id="abab454c2e16342ec9f59e4dadcaddde9">Describe the endocrine glands and hormones involved in the reproductive system.</p></li><li><p id="ad1f13f99669c48ada43485cdda3910e6">List the endocrine glands, identify their locations within the body and name the primary hormones that they secrete.</p></li><li><p id="acb4e413bc40742b8845ff5d747679ea1">Compare the hormones secreted from organs with secondary endocrine function and the primary function of these organs.</p></li><li><p id="afd8f4f53b5ae4abe8386fad84247a6c1">Identify how endocrine function regulates the homeostasis of different organ systems in the body.</p></li><li><p id="abd8306f80d5a417bb195ab38a9485a11">Describe how endocrine function regulates the homeostasis of water in the body and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="aba69468d2db34b79ab85f1708f3cb7da">Describe how endocrine function regulates the reproductive system. List the hormones that are common to males and females.</p></li><li><p id="aace1b48d7fbb47e1abc0510b09dd082d">Describe how endocrine function regulates the male reproductive system and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="aa66aa3878a1c49879dee89fe504e31d7">Describe how endocrine function regulates the female reproductive system and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="ac17d7db11fb94eca89022517f1aeec54">Describe how endocrine function regulates the production of milk and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="ad212e0ca73924512b5f48698138105ec">Describe how endocrine function regulates the homeostasis of glucose and list the hormones involved in the process. Compare the roles of insulin and thyroid hormones.</p></li><li><p id="af57cd1790fe04fe68a3e2e2be7fb282a">Describe how endocrine function regulates the homeostasis of calcium levels in the body and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="ab5f330be63a847c298264a0087bdf0d7">Describe how endocrine function regulates growth and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="af3897677dc4143f1ac87924a9b1f369f">Describe differences between short-term and long-term stress responses.</p></li><li><p id="ab1f7a82c4ef444be9e7076c6f6cc9e50">Describe how endocrine function impacts the body’s response to stress and list the hormones involved in the process.</p></li><li><p id="ac3170d167a674c27b4ed0b9a38cdee6b">Predict factors or situations affecting the endocrine system that could disrupt homeostasis.</p></li></ul><activity idref="u10_endofunitquiz" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="endo_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
