<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u10_m2_review"><head><title>Endocrine Homeostasis and Integration of Systems Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="db3ce432445240d8aa417740f35c152d">Maintaining a proper water balance in the body is important to avoid dehydration or excess water. The water concentration of the body is monitored by osmoreceptors in the hypothalamus, which detect the concentration of electrolytes in the blood. An increase in blood electrolyte levels results in a neural signal being sent from the osmoreceptors to the hypothalamus. The hypothalamus produces antidiuretic hormone (ADH), which is transported to, and released from, the posterior pituitary. Another hormone responsible for maintaining electrolyte concentrations in extracellular fluids isaldosterone, a steroid hormone that is produced by the adrenal cortex. In contrast to ADH, which promotes the reabsorption of water to maintain proper water balance, aldosterone maintains proper water balance by enhancing Na+ reabsorption from extracellular fluids. </p><p id="b1d49c651c484b14a3c4400ffe22af38">Regulation of the reproductive system is a process that requires the action of hormones from the pituitary gland, the adrenal cortex, and the gonads. During puberty in both males and females, the hypothalamus produces gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH), which stimulates the release of follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and luteinizing hormone (LH) from the anterior pituitary. These hormones regulate the gonads (testes in males and ovaries in females) and therefore are calledgonadotropins. In both males and females, FSH stimulates gamete production, and LH stimulates production of hormones by the gonads. An increase in gonad hormone levels inhibits GnRH production through a negative feedback loop.</p><p id="a30848252e9c4a3dbfec798e87dd4669">In order to manage nutrient intake, storing excess and utilizing stores when necessary, the body uses hormones to modulate energy metabolism. Insulin is produced by the beta cells of the pancreas, which are stimulated to release insulin as blood glucose levels rise, for example, after a meal is consumed. When blood glucose levels decline below normal levels, for example, between meals or when glucose is utilized rapidly during exercise, the hormone glucagon is released from the alpha cells of the pancreas. </p><p id="de23a89579f74f3cb6ec9b54be128a9b">Blood calcium levels are regulated by parathyroid hormone (PTH), which is produced by the parathyroid glands. PTH is released in response to low blood Ca2+ levels. PTH increases Ca2+ levels by targeting the skeleton, the kidneys, and the intestine. The hormone calcitonin is produced by the parafollicular or C cells of the thyroid and has the opposite effect on blood calcium levels as PTH. Calcitonin decreases blood calcium levels by inhibiting osteoclasts, stimulating osteoblasts, and stimulating calcium excretion by the kidneys. </p><p id="cdb1d02bc4dc44678461d630bf88d9eb">Hormonal regulation is required for the growth and replication of most cells in the body. Growth hormone (GH) produced by the anterior pituitary accelerates the rate of protein synthesis, particularly in skeletal muscle and bones. </p><activity idref="_u10_homeostasis_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
