<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u10_m1_review"><head><title>Endocrine Levels of Organization Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="a54ebef5fe9e439a8be1c99303d9692f">Hormones are the chemical messengers of the endocrine system. They elicit specific responses by binding to receptors on or in target cells. Hormones mediate changes in cells by binding to specific receptors; individual hormones have their own unique receptor or class of receptors. A cell that has a receptor for a specific hormone is called a target cell. A hormone can, therefore circulate throughout the body, contacting many different cell types, but affecting only those cells that possess the specific receptor.Hormones could be: </p><ul id="d51baac52a7d44e4aaf07dcdd35d2c90"><li><p id="af933f03cbb0743c59e3c6de4f0ec5f82">Lipid-derived, such as steroid hormones</p></li><li><p id="adca4098e497145febeb05bf3b3cd2f8a">Amino acid-derived, such as epinephrine</p></li><li><p id="ae63c6faf4b68411eaa96599c3237d2e9">Peptide-derived, such as growth hormone</p></li></ul><p id="a773d022cb364a418c29e37497192861">Hormone production can be regulated by positive and negative feedback pathways. In positive feedback systems, the release of a hormone leads to an action that stimulates release of more of the same hormone.There are three mechanisms by which endocrine glands are stimulated to synthesize and release hormones: humoral regulation, hormonal regulation, and neural regulation. Make sure you understand the various components of the endocrine system, such as the hypothalamus and anterior pituitary, and their endocrine functions.</p><activity idref="_u10_LOO_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
