<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="DNA Transcription" >
     <step stepURL="swfs/steps.swf" menustep=" RNA Synthesis steps: ">
         <text>&lt;html&gt;The steps illustrated in this section occur at all of the promoters in &lt;i&gt;E. coli&lt;/i&gt;.  &lt;b&gt;RNA polymerase (RNAP)&lt;/b&gt; is a large, multi-subunit enzyme. The "core" enzyme contains the catalytic site for RNA synthesis; it is shown here as a single gold-colored unit.  The &lt;b&gt;sigma subunit&lt;/b&gt; (in orange) combines with the core to form the complete holoenzyme.  Sigma is responsible for recognizing the DNA sequences 35 bp and 10 bp on the 3’ side of the transcription start site &lt;b&gt;(the -35 and -10 regions)&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>    
    
    <step stepURL="swfs/open.swf" menustep="      Open Complex formation  ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The initial (reversible) binding of RNAP at the promoter results in the formation of a "closed complex".  The second step results in DNA strand separation from about -12bp to +2bp relative to the transcription start point (+1).  The "open complex" thus formed is then committed to the transcription process.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>    
    
    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation.swf" menustep="      Initiation ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;&lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;ibo&lt;b&gt;n&lt;/b&gt;ucleotide &lt;b&gt;t&lt;/b&gt;ri&lt;b&gt;p&lt;/b&gt;hosphates (rNTPs) bind in a template-directed order and are polymerized unidirectionally from 5' to 3' by RNAP.  Each triphosphate contributes one nucleotide unit to the newly synthesized RNA.  Phosphodiester bond formation is catalyzed by RNAP with the release of inorganic pyrophosphate (PPi).  When the RNA chain is about 10-12 nucleotides long, sigma subunit dissociates, leaving the core enzyme to finish the RNA chain.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>    
    
    <step stepURL="swfs/elongation.swf" menustep="      Elongation ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Chain elongation occurs rapidly (~50 nucleotides/sec) and processively (continuously) through all genes of the operon.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>    
    
    <step stepURL="swfs/termination.swf" menustep="      Termination ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The E. coli Rho protein (blue hexigon) assists RNA chain termination in many transcription units.  Rho binds to segments of RNA about 70 nucleotides long that are undergoing transcription and are not complexed by ribosomes.  Thus, after RNAP proceeds beyond the last gene of the operon, Rho can bind to the RNA.  In addition, Rho is an RNA helicase, i.e. it uses the energy of ATP hydrolysis to move (5'-> 3') along the RNA.  The Rho helicase action results in the removal of the RNA from the transcribing complex and the dissociation of core RNAP enzyme from the DNA. The core enzyme can then rebind sigma to form holoenzyme and begin another transcription cycle.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>    
</TUTORIAL>