<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="caseii2lbd">
    <head>
        <title>Case C→C</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>An Associated Press article captured the attention of readers with the headline "Night
            lights bad for kids?" The article was based on a 1999 study at the University of
            Pennsylvania and Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, in which parents were surveyed
            about the lighting conditions under which their children slept between birth and age 2
            (lamp, night light, or no light) and whether or not their children developed
            nearsightedness (myopia). The purpose of the study was to explore the effect of a young
            child's nighttime exposure to light on later nearsightedness. </p>
        <p>In this activity, we use the collected data to:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Learn how to build a two-way table and compute conditional percentages.</li>
            <li>Interpret the data in terms of the relationship between a young child's nighttime
                exposure to light and later nearsightedness.</li>
        </ul>
        <pullout>
            <alternatives group="statistics.package">
                <default><pref:value preference="statistics.package"/></default>
                <alternative value="r">
                    <title>R Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open R with the dataset preloaded, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/r/nightlight.RData" target="self">here</link>
                        and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Then find
                        the downloaded file and double-click it to open it in R.</p>
                    <p>The data have been loaded into the data frame <code>nightlight</code>. Enter
                        the command <code>nightlight</code> to see the data. There are two
                        variables: <code>Light</code> and <code>Nearsightedness</code>.</p>
                    <p>You should see a report about 479 subjects with two columns. The first column
                        records what kind of light, if any, was used in the subjects’ bedrooms while
                        they slept, and the second column indicates whether or not the subjects
                        later became nearsighted.</p>
                    <p>Since there are only two variables in the data frame, we can obtain a summary
                        of the data in a two-way table by using the <code>table()</code> command on
                        data frame name:</p>
                    <code style="inline">t = table(nightlight);t</code>

                    <!--                    <codeblock syntax="text">               Nearsightedness
  Light          No Yes
    lamp         34  41
    night light 153  79
    no light    155  17-->
                    <p>If the data frame had more than two variables then specific variables must be
                        identified within the <code>table()</code> command, with the first entry
                        representing the row values and the second entry representing the column
                        values.</p>
                    <code style="inline">tt =
                        table(nightlight$Light,nightlight$Nearsightedness);tt</code>

                    <!--                    <codeblock syntax="text">                 No Yes
    lamp         34  41
    night light 153  79
    no light    155  17-->
                    <p>To create a table of conditional proportions showing which proportion of
                        children in each treatment group became nearsighted, we must divide each
                        table entry by the total number of entries in its row. To do this, copy the
                        following command to R:</p>
                    <code style="inline">prop.table(t,1)</code>
                    <!--                    <codeblock syntax="text">               Nearsightedness
  Light                 No        Yes
    lamp        0.45333333 0.54666667
    night light 0.65948276 0.34051724
    no light    0.90116279 0.09883721-->
                    <p>To create a table of conditional proportions showing which proportion of
                        children who are nearsighted or not were in each treatment group, we must
                        divide each table entry by the column totals. To do this, copy the following
                        command to R:</p>
                    <code style="inline">prop.table(t,2)</code>
                    <!--                    <codeblock syntax="text">               Nearsightedness
  Light                No       Yes
    lamp        0.0994152 0.2992701
    night light 0.4473684 0.5766423
    no light    0.4532164 0.1240876-->
                    <p>To create a table of conditional percentages, simply muliply the above
                        commands by 100, like so:</p>
                    <code style="inline">prop.table(t,1)*100</code>
                    <!--                    <codeblock syntax="text">               Nearsightedness
  Light                No       Yes
    lamp        45.333333 54.666667
    night light 65.948276 34.051724
    no light    90.116279  9.883721-->
                </alternative>
                <alternative value="StatCrunch">
                    <title>StatCrunch Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open this file in StatCrunch you must first right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/excel/nightlight.xls" target="self"
                            >here</link> and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your
                        computer. Next click <link href="http://www.statcrunch.com/" target="new"
                            >here</link>to open StatCrunch in a separate window and login using your
                        username and password.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Click on the link "Open StatCrunch" at the top of the My StatCrunch
                            page. </li>
                        <li>To open the data set, select the "My computer" link under "Load a data
                            set" from box on the left side of the page.</li>
                        <li>Select the "Browse" or "Choose File" (depending on which browser you're
                            using) and select the data set you downloaded.</li>
                        <li>Scroll to the bottom of the page and click on "Load File."</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To ask StatCrunch for a two-way table that contains both the counts and
                        conditional percentages:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose: Stat → Tables → Contingency → with data.</li>
                        <li>Row variable: Light, Column Variable: Nearsightedness.</li>
                        <li>Press Next.</li>
                        <li>Check: Row percent. Uncheck all other options.</li>
                        <li>Press Calculate.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>
                <alternative value="minitab">
                    <title>Minitab Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open Minitab with the data in the worksheet, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/minitab/nightlight.mtw" target="self"
                            >here</link> and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your
                        computer. Then find the downloaded file and double-click it to open it in
                        Minitab. Note: you will likely see a dialog box appear that says "A copy of
                        the content of this file will be added to the current project"&#8212;just
                        click OK.</p>
                    <p>To ask Minitab for a two-way table that contains both the counts and
                        conditional percentages:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Choose: Stat → Tables → Cross Tabulation and Chi-Square.</li>
                        <li>Under "Categorical Variables": <ul>
                                <li>Next to "For rows" enter the explanatory variable ("Light" in
                                    this case).</li>
                                <li>Next to "For columns" enter the response variable
                                    ("Nearsightedness" in this case).</li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                        <li>Under "Display" check "Counts" and "Row percents."</li>
                        <li>Click OK. (A two-way table will appear in the session (upper) window.
                            Note the "Cell Contents" below the table, which tells you what the two
                            entries in each cell in the table are.) </li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>
                <alternative value="excel">
                    <title>Excel 2013 and 2016 Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open the dataset, click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/excel/nightlight.xls" target="self"
                            >here</link> to download the file to your computer. Then find the
                        downloaded file and double-click it to open it in Excel. When Excel opens
                        you may have to enable editing.</p>

                    <p>To create a two-way table in Excel:</p>
                    <p>First we need to sort our data to make it easier to tabulate:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Type Control-A twice to select all of the data in the worksheet.</li>
                        <li>Choose <em>Sort &amp; Filter → Custom Sort</em> from the
                                <em>Editing</em> group in the <em>Home</em> tab.</li>
                        <li>In the pop-up window, make sure that <em>My data has headers</em> is
                            checked and then choose <em>light</em> from the pull-down menu next to
                                <em>Sort by</em>.</li>
                        <li>Click the <em>Add Level</em> button and then choose
                                <em>nearsightedness</em> from the pull-down menu next to <em>Sort
                                by</em> in the new row that was just added. Click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Now we'll create our two-way table. First we'll make the row and column
                        headings and then use Excel formulas to get the counts:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Pick a cell outside of the two columns of data, and type
                                <em>Statistic</em>. Then move to the right one cell and type
                                <em>No</em>, move right and type <em>Yes</em>, and move right and
                            type <em>Total</em> for our column headings.</li>
                        <li>For the row headings, start in the cell under <em>Statistic</em> and
                            type <em>lamp</em>, then move down one cell and type
                                <em>night-light</em>, move down and type <em>no light</em>, and move
                            down and type <em>Total</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now select the cell under <em>No</em> and to the right of <em>lamp</em>,
                            and type <em>=counta(B2:B35)</em>.</li>
                        <li>Move one cell to the right (under <em>Yes</em> and to the right of
                                <em>lamp</em>) and type <em>=counta(B36:B76)</em>. Repeat this for
                            each cell in the table, adjusting the data range appropriately.</li>
                        <li>To fill in the Total column you can use the <em>sum function</em>. For example,
                            to fill in the cell under Total and to the right of Lamp you could type
                            <em>=sum(F3,G3)</em> where F3 and G3 refer to the counts you calculated for Lamp
                            from before (your cell locations may be different based on where you put
                            your table in Excel).</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To create a table of conditional percentages, we'll make a new table
                        underneath the two way-table, and use the same row and column labels as the
                        two-way table.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Pick a cell underneath the two-way table, and type the same row and
                            column labels in that we used for the two-way table.</li>
                        <li>Now select the cell under <em>No</em> and to the right of <em>lamp</em>.
                            In this cell, we want the percentage of children who slept with a lamp
                            and did not develop nearsightedness. Thus, we want to divide the number
                            of children who slept with a lamp and did not develop nearsightedness by
                            the total number of children who slept with a lamp, and then multiply by
                            100 to convert to a percentage. The specific cell references depend on
                            where exactly you created your two-way table, but if cell location D2
                            represents the number of children who slept with a lamp and did not
                            develop nearsightedness, and cell location F2 represents the total
                            number of children who slept with a lamp, the formula would be
                                <em>=(D2/F2)*100</em>.</li>
                        <li>Calculate the percentages for the other cells in the same manner.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>
                <!--   <alternative value="excel2003">
                    <title>Excel 2003 Instructions</title>
                    <p>To open Excel with the data in the worksheet, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/excel/nightlight.xls" target="self"
                            >here</link> and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your
                        computer. Then find the downloaded file and double-click it to open it in
                        Excel.</p>
                    <p>To create a two-way table in Excel:</p>
                    <p>First we need to sort our data to make it easier to tabulate:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Type Control-A to select all of the data in the worksheet.</li>
                        <li>Choose <em>Data → Sort</em> from the menu bar.</li>
                        <li>In the pop-up window, under <em>Sort by</em> choose <em>light</em>,
                            under <em>Then by</em> choose <em>nearsightedness</em>, make sure
                                <em>Header row</em> is selected towards the bottom of the window,
                            and click <em>OK</em>.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Now we'll create our two-way table. First we'll make the row and column
                        headings and then use Excel formulas to get the counts:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Pick a cell outside of the two columns of data, and type
                                <em>Statistic</em>. Then move to the right one cell and type
                                <em>No</em>, move right and type <em>Yes</em>, and move right and
                            type <em>Total</em> for our column headings.</li>
                        <li>For the row headings, start in the cell under <em>Statistic</em> and
                            type <em>lamp</em>, then move down one cell and type
                                <em>night-light</em>, move down and type <em>no light</em>, and move
                            down and type <em>Total</em>.</li>
                        <li>Now select the cell under <em>No</em> and to the right of <em>lamp</em>,
                            and type <em>=counta(B2:B35)</em>.</li>
                        <li>Move one cell to the right (under <em>Yes</em> and to the right of
                                <em>lamp</em>) and type <em>=counta(B36:B76)</em>. Repeat this for
                            each cell in the table, adjusting the data range appropriately.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>To create a table of conditional percentages, we'll make a new table
                        underneath the two way-table, and use the same row and column labels as the
                        two-way table.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Pick a cell underneath the two-way table, and type the same row and
                            column labels in that we used for the two-way table.</li>
                        <li>Now select the cell under <em>No</em> and to the right of <em>lamp</em>.
                            In this cell, we want the percentage of children who slept with a lamp
                            and did not develop nearsightedness. Thus, we want to divide the number
                            of children who slept with a lamp and did not develop nearsightedness by
                            the total number of children who slept with a lamp, and then multiply by
                            100 to convert to a percentage. The specific cell references depend on
                            where exactly you created your two-way table, but if cell location D2
                            represents the number of children who slept with a lamp and did not
                            develop nearsightedness, and cell location F2 represents the total
                            number of children who slept with a lamp, the formula would be
                                <em>=(D2/F2)*100</em>.</li>
                        <li>Calculate the percentages for the other cells in the same manner.</li>
                    </ul>
                </alternative>-->
                <alternative value="ti">
                    <title>TI Instructions</title>
                    <p><em>Important Note!</em> TI 83/84 calculators do not have the built-in
                        capability to create a table of counts and percents or to construct a pie
                        chart. Thus, for this activity, we suggest trying one of the other
                        technologies available in OLI Statistics. <link
                            href="http://cran.r-project.org/">R</link> is an excellent statistical
                        package that is free to download and that is available for both Windows and
                        Mac OS X.</p>
                    <p>If you want to continue with the TI Calculator, you can produce a two-way
                        table by hand using your TI to help. </p>
                    <p>To open a group of lists with the night-light data loaded, right-click <link
                            href="../../../webcontent/ti/nightlight.8xg" target="self">here</link>
                        and choose "Save Target As" to download the file to your computer. Then find
                        the downloaded file and send it to your calculator. For instructions on how
                        to connect your calculator to your computer and transfer a file, click
                            <activity_link idref="ti_instructions" target="new"
                        >here</activity_link>.</p>
                    <p>You have stacked data in two lists: one for the explanatory variable <code
                            style="inline">Light</code>and one for the response variable <code
                            style="inline">Nearsightedness</code>. The explanatory variable is
                        sorted by category, and then the response variable has been sorted for each
                        category of the explanatory variable:</p>
                    <ul style="none">
                        <li>L1: Light (0 = no light, 1 = night-light, 2 = lamp). This list is
                            sorted.</li>
                        <li>L2: Nearsightedness (0 = No, 1 = Yes). This list is sorted separately
                            for each category of the explanatory variable <code style="inline"
                                >Light</code>.</li>

                    </ul>
                    <ul>
                        <li>To access one of the built-in lists, press <code>2ND</code> and then the
                            number of the list, followed by <code>ENTER</code>. For example, to
                            access L1, you would press <code>2ND/1/ENTER</code>.</li>
                        <li>Use the right and left arrows to scroll through the list.</li>
                        <li>You can also choose <code>Stat/Edit/1:Edit</code> to see the lists in
                            table form. You can scroll through the table using the arrow keys.</li>
                    </ul>


                    <p> For each category of the explanatory variable, count the data values in each
                        category of the response variable. </p>
                    <p>The page <activity_link target="new" idref="caseii2">Module 2, Case C → C (2
                            of 2)</activity_link> describes how to create a two-way table with
                        counts and with percentages. </p>
                </alternative>
            </alternatives>

        </pullout>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_casecc2_lbd_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_casecc2_lbd_tutor2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_casecc2_lbd_tutor3" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_casecc2_lbd_tutor4" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
