<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemIntroduction_5">
	<head>
		<title>Neuron Anatomy</title>
		<objref idref="neuron_anatomy_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Neurons are classified according to 2 different characteristics: their morphology
			(anatomical or structural features) and their function. Although we describe both here,
			the functional classification will be used predominantly in later units.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_5.jpg"
			alt="Neuron functions classified into motor and sensory">
			<caption>Neurons can be classified according to their
				function. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
		
		<p>Functional classification of neurons is based on the direction of information flow along
			axons relative to the CNS. Based on this criterion, there are 3 types of neurons:
			sensory neurons, interneurons, and motor neurons.</p>
		<p><term>Sensory (afferent) neurons</term> are specialized for detection of sensory
			information (e.g. light, pressure, vibration, temperature, chemicals, etc.). They
			transduce physical and chemical stimuli into electrical signals and transfer this
			information from the periphery towards the central nervous system for processing. In
			many cases, sensory neurons have their dendrites, soma and a part of their axon residing
			outside the CNS with axon terminals forming connections (synapses) with other neurons
			within the CNS.</p>
		<p><term>Interneurons (association neurons)</term> are located entirely within the
			central nervous system (with the dendrites, soma and axons of the cell all residing
			within the CNS). Interneurons are also referred to as association neurons, in part
			because they are sandwiched between sensory and motor neurons where they integrate and
			distribute sensory information and coordinate motor output. Interneurons account for 90%
			of all neurons of the CNS and therefore are the most numerous neurons in the body.
			Almost all interneurons are multipolar (see below).</p>
		<p><term>Motor (efferent) neurons</term> carry impulses or motor commands away from
			the central nervous system to effectors/target organs (e.g. muscles and glands). Most
			motor neurons have dendrites and cell bodies in the CNS and axons that exit the CNS to
			form peripheral nerves that travel to effectors (targets).</p>
		<p>The structural classification of neurons is based on the number of processes that extend
			from the soma. There are 4 basic neuronal structures like those shown in the figure
		below though there are many subtle variations on each theme.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_6.jpg"
			alt="Neuron structures classified into multipolar, bipolar, unipolar, and anaxonic" width="450">
			<caption>Neurons can be classified according to their
				structure. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
		<p><term>Bipolar neurons</term> have a single dendrite extending from one side of
			the cell body and a single axon extending from the other side. Bipolar neurons are small
			cells, typically extending for less than 30 microns from dendrite to axon terminal.
			There are not many true bipolar cells in the body. A few examples are found in the
			special sense organs for vision and olfaction (smell).</p>
		<p><term>Unipolar or pseudounipolar neurons</term> have a single process that
			emanates from the cell body. The single process has dendrites on one end and the rest of
			the process is an axon. Most sensory neurons of the peripheral nervous system are
			unipolar neurons. The dendrites are located in the periphery, where stimuli are
			detected. The sensory information travels on the dendrite toward the soma 
			(usually located ganglia just outside the CNS).. The axon stretches into the CNS at the spinal cord.</p>
		<p><term>Multipolar neurons</term> have two or more dendrites on one side and a
			single axon on the other side of the soma. Multipolar neurons are the most common
			neurons in the CNS. One example are motor neurons which have dendrites and somas located
			in the spinal cord and axons that leave the CNS to innervate skeletal muscles.</p>
		<p><term>Anaxonic neurons</term> are small, stellate (star-shaped) cells with
			processes that all look alike with no apparent axon. Anaxonic neurons can be found in
			the central nervous system, the retina, and in the adrenal medulla. Their functions are
			not well understood.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="neuron_anatomy_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"
			src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
			<param name="interfaceDescription"
				>../../webcontent/neuron_anatomy_layout.xml</param>
		</wb:inline>
		
		<wb:inline idref="neuron_anatomy_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
