<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSystemLOO_7"><head><title>Neuron Electrical Response</title><objref idref="explain_electrical_response_LO" /></head><body><p id="ad3e3ecaf5a24e4a982d0cfffd78afcd">Neurons can be excited by various stimuli such as light, chemicals, heat or pressure. These stimuli, which are typically received at the dendrites, cause small, localized changes in membrane voltage. The stimuli open ion channels in the membrane, which allows specific ions to flow in or out of the cell. This ion movement produces a change in the membrane voltage around the area of the open channels. These local shifts in membrane potential are called local (or graded) potentials. Local potentials have the following characteristics:</p><p id="ee2a614348e142c3b449b60ece2e9e97">They are <term>graded</term>, which means the change in membrane voltage that occurs is proportional to the size of the stimulus. A stronger stimulus can open more ion channels. A stimulus that lasts for a long time can either open more ion channels or keep channels open for a longer time. In either case, more ions are able to cross the cell membrane, which produces a larger change in membrane voltage.</p><p id="baaf999008824a16ab97c2abadc3945a">They are <term>decremental</term>, meaning that the signal grows weaker as it moves farther from the site of stimulation. Ion channels are opened at the site of stimulation and that is where ions move across the cell membrane. As a result, there is a high concentration of ions right around the ion channels. Once the ions cross the membrane, they diffuse away from the channel and there are fewer and fewer ions as they move away from the open channels. Fewer ions results in a smaller change in membrane potential.</p><p id="b4566bf683c04e15a614d6f153ad3d64">They are <term>reversible</term>. If the stimulus comes to an end, the ion channels close and resting membrane potential is re-established before the signal travels very far.</p><p id="f512bbdbd02445ab8bcebaf5269f99eb">They can either <em style="italic">excite the cell</em> or <em style="italic">inhibit the cell</em> depending on what type of ion channel is opened. If the stimulus opens a sodium channel, sodium enters the cell and <term>depolarizes</term> (make the membrane potential less negative) the membrane around the open channels. If the stimulus opens a chloride channel, chloride ions enter the cell and make the local membrane potential more negative than the RMP (<term>hyperpolarizes</term> the cell). Depolarization excites the cell and makes it more likely to send a signal to other cells. Hyperpolarization inhibits the cell and makes it less likely to send a signal to other cells.</p><p id="b96a9da6426e443ba9fd26dcaf07baa9">A stimulus can also affect potassium channels. If the stimulus causes potassium channels to open, the effect will be hyperpolarization of that area of cell membrane. Potassium leaves the cell through the open channels, which removes positive charges from the ICF making the inside of the cell more negative. If the stimulus closes potassium channels, the membrane will depolarize around the closed channels because fewer potassium ions are leaving the cell.</p><p id="bd7b0bef818241de9e867eeca6f583b6">Neurons generally receive multiple stimuli at the same time – some may be excitatory and others inhibitory. The overall response of the neuron will depend on the net effect of all the stimuli. In some cases, the neuron will produce a signal that will travel to other cells. In other cases, no signal will be sent from the neuron.</p></body></workbook_page>
