<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemIntroduction_6">
	<head>
		<title>Glial Cells</title>
		<objref idref="glial_types_LO"/>
		<objref idref="list_glial_cells_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Most neurons are surrounded by glial cells (neuroglia), the other cell type found in the
			nervous tissue. Glial cells are the supportive cells of the nervous system and are 10
			times more numerous than neurons. The most well defined role for neuroglia is to provide
			structure to the delicate nervous tissue. They fill the space between neurons, serving
			as mortar or “glue” and thus hold nervous tissue together. Unlike neurons, glial cells
			retain the ability to divide throughout one’s lifetime. When neurons are injured,
			neuroglia are stimulated to divide and form glial scars. Glial cells have different
			shapes and sizes and their processes are indistinguishable in contrast to the distinct
			axon and dendrites found in neurons.</p>
		<p>There are 6 types of glial cells, 4 types are found in the CNS and 2 types in the PNS.
			The CNS neuroglia are: <term>astrocytes</term>; <term>oligodendrocytes</term>; <term>microglia</term>, and <term>ependymal cells</term>. The 2 types of glia found only in the peripheral nervous
			system (PNS) are <term>satellite cells</term> and <term>Schwann
				cells</term>.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_7.jpg"
			alt="Descriptions of the 6 types of glial cells: 4 found in CNS
			and 2 in the PNS">
			<caption>There are 6 types of glial cells: 4 found in CNS
				and 2 in the PNS. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
<section>		
	<title>CNS Glial Cells</title>
	<body>
		<p><term>Astrocytes</term> are star-shaped neuroglia and are the most numerous cells in the central
		nervous system. They make up half of all cells in the brain. Astrocytes provide a
		structurally supportive framework for neurons with their processes wrapping most
		non-synaptic regions of neurons in gray matter and covering the entire outer surface of
		the brain to form the glial – pia (connective tissue meninx) interface. Astrocytes help
		form the protective blood-brain barrier by encircling CNS capillary endothelial cells
		and stimulating the cells to form tight-junctions. They help to maintain the
		concentration of chemicals in the extracellular space and remove excess signaling
		molecules. Astrocytes also react to neural tissue damage by forming scar tissue in the
		damaged space.</p>
	<!--Erin Czerwinski:Link to section on meninges-->
	<p><term>Oligodendrocytes</term> are glial cells of the CNS that wrap and insulate
		axons and give the CNS white matter its characteristic glossy, white appearance.
		Oligodendrocytes have a large soma with up to 15 processes. The processes reach out to
		axons of nearby neurons and wrap around them (like wrapping tape around a pencil)
		forming a high resistance sheath called <term>myelin</term>.
		Myelin insulates a small region of the axon (prevents ions from leaking out into
		the extracellular fluid), which facilitates signal propagation down the axon towards the
		synaptic terminal. A single oligodendrocyte’s processes will wrap axons of numerous
		different neurons. Processes from many different oligodendrocytes contribute to the
		myelin sheath of a single neuron’s axon.</p>
	<p><term>Microglia</term> are small highly mobile, phagocytic neuroglia that
		protect nervous tissue from pathogen infection, remove debris and waste, and may play a
		role in remodeling of the synapse that occurs during development and with learning.
		About 10-15% of CNS glial cells are microglia. Microglia are derived from monocytes and
		thus are more closely related to white blood cells than to the other glial cells. Since
		cells of the immune system cannot penetrate the blood brain barrier, microglia serve as
		brain macrophages, destroying foreign invaders, promoting inflammation and destroying
		cancer cells and cells infected with virus. Clusters of microglia in nervous tissue
		provide pathologists with evidence of recent injury.</p>
	<p><term>Ependymal cells</term> are cuboidal-shaped glial cells that are joined
		together to form a continuous sheet lining the fluid-filled ventricles and central canal
		of the brain and spinal cord. Ependymal cells produce and secrete cerebrospinal fluid
		(CSF), the fluid that bathes the tissues of the CNS. The basal side of the cell has
		rootlets that anchor the cells to the underlying tissue. The apical surface is marked by
		cilia, which helps circulate the CSF.</p>
	</body>
</section>
		
		
		
		<wb:inline idref="glial_types_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
		
		<section>
			<title>PNS Glial Cells</title>
			<body>
				<p>The remaining two glial cells, Schwann cells and satellite cells, are found solely in the
					peripheral nervous system.</p>
				<p>Schwann cells are analogous in function to oligodendrocytes (found
					in the CNS). They insulate the axons of peripheral nerves in one of two ways. A Schwann
					cell can wind its way round and round the axon (up to 100 times), while squeezing its
					cytoplasm out of the way (much like a toothpaste tube could be wrapped around a pencil),
					forming a myelin sheath. Like myelinating a single fiber in the CNS, which requires many
					oligodendrocytes, a complete myelin sheath in the PNS requires many Schwann cells.
					Schwann cells can also envelop PNS axons without forming a myelin sheath. Instead of
					wrapping a single axon many times, the Schwann cell forms an envelope around a bundle of
					unmyelinated axons.</p>
				<p>Additionally, Schwann cells can also assist in the regeneration of a damaged peripheral
					nerve. If a peripheral nerve is damaged, it may regenerate if its soma is undamaged and
					the <term>neurilemma</term> (the plasma membrane of the Schwann cell)
					enveloping it is intact.</p>
				<p>Satellite cells are found surrounding neural somas in peripheral
					<term>ganglia</term> (collections of cell bodies located outside the CNS).
					Satellite cells resemble CNS astrocytes and are thought to have similar functions,
					providing structural support and regulating the chemical environment.</p>				
				
			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="glial_types_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"
			src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
			<param name="interfaceDescription"
				>../../webcontent/glial_types_layout.xml</param>
		</wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="list_glial_cells_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<wb:inline idref="list_glial_cells_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
