<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemLOO_11">
	<head>
		<title>Synapse Transmission</title>
		<objref idref="explain_synapses_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="synapses_LO"/>
		<objref idref="synapse_events_LO"/>
		<objref idref="explain_ion_flux_LO"/>-->
		
	</head>
	<body>
	
		<p>There are two types of synapses found in your body: electrical and chemical. Electrical
			synapses allow the direct passage of ions and signaling molecules from cell to cell. In
			contrast, chemical synapses do not pass the signal directly from the presynaptic cell to
			the postsynaptic cell. In a chemical synapse, an action potential in the presynaptic
			neuron leads to the release of a chemical messenger called a <term>neurotransmitter</term>. The neurotransmitter then diffuses across the synapse and
			binds to receptors on the postsynaptic cell. Binding of the neurotransmitter leads to
			the production of an electrical signal in the postsynaptic cell.</p>
		<p>Why does the body have two types of synapses? Each type of synapse has functional
			advantages and disadvantages. An electrical synapse passes the signal very quickly,
			which allows groups of cells to act in unison. A chemical synapse takes much longer to
			transmit the signal from one cell to the next; however, chemical synapses allow neurons 
			to integrate information from multiple presynaptic neurons, determining whether or 
			not the postsynaptic cell will continue to propagate the signal. Neurons respond differently 
			based on information transmitted by multiple chemical synapses.  Let’s take a
			closer look at the structure and function of each type of synapse.</p>
		<p><term>Electrical synapses</term> transmit action potentials via the direct flow
			of electrical current at <term>gap junctions</term>. Gap junctions are formed
			when two adjacent cells have transmembrane pores that align. The membranes of the two
			cells are linked together and the aligned pores form a passage between the cells.
			Consequently, several types of molecules and ions are allowed to pass between the cells.
			Due to the direct flow of ions and molecules from one cell to another, electrical
			synapses allow bidirectional flow of information between cells. Gap junctions are
			crucial to the functioning of the <term>cardiac myocytes</term> and smooth muscles.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_48.jpg" alt="Structure of an electrical synapse (gap junction), with connections and channels.">
			<caption>Structure of an electrical synapse (gap junction). By (<link
					href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b/b7/Gap_cell_junction-en.svg/500px-Gap_cell_junction-en.svg.png"
					>https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b/b7/Gap_cel_junction-en.svg/500px-Gap_cell_junction-en.svg.png</link>).</caption>
		</image>

		
		<p><term>Chemical synapses</term> comprise most of the synapses in your body. In a
			chemical synapse, a <term>synaptic gap</term> or <term>cleft</term>
			separates the <term>pre-</term> and the <term>postsynaptic</term>
			cells. An action potential propagated to the axon terminal results in the secretion
			of chemical messengers, called neurotransmitters, from the axon
			terminals. The neurotransmitter molecules diffuse across the synaptic cleft and bind to receptor proteins on the cell membrane
			of the postsynaptic cell. Binding of the neurotransmitter to the
			receptors on the postsynaptic cell leads to a transient change in the postsynaptic
			cell’s membrane potential.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_49.jpg" alt="Structure of an chemical synapse, with a presynaptic neuron and close-up of the membrane.">
			<caption>Structure of a chemical synapse.  (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
		
		<p>The process of synaptic transmission at a chemical synapse between
			two neurons follows these steps:</p>
		<p>An action potential, propagating along the axon of a presynaptic neuron, arrives at the
			axon terminal.</p>
		<p>The depolarization of the <term>axolemma</term> (the plasma membrane of the
			axon) at the axon terminal opens Ca<sup>2+ </sup>channels and Ca<sup>2+ </sup>diffuses
			into the axon terminal.</p>
		<!--<p>Calcium ions cause exocytosis of neurotransmitter into the synaptic cleft.</p>-->
		<p>Ca<sup>2+ </sup>bind with <term>calmodulin</term>, the ubiquitous intracellular
			calcium receptor, causing the <term>synaptic vesicles</term> to migrate to and
			fuse with the presynaptic membrane.</p>
		<p>The neurotransmitter is released into the synaptic cleft by the process of <term>exocytosis</term>.</p>
		<p>The neurotransmitter diffuses across the synaptic cleft and binds
			with <term>receptors</term> on the postsynaptic membrane.</p>
		<p>Binding of the neurotransmitters to the postsynaptic receptors causes a response in the
			postsynaptic cell.</p>
		<p>The response can be of two kinds:</p>
		<ol>
			<li>A neurotransmitter may bind to a receptor that is associated with a specific ion-channel
			which, when opened, allows for diffusion of an ion through the channel. If Na<sup>+
			</sup>channels are opened, Na<sup>+ </sup>rapidly diffuses into the postsynaptic cell
			and depolarizes the membrane towards the threshold for an action potential. If K<sup>+
			</sup>channels are opened, K<sup>+ </sup>diffuses out of the cell, depressing the
			membrane polarity below its resting potential (hyperpolarization). If Cl<sup>-
			</sup>channels are opened, Cl<sup>- </sup>moves into the cell leading to
			hyperpolarization. </li>
			<li>The neurotransmitter may bind to a transmembrane receptor protein, causing it to activate
				a G-protein on the inside surface of the postsynaptic membrane. A cascade of events
				leads to the appearance of a second messenger (calcium ion, cyclic AMP (cAMP), or
				IP<sub>3</sub>) in the cell. Second messengers can have diverse effect on the cell
				ranging from opening an ion channel to changing cell metabolism to initiating
				transcription of new proteins.</li>
		</ol>
		
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body><wb:inline idref="synapses_sc3" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="synapses_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="synapse_events_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline></body></section>
		
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body><wb:inline idref="synapses_sc2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		<!--<wb:inline idref="synapses_sc" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>-->
		<wb:inline idref="synapses_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
				<wb:inline idref="synapses_sc4" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>	
			</body></section>
		
		
		
		
		<!--<p><em style="bold">Concept Check. [LO: The process involved in release of neurotransmitters
			form axon terminal]</em></p>
			<p>What type of channels are the calcium channels on the axon terminal? [hint: Why do the
			Ca<sup>++</sup>-channels open?]</p>
		<p>Ligand gated</p>
		<p>Voltage gated</p>
		<p>Mechanically gated</p>
		<p>Photon gated</p>-->
		
		
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
