<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSystemIntroduction_4"><head><title>Neurons</title><objref idref="describe_neuron_LO" /></head><body><p id="b40b01985a6042eba082f93c60a12038">Neurons are considered the simplest functional unit of nervous tissue. They are long-lived (most live for your entire life), electrically active cells that consume a lot of energy. Neurons are capable of responding to stimulation, conducting electrical signals, and secreting chemicals that allow them to communicate with other cells. They cannot usually regenerate if damaged since most neurons do not retain the ability to divide. Neurons have anatomically and functionally distinct regions for receiving, integrating and sending information from one part of the body to another.</p><image id="b64010c43a16441fb859933d597caeca" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_3.jpg" alt="Neuron regions - nucleus, Axon, Schwann cell, Myelin sheath, Node of Ranvier, Terminals" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><caption><p id="ce2d217d229c4ae2993da59d6c2779ae">Like epithelia, neurons are polarized with anatomically and chemically distinct regions. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c8b1e7e9dbd94b258f3dfcfbcf89df67">A typical neuron, like that shown above, has two distinct processes or cytoplasmic extensions on either side of a soma (cell body). On one side of the soma are short, tapering processes called <term>dendrites</term> (Greek, dendreon – tree). Most neurons have many, highly branched dendrites, although they may have as few as one. Dendrites receive information from other neurons and transfer it to the cell body. The greater the number of dendrites, the more information the neuron can collect to use during decision making.</p><p id="d2501cd44d444044a25c5346b8c90016">The <term>soma (cell body)</term> is the region of the neuron that integrates all the incoming information from the dendrites. The cell body is somewhat spherical in shape and for humans, typically ranges in size from 5 – 100 microns in diameter. The soma contains the neuron’s nucleus and housekeeping organelles (e.g. mitochondria, lysosomes, Golgi complex, rough endoplasmic reticulum, etc.). The soma is the only site in a neuron that can synthesize proteins, neurotransmitters, or materials needed for cell maintenance and repair. The soma is similar to the dendrites in that it can also receive inputs from other neurons. The incoming information is coded as electrical signals that are integrated to determine what, if any, response is required. If the incoming signal is large enough, it travels to the process on the other side of the soma called the <term>axon</term>. If the incoming signal is small, it dies out before it reaches the axon.</p><p id="ef77236aee4f48c3947435cb8d6cbcab">The axon functions like a cable, relaying electrical signals away from the cell body towards other neurons or cells (e.g. muscles, glands). Axons are also called nerve fibers. The axon has three regions. As it emerges from the cell body, the axon forms a structure called the <term>axon hillock</term>, a tapered region that contains the <term>initial segment</term>, or <term>trigger zone</term>, where propagating electrical signals called action potentials are initiated or generated. The next part of the axon is the longest, typically a single, thin (.5 - 3 microns), almost constant diameter process that extends to a target. Axons can be long, short or in between.</p><example id="e6e6de3b57df4ab5a44ef56f47c55e9f"><title>Title</title><p id="cc70d0006f914d0ab6e67f9e62c9b437">For example, neurons that command the big toe muscles to contract have dendrites and cell bodies in the spinal cord and axons that leave the vertebral column to travel the length of the leg to the big toe. For a 7 foot tall basketball player, the axon that controls the big toe might be 3 feet long. On the other hand, short axons (a few microns long) are found on interneurons, neurons that have all processes within the CNS and nearby targets.</p></example><p id="d8b2b0bca9534c5dbbcac7d7e19698fc">The axon may travel to its target as a single fiber, but some axons form branches called collaterals, so that they can interact with not just one, but many target cells. The third region of the axon is found when it reaches its target. Here the axon branches extensively forming the <term>synaptic terminals</term> (<term>terminal arborization</term>). Each branch ends with a small swelling called a <term>synaptic knob</term>, which contains vesicles filled with chemical messengers (<term>neurotransmitters</term>) that conduct the signal to the next cell.</p><wb:inline idref="describe_neuron_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="describe_neuron_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
