<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemLOO_12">
	<head>
		<title>Neurotransmitter Effects</title>
		<objref idref="explain_neurotransmitters_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>The response of the postsynaptic cell to a neurotransmitter depends on the specific
			receptors that are present on its cell membrane. Most neurotransmitters can bind to more
			than one receptor found in the body and the cell’s response is dependent on which
			receptor is bound. Different receptors produce different cellular responses because they
			activate processes in the cell.</p>
		<example>
			<title>Cholinergic Receptors</title>
			<p>Let’s look at an example. Receptors that can bind the neurotransmitter acetylcholine
			(ACh) are termed cholinergic receptors – this is the type of receptor. There is more
			than one cholinergic receptor – the different cholinergic receptors are termed subtypes.
			One subtype, the nicotinic cholinergic receptor, opens a sodium channel when it binds
			ACh. Stimulation of a nicotinic cholinergic receptor leads to depolarization of the
			cell. Another subtype, the muscarinic cholinergic receptor, opens a potassium channel
			when it binds ACh. Stimulation of a muscarinic cholinergic receptor leads to cell
			hyperpolarization. Acetylcholine can either excite or inhibit the postsynaptic cell
			depending on whether that cell has the nicotinic or muscarinic receptor subtype.</p>
		
			<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_50.jpg" alt="Cholinergic receptors that open ion channels cause changes
				in membrane potential." width="400">
				<caption>Cholinergic receptors that open ion channels cause changes
					in membrane potential. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
					Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
						href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
						>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
			</image>
			</example>
		<p>In the example we just considered, both receptor subtypes were linked to distinct ion
			channels. It is also possible for one receptor subtype to be linked to an ion channel
			while another subtype leads to the production of a second messenger. In this case, the
			timing of the postsynaptic cell’s response is different. Opening an ion channel takes
			very little time compared to the complex signaling that occurs with a second messenger.
			The response is fast with a receptor linked to an ion channel and is slow with a
			receptor that leads to a second messenger cascade. Although slower, second messenger
			cascades can produce more diverse cellular effects and have the advantage of amplification.
			Binding of a single molecule of neurotransmitter can produce many molecules of the
			second messenger. In contrast, if the receptor opens an ion channel, a single molecule
			of neurotransmitter (or sometimes two molecules) is needed to open a single ion channel
			in the postsynaptic cell.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_51.jpg" alt="A receptor that produces a second messenger in the
			postsynaptic cell. Second messengers can lead to a wide range of effects in the
			postsynaptic cell." width="400">
			<caption>A receptor that produces a second messenger in the
				postsynaptic cell. Second messengers can lead to a wide range of effects in the
				postsynaptic cell. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_neurotransmitters_excite_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_neurotransmitters_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
