<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSystemLOO_6"><head><title>Neuron Resting Membrane Potential</title><objref idref="explain_resting_potential_LO" /></head><body><p id="c25ba84e514f4c47a121a5c300b4836d">The resting membrane potential arises due to the combined effects of three factors, which determine what ions move across the cell membrane in an unstimulated cell (at rest).</p><p id="f4951a4b4ca14f89af1914d467e08d0e">Ions are not evenly distributed between the inside and the outside of a cell. As we just learned, sodium is nearly 10 times more concentrated outside the cell than inside. Conversely, potassium is nearly 30 times more concentrated inside the cell than outside. The uneven distribution of ions leads to concentration gradients across the cell membrane. Given the opportunity, ions will move down their concentration gradient (i.e., from an area where they are highly concentrated to an area where they are less concentrated). So, given the chance, sodium ions would move into the cell and potassium ions would move out of the cell based on their respective concentration gradients.</p><p id="f71d646e310a43b59b95ed73e2ff1c14">The ionic composition of body fluids is tightly regulated. Small increases or decreases in ion concentrations can disrupt normal functions of the brain, heart, skeletal muscle or other organs. In many instances, you or one of your loved ones may need to receive treatment for an electrolyte imbalance. These situations might be as simple as that restoring blood lost in an accident, or receiving fluids to rehydrate you following a soccer tournament. The article below shows how critically important it is that people receive solutions with appropriate ion concentrations in their treatments.</p><example id="f8aa411ac7974fcda39e1ea6559d1470"><p id="edf1f709e3704b149a90671531edfd06">Let’s review a tragic case where simple calculations to double check a dose of CaCl<sub>2 </sub>given to a baby to restore body fluids, might have saved her life. </p><p id="b053cc1781bd4af3955926a6d0eeea41"><em style="emphasis">Baby dies at Seattle Children&apos;s hospital after overdose</em></p><p id="d2d3b952a4224fcd945630e5dbd5e5c9">An infant in the intensive-care unit of Seattle Children&apos;s hospital died after she was administered 10 times the dose of a medication, calcium chloride, by a hospital nurse, according to a notice sent by hospital CEO Tom Hansen to the staff.</p><p id="bdf6e8d7639142e3a271f4ccdcf4fd1b">By Carol M. Ostrom, Seattle Times health reporter</p><p id="e34afe247d23478cb126925965c42620">Eight-month-old Kaia Zautner was in the intensive-care unit of Seattle Children&apos;s hospital, battling back from serious heart problems and surgeries, when a hospital nurse gave her 10 times the proper dose of a medication, calcium chloride.</p><p id="ead15d53abae464c9800dead8c2e5929">Five days later, on Sept. 19, after suffering a brain hemorrhage, the baby died.</p><p id="c26d9b8b3a5e43418477384dc870bb50">Tom Hansen, hospital CEO, in a notice to staff on Sept. 22, said the hospital has offered &quot;heartfelt apologies&quot; to the family, without naming them. &quot;This was a catastrophic outcome for the patient and the family, and caused serious distress for staff members as well,&quot; Hansen said.</p><p id="e1a9f23194d34703892a291b50bd07c0">In a family blog, Kaia&apos;s parents, Jared and Alana Zautner, of Puyallup, had described their baby&apos;s fight to overcome the heart problem she&apos;d had since her birth on Jan. 12 and then, just days after her &quot;8th month birthday,&quot; the &quot;horrible turn of events&quot; that gave them &quot;one of the scariest days of our lives.&quot;</p><p id="f74dfd135b1f4fc787da8aa3ad0a19ef">The overdose was an accidental miscalculation, Alana Zautner wrote on the blog, thanking friends for their continued prayers.</p><p id="e63e44fde749489da641a5d00eb324a5">&quot;I have seen such strength in my daughter these last few hours and I have faith that she will pull through this,&quot; she wrote. &quot;I just pray for a miracle and that she will be completely touched and healed.&quot;</p><p id="a9e3b545308544ce865bae924e7ed05b">A memorial for Kaia was held Saturday at Lighthouse Christian Center (Alana wrote that all doctors and nurses were welcome), and a &quot;Hawaii Lei Ceremony and Scattering of the Ashes&quot; is planned for Oct. 2 on Maui, Hawaii.</p><p id="cbee9622c8054e51990780fb5d88b832">The hospital, as required, reported the overdose to the state Department of Health, which collects statistics on &quot;adverse events&quot; in hospitals.</p><p id="c56e52df42d3472594cbcdb205ac9665">The hospital reviewed the clinical record after the overdose and began a detailed analysis of why the usual safety checks had not prevented it, Hansen said in the letter to staff.</p><p id="d02e7317294243a28a5d63049534ca21">&quot;Perhaps the best tribute we can pay to this family is by doing everything we can to prevent future medical errors in our system,&quot; Hansen said in the letter. &quot;An important way we can make medicine safer is if we admit that mistakes occur and openly investigate them. We must learn from these events and work together to evaluate our processes and to error-proof our care processes.&quot;</p><p id="a201c16682af4e73acbf30bf16e199e4">Hansen said it is personally important to him that all staff and faculty feel safe to report mistakes.</p><p id="a9cce040991d4c788b56233fd712a4b2">While the investigation is under way, he said, the hospital will allow only pharmacists and anesthesiologists to fill needles with calcium chloride in nonemergency situations, but the drug can still be accessed by medical or nursing staff if needed in an emergency.</p><p id="e43d23b963dd462c9a179267f8b0e007">Hansen did not say whether the nurse who administered the overdose was disciplined by the hospital.</p><p id="f54948f714ed44f6ad7260b9223bc32c">The state&apos;s Nursing Care Quality Assurance Commission has also opened an investigation, according to Department of Health spokesman Tim Church.</p><p id="be21c9b776964206981b9ea832b341dd">&quot;We don&apos;t even have a name yet,&quot; he said. &quot;The nursing commission is opening (the investigation) because it&apos;s aware of the situation — not under any particular name.&quot;</p><p id="a783604d2ace4bb88d609d0cc4648996">The hospital will have 45 days to complete a &quot;root cause&quot; analysis of the event, Church said, but that report will not be publicly available.</p><p id="ea1b031505a64b809273c28da6c74a15">In 2009, a 15-year-old Kent boy died after using a painkilling patch prescribed by his dentist at Children&apos;s. The boy, Michael Blankenship, had four teeth extracted at the hospital and was sent home with the pain patch containing Fentanyl, prescribed by his dentist at the hospital. The teen was found dead the next morning.</p><p id="a126819f68c14ea1a85b6826428257f7">The teen was autistic and could not tolerate pills or liquid medicine.</p><p id="de4781b393604e788220a2772e18a215">The hospital&apos;s medical director said the highly potent narcotics patch should not have been prescribed.</p><p id="d0da615c02d14a22b1cccce32306f7ec">His family filed a lawsuit against the hospital last September.</p><p id="e87fc53dc0824403819cfe2c9327a14b">Update, 11:32a.m., Sept. 29: The family reached a settlement earlier this year, but didn&apos;t disclose the terms</p><p id="af819c016d0d24b8683d1c0b2471ac49d">Source:</p><p id="acf24a8e1432c49989ced208326c97696">Seattle Times, January 2013</p></example><p id="c8a0a1500a174d56a714cde0aa6515af">However, the cell membrane is not freely permeable to ions. Ions cannot freely cross the plasma membrane because of its structure. The lipid core of the cell membrane is hydrophobic and does not allow charged molecules to pass through it. Rather the cell membrane is selectively permeable, meaning it allows certain ions to pass. You know that the ions do not pass directly through the cell membrane, but rather pass through ion channels. The membrane is permeable to a specific ion if there are open channels for that ion. Recall that ion channels open and close based on the presence of electrical or chemical stimuli. Voltage-gated channels open at specific membrane potentials and are either inactivated (while the stimulus persists) or close when the membrane potential changes. Ligand-gated channels open when they bind chemicals and close when the chemical is no longer bound.</p><p id="fdf3d44a30e544a0b223aabe354dd170">At rest, the cell membrane is most permeable to potassium because there are more open potassium channels at the resting membrane potential than channels for any other ion. As a result, potassium “leaks” out of the resting cell. The resting membrane is less permeable to sodium, and, at rest, a small amount of sodium “leaks” into the cell.</p><p id="f32a46edb8054981a4df77c2a20ec93f">If these were the only things happening in the resting cell, the resting membrane potential would not be stable, but rather the net movement of potassium ions would cause the membrane potential to change. Ions move not only based on their individual concentration gradients, but they also move based on charge attraction and repulsion. Ions move away from like charges (ex. sodium and potassium ions move away from each other) and move towards opposite charges (ex. potassium ions would move toward chloride ions). The net movement of a particular ion is influenced by its <term>electrochemical gradient</term> (the balance of its concentration gradient and any charge attraction or repulsion).</p><example id="cecf7497b15542edbed4a5f17241c0ea"><title>Electrochemical Gradient</title><p id="cfdd139ebe224bb0aea0030a3f568ff3">Let’s consider how the electrochemical gradient affects a potassium ion. You’ve already learned that the RMP ranges from -60 mV to -90 mV in living cells. The negative sign indicates that the inside of the cell is negatively charged with respect to the outside. You also know that potassium is 30 times more concentrated on the inside of the cell than the outside. So, the concentration gradient causes potassium ions to leave the cell (through open ion channels), but the electrical gradient causes the positively charged potassium ion to be attracted to re-enter the cell. As a result, potassium ions not only leave the cell at rest (due to the concentration gradient), but they also re-enter the cell (due to the electrical gradient). The overall movement of the ion depends on the strength of each of the two gradients. The concentration gradients are stronger in a resting cell; therefore, more ions will move in the direction favored by the concentration gradient than will move based on the electrical gradient.</p></example><p id="b841650b63b04934be378f4eb2bbb7a1">One final factor also plays a role in determining the RMP. The sodium potassium pump operates continually in living cells. At maximum capacity, it pumps 3 sodium ions out of the cell and 2 potassium ions into the cell, and hydrolyzes 1 ATP to provide the energy for the ion transport.</p><image id="f8bc4f1508de4b1a96de01c670f13d1a" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_42.jpg" alt="Both ions are moved against their    electrochemical gradients, so the transport requires hydrolysis of 1 ATP. Because an    unequal number of charges are transported across the cell membrane, there is a net    negative charge on the inside of the membrane due to the operation of the sodium    potassium pump." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><caption><p id="d3069c83bcbf45e6b0d352045e1826fa">The sodium potassium pump transports 3 Na<sup>+ </sup>to the ECF and 2 K<sup>+ </sup>to the ICF. By Mariana Ruiz Villarreal (<link href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a5/scheme_sodium-potassium_pump-en.svg/300px-scheme_sodium-potassium_pump-en.svg.png" target="new" internal="false">http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a5/scheme_sodium-potassium_pump-en.svg/300px-scheme_sodium-potassium_pump-en.svg.png</link>) Public Domain.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d34223e2a0e44c15b74e385923530e1f">The sodium potassium pump is <term>electrogenic</term> (there are an uneven number of charges transported into and out of the cell resulting in a net charge associated with each exchange cycle). Since 3 sodium ions leave the cell and only 2 potassium ions enter the cell, there is a net negative charge on the inside of the cell due to the sodium potassium pump.</p></body></workbook_page>
