<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemLOO_14">
	<head>
		<title>Neurotransmitters Classes</title>
		<objref idref="identify_neuro_classes_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Neurotransmitters are organic molecules that allow neurons to communicate
			with each other and with target cells. Neurotransmitters fall into four classes based on
			their chemical makeup.</p>
		<p><term>Acetylcholine (ACh)</term> is a small molecule formed from acetate and
			choline. It is in a class by itself. Acetylcholine is the sole neurotransmitter used at
			the neuromuscular junction and is also the neurotransmitters used by the parasympathetic
			nervous system.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Acetylcholine.png" alt="The molecular structure of acetylcholine, pointing out the choline and acetyl groups of the molecule." width="400">
			<caption>The structure of acetylcholine.</caption>
		</image>
		
		<p>Some amino acids act as neurotransmitters. Glycine and
			γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA) are the most common inhibitory neurotransmitters in the
			spinal cord and brain, respectively. Glutamate (glutamic acid) and aspartate are
			excitatory neurotransmitters found in the brain and spinal cord, respectively.</p>
		
		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_54.jpg" alt="The molecular structures of various amino acid neurotransmitters - GABA, Glycine, Asparticacid, and Glutamic acid.">
			<caption>The structures of amino acid neurotransmitters. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->
	
		
		<p><term>Biogenic amines</term> (monoamines) are formed from amino acids from which
			the carboxyl terminus is removed. Three of the biogenic amines, called the <term>catecholamines</term>, are grouped together as they are all derived from
			the same amino acid, L-tyrosine. The catecholamines include: <term>norepinephrine</term> (noradrenalin), <term>epinephrine</term> (adrenalin)
			and <term>dopamine</term> (dopamine can also be made from phenylalanine).
			Norepinephrine (NE) is the neurotransmitter of the sympathetic nervous system (your
			fight or flight response). Epinephrine (E) has similar effects to NE, but is less
			abundant. Dopamine is best known for its role in motor inhibition. Loss of dopamine
			producing neurons in Parkinson disease leads to dyskinesias (movement disorders).
			Catecholamines bind to adrenergic receptors. Other biogenic amines include serotonin and
			histamine.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_54.jpg" alt="The molecular structures of various amino acid and biogenic amine
			neurotransmitters - Epinephrine, Norepinephrine, Dopamine, Serotonin, Histamine." width="450">
			<caption>The structures of the biogenic amine
				neurotransmitters. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
		<p><term>Neuropeptides</term> are small proteins that function as
			neurotransmitters. They are the largest neurotransmitters and can range from just a
			couple of amino acids to as many as 40. An example of neuropeptide neurotransmitters is
			β-endorphin, the chemical associated with the elevated mood experienced with
			exercise.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_55.jpg" alt="Molecular examples of neuropeptide neurotransmitters - Enkephalin, Substance P, Cholecystokinin, B-endorphin." width="450">
			<caption>Examples of neuropeptide neurotransmitters. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
	<!--	<p><em style="bold">Did I get this?</em></p>
		<p>In the brain, the major excitatory neurotransmitter is _______, and the major inhibitory
			neurotransmitter is ___________</p>
		<p><em style="bold">Glutamate; GABA</em> (Correct)</p>
		<p>GABA; Glutamate (wrong)</p>
		<p>Noradrenaline; Neuropeptides (wrong)</p>
		<p>Neuropeptides; Noradrenaline (wrong)</p>-->
	</body>
</workbook_page>
