<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemLOO_9">
	<head>
		<title>Action Potential Refractory Period</title>
		<objref idref="explain_action_potential_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="explain_refractory_LO"/>
		<objref idref="explain_all_actionpot_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The duration of time that the membrane is hyperpolarized following an action potential is
			termed its <term>refractory period</term>. The refractory period is an interval
			of time during which that part of the membrane cannot be excited (to produce another
			action potential) or requires a larger than normal stimulus to be excited. The
			refractory period is divided into two parts based on whether or not the membrane can be
			stimulated to produce an action potential. During the <term>absolute
				refractory period</term>, the membrane cannot be stimulated to produce another action
			potential regardless of the strength of the stimulus. During the <term>relative refractory period</term>, the membrane can be stimulated to produce an
			action potential, but a stronger than normal stimulus is required.</p>
		
		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_45.jpg"
			alt="Note how the
			membrane excitability changes from the resting state through the duration of the action
			potential. The change in excitability is related to the states of the ion channels.">
			<caption>The absolute and relative refractory periods. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->
		
		
		<p>The absolute refractory period lasts from the beginning of the action potential (when the
			membrane reaches the threshold voltage) until the fast Na<sup>+ </sup>channels reset to
			their resting state. As long as the Na<sup>+ </sup>channels are open or inactivated, a
			new action potential cannot be generated.</p>
		<p>The relative refractory period continues from the end of the absolute refractory period
			until the membrane is no longer hyperpolarized (returns to the resting membrane
			potential). During hyperpolarization, slow K<sup>+ </sup>channels are still open, but
			are in the process of closing. In order to stimulate an action potential during this
			time, a very strong stimulus is needed to overcome the effect of potassium flowing out
			of the cell and depolarize the cell.</p>
		<p>Previously, we considered the characteristics of local potentials. They are graded,
			decremental, reversible, and can either excite or inhibit the membrane. In contrast,
			action potentials are all-or-none, nondecremental, irreversible and always
			excitatory.</p>
		<p>Action potentials within a particular cell are all identical regardless of stimulus
			strength. If the membrane at the trigger zone reaches the threshold voltage or a voltage
			above the threshold, a maximal action potential will be generated. If the threshold
			voltage is not attained, no action potential is generated (no signal is propagated). In
			this way, action potentials are <term>all-or-none</term> – a cell either fires
			a full action potential or no action potential at all.</p>
		<p>The action potential at the axon terminal looks exactly like the action potential that
			was initially generated at the trigger zone. Since the signal does not change as it
			travels the length of the axon it is <term>nondecremental</term>. It should be
			noted that the action potential at the axon terminal is not the same one that originated
			at the trigger zone. Rather, a series of identical action potentials are generated as
			the signal travels toward the axon terminal.</p>
		<p>If the membrane reaches threshold, an action potential will be initiated and the signal
			will be propagated down the entire axon. Once the events are set in motion there is no
			stopping them. The process is <term>irreversible</term>.</p>
		<p>In contrast to local potentials, which can either excite or inhibit the membrane, action
			potentials are all excitatory (cause an initial depolarization of the membrane).</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="explain_all_actionpot_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_all_actionpot_sc" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
		<!--<p><em style="bold">Table Caption: </em>Summary of the characteristics of local potentials
			versus action potentials.</p>-->
	</body>
</workbook_page>
