<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSystemIntroduction_3"><head><title>Nervous Levels of Organization</title><objref idref="classify_cns_pns_LO" /></head><body><p id="c82dd62431a4462490be3cb0215177f6">The nervous system consists of two major divisions:</p><ol id="ee206c776a644630a74638e093cfc775"><li><p id="ac32a15b2b5b64a1bb1320652866eea0d">The central nervous system (CNS) consists of the brain and the spinal cord, which are enclosed in the skull and vertebral column, respectively.</p></li><li><p id="ae848b0a2a139426098376519c8629423">The peripheral nervous system (PNS) consists of all the neural tissue outside of the brain and spinal cord. The PNS includes the cranial nerves and spinal nerves, sensory receptors and ganglia (cell bodies (somas) of neurons that lie outside the CNS). The nerves connect all other parts of the body with the CNS.</p></li></ol><image id="af13e20f96ac47fea85773650dcb6c63" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_1.jpg" alt="Divisions of the Nervous System into CNS and PNS" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><caption><p id="e8b0b17a7be3409b8bc8ca2978a11486">Divisions of the Nervous System. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="e2677c7246554db79cf9155f3838d87d">The peripheral nervous system has several subdivisions. It is first divided based on function into sensory (afferent) and motor (efferent) divisions. Each of these is further subdivided into somatic and autonomic (visceral) divisions.</p><image id="b046e3685c8a4ae587f3eb32c184509a" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_2.jpg" alt="Subdivisions of the Nervous System and explainations of each" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="f606bb636628458a870aed0c404431e1">Subdivisions of the Nervous System.This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="e71631af5ac849369fa94877b0fd9629">The nerves that comprise the peripheral nervous system can be divided into two divisions based on whether information is traveling into the CNS or information is leaving the CNS. The <term>sensory division</term> of the PNS contains nerves carrying sensory information into the CNS. These sensory nerves are also called <term>afferents</term> (carrying toward). The <term>motor division </term>contains nerves carrying information out of the CNS to target organs. These motor nerves are also called <term>efferents</term> (carrying away).</p><p id="b3dc27db6f694dca9571cd5755adc560">The <term>sensory (afferent)</term> division of the PNS has two subdivisions. The <term>somatic sensory division</term> conducts signals from receptors located in the skeletal muscles and skin. The <term>visceral</term> or <term>autonomic sensory division</term> conducts signals predominantly from organs contained in the thoracic and abdominopelvic cavities (ex. heart, lungs, intestines, bladder, etc.).</p><p id="e2da192ed40342d784b7af6d4ef0411b">The <term>motor (efferent)</term> division of the PNS is also subdivided into somatic and visceral divisions. The <term>somatic motor division</term> controls the voluntary actions of the skeletal muscles in the body. The <term>visceral motor division</term>, more commonly called the <term>autonomic nervous system</term>, controls the actions of cardiac muscle, smooth muscle, and glands. The responses in these targets are usually involuntary.</p><p id="dc7de6d5061f4bf68fda786fab37c20a">The autonomic nervous system (ANS) is further subdivided into the <term>sympathetic division</term> and the <term>parasympathetic division</term>. Generally, the sympathetic division is involved in getting the body ready to respond to a physical challenge or an emotional threat, classified historically as the “fight or flight” division of the ANS. The parasympathetic division functions in opposition to the sympathetic nervous system. It is responsible for &quot;rest and digest&quot; activities, and is involved in salivation, digestion, urination and defecation.</p><wb:inline idref="classify_cns_pns_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="classify_cns_pns_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
