<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<item ident="questionid" title="_u4_m3_digtutor7a">
  <presentation>
    <material>
      <mattext texttype="text/plain">(a) Place the flags 1 standard deviation on either side of the mean. What is the area between these two values? What does the standard deviation rule say this area is?
        
        (b) Repeat for 2 and 3 standard deviations on either side of the mean. Again, compare the standard deviation rule with the area given in the applet.
      </mattext></material>
    <response_str ident="Short answer 1">
      <render_fib fibtype="String" prompt="Box">
        <response_label ident="Res 1"/></render_fib></response_str></presentation>
  <resprocessing>
    <outcomes/>
    <respcondition>
      <conditionvar>
        <other/></conditionvar>
      <displayfeedback linkrefid="Feedback always"/></respcondition></resprocessing>
  <itemfeedback ident="solution">
    <solution>
      <solutionmaterial>
        <material>
          <mattext texttype="text/plain">(a) According to the applet, the exact probability that a normal random variable will get a value that is within 1 standard deviation of its mean is <!--0.6826-->0.6827, which is pretty close to what the standard deviation rule tells us (0.68).
            
            (b) According to the applet, the exact probability that a normal random variable will get a value that is within 2 standard deviations of its mean is <!--0.9544-->0.9555, which again is pretty close to what the standard deviation rule tells us (0.95).
            
            Also, according to the applet, the exact probability that a normal random variable will get a value that is within 3 standard deviations of its mean is <!--0.9974-->0.9973, which is very close to what the standard deviation rule tells us (0.997).  
            
            We conclude that the standard deviation rule is very accurate.</mattext></material>
      </solutionmaterial>
    </solution>
  </itemfeedback></item>
