<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="obesity_quiz" recommended_attempts="3" max_attempts="3"><title>Obesity&apos;s Effect on the Whole Body unused questions</title><page id="e8b853d1a3a0401bb8089bff7d00c0f9"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><multiple_choice id="obese1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad893d8a3723444f7a37b2faf51921099">Which of these factors is directly responsible for the high incidence of breast cancer in older, obese women?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="fa15a454a2d341ae977101a2f2d50987" labels="false"><choice value="a">Large amounts of fat tissue produce lots of estrogen</choice><choice value="b">Breast tissue becomes more sensitive to estrogen</choice><choice value="c">Reduced number of hormonal receptors on breast tissue cells</choice><choice value="d">Buildup of fat tissue around the breast results in tumor formation</choice></input><part id="obese1_p1"><skillref idref="predict_dysfunction_across_systems_SKILL" /><skillref idref="ident_examples_system_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="predict_dysfunction_homeo_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="1"><feedback><p id="aa9b14ffff68445f392153caccb25d046">Correct. After menopause, the ovaries stop producing hormones, which puts the burden of estrogen production on fat tissue. Since obese women have greater amounts of fat tissue, their estrogen levels are higher. </p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae4a1d3b920fa4dcfb5eb0e715c69c50b">Incorrect. Sensitivity to estrogen in breast tissue does not change with age. </p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad8440fb416df479b839eddf525a5718d">Incorrect. This would have the opposite effect, as estrogen receptors on breast tissue cells promote tumor growth.</p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback><p id="af7fdb3569c674109a38b38f9b93a229e">Incorrect. Fat tissue build up is not directly responsible for breast cancer.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="abb54346859ab4a12b731f97610b4cfb8">The growth of many breast tumors is estrogen-responsive. </p></hint></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="obese2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aea154f3b38c0468096d49141fcd11aed">How else can excess fat affect negatively affect the body?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="a03e007c2d854f82942bcfa049578fb5" labels="false"><choice value="a">Back and spinal pain</choice><choice value="b">Pain in muscles of the upper chest and throat</choice><choice value="c">Arthritis in the joints</choice><choice value="d">All of the above</choice></input><part id="obese2_p1"><skillref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_SKILL" /><skillref idref="predict_dysfunction_across_systems_SKILL" /><skillref idref="ident_examples_system_integration_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback><p id="abf3466af73a8403a99b7866ba5da39ba">Incorrect. The spine essentially carries the body&apos;s weight, so excess weight may result in structural compromise and damage. However, there are other negative effects of excess fat.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="af9b54145da8641468b8d26214c3ad807">Incorrect. Although the presence of excess fat prevents the diaphragm from working efficiently, thereby putting more pressure on the muscles of the upper chest and throat, there are other negative effects of excess fat.</p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="aca0d680ce621407e81e393b0cb6a1b5f">Incorrect. The extra mass resulting from obesity adversely affects weight-bearing joints, often manifesting itself in osteoarthritis. However, there are other negative effects of excess fat.</p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="1"><feedback><p id="aebea190d8d464fc8bbf708656876f02a">Correct. All of these conditions are correlated with obesity. </p></feedback></response><hint><p id="ae9392699d0774b7392239e019a125967">Imagine you are forced to walk around for a day in clothing that adds an additional 50 pounds to your weight. How do you imagine this would affect your body?</p></hint></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="obese3" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ab653d0aff3574c6983155e29a52a313b">Which of the following conditions is not a potential result of obesity?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b8df92da3bbc47c583a0a5f525eebc3f" labels="false"><choice value="a">acanthosis nigricans</choice><choice value="b">cellulitis</choice><choice value="c">callus</choice><choice value="d">contact dermatitis</choice></input><part id="obese3_p1"><skillref idref="predict_disfunction_across_scales_SKILL" /><skillref idref="ident_examp_sf_across_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback><p id="aadab82ec08e14f6bb4caca4bb47e85c9">Incorrect. Insulin resistance as a result of obesity can manifest itself in the form of the disease acanthosis nigricans.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="acfe22df5d7644cc283d30069bcae61c3">Incorrect. Obese individuals are more likely to suffer from edema, which increases their odds of developing cellulitis. </p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab7ded6b3f9834876bac73ac230d5a98e">Incorrect. Because the feet of obese individuals are forced to absorb the impact from extra weight, the odds of developing a callus is increased.</p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback><p id="af1635a470e604fecac2709fc2ef94031">Correct. This is an autoimmune allergic reaction which is not affected by obesity. </p></feedback></response><hint><p id="ada080a04964f406592ba5a201b039bf8">One of the following conditions is an autoimmune disorder that is unrelated to obesity.</p></hint></part></multiple_choice><short_answer id="obese4" grading="automatic"><body><p id="a7f4bbae8868441eab052170358c54ab">What is the link between obesity and insulin insensitivity in cells?<input_ref input="obese_sc" /></p></body><part id="ca5e2f546f9b43aa854e50a1cdd2cf92"><response match="*" score="1" input="obese_sc"><feedback><p id="b291414a3a534bc1bd5afad7b482a61b">Diets consisting largely of intake of large amounts of fats and simple sugars can result in insulin resistance. Body cells are desensitized to the normal actions of insulin, and are thereby unable to uptake glucose, amino acids and fatty acids, which begin to leak out of the cells. In order to account for this insulin insensitivity, larger concentrations of insulin circulate in the bloodstream. When insulin spills over into the skin, abnormal growth increases occur, referred to as as hyperplasia of the skin. This condition is typically associated with type 2 diabetes, obesity, and polycystic ovary syndrome, to name a few examples.</p></feedback></response></part></short_answer></page></assessment>
