<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_4.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>

<assessment id="u3_m4_proportion2_tutor1">
    <title>Tutor</title>
    <page>
        <question id="q1">
            <body>
                 <p>Explain how these simulations illustrate the theory discussed above.</p>
            </body>
            <short_answer id="A"/>
            <part id="p1">
                <response input="A" match="*" score="1"/>
                <hint>Do the simulations verify what the theory tells us about the shape, center and
                    spread of the sampling distributions?</hint>
                <hint><em style="bold">Shape:</em> if np &#8805; 10 and n(1 - p)
                        &#8805; 10, is the shape normal? Is the shape normal
                        when these conditions are not met? <em style="bold">Center:</em> Do all distributions have a mean equal to
                        p? <em style="bold">Spread:</em> Is the standard deviation of each distribution
                        close to sqrt( p(1 - p) / n )?
                </hint>
                <explanation>
                    <p><em style="bold">Shape:</em><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T175840-0500"?>
                        <?oxy_insert_end?>Theory tells us that if np &#8805; 10 and n(1 - p) &#8805;
                        10, then the sampling distribution is approximately normal. When p = 0.10,
                        these conditions are not met for n = 20 or n = 50. We can see that the
                        distributions are skewed to the right for these sample sizes. As the sample
                        size increases, we see the distributions becoming more normal. For n = 100
                        and for larger samples, the conditions are met, and we see that a normal
                        distribution is a pretty good model for the sampling distribution.</p>
                    <p><em style="italic">Note: We only collected
                            1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T175914-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>005
                            samples. The theory presumes we have collected all possible samples. So
                            we don't expect the simulations to give perfectly normal
                            distributions.</em></p>
                    <p><em style="bold">Center:</em> All of the sampling distributions are centered
                        at approximately p = 0.10.</p>
                    <p><em style="bold">Spread:</em> The standard deviation of each sampling
                    distribution is very close to the value predicted by</p>
                    <image src="../webcontent/lbdtutor1_formula1.gif" alt="equation for estimate for standard deviation"/>
                    <p>For example, using this formula for n = 20, the standard deviation is
                        predicted to be 0.0671. We see in the simulation
                        <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101122T175954-0500"?>that
                        <?oxy_insert_end?>the standard deviation is 0.0675, which is very close to
                        the predicted value.</p>
                </explanation>
                
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
