<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="ap_muscular_org1_7">
	<head>
		<title>Smooth Muscle Cells</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_type_of_muscle"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Smooth muscle tissue is found in many different body systems, including as part of organs in
			the digestive, respiratory, and reproductive tracts and in the walls of blood vessels.
			Smooth muscle cells are approximately the same size as cardiac muscle cells and also
			have only one nucleus. However, smooth muscle cells are not branched and, unlike both
			cardiac and skeletal muscle, smooth muscle cells don't have sarcomeres.  Smooth muscle
			cells form layers that are usually arranged so that one runs parallel to an organ and
			the other wraps around it. These two muscle layers then contract in turn, causing
			alternating dilation and contraction or lengthening and shortening of the organ, moving
			substances through internal passages. This is called
				<term><?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120105T155224-0500" comment="Should this term be highlighted or bolded?"?>peristalsis<?oxy_comment_end?></term>
			and is displayed in the process of digestion as food moves through the gastrointestinal
			tract.</p>
		<p>Similar to skeletal and cardiac muscle cells, smooth muscle can undergo hypertrophy to
			increase in size. Unlike the other two muscle types, mature smooth muscle cells can also
			divide to produce more cells, a process called <term>hyperplasia</term>. This can be
			observed in the uterus, which responds to increased estrogen levels by producing more
			uterine muscle cells.</p>
		<p>Smooth muscle cells also do not possess T tubules and do not have a very extensive
			sarcoplasmic reticulum. Smooth muscle has actin and myosin but they are not organized
			into sarcomeres, so there are no obvious bands or striations. Instead, actin and myosin
			is organized into <term>dense bodies</term> attached to the sarcolemma, shortening the
			muscle cell as thin filaments slide past thick filaments. Thin and thick filaments are
			aligned in a diagonal pattern across the cell so that contraction produces a twisting or
			corkscrew motion, rotating one way as it contracts and the other way as it relaxes.
			Cross-bridge formation and filament sliding processes are the same in smooth muscle as
			they are in skeletal and cardiac muscle. Actin, myosin, and tropomyosin are all present,
			but smooth muscle cells do not possess troponin as their regulatory protein. Instead, a
			molecule called calmodulin binds to calcium and activates myosin cross-bridge formation.
			There is also a greater ratio of actin to myosin in smooth muscle, meaning that there
			are more thin filaments for every thick filament.</p>
		<p>Most smooth muscles must function for long periods without rest, so their power output is
			relatively low, but contractions can continue without utilizing large amounts of energy.
			This occurs because the ATPase in myosin works at a relatively slow rate, meaning that
			high levels of ATP are not available for powerful contractions but a steady supply is
			produced for sustained contractions. Smooth muscle can also maintain contractions
			through a <term>latch state</term>, during which actin and myosin remain locked
			together, or latched, in the absence of Ca2+ ions. This does not require ATP, thereby
			producing sustained contractions without using energy. This allows smooth muscles to
			keep your blood vessels partially contracted for your entire life without them
			fatiguing.</p>
		<p>Similar to cardiac muscle, smooth muscle is not under voluntary control. In addition to
			spontaneous stimulation, smooth muscle can be stimulated by <term>pacesetter
				cells</term> that are similar to pacemaker cells and trigger waves of action
			potentials in smooth muscle. Smooth muscle can also be stimulated by the autonomic
			nervous system or hormones. Neuromuscular junctions are not present in smooth muscle,
			but <term>varicosities</term>, enlargements along autonomic nerves, release
			neurotransmitters into synaptic clefts. Smooth muscle can respond to a variety of
			neurotransmitters to produce different effects at different locations.</p>
		<p>Smooth muscle can be divided into two types based on how depolarization and muscle contraction
			occur. <term>Single-unit smooth muscle cells</term> contain gap junctions, which allow
			the cells to be electrically coupled. Electric couplings allow action potentials to
			spread quickly from one cell to the next, permitting coordinated depolarization and
			contraction. In this manner, groups of muscle cells act as a single unit, contracting in
			unison. This type of smooth muscle is found in hollow organs, including the
			gastrointestinal tract, and in the walls of small blood vessels, and it is often
			stimulated spontaneously or by stretching, to produce an action potential.</p>
		<!--<p>Smooth muscle are classified based on coupling of depolarization. Single-unit smooth
			muscle cells contain gap junctions <!-\-[link to this in the cell unit]-\->, which allow
			the cells to be electrically coupled. Electric couplings allow action potentials to
			spread quickly from one cell to the next, which coordinates depolarization and
			contraction. In this manner, groups of muscle cells act as a single unit, contracting in
			unison. This type of smooth muscle is found in hollow organs, including the
			gastrointestinal tract, and in the walls of small blood vessels, and it is often
			stimulated spontaneously or by stretching, to produce an action potential.
			<!-\-[link to skin arrector pilli section]-\-></p>-->
		<p><term>Multiunit smooth muscle cells</term> rarely possess gap junctions, so they are not electrically
			coupled. Stimuli for multiunit smooth muscles come from autonomic nerves or hormones but
			not from stretching. This type of tissue is found in the walls of large blood vessels,
			in the respiratory airways, and connected to hair follicles (to make your hair "stand
			up”), among other places. </p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_u3_no-smooth_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_type_of_muscle_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
