<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="ap_muscular_org1_5">
	<head>
		<title>Skeletal Muscle Cells</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_type_of_muscle"/>
		<objref idref="_u5_myoblast"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<section>
			<title>Skeletal Myocytes—Myoblast Fusion, Myotube Organization in Skeletal Muscle Tissue
				and Satellite Cells</title>
			<body>

				<materials orient="horizontal">
					<material>
						<image src="../../webcontent/Epithelial_Cell.jpg" alt="Epithelial Cell"
							vertical-align="middle" style="block" width="200"
							title="Epithelial Cell"/>
					</material>
					<material>
						<image src="../../webcontent/Myotube_Myofiber.jpg" alt="Myotube Myofiber"
							vertical-align="middle" style="block" width="200" title="Myotube"/>
					</material>
				</materials>

				<p>Each skeletal muscle fiber is a single skeletal muscle cell, also known as a
					skeletal myocyte ("myo-" refers to "muscle" and "-cyte" refers to "cell"), that
					is formed from the fusion of precursor cells. As described before, cell fusion
					leads to multinucleation of each mature muscle fiber. Each myoblast, the
					embryonic cell type that differentiates into muscle, contributes one nucleus
					when the muscle fiber is formed during development.</p>
				<p>During development, individual <term>myoblasts</term> ("-blast" refers to
					"building" … like osteoblasts), migrate to different regions in the body and
					then fuse to form a <term>myotube</term>. A myotube is a type of
					<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120105T122914-0500" comment="should this term be highlighted?"?>syncytium<?oxy_comment_end?>,
					which is the term used for a group of fused cells. Skeletal muscle cells are
					multinucleate because the syncytium
					(<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120105T123222-0500" comment="I think it would be more accurate, both in general and in this specific context, to say that &quot;syn&quot; means &quot;together&quot; and &quot;cyt&quot; refers to &quot;cells.&quot;"?>"syn-"
					means "same" and "cyt" refers to "cytoplasm"<?oxy_comment_end?>) fusion retains
					the nucleus of each contributing myoblast. This syncytium leads to the
					collective sarcoplasm and sarcolemma, described above.</p>
				<p>Mature muscle does not grow by this process. Mature cells can change in size, but
					new cells are not formed when muscles grow. Instead, structural proteins are
					added to muscle fibers in a process called <term>hypertrophy</term>. The
					reverse, when structural proteins are lost and muscle mass decreases, is called
						<term>atrophy</term>. Cellular components of muscles can also undergo
					changes in response to changes in muscle use.</p>
				<p>Although the number of muscle cells is set during development, <term>satellite
						cells</term> help to repair skeletal muscle fibers. Satellite cells are
					similar to myoblasts in that they are able to divide, fuse and differentiate.
					These satellite cells are located outside the muscle fibers and are stimulated
					to grow and fuse with muscle cells by growth factors that are released by muscle
					fibers under certain forms of stress. Satellite cells can regenerate muscle
					fibers to a very limited extent, but they primarily help to repair damage in
					living cells. Satellite cells facilitate the protein synthesis required for
					repair and growth. If a cell is damaged to a greater extent than can be repaired
					by satellite cells, the muscle fibers are replaced by scar tissue in a process
					called <term>fibrosis</term>. Because scar tissue cannot contract, muscle that
					has sustained significant damage loses strength and cannot produce the same
					amount of force or endurance as it could before being damaged.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_amitotic_DIGT" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_myoblast_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
