<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="ap_muscular_org1_6">
	<head>
		<title>Cardiac Muscle Cells</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_type_of_muscle"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Cardiac Myocytes</title>
			<body>
				<p>Cardiac tissue is only found in the walls of the heart chambers, where it
					provides the muscle contractions required to pump blood throughout the body. At
					the tissue level, cardiac muscle is striated (or striped) since, like skeletal
					muscle, it has organized sarcomeres. However, cardiac muscle fibers are shorter
					than skeletal muscle fibers and usually contain only one nucleus, which is
					located in the central region of the cell.</p>


				<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_9a.jpg" alt="cardiac muscle cells and fibers"
					width="500"/>
				<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_9b.jpg" alt="cardiac muscle cells and fibers"
					width="300"/>

				<p>Cardiac muscle fibers are branched, whereas skeletal muscle fibers are
					unbranched. This branching allows individual cells to contact several adjacent
					cells at specialized cell junctions called <term>intercalated discs</term>.
					Intercalated discs are part of the sarcolemma and contain two structures
					important in cardiac muscle contraction: gap junctions and desmosomes. <term>Gap
						junctions<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120105T153656-0500" content=" "?></term><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120105T153658-0500"?>
					<?oxy_insert_end?>are tunnels or protein channels in the cell membrane
					connecting adjacent cardiac muscle cells, allowing ions involved in electric
					currents to move quickly from one cell to the next. This is called
						<term>electric coupling</term>, and in cardiac muscles, it allows the quick
					transmission of action potentials and synchronized contraction of the entire
					heart. Desmosomes are especially strong cell-to-cell junctions that help
					maintain structural integrity at the connections between these contractile
					cardiac muscle cells.</p>
				<!--<p><em style="highlight">[link to cell sections on junctions and desmosomes]</em></p>-->
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>

			<title>Cardiac Cell Specialization</title>
			<body>
				<p>There are two specialized types of cardiac cells: the contractile cells and the
					pacemaker cells. The contractile cells that produce the force for the beating of
					the heart have the capability to beat on their own, but for useful organ level
					contractions, the cells must beat as a unit. The stimulus for contraction is
					normally provided by the pacemaker cells and this stimulus is passed through gap
					junctions to synchronize the signals. These electrically conductive pacemaker
					cells are important for electrical stimulation since cardiac muscle cells are
					not under voluntary control. Pacemaker cells are spontaneously depolarizing at
					set intervals (faster than contractile cells would do on their own), starting a
					wave of depolarization that then spreads throughout the heart and triggers
					contraction. Because the pacemaker cells are located in the heart, the heart is
					said to control its own contraction, which is called
						<term>autorhythmicity</term> (or <term>automaticity</term>). Pacemaker cells
					depolarize at set intervals, and the heart beats a steady, predictable 60 to 80
					beats per minute at rest. These repetitive contractions ensure a constant blood
					supply to all body cells.</p>
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<wb:inline idref="_u5_u3_contraction_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
						<wb:inline idref="_u5_type_of_muscle_2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
					</body>
				</section>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>

			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_cardiac_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
