<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_muscular_org1_4"><head><title>Microscopic Level - Organelles and Cell Structures</title><objref idref="_u5_org_contract" /></head><body><image id="af288a024d88455d86e7ce659bc0c002" src="../../webcontent/Muscle_07.jpg" alt="muscle anatomy detail" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><caption><p id="ae4ccfaecdc5a45e4b780954322228054"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="c8b7d1cf4adc4055b6b4c8f5356d363d"><title>Cellular Organelles and Structures</title><body><p id="c8cd9b78c29a40338df309c0016f6030">Muscle cells contain organelles found in all cells, including nuclei, the endoplasmic reticulum, mitochondria and the Golgi apparatus. The amount and organization of organelles and structures is slightly different in muscle cells. Actin is found inside every cell in the body, but actin is specially organized within the sarcomeres of muscle cells. Muscle cells also have extremely high numbers of mitochondria to produce ATP for force generation. Recall that an ATP molecule is required for one myosin to perform one power stroke. </p><p id="f6b1b26b2981458f9d1bcb228f4cd024"><activity_link idref="levels_m2_cell" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">Click here to review cells and organelles in the Levels of Organization Unit.</activity_link></p></body></section><section id="e850c96c86f94c4c992406f2625519af"><title>Organelles and Structures Specific to Muscle Cells</title><body><image id="fa5e05ac9f114ec9ab5f373facb8d93e" src="../../webcontent/Muscle_07a.jpg" alt="skeletal muscle fiber detail" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><caption><p id="abb9d81b0b7a644d4ae207963a178a5ec">This image shows the internal organization of a muscle cell.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="e91b9908676341e7954e578836e3dd6a" src="../../webcontent/Muscle_7b.jpg" alt="skeletal muscle fiber detail" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><caption><p id="ac13ba27756d64e709fd850914bc29138">The image is a light microscopic image of skeletal muscle in cross section showing a group muscle cells, each surrounded by epimysium and the group surrounded by perimysium. Blood vessels are seen passing through the image and in cross section on the right. The magnified image shows cross section of a single cell (fiber) at higher magnification with many myofibrils visible (small dark circles). </p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c5302eaa895240f99a70d877eb3cb749">Each skeletal muscle fiber is a single cell produced from the fusion of many precursor cells. These fused cells are therefore functionally quite large, with diameters of up to 100 micrometers and lengths of up to 30 centimeters. Compare this with a cell of the skin which is a cube of 20 micrometers in nearly every diameter. In muscle fibers, sarcomeres arrange into parallel structures called <term>myofibrils</term>, so both the Z disc and the M line hold myofilaments in place to maintain the structural arrangement and layering. Myofibrils are connected to each other by intermediate, or desmin, filaments that attach to the Z disc.</p><p id="bb7876a7d3e54056a45b88d0a8ccdaf8">There is some special nomenclature associated with these fused cells. Each skeletal muscle fiber cell has more than one nucleus, which is called <term>multinucleate</term>. The plasma membrane of this fused skeletal muscle cell is called the <term>sarcolemma</term>. The muscle interacts with the nerves that stimulate the muscle at the sarcolemma, and we will describe this interaction later. Within the sarcolemma is the <term>sarcoplasm</term>, which is the cytoplasm of the fused muscle fiber. The sarcoplasm has most of the same components as standard cytoplasm in addition to high levels of the protein myoglobin, which stores oxygen.</p><p id="aa687ee62de049ba93a5b56b9b410354">Also, the sarcolemma contains many structures similar to the plasma membrane of other cells, but it also possesses structures unique to muscle cells. The sarcolemma has transverse tubules, or <term>T tubules</term>, which are indentations of the sarcolemma into the interior of the cell along the length of the muscle cell. The T tubules are filled with extracellular fluid, and they conduct the action potential from the nerve deep into the interior of the muscle cells, which can be very large. With T-tubules, nerves can stimulate entire muscles and muscle groups quickly and effectively. Without T tubules, action potential conduction into the interior of the cell would happen much more slowly, causing delays between neural stimulation and muscle contraction, resulting in slower, weaker contractions. </p><p id="b799c5c9e57f4887aa0a4f62a286dbcc">Inside skeletal muscle fibers is a network of membranous tubules called the sarcoplasmic reticulum (SR), which is similar to the smooth endoplasmic reticulum found in other cells. SR tubules are filled with high-calcium fluid, and they surround each myofibril. <term>Terminal cisternae</term> are dilated regions of the SR that form on either side of each T tubule extending into the cell. A grouping consisting of a T tubule, from the outside of the muscle fiber, and two terminal cisternae, from the inside of the muscle fiber, is called a <term>triad</term>.</p><p id="dc74d77ac7fa4a23ad7667b83417501f">T tubules conduct an action potential along the surface of the muscle fiber into triads that trigger the release of Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions from the nearby terminal cisternae. This, in turn, triggers muscle contraction when the calcium ions in the sarcoplasm can bind to the troponin of the sarcomeres.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u5_org_contract_2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
