<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ap_muscular_org1_2"><head><title>Molecular Level - Actin and Myosin</title><objref idref="_u5_actin_myosin" /></head><body><image id="f1831a492a1545d79c520cd18aa581c8" src="../../webcontent/Muscle_2.jpg" alt=" ATP to ADP conversion" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="be57be27ef6e4e9db5dcde397dc0c7e5"><term>Myosin</term> is a protein that converts the chemical energy stored in the bonds of ATP into the kinetic energy of movement. Myosin is the force-generating protein in all muscle cells, and a coordinated effort among many myosin molecules pulling on actin, generates force for movement. Myosin molecules have two main structural parts. The tail of a myosin molecule consists of two polypeptide subunits wound together, whereas the head is composed of two globular subunits. The tail of a myosin molecule connects with other myosin molecules to form the central region of a thick filament, whereas the heads align on either end of the thick filament where thin filaments overlap with the thick filament. The point at which the head and tail of the molecule meet is flexible and allows the head to move back and forth. This allows myosin to “walk” and pull on <term>actin</term> filaments. Actin filaments are made of individual globular (spherical) protein subunits that assemble linearly into helical (twisted) filaments. </p><p id="d43aa208ef9d4fcab95024fda5377241">ATP binding to myosin causes it to release actin, allowing actin and myosin to detach from each other. After this occurs, ATP is converted to ADP and Pi. The binding site on myosin that hydrolyzes ATP to ADP is called <term>ATPase</term>. The energy released during ATP hydrolysis changes the angle of the myosin head into a “cocked” position. The myosin head is then in a position for further movement, possessing potential energy; however, ADP and Pi are still attached.</p><p id="df5fba5a1461484ca073fe9492cb52d4">Cross-bridge formation occurs at this point, as actin binds while ADP and Pi are still bound to myosin. Pi is then released, causing myosin to form a stronger attachment to actin, and the myosin head moves toward the M line, pulling actin along with it. As actin is pulled, the filaments move approximately 10 nanometers toward the M line. This movement is called the <term>power stroke</term>, as the thin filament “slides” over the myosin and ADP is released during this step.</p><p id="d7f48f9d67104e5da80d099fab828341">When the myosin head is “cocked,” myosin is in a high-energy configuration. This energy is expended as the myosin head moves through the power stroke. At the end of the power stroke, the myosin head is in a low-energy position. Each myosin molecule may form many cross-bridges during muscle contraction. The collection of power strokes and cross-bridges allows collections of individual molecules to generate large forces.</p><image id="d8605a2b27b44411bce656f6d327275b" src="../../webcontent/Muscle_3.jpg" alt="tropomyosin and troponin" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d169885084ce4c728093ccc63fe9c038">In skeletal muscle, <term>tropomyosin</term> and <term>troponin</term> regulate contraction by controlling the interaction between actin and myosin filaments. Tropomyosin acts to block myosin binding sites on the actin filament, preventing cross-bridge formation and thus preventing contraction in a relaxed muscle. Calcium triggers muscle contraction by binding to troponin and altering its shape so that tropomyosin does not block the myosin binding sites on actin, thus allowing muscle contraction to occur. Calcium is generally an important molecule in muscle function, as we will discuss later.</p><p id="adb9de0d48da406b9611be37f6d44837"><term>Titin</term>, as the name implies, is a very large structural protein in muscle cells. Unlike actin and myosin, which bundle together to form a multiprotein complex, titin is a single protein that holds large structures together. Thus, titin is a large, multifunctional protein (hundreds of times bigger than these other proteins) that forms an elastic filament. Titin helps align the myosin proteins and allows the muscle cell to maintain structural integrity by resisting extreme stretching, preventing damage due to overstretching.</p><p id="d2dfcf6fb1e24086abaf33414402fcf2"><term>Dystrophin</term> is a protein that helps bind actin to the muscle cell membrane. Insufficient dystrophin production results in an inability to transfer the force of the organized actin-myosin contraction to the muscle cell membrane and ultimately to the tendons. Loss or insufficient production of this molecule causes Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD).</p><wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_actin-bound_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /><example id="ad9e9fe026c74c988f245314205282a5"><title>Rigor and Rigor Mortis</title><p id="fb742fbdc2da4640a35b8ca8bccf0b79">At the end of the power stroke, the actin-myosin cross-bridge is still in place (until ATP binds to the myosin head to change its shape). When energy is depleted, ATP is no longer available to bind to myosin; without ATP, actin remains bound to myosin, making both relaxation and further contraction impossible. This state, with an intact cross-bridge and depleted ATP, is called <term>rigor</term>.</p><p id="a9070a3145fd4bc287e70da37e56f559">This situation is exemplified during rigor mortis, which occurs after death. Dead cells can no longer produce ATP. Without ATP, the myosin heads can not detach from actin. Recall that ATP is required for the myosin to come off of the actin. Rigor mortis eventually subsides as proteins in the body, including actin and myosin, degrade.</p></example><wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_rig-mort_SC_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
