<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="Neuromuscular_Junctions_3">
	<head>
		<title>Neurotransmitters</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_electrical_signal"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_14.jpg" alt="acetylcholine"/>

		<p><em style="bold">Acetylcholine</em>, often abbreviated as ACh, is a neurotransmitter
			released by motor neurons that binds to receptors in the motor end-plate. It is an
			extremely important small molecule in human physiology. On the neuron side of the
			synaptic cleft, there are typically 300,000 vesicles waiting to be exocytosed at any
			time and each vesicle contains up to 10,000 molecules of acetylcholine.</p>
		<p>ACh is produced by the reaction of Acetyl coenzyme A (CoA) with a choline molecule in the
			neuron cell body. After it is packaged, transported, and released, it binds to the
			acetylch<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120106T132855-0500" comment="addition correct?"?>oline<?oxy_comment_end?>
			receptor on the motor end-plate; it is degraded in the synaptic cleft by the enzyme
			acetylcholinesterase (AChE) into acetate (and acetic acid) and choline. The choline is
			recycled back into the neuron. AChE resides in the synaptic cleft, breaking down ACh so
			that it does not remain bound to ACh receptors, which would interrupt normal control of
			muscle contraction. In some cases, insufficient amounts of ACh prevent normal muscle
			contraction and cause muscle weakness.</p>
		<example title="Botulinum">
			<title>Botulinum's Effect on ACh</title>
			<p>Botulinum toxin prevents ACh from being released into the synaptic cleft. With no ACh
				binding to its receptors at the motor end-plate, no action potential is produced,
				and muscle contraction cannot occur. Botulinum toxin is produced by <em
					style="italic">Clostridium botulinum</em>, a bacterium sometimes found in
				improperly canned foods. Ingestion of very small amounts can cause botulism, which
				can cause death due to the paralysis of skeletal muscles, including those required
				for
				<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120106T154541-0500" comment="All three of the below questions have &quot;a&quot; as the right answer. I recommend varying the location of the correct answer in each question -- especially in questions presented together."?>breathing.<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
		</example>

		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_botulinum_treatment" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

				<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_nicotine_spasms" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_electrical_signal" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_immune_attack" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
