<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="Neuromuscular_Junctions_5">
	<head>
		<title>Sarcomere Contraction</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_generate_ATP"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>You have already learned about the <activity_link
			idref="ap_muscular_org1_3" target="new">anatomy of the sarcomere</activity_link>,with its coordinated actin thin filaments and myosin
			thick filaments. For a muscle cell to contract, the sarcomere must shorten in response
			to a nerve impulse. The thick and thin filaments do not shorten, but they slide by one
			another, causing the sarcomere to shorten while the filaments remain the same length.
			This process is known as the <term>sliding filament model of muscle
				contraction</term>. The mechanism of contraction is accomplished by the binding of
			myosin to actin, resulting in the formation of cross-bridges that generate filament
			movement.</p>
		<p>When a sarcomere shortens, some regions shorten while others remain the same length. A
			sarcomere is defined as the distance between two consecutive Z discs or Z lines. When a
			muscle contracts, the distance between the Z discs is reduced. The H zone, the central
			region of the A zone, contains only thick filaments and shortens during contraction. The
			I band contains only thin filaments and also shortens. The A band does not shorten; it
			remains the same length, but A bands of adjacent sarcomeres move closer together during
			contraction. Thin filaments are pulled by the thick filaments towards the center of the
			sarcomere until the Z discs approach the thick filaments. The zone of overlap, where
			thin filaments and thick filaments occupy the same area, increases as the thin filaments
			move inward.</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_6.jpg" alt="sarcomere contraction" width="600"/>

		<p>The ideal length of a sarcomere to produce maximal tension occurs when all of the thick
			and thin filaments overlap. If a sarcomere is stretched past this ideal length, some of
			the myosin heads in the thick filaments are not in contact with the actin in the thin
			filaments, and fewer cross-bridges can form. This results in fewer myosin heads pulling
			on actin, and less tension is produced. If a sarcomere is shortened, the zone of overlap
			is reduced as the thin filaments reach the H zone, which is composed of myosin tails.
			Because myosin heads form cross-bridges, actin will not bind to myosin in this zone,
			again reducing the tension produced by the muscle. If further shortening of the
			sarcomere occurs, thin filaments begin to overlap with each other, further reducing
			cross-bridge formation and the amount of tension produced. If the muscle<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120106T170109-0500"?>
			<?oxy_insert_end?>were stretched to the point where thick and thin filaments do not
			overlap at all, no cross-bridges are formed, and no tension is produced. This amount of
			stretching does not usually occur, as accessory proteins and connective tissue oppose
			extreme stretching.</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_16.jpg" alt="tension over resting length of muscle"
			width="400"/>

		<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_force_direction" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

		<!--<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_weak_motors" purpose="myresponse"/>-->


		<p>With large numbers of relatively weak molecular motors, we can more easily adjust the force to
			meet our needs. Otherwise, we would regularly be producing too little or too much force
			for most of our tasks. Also, molecules are only capable of generating small forces based
			on their molecular structure.</p>

		<!--Figure: slide 17 (not needed, but fun)-->
		
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_generate_ATP_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
