<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="Neuromuscular_Junctions_4">
	<head>
		<title>Cellular Muscle Contraction</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_energy"/>
		<objref idref="_u5_generate_ATP"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>ATP supplies the energy for muscle contraction to take place. In addition to its direct role in
			the cross-bridge cycle, ATP also provides the energy for the active-transport
				Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumps. Muscle contraction does not
			occur without sufficient amounts of ATP. The amount of ATP stored in muscle is very low,
			only sufficient to power a few seconds worth of contractions. As it is broken down, ATP
			must therefore be regenerated and replaced quickly to allow for sustained
			contraction.</p>


		<wb:inline idref="_u5_m3_sarcomere_force" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<p>One ATP moves one myosin head one step. This can generate three picoNewtons (pN) of isometric
			force, or move 11 nanometers. Three pN is a very small force—a human bite, generated by
			muscle, can generate 500 trillion pN of force. And 11 nm is a very small distance— one
			inch has 25 million nanometers.</p>

		<p>There are three mechanisms by which ATP can be regenerated: creatine phosphate
			metabolism, anaerobic glycolysis, and aerobic respiration.</p>

		<p><term>Creatine phosphate</term> is a phosphagen, which is a compound that can store
			energy in its phosphate bonds. In a resting muscle, excess ATP (adenosine triphosphate)
			transfers its energy to creatine, producing ADP (adenosine diphosphate) and creatine
			phosphate. When the muscle starts to contract and needs energy, creatine phosphate and
			ADP are converted into ATP and creatine by the enzyme creatine kinase. This reaction
			occurs very quickly; thus, phosphagen-derived ATP powers the first few seconds of muscle
			contraction. However, creatine phosphate can only provide approximately 15 seconds worth
			of energy, at which point another energy source has to be available.</p>

		<p>After the available ATP from creatine phosphate is depleted, muscles generate ATP using
			glycolysis. <term>Glycolysis</term> is an anaerobic process that breaks down glucose
			(sugar) to produce ATP; however, glycolysis cannot generate ATP as quickly as creatine
			phosphate. The sugar used in glycolysis can be provided by blood glucose or by
			metabolizing glycogen that is stored in the muscle. Each glucose molecule produces two
			ATP and two molecules of <term>pyruvate</term>, which can be used in aerobic respiration
			or converted to lactic acid.</p>

		<!--<p><activity_link idref="">[link to cellular respiration and mitochondria</activity_link></p>-->

		<p>If oxygen is available, pyruvic acid is used in aerobic respiration. However, if oxygen is not
			available, pyruvic acid is converted into <term>lactic acid</term>, which may contribute
			to muscle fatigue and pain. This occurs during strenuous exercise when high amounts of
			energy are needed but oxygen cannot be delivered to muscle at a rate fast enough to meet
			the whole need. Anaerobic glycolysis cannot be sustained for very long (approximately
			one minute of muscle activity), but it is useful in facilitating short bursts of
			high-intensity output. Glycolysis does not utilize glucose very efficiently, producing
			only two ATP molecules per molecule of glucose, and the by-product lactic acid
			contributes to muscle fatigue as it accumulates. Lactic acid is transported out of the
			muscle into the bloodstream, but if this does not happen quickly enough, lactic acid can
			cause cellular pH levels to drop, affecting enzyme activity and interfering with muscle
			contraction.</p>
		<p><term>Aerobic respiration</term> is the breakdown of glucose in the presence of oxygen to produce
			carbon dioxide, water, and ATP. Aerobic respiration in the mitochondria of muscles
			uses glycogen from muscle stores, blood glucose, pyruvic acid, and fatty acids.
			Approximately 95 percent of the ATP required for resting or moderately active muscles is
			provided by aerobic respiration. Aerobic respiration is much more efficient than
			anaerobic glycolysis, producing approximately 38 ATP molecules per molecule of glucose.
			However, aerobic respiration does not synthesize ATP as quickly as anaerobic glycolysis,
			meaning that the power output of muscles declines, but lower-power contractions can be
			sustained for longer periods.</p>

		<table title="The Metabolic Pathways for ATP Production">
			<tr>
				<th/>
				<th><?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120106T164231-0500" comment="The text calls this &quot;creatine phosohate metabolism&quot; -- should this term be changed here, or should the term used here be presented earlier?"?>Phosphorylation
					of creatine phosphate<?oxy_comment_end?></th>
				<th>Anaerobic glycolysis</th>
				<th><?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120106T164330-0500" comment="This is called &quot;aerobic respiration&quot; above -- should this term be changed here, or introduced above?"?>Aerobic
					metabolism<?oxy_comment_end?></th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td align="center"><em>Energy source</em></td>
				<td align="center">Creatine phosphate</td>
				<td align="center">Glucose</td>
				<td align="center">Glucose, pyruvic acid, fatty acids</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td align="center"><em>Rate of ATP synthesis</em></td>
				<td align="center">Very fast</td>
				<td align="center">Fast</td>
				<td align="center">Slow</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><em>Number of ATPs produced per unit</em></td>
				<td align="center">1</td>
				<td align="center">2</td>
				<td align="center">38</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td align="center"><em>Oxygen required</em></td>
				<td align="center">No</td>
				<td align="center">No</td>
				<td align="center">Yes</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
		<p>This combination of different energy sources is important for different types of muscle
			activity. As an analogy, a cup of coffee with lots of sugar provides a quick burst of
			energy but not for very long. A balanced meal with complex carbohydrates, protein and
			fats takes longer to impact us, but provides sustained energy.</p>
		<p>Muscles require a large amount of energy, and thus require a constant supply of oxygen and
			nutrients. Blood vessels enter muscle at its surface, after which they are distributed
			through the entire muscle. Blood vessels and capillaries are found in the connective
			tissue that surrounds muscle fascicles and fibers, allowing oxygen and nutrients to be
			supplied to muscle cells and metabolic waste to be removed. Myoglobin, which binds
			oxygen similarly to hemoglobin and gives muscle its red color, is found in the
			sarcoplasm.</p>

		<example title="Exercise and Energy">
			<title>Exercise and Energy</title>
			<p>After the first few seconds of exercise, available ATP is used up. After the next few minutes,
				cellular glucose and glycogen are depleted. After the next 30 minutes, the body's
				supply of glucose and glycogen are depleted. After that time, fatty acids and other
				energy sources are used to make ATP. That’s why we should exercise for more than 30
				minutes to lose weight (i.e. lose fat). Sometimes, time is important.</p>
		</example>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_energy_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
