<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="Neuromuscular_Junctions_6"><head><title>Neural Stimulation of Contraction</title><objref idref="_u5_twitch" /><objref idref="_u5_summation" /><objref idref="_u5_tetanus" /></head><body><p id="e3ed4c9cae2f4c9ea974ac2a75798c11">You have already learned about how the information from a neuron ultimately leads to a muscle cell contraction.</p><p id="ff8bcbb27361474fb0dd03210800e0ca"><activity_link idref="Neuromuscular_Junctions_1" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">Revisit previous material for a review of neuromuscular junctions.</activity_link></p><image id="a5381c0f08874b29be93694fef664219" src="../../webcontent/Muscle_18.jpg" alt="muscle contraction" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c08ec26fd8fc46f2a74f5e493e2f912e">One action potential in a motor neuron produces one contraction. This contraction is called a <term>twitch</term>. We think of &quot;muscle twitches&quot; as spasms that we can’t control, but in physiology, a twitch is a technical term describing a muscle response to stimulation. A single twitch does not produce any significant muscle contraction. Multiple action potentials (repeated stimulation) are needed to produce a muscle contraction that can produce work.</p><p id="a333873420c047688777eb0691a30ce2">A twitch can last from a few milliseconds up to 100 milliseconds, depending on the muscle type. The tension produced by a single twitch can be measured by a <term>myogram</term>, which produces a graph illustrating the amount of tension produced over time. When combined with a plot of electrical signaling, the myogram shows three phases that each twitch undergoes. The first period is the <term>latent period</term>, during which the action potential is being propagated along the membrane and Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions are released from the sarcoplasmic reticulum (SR). No tension or contraction is produced at this point, but the conditions for contraction are being established. This is the phase during which excitation and contraction are being coupled but contraction has yet to occur. The <term>contraction phase</term> occurs after the latent period when calcium is being used to trigger cross-bridge formation. This period lasts from the beginning of contraction to the point of peak tension. The last phase is the <term>relaxation phase</term>, when tension decreases as contraction stops. Calcium is pumped out of the sarcoplasm, back into the SR, and cross-bridge cycling stops. The muscle returns to a resting state. There is a very short refractory period after the relaxation phase (<activity_link idref="Neuromuscular_Junctions_2" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">Review the previous material about the physiology of a neuromuscular junction</activity_link>).</p><p id="fe61d5fc419f46cda0ab156d607ed57c">A single twitch does not produce any significant muscle activity in a living body. Normal muscle contraction is more sustained, and it can be modified to produce varying amounts of force. This is called a <term>graded muscle response</term>. The tension produced in a skeletal muscle is a function of both the frequency of neural stimulation and the number of motor neurons involved.</p><p id="b1c9008cad9e49daabcf109fab1f252f">The rate at which a motor neuron delivers action potentials affects the contraction produced in a muscle cell. If a muscle cell is stimulated while a previous twitch is still occurring, the second twitch will not have the same strength as the first; it will be stronger. This effect is called <term>summation</term>, or wave summation, because the effects of successive neural stimuli are summed, or added together. This occurs because the second stimulus releases more Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions, which become available while the muscle is still contracting from the first stimulus (the first wave of calcium ions released). This allows for more cross-bridge formation and greater contraction. Because the second stimulus has to arrive before the first twitch has completed, the frequency of stimulus determines whether summation occurs or not.</p><p id="a84532189d2249d395aa9e63d7030b6d">If the frequency of stimulation increases to the point at which each successive stimulus sums with the force generated from the previous stimulus, muscle tension continues to rise until the tension generated reaches a peak point. The tension at this point is about three to four times higher than the tension of a single twitch; this is referred to as incomplete tetanus. <term>Tetanus</term> is defined as continuous fused contraction. During incomplete tetanus, the muscle goes through quick cycles of contraction with a short relaxation phase. If the stimulus frequency is so high that the relaxation phase disappears completely, contractions become continuous in a process called complete tetanus. This occurs when Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations in the sarcoplasm reach a point at which contractions can continue uninterrupted. This contraction continues until the muscle fatigues and can no longer produce tension.</p><p id="a0d762d28060493bb7129b669b346c01">This type of tetanus is not the same as the disease of the same name that is distinguished by severe sustained contraction of skeletal muscles. The disease, which can be fatal if left untreated, is caused by the bacterium <em style="italic">Clostridium tetani</em>, which is present in most environments. The toxin from the bacterium affects how motor neurons communicate and control muscle contractions, resulting in muscle spasms or sustained contractions, also known as “lockjaw.”</p><p id="cc43d98453464b349dffb5ba2d2ae2d8">Slightly different from incomplete tetanus is the phenomenon of <term>treppe</term>. Treppe (from the German term for step, referring to stepwise increases in contraction) is a condition in which successive stimuli produce a greater amount of tension, even though tension goes back to the resting state between stimuli (in tetanus, tension does not decrease to the resting state between stimuli). Treppe is similar to tetanus in that the first twitch releases calcium into the sarcoplasm, some of which will not be taken back up before the next contraction. Each stimulus afterward releases more calcium, but there is still some calcium present in the sarcoplasm from the previous stimulus. This extra calcium permits more cross-bridge formation and greater contraction with each additional stimulus up to the point where added calcium cannot be utilized. At this point, successive stimuli will produce a uniform amount of tension.</p><p id="ee6cba1380814cfabe04ef54cc9b7ad5">The strength of contractions is controlled not only by the frequency of stimuli but also by the number of <term>motor units</term> involved in a contraction. A motor unit is defined as a single motor neuron and the corresponding muscle fibers it controls. Increasing the frequency of neural stimulation can increase the tension produced by a single motor unit, but this can only produce a limited amount of tension in a skeletal muscle. To produce more tension in an entire skeletal muscle, the number of motor units involved in contraction must be increased. This process is called <term>recruitment</term>.</p><p id="b5cc0aec64a04fe8a3a4b76b05d58601">The size of motor units varies with the sizes of muscle. Small muscles contain smaller motor units and are most useful for fine motor movements. Larger muscles tend to have larger motor units because they are generally not involved in fine control. Even within a muscle, motor units vary in size. Generally, when a muscle contracts, small motor units will be the first ones recruited in a muscle, with larger motor units added as more force is needed.</p><p id="e7daaa4a4251440c92289a5485a72dd1">All of the motor units in a muscle can be active simultaneously, producing a very powerful contraction. This cannot last for very long because of the energy requirements of muscle contraction. To prevent complete muscle fatigue, typically motor units in a given muscle are not all simultaneously active, but instead, some motor units rest, while others are active, allowing for longer muscle contractions by the muscle as a whole.</p><p id="a331673842ad42239d6ff5cf6d172959">The action potentials produced by pacemaker cells in cardiac muscle are longer than those produced by motor neurons that stimulate skeletal muscle contraction. Thus, cardiac contractions are approximately ten times longer than skeletal muscle contractions. Because of long refractory periods, new action potential cannot reach a cardiac muscle cell before it has entered the relaxation phase, meaning that the sustained contractions of tetanus are impossible. If tetanus were to occur, the heart would not beat regularly, interrupting the flow of blood through the body.</p><section id="a4c37b49e37c4a58bf3bdfb9d1d8f341" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u5_generate_ATP_sc" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="_u5_twtich_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="ca6f8950cb4f43ecadf44206242b712c" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u5_twitch_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="_u5_summation_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="_u5_tetanus_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
