<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="Neuromuscular_Junctions_1">
	<head>
		<title>Neuromuscular Junctions</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_sequence_contraction"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Skeletal muscle cell contraction occurs after a release of calcium ions from internal
			stores, which is initiated by a neural signal. Each skeletal muscle fiber is controlled
			by a motor neuron, which conducts signals from the brain or spinal cord to the
			muscle.</p>
		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_11.jpg" alt="skeletal muscle fiber" width="500"/>

		<p>The following list presents an overview of the sequence of events involved in the contraction
			cycle of skeletal muscle:</p>
		<ol>
			<li>The action potential travels down the neuron to the presynaptic axon terminal.</li>
			<li>Voltage-dependent calcium channels open and Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions flow from the extracellular
				fluid into the presynaptic neuron's cytosol.</li>
			<li>The influx of Ca<sup>2+</sup> causes neurotransmitter (acetylcholine)-containing
				vesicles to dock and fuse to the presynaptic neuron's cell membrane.</li>
			<li>Vesicle membrane fusion with the nerve cell membrane results in the emptying of the
				neurotransmitter into the synaptic cleft; this process is called exocytosis.</li>
			<li>Acetylcholine diffuses into the synaptic cleft and binds to the <term>nicotinic
					acetylcholine receptors</term> in the motor end-plate.</li>
			<li>The nicotinic acetylcholine receptors are ligand-gated cation channels, and open
				when bound to acetylcholine.</li>
			<li>The receptors open, allowing sodium ions to flow into the muscle's cytosol.</li>
			<li>The electrochemical gradient across the muscle plasma membrane causes a local
				depolarization of the motor end-plate.</li>
			<li>The receptors open, allowing sodium ions to flow into and potassium ions to flow out of the
				muscle's cytosol.</li>
			<li>The electrochemical gradient across the muscle plasma membrane (more sodium moves in than
				potassium out) causes a local depolarization of the motor end-plate.</li>
			<li>This depolarization initiates an action potential on the muscle fiber cell membrane
				(sarcolemma) that travels across the surface of the muscle fiber.</li>
			<li>The action potentials travel from the surface of the muscle cell along the membrane of T
				tubules that penetrate into the cytosol of the cell.</li>
			<li>Action potentials along the T tubules cause voltage-dependent calcium release channels in the
				sarcoplasmic reticulum to open, and release Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions from their storage
				place in the cisternae.</li>
			<li>Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions diffuse through the cytoplasm where they bind to troponin,
				ultimately allowing myosin to interact with actin in the sarcomere; this sequence of
				events is called excitation-contraction coupling.</li>
			<li>As long as ATP and some other nutrients are available, the mechanical events of contraction
				occur.</li>
			<li>Meanwhile, back at the neuromuscular junction, acetylcholine has moved off of the
				acetylcholine receptor and is degraded by the enzyme acetylcholinesterase (into
				choline and acetate groups), causing termination of the signal.</li>
			<li>The choline is recycled back into the presynaptic terminal, where it is used to
				synthesize new acetylcholine molecules.</li>
		</ol>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_sequence_contraction_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
