<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_17"><head><title>Skin Glands and Secretions</title><objref idref="sweat_glands" /></head><body><section id="cbb38c94050540aea7442e85c700b3ba"><title>Sweat (Sudoriferous) Glands</title><body><p id="eaee69ad100f4cf39f3ac40af7ebf061">When the body becomes overheated, sweat is produced to cool the body&apos;s temperature and prevent overheating. There are two types of sweat glands responsible for excreting sweat —<term>eccrine</term> (<term>merocrine</term>) <term>sweat glands</term> and <term>apocrine sweat glands</term>. Eccrine glands are present throughout the skin surface, especially on the palms of the hand, the soles of the feet, and the forehead. Like hair and nails, they are derived from the epidermis. They are coiled glands that lie in the dermis, with the duct opening to a pore on the skin surface, where the sweat is released(although some may open into hair follicles, like sebaceous glands). The sweat released by eccrine sweat glands is mostly water, with some salt, antibodies, traces of metabolic waste, and a microbe-killing compound called dermcidin. The main function of eccrine sweat glands is to help regulate body temperature through evaporation.</p><p id="db5075fec9eb4a9d94c14f91d8218645">Eccrine glands are controlled by the sympathetic division of the autonomic nervous system. The sympathetic division is known as the &quot;fight or flight&quot; division. When you are nervous, you might notice that your palms sweat. This is because when the sympathetic division is activated, it triggers sweating.</p><p id="e9b52c6ea43d420a97122b906b2a0c34">Apocrine glands are usually associated with hair follicles and are activated in densely hairy areas like armpits and genitals. They are larger than merocrine sweat glands and lie deeper in the dermis, sometimes even reaching the hypodermis. They release a thicker fluid due to a higher concentration of fatty acids, which may give it a whitish color. These fats are often decomposed by bacteria on the skin, resulting in an unpleasant odor, commonly called body odor. Apocrine glands do not begin to function until puberty. Apocrine sweat glands are stimulated during emotional stress and sexual excitement.</p></body></section><section id="c9bf992d524144cf83d0be6eec3893e1"><title>Sebaceous Glands</title><body><p id="a34809b7ae0d4014b20c3831eb7e1bcf"><term>Sebaceous glands</term> are oil glands that are found all over the body. Most are associated with hair follicles. They generate and excrete a mixture of lipids, called sebum, onto the hair and skin surface, thereby naturally lubricating the dry and dead layer of keratinized cells of the stratum corneum and hair shaft. Sebum also has antibacterial properties, and prevents water loss from the skin in low-humidity environments. The secretion of sebum is stimulated by hormones, many of which do not become active until puberty. Thus, sebaceous glands are relatively inactive during childhood and become active only after puberty has occurred. </p><example id="d4f3a2e0df01459b94c9f5c455665d79"><title>Acne</title><p id="b1725288e28c4f1e9b922ab892cac219"><em style="bold">Acne</em> is a skin disturbance that typically occurs on areas of the skin that are rich in sebaceous glands (the face and back). It is most common during the onset of puberty due to associated hormonal changes, but can continue into adulthood. Hormones such as androgen and other sex steroid hormones stimulate the release of sebum. When sebaceous glands overproduce and get blocked with sebum, it leads to the formation of blackheads<em style="bold">. </em>Blackheads are the result of hyperkeratinization of the area, which causes the formation of a keratin plug and blockage of hair follicles in the area. Blackheads are prone to infection by acne-causing bacteria (i.e. <em style="italic">Propionibacterium</em>and <em style="italic">Staphylococcus</em>), which leads to redness and swelling. In severe cases, acne can lead to scarring due to the production of scar tissue during the wound healing process.</p></example><wb:inline idref="sweat_glands" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="sweat_glands_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
