<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_05">
	<head>
		<title>Skin Cancer</title>
		<objref idref="skin_cancer"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p><term>Cancer</term> in general is initiated because of DNA damage that accumulates in a
			particular cell over time. Exposure to UV rays from the sun can ultimately lead to
			mutations in the genomes of various skin cells. Accumulation of genetic mutations over a
			period of
			time<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154227-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
			in addition to other possible
			causes<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154233-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
			can trigger cells to grow out of control. The normal signals that control cell divisions
			(even stem cells have these controls) are
			lost<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154246-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
			and cells grow to form a <term>tumor</term>, or mass of cells. While some tumors are
			benign (stay in one place), some produce cells that dislodge from the tumor and
			establish tumors in other areas of the body. In other words, they
				<term>metastasize</term> and form secondary tumors.</p>

		<section>
			<title>Basal Cell Carcinoma</title>
			<body>
				<p><term>Basal cell carcinoma</term> is caused by mutations that lead to lack of control over
					<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154428-0500" comment="Please doublecheck if my added word is correct"?>the
					<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154408-0500"?>growth
					<?oxy_insert_end?>of <?oxy_comment_end?>stem cells located in
					<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154456-0500"?>the
					<?oxy_insert_end?>stratum basale. It is the most common form of all cancers that
					occur in the United States. The head, neck, arms, and back are most
					susceptible<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T154546-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
					due to long-term sun exposure. Although UV radiation is the main culprit,
					exposure to other agents, such as electromagnetic radiation or carcinogenic
					chemicals, can also lead to this type of cancer. Injury to the skin due to open
					sores, tattoos, burns, etc. may be predisposing factors as well. Basal cell
					carcinoma usually starts as an uneven patch, bump, growth, or scar on the skin
					surface and responds best to treatment when caught early. Complete surgical
					excision of the lesion usually cures this form of cancer.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<image width="350" src="../../webcontent/IU_M2_5.jpg">
			<caption>Of skin cancers, about
				80<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155004-0500"?>
				percent<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155009-0500" content="%"?>
				are basal cell carcinoma,
				16<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155013-0500"?>
				percent<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155015-0500" content="%"?>
				are squamous cell carcinoma, and
				<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155709-0500"?>four<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155708-0500" content="4"?><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155020-0500"?>
				percent<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155022-0500" content="%"?>
				are melanoma.</caption>
		</image>
		<section>
			<title>Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
			<body>
				<p><term>Squamous cell carcinoma</term> is the second most common skin
					cancer<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T155036-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
					and affects the keratinocytes. Lesions are usually scaly and red and are most
					common on the scalp, ears, and hands. If not removed, they can metastasize.
					Surgery and radiation are used to cure squamous cell carcinoma.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Melanoma</title>
			<body>
				<p><term>Melanoma</term> affects melanocytes, the pigment-producing cells in the
					epidermis. It is the most fatal of all skin cancers, as it is highly metastatic
					and can be difficult to detect before it has spread. Melanomas usually appear as
					asymmetrical brown and black patches with uneven borders and a raised surface.
					Treatment typically involves surgical excision and immunotherapy.</p>
			</body>
		</section>


		<!--<p>cancer_cells_LBD</p>-->
		<wb:inline idref="skin_cancer" purpose="didigetthis"/>


	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
