<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_11">
	<head>
		<title>Thick Versus Thin Skin</title>
		<objref idref="epidermis_layers"/>
		<objref idref="epidermis_functions_tissues"/>
		
	</head>
	<body>
					<p>The thickness of thick skin is a function of the four upper layers of the epidermis:
			<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T170051-0500"?>the
			<?oxy_insert_end?>stratum spinosum, stratum granulosum, stratum lucidum, and stratum
			corneum. The stratum corneum, consisting of keratin-packed dead cells, is substantially
			thicker in thick skin than in thin skin
			(<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T170157-0500" content="&amp;gt;"?><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T170202-0500"?>more
			than <?oxy_insert_end?>300 layers versus 15 layers of cells). The palms of your hands,
			soles of your feet, and your lips have thick skin. Thick skin is adapted to specialized
			activities, including gripping, walking and suckling, and the wear and tear that goes
			with
			th<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180233-0500"?>ose<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180232-0500" content="at"?><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180235-0500"?>
			activities<?oxy_insert_end?>. Thick skin does not have hair, and has few glands.</p>
				<p>Most of the rest of your skin is thin. The stratum lucidum isn’t even present in thin skin.
			The packed keratin provides most of the protective properties associated with the
			epidermis. Whereas the stratum corneum of thin skin may be completely shed and replaced
			in about a
			week<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T181135-0500" content="’s time"?>,
			this replacement may take about a month in thick skin.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="thick_skin_SC" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<example>
					<title>Calluses</title>
					<p>When you wear shoes that do not fit well and are a constant source of abrasion on your toes,
				you tend to form <em style="bold"
					>calluses<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180638-0500" content=" "?></em><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180639-0500"?>
				<?oxy_insert_end?>at the point of contact. This occurs because the basal stem cells
				in the stratum basale are triggered to divide more often. This increases the
				thickness of the skin at the point of abrasion so as to provide greater protection
				to the underlying tissue. Calluses can also form on your fingers if they are subject
				to constant mechanical stress like long periods of
				writing<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180739-0500"?>
				or<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180739-0500" content=","?>
				playing
				string<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180730-0500"?>ed<?oxy_insert_end?>
				instruments<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180746-0500" content=","?>
				or video games. The formation of calluses is an example of how tissues can adapt to
				a minor or local stress. <em style="bold"
					>Corns<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180756-0500" content=" "?></em><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T180758-0500"?>
				<?oxy_insert_end?>are a specialized form of calluses. They are formed due to the
				abrasion on the skin as a result of an elliptical-type motion.</p>

				</example>
		
		<wb:inline idref="epidermis_functions_tissues" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
