<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_04"><head><title>Microscopic Level - Cells of the Epidermis</title><objref idref="identify_epidermis_cells" /><objref idref="epidermis_functions_cells" /></head><body><p id="d08b27b487bc4421bddebc6b1d70bc15">The <term>epidermis</term> (or epithelial layer) is stratified squamous epithelia, composed of four to five layers (depending on body region) of epithelial cells. The top layers of the epidermis are made up of <term>keratinocytes</term>, which are cells containing the protein <term>keratin</term>. The keratinocytes on the most superficial layer of the epidermis are dead, and periodically slough away, being replaced by cells from the deeper layers. As keratinocytes move superficially from the deeper layers, they lose cytoplasm and become flattened, allowing for many layers in a relatively small space.</p><image id="d079f0e2c70248f4815c42fdd5edc22e" src="../../webcontent/IU_M2_4.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d4abd9f4174441588464a1c95eaf0d0d"><term>Basal cells</term> are an example of tissue-specific <term>stem cells</term>, meaning they can turn into a variety of cell types found in that tissue. Under normal conditions, daughter basal cells most commonly replace lost keratinocytes.</p><p id="e1a896cd11db420c9d6aec70f47201e7">The deepest layer of the epidermis and the most superficial layer of the dermis give out projections that interlock with each other (like Velcro) and strengthen the bond between the epidermis and the dermis. The projections originating in epithelial cells of the bottom layer of the epidermis are called <term>desmosomes</term>,and the ones originating in the dermis are called dermal <term>papillae</term>. Think of the projections as a formation of folds of cellular matter. The greater the fold, the stronger the connections made.</p><p id="d50a8cc2132a480e9fc9312615db6eb9"><term>Merkel cells</term> are sensory receptors that detect light touch. They form synaptic connections with sensory nerves that carry touch information to the brain. These cells are abundant on the surface of the hands and feet.</p><p id="d22d6d9cf5084cef9d9f4e90da96e7d9"><term>Melanocytes</term> are cells in the bottom layer of epidermis that produce the pigment <term>melanin</term>, which gives hair and skin its color. Individuals whose melanocytes produce more melanin have darker skin color. Cellular extensions of the melanocytes reach up in between the keratinocytes. </p><p id="fc95f8de26ce45f1817f95cd4ac09518"><term>Dendritic</term> or <term>Langerhans cells</term> are tissue macrophages  that contribute to the immune function of the skin. They engulf foreign organisms and signal to the immune system. Since the skin is in constant contact with the environment, it is important to have immune cells to help destroy any pathogens that might get past the cell barrier of the epidermis.</p><example id="db1f765fe2154745988551b62e9b94a3"><title>Eczema</title><p id="ecde5f1c0b414510a6fbeaae27e304ee"><em style="bold">Eczema</em>is an allergic reaction that manifests as dry, itchy patches of skin that resemble rashes. Normally it is useful to have immune cells in the skin, but they can also lead to dysfunction if they become overactive. In eczema, this excess activity may be accompanied by swelling of the skin, flaking, and in severe cases, bleeding. Other allergic (immune-mediated) reactions include hives. Symptoms of these conditions are usually managed with moisturizers and topically with corticosteroid or antihistamine creams that reduce the inflammatory immune response.</p></example><section id="b1e81f48b86f475e9cdd667027803570" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="eczema_SC" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="epidermis_functions_cells" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
