<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_12"><head><title>Organ Level - Dermis</title><objref idref="describe_dermis" /><objref idref="dermis_histology" /></head><body><p id="c9ed9ecb66794cdabc29753541e70be1">The skin&apos;s <term>dermis</term> is made up of two distinct layers of connective tissue. The <term>papillary layer</term> is made up of <term>areolar connective tissue</term> and the underlying <term>reticular layer</term> is composed of dense irregular connective tissue. This dermal part of the skin (organ) is vasculated (has blood vessels) and is innervated (has nerves). As described earlier, the dermis is sparsely populated with fibroblasts that produce collagen and elastin fibers in the extracellular matrix. This leads to a strong and elastic tissue structure. The matrix can also contain mast cells involved in allergic reactions. </p><section id="c527cd4c4a8e4ac1a860218e566e54b1"><title>Papillary Layer</title><body><p id="a95b0e541eb94b87ba59f1f67975a500">The fibroblasts are dispersed within the collagen and elastin fibers of the areolar tissue (loose connective tissue) of the papillary layer. This forms a loose mat, which contains an abundance of small blood vessels. The dermal papillae with blood capillaries interdigitate (become interlocked) with the epidermal ridges of the stratum basale. In addition, the papillary layer contains phagocytes — defensive cells that help fight bacteria or other infections that have breached the skin. This layer is also interspersed with lymph vessels and sensory receptors.</p></body></section><section id="ad520a062f224c628f28129044e6b51c"><title>Reticular Layer</title><body><p id="c825a7306ebc49efb72808d611bd61fd">The reticular layer appears “reticulated” (net-like) because it is composed of a mesh of collagen fibers and elastin fibers. Fibrocytes form the bundles of collagen that extend into the papillary layer and the hypodermis, making these layers hard to distinguish. The flexible collagen provides structure and strength, while elastin lends limited elasticity to the skin. Collagen also binds with water, keeping the skin hydrated. Water is necessary to maintain the normal elasticity and resiliency (called&quot;turgor&quot;) of the skin. Dehydration causes a loss of turgor;if the skin of a dehydrated person is pinched it remains domed and does not immediately flatten out.</p><p id="ee900ee96b334b66ae40cfc35130a8e0">Collagen injections and Retin-A creams help restore skin turgor by introducing collagen externally in the former case or by stimulating blood flow and repair of the dermis in the latter case.</p></body></section><section id="b8cc3f93864c4a50abd1ccc02bb5dc09" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><materials id="fd9a043537164405950c0dde4f4c4a6d"><material><image id="d9190fe20bcb4c5db1155126a8e4a313" src="../../webcontent/Fingerprint_Whorl.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="187" width="200"><caption><p id="d53e2aa916304b9d9f3a4e928a196040">By NIST database (<link href="http://www.nist.gov/srd/fing_img.htm" target="new" internal="false">Fingerprint_Whorl</link>). Public Domain</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><wb:inline idref="describe_dermis" purpose="learnbydoing" /></material></materials></body></section><section id="fb5836a2eae444498978aacd15b6bb79" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="dermis_composition_DIGI" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="dermis_histology" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
