<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_06">
	<head>
		<title>Epithelial Tissue</title>
		<objref idref="id_epidermis_tissue"/>
		<objref idref="epidermis_dermis_cells"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The skin contains many tissue types. The epidermis is classified as <term>epithelial
				tissue</term> composed of stratified squamous epithelia. The dermis is made of
			different types of connective tissues including areolar and dense irregular connective
			tissue, and histiocytes (tissue macrophages). The hypodermis contains areolar connective
			tissue, adipose tissue, and glands.</p>
		<!--<p>skin_cell_matching_LBD</p>-->

		<p>The epidermis is mainly made up of stratified (layered) squamous (flat) epithelial cells.
			Epithelial cells found in the different layers of the epidermis have different shapes.
			Stratification (layering) is important in the epithelial tissue of the integumentary
			system, which forms a barrier. Epithelial cells found in other systems have other
			surface cell
			shapes<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T161358-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
			including cube-like (cuboid) and column-like (columnar) in
			<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T161440-0500"?>a
			<?oxy_insert_end?>single layer (simple) or multiple cell layers (stratified).</p>
		<image src="../../webcontent/IU_M2_6.jpg"/>
		<p>The epidermis contains several cell types of different
			origins<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T162048-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
			including keratinocytes
			(95<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T162141-0500"?>
			percent<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T162144-0500" content="%"?>
			of the cells are keratinocytes), melanocytes, Langerhans cells and Merkel cells. The
			epidermis does not contain blood vessels or nerves, but Merkel cells provide signals to
			the sensory neurons below this layer in the dermis. Since there are no blood vessels,
			living cells of the epidermis are nourished by diffusion from the capillaries of the
			dermal
			p<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121115T162723-0500"?>ap<?oxy_insert_end?>illae
			below.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="epidermis_dermis_cells" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
