<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_03"><head><title>Molecular Level - Vitamin D</title><objref idref="integument_vitaminD" /></head><body><p id="a3c38072711c4ca69c2aeb819aa52d65">The epidermal layer of human skin synthesizes the precursor to <term>vitamin D</term>when exposed to UV radiation. In the presence of sunlight, an isomer of vitamin D<sub>3</sub>, cholecalciferol, is synthesized from a derivative of the steroid cholesterol in the skin. The liver converts cholecalciferol to calcidiol, which is then converted to calcitriol (the active chemical form of the vitamin) in the kidneys. Vitamin D, which is really a hormone, is essential for normal absorption of calcium and phosphorous, which are required for healthy bones. In the present day, this hormone is added as a supplement to many foods including milk and orange juice, compensating for the need for sun exposure.</p><p id="bf43ae177d1944169cd72ce40a62902f">In addition to affecting bone health, Vitamin D is essential for general immunity against bacterial, viral and fungal infections. Recent studies are also finding a link between insufficient vitamin D and cancer.</p><example id="fc0f4b941f8945f48712bd6c652a84fb"><title>Rickets</title><image id="dd6fa7b0ffa54c129de8b5f6fed4a5d6" src="../../../_u5_skeletal/webcontent/Rickets.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a91c92ebb5454b36a5e0417d7260a7f4">Rickets is a disease of bone deterioration often caused by insufficient vitamin D, leading to insufficient calcium absorption. Children are especially prone to effects from this vitamin deficiency due to their rapid bone turnover and formation. In adults, the deficiency of vitamin D is called osteomalacia. Typically rickets is found in developing countries where malnutrition would prevent proper supply of calcium and dietary vitamin D.</p></example><wb:inline idref="recent_rickets_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></workbook_page>
