<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_07">
	<head>
		<title>Connective Tissue</title>
		<objref idref="explain_wrinkles"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>While the epidermis is composed of epithelial cells, the dermis is composed of <term>connective
				tissue</term>. The dermis connects the epidermis to the hypodermis and provides
			structure and elasticity
			from<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T145958-0500" content=" the"?>
			collagen and elastin fibers. These proteins are made by fibroblasts found in the dermis.
			Collagen and elastin work together: collagens provide strength; elastins, as the name
			implies, are elastic and allow for distension. The skin must remain strong to protect
			you from abrasions and other cuts. However, the skin also needs to
			<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150126-0500"?>be able to
			<?oxy_insert_end?>deform and, hopefully, return to its original shape.</p>

		<example>
			<title>Wrinkles</title>
			<p>The permanent folds in the skin caused by a lack of
				<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150149-0500"?>"<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150148-0500" content="‘"?>retraction<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150152-0500"?>"<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150152-0500" content="’"?>
				are called wrinkles. Wrinkling in the skin is caused by habitual facial expressions,
				aging, sun damage, smoking, poor hydration, and various other factors. Wrinkling is
				a surprisingly complex phenomenon. Primarily, sun or other damage to the skin causes
				a breakdown in collagen and elastin as well as a breakdown in the replacement of
				these extracellular matrix proteins in the dermis.</p>
		</example>
		<example>
			<title>Stretch marks</title>
			<p>Stretch marks usually accompany rapid weight gain during puberty and pregnancy as well as
				during the rapid gain of muscle associated with weight lifting. When the dermis (and
				possibly the hypodermis) is stretched beyond its limits of elasticity, the skin
				stretches to accommodate the excess pressure. In some cases, the dermis can’t
				adequately fill in over the stretched areas and
				m<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150537-0500"?>a<?oxy_insert_end?>y
				actual<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150542-0500"?>ly<?oxy_insert_end?>
				tear<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121125T150549-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
				causing the epidermis to become thin and making the underlying blood vessels more
				visible. They initially have a reddish hue, but lighten over time as the tissue
				repairs itself and heals. Other than for cosmetic reasons, treatment of stretch
				marks is not required. They occur most commonly over the hips and abdomen.</p>
		</example>

		<wb:inline idref="explain_wrinkles" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_wrinkles2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
