<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m2_Integ_LOO_02"><head><title>Molecular Level - Keratin and Melanin</title><objref idref="integument_keratin" /><objref idref="integument_melanin" /></head><body><section id="d8e512c2201f475c919384621b4117b9"><title>Keratin</title><body><p id="f467182ff43346f2a2a77f63907bf7ba">Keratin is a group of fibrous proteins that give hair, nails, and skin their tough, water-resistant properties. Keratins are filaments formed from the polymerization of <activity_link idref="levels_m2_organelles_1" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">intermediate filament proteins</activity_link>. In addition to intra- and intermolecular hydrogen bonds, keratins have large amounts of the sulfur-containing amino acid cysteine, which forms disulfide bridges that confer additional strength.</p><p id="a15a040a373c46ce8137e4b6ffe03e0b">Keratins are an excellent example of protein assembly. Keratins have an alpha-helix secondary structure in the central rod domain. Two keratin proteins then come together and the helices wind around themselves to form a quaternary structure of a coiled-coil dimer. These dimers then assemble into protofilaments and then filaments. The twists of twists are similar to fibers inside of ropes. However, keratins aren&apos;t twisted by machines; they self assemble based on their <activity_link idref="levels_m1_protein" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">primary structure</activity_link>.</p><materials id="cfd92784f09a46f7bb6e11f73db74756"><material><image id="cea71410a775453aa79fc71d0f16549e" src="../../webcontent/IU_M2_2.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><image id="ccc485bbf2fe4f34b06fd9df98721d39" src="../../webcontent/IU_M2_3.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material></materials></body></section><section id="ec14277990064a12ae9c2a617e0b9ad2"><title>Melanin</title><body><p id="d19ec82f5ddc4d0bb77ca804e1ad07de">Melanin is a class of photopigment (&quot;photo,&quot; meaning &quot;light,&quot; and &quot;pigment,&quot; meaning&quot;colored material&quot;) with a molecular structure that allows it to absorb UV (ultraviolet) radiation from the sun. Melanin transforms the energy from the radiation into harmless heat, and melanin prevents the indirect DNA damage from the sun that is responsible for many skin cancers. Melanin also gives skin, hair and eyes their color. Melanin is produced by specialty cells called melanocytes, inside special vesicles called melanosomes. About 10 days after initial sun exposure, melanin synthesis peaks, which is why pale-skinned individuals tend to suffer sunburns of the epidermis initially. </p><section id="d0731f804a9d4a038812a4cf2db13631" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="melanin_keratin_DIGI" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="integument_keratin_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><example id="c15616b8b8674bf49479be550acff978"><title>Albinism</title><p id="bb48f6ae749d4f54b8603eda7e522254"><em style="bold">Albinism</em>is a genetic disorder that affects (completely or partially) the coloring of skin, hair, and eyes. The defect is primarily due to the inability of melanocytes to produce melanin. Individuals with albinism tend to appear white or very pale due to the lack of melanin in their skin and hair. Melanin protects the DNA of skin cells from the harmful effects of UV rays from the sun. Individuals with albinism need more protection from the sun and must limit their outdoor activities. Treatment of this disorder usually involves addressing the symptoms.</p></example><wb:inline idref="albinism_disease_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
