<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_02"><head><title>Digestive System</title><objref idref="_u1_describe_digestive_system" /></head><body><image id="c16a39caf9464b7e900d3dd89b7d987d" src="../webcontent/I_M2_1.jpg" alt="labeled diagram of the digestive system organs and their locations" style="block" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><caption><p id="ae7c1c800e6f541b481d7640e6d5cbfc8"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="fc382f573f27428486579eda2ec0dad1"><title>Digestive System - Function</title><body><p id="bc1ce282c8a349f994a8832a696bcedf">Also called the <term>gastrointestinalsystem</term>, the digestive system breaks down eaten material into nutrient molecules, absorbs water and ions, and eliminates undigested residue. </p><p id="bec099ff2ec04c89a6f1a7c4f258fbec">The digestive system is a continuous tube (the digestive tract or alimentary canal). Areas along this tube are specialized to perform different functions related to getting the nutrients from your food to the cells that need them. Accessory organs add secretions into different areas along the tube.</p><p id="aff8b3048dc94afa963b44e1faa34701">Your cells can’t use the pizza you had for lunch in pizza form. It needs to be broken down into molecules that are small enough to be absorbed. As the pizza travels along the digestive tract, each organ along the way breaks it down further. Muscles in the walls of the digestive tract keep things moving along, and glands in the tissues secrete digestive juices—mostly enzymes and acids—that break up the larger substances in the pizza into smaller molecules. Food is physically broken into smaller pieces in a process termed mechanical digestion. These pieces are then chemically broken down into smaller units in a process termed chemical digestion. Proteins are broken down into amino acids. Carbohydrates are broken down into simple sugars. Fats are broken down into molecules like fatty acids and cholesterol. It is important that the large particles are broken into their smallest units so they can be absorbed from the digestive tract into the bloodstream. Therefore, the main functions of the digestive system are to ingest, break down, and absorb the nutrients from our food. It also eliminates the wastes (anything not absorbed) as feces.</p><wb:inline idref="functions_of_digestive_system" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="af37ac288b6a43aa820c95d6b9e7ebbb"><title>Digestive System - Organs</title><body><p id="d904a319e0af47bb92d8504e31a4ef3b">The specialized organs of the digestive tract extend in a roughly superior to inferior direction from the mouth (where food goes in) to the anus (where waste comes out) in the following order:</p><ul id="cde2490d1ec54120a40a87efefdcdf2c"><li><p id="acb9447d5262949acaf125b64f9cd5d9f">Mouth</p></li><li><p id="f2d26d2d3c2b4d418020ae8ca909b05f"><term>Pharynx</term></p></li><li><p id="be168fcecd8a4c6b94055ca43e83581a"><term>Esophagus</term></p></li><li><p id="adf8bcdebd83e4c44b6d5c414368168f4">Stomach</p></li><li><p id="afb936c7862a44531ba536c8588d94bc1">Small intestine (including the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum)</p></li><li><p id="eaf6a5ccf8114844ae78ef7bab09d0c0">Large Intestine (including the cecum, colon, and <term>rectum</term>)</p></li><li><p id="aac3f60d9866c4300a43e4d9b0284b012">Anus</p></li></ul><p id="f87d8d617fdb40f8a7d8be4d506b5a3a">Accessory organs in the digestive system are connected to the digestive tract and secrete additional digestive juices. </p><p id="f1fc4e794489452c9574239e281cd90a">The <term>salivary glands</term> produce saliva containing (among others) amylase, an enzyme that breaks down carbohydrates.</p><p id="f36e740c021149578eff9cb27e82a856">The <term>pancreas</term> secretes a variety of enzymes that break down fats, carbohydrates, and proteins, as well as bicarbonate ions that neutralize stomach acids. It is important to note that this function corresponds to the exocrine portion of the pancreas.</p><p id="e389506c76624ed48a077db83e3f1e78">The <term>liver</term> produces bile, which aids in fat digestion and absorption.</p><p id="e845a8a3938e41c2a40c07da3e1a5836">The <term>gall bladder</term> stores and concentrates bile and secretes it into the small intestine.</p><p id="c936802d13354e0197dc4286b0c9b4e6">The <term>stomach</term> is a sort of muscular sac that can expand to hold a large meal. Glands in the walls of the stomach secrete enzymes and acids that break down food. Muscles in the walls of the stomach churn the food and digestive juices together. Although the stomach can receive a large amount of food at a time, it releases its contents gradually into the small intestine, so that the intestine can better perform its function.</p><p id="d50b29310b1743ff933d3fe4bcd24146">Digestion continues in the <term>small intestine</term>, with additional digestive juices produced by the pancreas, liver, and the walls of the small intestine itself. The walls of the small intestine have numerous tiny folds, which increase its surface area, allowing for efficient absorption of nutrients into the circulatory system, which in turn takes the nutrients to all the cells of the body. </p><p id="a7965d5017304cb88f2973c3376ecaba">Excess water is reabsorbed in the <term>large intestine</term>, and the undigested portion of your pizza leaves the body. Resident microbes of the large intestine (gut microbiota) can digest substances that our cells cannot. </p><section id="e9d31f3a502946e68bde5efae2aeb1eb" purpose="walkthrough"><title> </title><body><youtube id="c61c73d90e2f401aaafc11b0c8a48944" src="UvYxngt-mC4" height="300" width="500" controls="true"><cite id="ibfe51f9fa3724f579819ae81991eb0ef" /><caption><p id="bfe87b9a354940c4851d3d36ce39ba6d"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube></body></section></body></section><section id="faaa69848d434976ab0a5dd3fc1d7157" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><materials id="fbfb302af7894680ab0e79186dfb500b"><material><image id="f6aeb5b4b2274d0da59d74d9466b39d0" src="../webcontent/Digestion_identify.jpg" alt="diagram of digestive system organs                     with each organ numbered 1-9" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption><p id="af7712cfa684c4fa6b130f5b579a0dc40"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_exchange_digestive_inline01" purpose="learnbydoing" /></material></materials></body></section><section id="d92c85f9888547eca4da0e9ee77bae92"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_digestive_identify_extra_inline" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="ae90e3b8a6974b9ebf0da8239c8afc54"><title>Digestive System - Anatomy and Direction</title><body><p id="c46308b6178a46eb8319932899a4a0dd">The digestive system is located primarily in the abdomen. </p><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_exchange_digestive_inline01-b" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
