<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_09">
    <head>
        <title>Integumentary System</title>
        <objref idref="_u1_describe_integumentary_system"/>
    </head>
    <body>
       
            <image src="../webcontent/Upper_body_man.jpg" alt="Integumentary System: Skin, Hair and Nails" 
             vertical-align="middle" style="block" height="350" width="267"></image>
        
        <section>
            <title>Integumentary System - Function</title>
            <body>
                
                <p>We often don't think of the skin as a complex organ, but it is. The skin is the primary organ in the 
                    integumentary system, which also includes hair, nails, and certain glands. The integumentary system 
                    helps to provide support and structure for the body, but it also plays several other important roles:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>It is the first line of defense against foreign organisms and the external environment.</li>
                    <li>It helps to regulate body temperature. </li>
                    <li>It senses changes in the environment (pain, pressure, touch). </li>
                    <li>It supports the removal of wastes (as sweat). </li>
                    <li>It aids in the production of vitamin D. </li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>The integumentary system is one of the most active parts of our body, even though
                    we are not as aware of its activity as we are with the heart, lungs or stomach.
                    The integumentary system encapsulates and protects the body. The skin is
                    actually the largest organ in the body because of its large surface area. In
                    some ways, the skin can be thought of as an immune system organ, since it
                    protects the body from foreign organisms. In other ways the skin can be thought
                    of as a sensory organ because it contains many nerves that are related to the
                    sense of touch. The skin also integrates with muscles and allows for movements
                    such as facial expression. </p>
                
            </body>
        </section>
        
    <section>
        <title>Integumentary System - Organs and Structures</title>
    <body>
        
       <image src="../webcontent/Skin_layers_rev-Labels.jpg" 
            alt="Diagram of the Integumentary System" vertical-align="middle" style="block" height="349" width="400"> </image>
        
        <p>If we take a closer look at the skin, you can see that there are many layers. Within the skin there are hair follicles from which hair grows. Also, there are sweat glands that produce sweat for thermal regulation of the body and sebaceous glands that secrete oil to waterproof and moisturize the skin. Nails are also included in the integumentary system, as are horns, feathers, claws and hooves...but hopefully you don't have any of those.</p>
            
            
           <p> The major structures within the integumentary system are:    </p>   
            <ul>
                <li>skin </li>
                <li>hair, nails </li>
                <li>sebaceous glands </li>
                <li>sweat glands</li>
            </ul>   
        <p><term>Skin</term>, the largest organ of the body, is the primary organ of the integumentary
                    system. Skin is composed of three main layers, each of which has specific
                    functions related to its structure. The three main layers of the skin are:</p> 
             <ul>
                 <li><term>epidermis</term>, which acts as a seamless, waterproof barrier to the
                        external environment and prevents excessive water loss from the body (the
                        root "epi-" means "above"). </li>
                 <li><term>dermis</term>, which provides the tensile strength and elasticity of the skin, contains nerves and sensory receptors and 
                     contains blood vessels that aid in regulating body temperature. </li>
                 <li><term>hypodermis</term>, which attaches skin to other structures below it and acts
                        as an insulator and shock absorber (the root "hypo-" means "below"); the
                        hypodermis is also known as the subcutaneous layer. </li>       
             </ul>   
        <p><term>Hair</term>, another component of the integumentary system, is found in nearly all
                    regions of the skin, except on the palms, soles of the feet, and some parts of
                    the genitals. Hair grows from <term>hair follicles</term> that are part of the
                    epidermis, even though they extend down and the dermis extends up around them.
                    Hair helps regulate body temperature and protect the surface of the body,
                    including eyelashes that protect the eyes. </p>
        
        <p><term>Nails</term> are located on the end of each distal phalanx (each finger and each toe).
                    They protect the phalanges from trauma, and provide mechanical support for
                    manipulating objects. Nails grow from epidermal cells in the nail beds.</p>
   
        <p>Glandular structures are also part of the epidermis, and are present in different regions
                    of the skin. They secrete substances that are important for many physiological
                    functions. There are three main types of glands:</p>
          <ul>
            <li><term>sebaceous glands</term>, whose secretions maintain the softness and hydrophobicity
                        (water repellency) of the hair and skin. </li>
            <li><term>apocrine glands</term>, whose secretions moisten the skin during pain, fear, sexual arousal and emotional upset.</li>
            <li><term>merocrine (eccrine) glands</term>, which secrete sweat to regulate body temperature.</li>
          </ul>
        
    </body>
        
    </section>
         
        <!--         
        <p><em style="highlight">Walkthrough video illustrating the Integumentary System</em></p>
          
        <pullout type="note">
            <title><em style="highlight">FIXME - Walkthrough of the integumentary system</em></title>
            <image src="../webcontent/film_strip_brown-1.png" alt="Video Film Strip" 
                vertical-align="middle" style="block" height="75" width="102"></image>
            
            <p>
                        The integumentary system encapsulates and protects the
                            body. The skin is actually the largest organ in the body because of its
                            large surface area. In some ways, the skin can be thought of as an
                            immune system organ, since it protects the body from foreign organisms.
                            In other ways the skin can be thought of as a sensory organ because it
                            contains many nerves that are related to the sense of touch. The skin
                            also integrates with muscles and allows for movements such as facial
                            expression. If we take a closer look at the skin, you can see that there
                            are many layers. Within the skin there are hair follicles from which
                            hair grows. Also, there are sweat glands that produce sweat for thermal
                            regulation of the body and sebacious glands that secrete oil to
                            waterproof and moisturize the skin. Nails are also included in the
                            integumentary system, as are horns, feathers, claws and hooves ... but
                            hopefully you don't have any of those.</p>
        
        
       Inline assessment 1: Functions and Structures of the Integumentary System -->
        
        <section purpose="learnbydoing">
            <title/>
            <body>
              <materials orient="horizontal">
                  
                  <material><image src="../webcontent/IU_M1_1nolabel.jpg" width="300"></image> </material> 
                <material>  <wb:inline idref="_u1_describe_integument_structure_lbd"></wb:inline></material>
              </materials>
                
            </body>
        </section>
        
        
        
        
        <wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_integumentary_inline01" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
       
        <!-- 
        <p><em>Did You Get It?</em> If so, then go ahead and move on to the next page. If not, then
            click the link below for some additional practice.</p>
        -->
        
        
  

        
        
                <wb:inline idref="functions_of_integumentary_system" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
               
        
        <section>
            <title>Integumentary System - Anatomy and Direction</title>
            <body>
                <!-- 
                <image src="../webcontent/Surface_projections_of_the_organs_of_the_trunk_353x500px.png"  alt="Organs Projected on the Body Surface" 
                    height="400" width="282" vertical-align="middle" style="inline"/> 
                -->
                <p>The skin covers the outside surface of the body. Special structures such as hair, nails and glands are 
                    part of the integumentary system. </p>
                
                <!-- MJB: Inline assessment activities -->
                <wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_integumentary_inline02" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline> 
                
            </body>
        </section>
       <!-- <section>
            <title>Related Topics for Further Study</title>
            <body>
                <p><em>Cells and cell
                        renewal:<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20111031T174949-0400" content=" "?></em>
                    One way that our skin is able to protect us from environmental damage is that it
                    continually renews cells. Cells in the deeper regions of the skin reproduce by
                    mitosis and push their way to the outer layers of the skin, where they are shed
                    off. Thus, as outer cells are damaged, they are replaced by newer cells.</p>
               
                <p><em>Pheromones:</em> The secretions from apocrine glands commonly contain
                    chemicals called pheromones. These chemical signals are detected by other people
                    and can affect their behavior or hormone production, including reproductive
                    cycles. These signals are active in humans, not just in other animals. </p>               
             </body>
        </section>-->
    
    </body>
 
</workbook_page>
