<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_05">
    <head>
        <title>Fluid Transport Within the Body</title>

    </head>

    <body>
        <p>Our body constantly transports molecules from one place to another to carry out the
            required metabolic functions for daily living. As we take in nutrients and oxygen, these
            molecules must be delivered to the cells, tissues, and organs that need them for
            metabolic processes. Furthermore, our body must have a system for disposing of wastes
            generated by metabolism and foreign particles, which may potentially disturb optimal
            body function. The cardiovascular and lymphatic systems coordinate a diverse set of
            transport functions.</p>

        <p>The <extra>
                <anchor><term>cardiovascular</term></anchor>
                <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/cardiovascular.mp3"
                    type="audio/mp3"/>
            </extra> system consists of the blood, heart, and blood vessels. The heart supplies the
            force to circulate blood throughout the body via the blood vessels. Blood is the main
            fluid used to deliver nutrients to the body’s tissues and to receive wastes that will
            ultimately be removed from the body by the urinary system. The respiratory and
            cardiovascular systems work together to take oxygen in from the external environment and
            deliver it, via blood, to cells. In a similar fashion, these systems also use the blood
            to remove carbon dioxide from cells and release it into the external environment. The
            red blood cells or erythrocytes are responsible for the transport of respiratory gasses.
            The <extra>
                <anchor><term>lymphatic</term></anchor>
                <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/lymphatic.mp3" type="audio/mp3"
                />
            </extra> system consists of lymphatic vessels which are near blood vessels and several
            organs such as lymph nodes, the thymus gland, and spleen. It returns excess tissue fluid
            to the cardiovascular system while initiating immune responses to ensure that the
            delivered blood is not compromised, responding to foreign invasion in multiple ways. The
            lymphatic system is an integrated part of the immune system to cleanse body fluids of
            dead cells, toxins, and pathogens. Together, the transport systems of the body
            coordinate the efforts of nutrient delivery and removal of wastes and other harmful
            substances. In addition to transporting the fluid, fluid/electrolyte balance must be maintained by integrated function of these organ systems: urinary, lymphatic and cardiovascular.</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
