<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u1_m2_intro_systems_ex_10"><head><title>Skeletal System</title><objref idref="_u1_describe_skeletal_system" /></head><body><materials id="skeletal" title="skeletal_front-back"><material><image id="d5e82180b8514d36b60bf99d84658e9c" src="../webcontent/Skeletal_Front.jpg" alt="Skeletal System" style="block" vertical-align="middle" height="200" width="200"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><image id="e63491cbde5e42bc9e119bb8019174a1" src="../webcontent/Skeletal_Back.jpg" alt="Skeletal System" style="block" vertical-align="middle" height="200" width="200"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material></materials><section id="b44ab0c32d84468bb8f50475dd5a7392"><title>Skeletal System - Function</title><body><p id="e0d3d39877494a0babb1091bef77e9a5">The skeletal system, which includes the skeleton and articulations (joints), provides support and protection for soft tissues and organs, aids in movement, serves as a reservoir of calcium, and produces all blood cells.</p><p id="cfc9e75310d64c29ba0eab0ae36c8bfe">Although we often think of bones as the only organs of the skeletal system, cartilage, ligaments and tendons are equally important organs. These structures of the skeletal system work together to:</p><ul id="c31bb41ff4a34f5086f9e77295c3013c"><li><p id="ae681d729276c45f5ae18c0618b9b062b">provide leverage and resist forces from muscles and gravity.</p></li><li><p id="ae33740ef88b4425cb805b2a649561c19">keep joints together. </p></li><li><p id="aaf621a74e4b144ccb7e10412eb4bf593">allow flexibility within joints. </p></li><li><p id="ace8ba24ded1342e8bc7cb86ef836fc3c">maintain a safe range of motion. </p></li></ul><p id="ff3626c1344c4163b32759b009630058">Bones are found throughout the body from the skull in the head to the 26 bones in the foot. Bones allow us to maintain our stature, they protect softer internal organs, and they let us move around. Bones are interconnected by articulations, another word for joints. In an articulation, where bone meets bone, there is a layer of softer cartilage. Articulations are then stabilized by ligaments, which help keep the bones aligned properly. Bones are connected to the muscular system by tendons, which allow the body to move.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u1_describe_skeletal_structure_lbd2" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="dc536d792b52403ca106dfdb12cec75e"><title>Skeletal System - Organs</title><body><image id="c4acff6be8784bf7a3c2a562a705abe0" src="../webcontent/S_M9_10A2.jpg" alt="" style="block" vertical-align="middle" height="349" width="350"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="beca773f662544a6a055a0e4b5e2d2ea">The major structures within the skeletal system are: </p><ul id="f1ff42e9cd0a429fb70291eb9b8d2fc1"><li><p id="aa775c367868344a5a10ea3082fb13398">bones</p></li><li><p id="ab7c1865db5d14eb4861e932a604661e8">cartilage</p></li><li><p id="ab48530f8371d4755a8367cd08e3bd034">ligaments</p></li><li><p id="ab319e6b48a984ba9934464e807bc7dd4">tendons</p></li></ul><p id="ca70bdbc199f42789c80ed2f282c490a">The skeletal system consists of bones, ligaments, tendons, and cartilage. Bone is the primary organ of the skeletal system. Although there are different types of bones in our body, the basic components of all bone tissue are the same: </p><ul id="a7ba0558d2a34f36a33276be525eb144"><li><p id="ab845fa2f073e484f87b96cb977b46371">Osteoblasts, osteoclasts, and osteocytes, which are specialized cells that are responsible for bone formation, regulation and repair. </p></li><li><p id="ae7b429cfe0b6434d92d8a11ac15984bb">Collagens and other proteins, which give bone its flexibility.</p></li><li><p id="aecebbc0a7846422d9a5fd0d2605009a8">Inorganic calcium and phosphate minerals, which give bone its hardness.</p></li><li><p id="ad9a85b0ec57b44b1b859b11f5375cde6">Red bone marrow, which produces all blood cells in a process termed hematopoiesis (or hemopoiesis).</p></li></ul><p id="a0efc7531d424632b4e13d0e0ee3666f">These basic components give bone tissue its load-bearing, protective qualities. The living cells in bone allow it to sense and respond to stress. The inorganic matrix of bone gives the bone rigidity and also acts as a storage depot for calcium and phosphorus in the body. </p><p id="bfae7f796b35444489985d3575c1a79c"><term>Cartilage</term> is a firm, flexible, and smooth connective tissue found at the ends of bones. Cartilage is present in joints to protect the bone and to evenly distribute forces to the underlying bone. </p><p id="b5be401a390c4da5a924e4df281eb5bc"><term>Ligaments</term> are band-like elastic structures that surround joints to hold them together. Ligaments connect one bone to another bone, and allow movement in very specific directions. </p><p id="a14ffacaa4c24ecc823824a9a5eb4c3e"><term>Tendons</term> are band-like structures similar to ligaments. However, tendons are more rigid and connect bones to muscles. Tendons play a role in integrating the force generation of the muscle with the rigid bone, which helps actuate large-scale motion. </p><p id="e671e95ab4c44c1bb760c05b69a73683">The numerous organs and structures of the skeletal system allow it to serve an important role in the support and protection of our body. Bones are very strong, yet flexible which makes them perfect for supporting our weight and allowing movement. The connective tissues such as cartilage, ligaments, and tendons aid in protecting our joints and providing stability. The red bone marrow inside the bone is vital for hematopoiesis or the production of all blood cells. Bones are also a reservoir for calcium. If your diet is deficient in calcium, a hormone will mobilize calcium from the bones to the blood, and your bones will be weaker.</p><wb:inline idref="_u1_describe_skeletal_structure_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="d426aa6f3c91494d8a7054e1f85fcc8a" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><image id="f69248c8bab041cc91522cc95cd90810" src="../webcontent/knee_joint.png" alt="Knee joint" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_skeletal_inline01" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u1_describe_skeletal_function_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="e9669f5b0bef4fac8b6706ce5abff3a3"><title>Skeletal System - Anatomy and Direction</title><body><p id="ed5b28e64df048a18fd458d462c35209">Bones are found throughout the body. Regions capable of more intricate movements, such as the hands and feet, have more articulations and therefore more bones. Each articulation has cartilage and is stabilized by ligaments.</p><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_skeletal_inline02" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
