<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.2//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_2.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u0_devskills2_tutor4">
    <title>Tutor</title>
    

  
    <page>
        <question id="q1">
            <body>Pablo has a busy semester, and he does not want to give too much time to OLI Statistics.
               So he puts off working through the course, figuring that he’ll spend a couple of weeks at the end of the semester
                doing it all at once. In the end, he fails the final exam. His principal
                mistake was that he did not <input_ref input="ans5"/></body>

            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" id="ans5">
                <choice value="A">properly assess the task.</choice>
                <choice value="B">accurately evaluate his own strengths and weaknesses.</choice>
                <choice value="C">plan an effective strategy for working through the
                    course.</choice>
                <choice value="D">successfully monitor his own performance.</choice>
                <choice value="E">adjust his approach.</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="1">
                    <feedback>Correct. Pablo underestimated the task, and left himself too little
                        time to prepare for the final exam. This underestimation is reflected in his
                        strategy; because he did not properly assess the task, he did not plan
                        appropriately.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback> Incorrect. Because Pablo did not bother to assess the task, he never
                        had the opportunity to evaluate his own strengths and weaknesses in relation
                        to the learning objectives. </feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Pablo’s plan for working through the course did not allow
                        sufficient time, but that was mostly because of his inaccurate assessment of
                        the task.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Pablo had limited opportunity to monitor his own
                        performance because he failed to assess the task accurately, and thus left
                        all his work until the last minute.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The problem is not that Pablo didn't reflect back on his
                        approach; the problem is that he failed to properly assess the
                        task.</feedback>
                </response>
                <!--<hint>Click on the definitions for each skill in the metacognitive cycle from the
                    earlier page to see if one looks like a match.</hint>
                <hint>Notice that Pablo wound up in trouble because he didn’t consider how long it
                    would actually take to complete the course successfully.</hint>-->
                
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
