<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u0_devskills1_tutor1"><title>Tutor</title><page id="f8dd9806ff204fe7b29b7e4dc8c76ead"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><content available="always"><p id="bf6c06d6154e4d5fbfd52501f4e2d6c5">Joe has just started the doing work in the statistics course. He wants to get through it as quickly as possible while still making sure he is prepared to do well on the Checkpoint activity in two weeks. He sees a bunch of text with some activities sprinkled throughout, and is trying to decide how to proceed. </p><p id="a7025073354e4b3ea190beea27e096bb">Indicate whether each of the following would likely be an effective and efficient strategy for Joe:</p></content><question id="q1"><body><p id="ee73624b78e3425c9c8454f3283500fd">Jump straight to the activities without reading the text. For each activity, select different answer choices to see if they’re right or wrong and read the feedback that appears.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="a107a9d27efc46c79f32b3e9c5369ff5"><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback><p id="a550774cf5434c98b4ee13133f5e3f20">Not quite right. Learning by doing can be a good idea. However, Joe should keep in mind that the feedback for correct and incorrect answers is not as complete as the preceding text, so he might be missing important information. </p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback><p id="b74be189468046d6802abb5d49d048fd">Correct. Learning by doing can be a good idea. However, Joe should keep in mind that the feedback for correct and incorrect answers is not as complete as the preceding text, so he might be missing important information. </p></feedback></response><hint><p id="cd5cfa7320214e9a8c0e090396a4547e">Think about which of these different strategies will be most likely to give Joe (a) all the information he needs for the final exam and (b) opportunities to practice applying the information and checking his understanding.</p></hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="a0bc527894c347929c5989d7bba7138b">Jump straight to the first activity and if he cannot answer it, go back to the beginning of the unit to read the text.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="b4fac780a6d04be7ab112690cf1c179c"><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback><p id="d20b3e125a024285888e38de29c3f041">Correct. If Joe has some previous experience with statistics, this may be the most efficient and effective strategy for him. The good thing about this strategy is that Joe uses the activities as a way to assess his own capabilities and then adjusts his approach accordingly. Moreover, by deciding to go back to read the preceding text, Joe is giving himself a chance to practice independent learning.</p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback><p id="c99a481dfd7d46599af3029227042298">Not quite right. If Joe has some previous experience with statistics, this may be the most efficient and effective strategy for him. The good thing about this strategy is that Joe uses the activities as a way to assess his own capabilities and then adjusts his approach accordingly. Moreover, by deciding to go back to read the preceding text, Joe is giving himself a chance to practice independent learning.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="d25732e520b74266aa05c4e50ec9bc6e">Think about which of these different strategies will be most likely to give Joe (a) all the information he needs for the final exam and (b) opportunities to practice applying the information and checking his understanding.</p></hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p id="dd961c190a444e5ba6cc8a01a79c64b7">Jump straight to the activities, and after realizing that he has no idea how to answer the first few, quit and plan to attend recitation that week.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="ca5cf7afa32848f88bcfdccd1a033122"><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback><p id="e5fc390ef17c4e6da05b9e191e9f5c77">Not quite right. This approach is unlikely to be effective, since Joe will not know what questions to ask at the recitation. By seeking help before trying to learn the material himself, Joe misses the chance to practice learning independently.</p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback><p id="b5400505a5e545d8bab4a80a53095712">Correct. This approach is unlikely to be effective, since Joe will not know what questions to ask at the recitation. By seeking help before trying to learn the material himself, Joe misses the chance to practice learning independently.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="faadcc05b60644b7a2baaf0eee747773">Think about which of these different strategies will be most likely to give Joe (a) all the information he needs for the final exam and (b) opportunities to practice applying the information and checking his understanding.</p></hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p id="eb2416285be440ab9c463c588a82ba42">Read the unit straight through from the beginning and do the activities as they come up.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="f08152d04ebd4dd2a8c491caaeed3adb"><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback><p id="f7944897c77745adbc35835a862deb81">Correct. If this is Joe&apos;s first statistics course, this may be the most efficient and effective strategy for him. </p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback><p id="b8cc77712a4f44f09ac1d7367725ce07">Not quite right. If this is Joe&apos;s first statistics course, this may be the most efficient and effective strategy for him. </p></feedback></response><hint><p id="d3485a6d2d9a4d5abb820a5341acee31">Think about which of these different strategies will be most likely to give Joe (a) all the information he needs for the final exam and (b) opportunities to practice applying the information and checking his understanding.</p></hint></part></question><question id="q5"><body><p id="b839dcc116634c57b0e5b99f6b1ad4d9">Read the unit straight through from the beginning, but skip the activities.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="d77f57abee8b4db5b2c62986b83161a8"><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback><p id="fa6b090e1365413d859f3022e7634ec8">Not quite right. Although reading the text will provide Joe with the information content of the unit, by skipping the activities he misses the chance to practice and check his understanding.</p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback><p id="c00de7333b61405c908dc488b5eef3fc">Correct. Although reading the text will provide Joe with the information content of the unit, by skipping the activities he misses the chance to practice and check his understanding.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="fb52f74d5d4f46e1857a27c3b06c323c">Think about which of these different strategies will be most likely to give Joe (a) all the information he needs for the final exam and (b) opportunities to practice applying the information and checking his understanding.</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
