<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_9"><head><title>Cells of the Innate Immune Response</title><objref idref="lymph_wbc_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_innate_LO" /></head><body><ol id="e8ec6b46a1b947a9830f0a1bac86b918" style="none"><li><p id="bdbdf9d9e1004a449f55f9bd88696d16"><term>Mast cells-</term></p><p id="cf0713282353401ba12537e58540aebf">When an infection occurs, local immune cells react and emit signals or chemicals to recruit other immune cells. Among the first to respond are the mast cells that are found surrounding tissues and lymphatic vessels. When bacteria infect tissues, mast cells recognize parts of the bacterial cell wall and release cytokines that recruit neutrophils, eosinophils, basophils and T cells. As part of adaptive immunity, IgE antibodies mediate release of granules, a combination of chemicals that cause vasodilation (histamine, bradykinin), anti-coagulation (heparin), or cell lysis (lysozymes). In this way, mast cell orchestrate allergic responses.</p></li><li><p id="a2169192b04d47b3af972870ef156036"><term>Monocytes and Macrophages-</term></p><p id="cc66824801b04823918e89a6c77880d7">Monocytes circulate in the blood. Chemokines and cytokines signal for the influx of monocytes to a specific area. The cells circulate to the location, migrate into the tissues and differentiate into macrophages. Macrophages reside in almost all tissues. Macrophages engulf pathogens and assist in the immune response by presenting antigenic peptides to helper T cells. Macrophages secrete cytokines that promote inflammation and fever.</p><image id="bc11b175ea124f31a6786cb3fcd18f7c" src="../webcontent/Lymph_19.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="900" width="649"><caption><p id="aa99f93d229374deb9382350fe3081846">Interaction of Innate and Adaptive Immunity</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></li><li><p id="c22267dc489e4d879ecf1f4b0e71b69a"><term>Neutrophils-</term></p><p id="e4f176a4132645df96c8fe8e6a01e418">Neutrophils are the most abundant circulating white blood cell, comprising 50 - 70% of all infiltrating leukocytes. Tissue damage from an infection results in the release of chemokines and other chemical attractant agents called cytokines. These chemokines and cytokines signal for the influx of neutrophils to a specific area. Neutrophils engulf bacteria, digest it and eliminate the infection in a process called phagocytosis.</p></li><li><p id="e91a89e4e81948fb9eaeb26fc961339c"><term>Eosinophils-</term></p><p id="a24baf50ad254ae685e046497601dddd">Eosinophils target parasitic infections and are abundant in allergic reactions, although eosinophils only constitute a small percentage (1-6%) of leukocytes. The granules of eosinophils include cytotoxic and neurotoxin proteins that can be released to kill multicellular worm parasites. Eosinophils release their toxic and inflammatory mediators through an adaptive immune response. Antibodies (IgE) mediate release of their granules.</p></li><li><p id="acfc24710c574c27b123e67fccb022e8"><term>Basophils-</term></p><p id="b6675ac824d04c16bc38dfc5fee5269c">Basophils are the least abundant circulating white blood cell, constituting only 1–2% of leukocytes. Basophils are recruited by cytokines from the blood to sites of infection. Basophils release histamine, a vasodilator, and heparin, an anti-coagulant, that aid in the infiltration of leukocytes from the bloodstream to site of infection. Basophils are activated through innate receptors and IgE antibodies.</p></li><li><p id="a65ec7446bbc497f9413fcd316c72d02"><term>Dendritic cells-</term></p><p id="ec7949e718274f978f71dc0ac841a2ca">Dendritic cells are large, motile cells with long, cytoplasmic extensions. There are several kinds of dendritic cells. These cells migrate through the blood stream from bone marrow and enter tissues. They engulf particulate matter and continually ingest large amounts of extracellular fluid and its contents. Like macrophages and neutrophils, they degrade the pathogens, but their main role is not the clearance of microorganisms. Instead, encounter with pathogen stimulates dendritic cells to activate a particular class of T lymphocytes.</p></li></ol><image id="e517a1aabb554bfb8162c0777fce2168" src="../webcontent/Lymph_10.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="554" width="400"><caption><p id="aca9994d23308477f863de7bd8631fcc3">Dendritic Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><ol id="fd5b4317e0674479ba3c47e8ff96f520" style="none"><li><p id="e156336f3d1c4ad0a221d9b2127eca2e"><term>Natural killer cells-</term></p><p id="a9eaa845b4de406ea0d93620acf3735e">Natural killer cells or NK cells are leukocytes that are critically important in the lysis of viral-infected cells. It is thought that NK cells are also able to lyse and eliminate tumor cells. Therefore, many researchers are trying to learn how NK cells function to eliminate tumors in order to design better anti-cancer agents. Binding of NK cells to a target cell, causes the release of granules containing toxic substances. Some granules contain a protein called <term>perforin</term>. These perforin proteins insert into the plasma membrane of the target cell and create holes in the membrane. Extracellular fluid flows through these channels and the cell bursts. Other granules of NK cells release <term>granzymes</term> which induces the tumor or infected cell to undergo self-destruction (apotosis). Unlike traumatic cell death (necrosis), apoptosis is a controlled cell death that produces cell fragments that can be quickly removed before there is damage to the surrounding cells.</p></li></ol><section id="f4683c413e314564bea3bf584d203f3f"><title>White Blood Cells and Their Function in Innate Immunity</title><body><table id="ef2b2780f7024f268b80c414f371a2db" summary="" rowstyle="alternating"><cite id="i39c415b80e1b48ad842a607241e132b0" /><caption><p id="aba55f8be71154ce28f27c0d532bffc12"></p></caption><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="aa656c4b5cc954db0a3f15970f22078c0">Cell</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="aabd7780c71cb4310a3246ecb739480b4">Function</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adc37ab0eee194b61bc723ab1aa90d8c6">Mast cell</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abbf5057c52a34c779314f1fad881f709">release chemicals to initiate an immune response and orchestrate allergic response</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa7a3043303dc42dea4a456774fa98796">Macrophages</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac9a541bcfede4dc8869ea6debc1eeddc">phagocytosis of pathogen and release cytokines to orchestrate immune response</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af5ce4db7920a4c9580ef26db127c3453">Neutrophils</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af56d6e693c434b63af37b21bc9863101">phagocytosis of pathogen</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaba652ceea1b42b3b5fc3e429a89fe8c">Eosinophils</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac46d73755388455dab6bf4c0ae3baf22">destruction of worm parasites and abundant in allergic response</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaffe6ae61b9641df89aa0acc8296ced1">Basophils</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa10e218a01c54e80a4f3d55d06254496">release chemicals to initiate an inflammatory response</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aedd59c7e66c341a389e6ed9665e0d9c5">Dendritic cells</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa31c73edb0484f709e8ec2af3a63093d">phagocytosis and presentation of pathogen as bridge between innate and adaptive immune responses</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afcf62506f2714ec9a486b3514169fd8f">Natural killer cells</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad6e04437a578409dba4ea0002df01d2e">release chemicals to kill virally infected cells and cancer cells</p></td></tr></table></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_innate_lbd_assessment" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/lymph_innate_lbd_layout.xml</param></wb:inline><section id="e578b446d399418e9c8039f162c20599" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="lymph_innate_digt" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
