<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_15"><head><title>Cells in Innate Immunity </title><objref idref="lymph_roles_wbc_LO" /></head><body><p id="d9664ac424ab4e2d94fdf858cd40ec38">Many of the immune cells involved in innate immunity have the property of pattern recognition, the ability to recognize a given class of molecules. Some types of molecules are unique to microbes and never found in humans. A strong feature of innate immunity is the ability to immediately recognize that a foreign molecule is in the body and rapidly remove it. Immune cells recognize specific molecules on the surface of foreign pathogens called <term>pathogen-associated molecular patterns</term> (<term>PAMP</term>).These PAMPs are common to groups of pathogens, but are not found in human cells. <term>Pattern recognition receptors (PRR) </term>found on the surface of the immunecell bind the PAMPs and initiate the innate immune response. <term>Toll-like receptors</term> (<term>TLRs</term>) are the most important family of innate immunity receptors.</p><p id="db3ab1fe1f6d4276b63e24d4e0ed36ce">Both innate and adaptive immune responses depend on responses of white blood cells. Thesecells all originate in the bone marrow. There are two main lineages of leukocytes, the <term>myeloid</term> and <term>lymphoid</term>. Most of the cells of innate immunityare derived from the myeloid lineage. The common myeloid progenitor is the precursor of the macrophages (the mature form of the monocyte), mast cells, dendritic cells and granulocytes. Granulocytes can further differentiate into neutrophils, eosinophils, and basophils. Collectively, these cells are referred to as the <term>inflammatorycells</term>. Influx of these cells into an infected area produces inflammation thatis characterized by redness, heat, pain and swelling.</p><p id="a0ab8f603ebf42e384f44d8212e1585f">When an infection occurs, local immune cells react and emit signals or chemicals torecruit other immune cells. Among the first to respond are the nonmotile mast cells that are found near capillaries in the connective tissue of the skin, lungs, gastrointestinal tract and urogenital tract. Through PPRs, mast cells are stimulated to release cytokines that recruit neutrophils, eosinophils, basophils and T cells.</p><example id="d624d76662ff4e13abfd1ba36224484d"><title>Local Immune Cell Reaction</title><p id="e0b8939c556549e489bb96cdd341794a">When bacteria infects the body, mast cells recognize parts of the bacterial cell walland release a combination of chemicals including histamine, heparin, serotonin, bradykinin, and lysozymes that cause vasodilation (histamine, bradykinin), blood thinning or anti-coagulation (heparin), or cell lysis (lysozymes). Together, these chemicals increase the permeability of the capillaries to allow for other immune cells to infiltrate the extracellular space of the local infected region.</p></example><p id="f3f176d086f941ba98900bb54b9a0cf9">In addition to mast cells, other specialized immune cells including a group of cells,called the granulocytes, respond to infection. Granulocytes include <term>neutrophils</term>, <term>eosinophils</term>, and <term>basophils</term>.Neutrophils are the most abundant white blood cell, comprising 50 - 70% of all infiltrating leukocytes. Neutrophils are usually the first cells to leave the blood and enter infected tissues in large numbers. They are especially effective in engulfing and digesting bacteria as a way of combating infections. Neutrophils are programmed to die by apoptosis after ingesting bacteria. <term>Pus</term> is an accumulation of deadneutrophils, dead pathogens, tissue debris and fluid. Eosinophils target parasitic infections and are abundant in allergic reactions, although eosinophils only constitute a small percentage (1-6%) of leukocytes. Eosinophils release chemical factors called <term>chemokines</term>. These are chemicals that attract other immune cells andinitiate an adaptive immune response. Basophils are the least abundant, constituting only 1–2% of leukocytes. Basophils release histamine, a vasodilator, and heparin, an anti-coagulant, that aid in the infiltration of leukocytes from the bloodstream to site of infection.</p><p id="ed9e4afdc21e454cb4e1f0a79e2ff475"><term>Monocytes</term> circulate in the blood and continually migrate into tissues wherethey mature into macrophages. Macrophages are large motile cells that leave the blood and accumulate in infected tissues after neutrophils. They outlive neutrophils and can ingest more and larger substances than neutrophils can. They are responsible for most of the activity in the late stages of an infection, including the cleanup of dead neutrophils and general debris. Macrophages are also permanent residents beneath the free surfaces of the body and around blood and lymphatic vessels. In these locations macrophages provide protection by trapping and destroying pathogens entering the tissues. Macrophages are waiting within the lymph nodes, spleen, bone marrow and liver as well. An additional role of macrophages is to coordinate immune responses: they induce inflammation, which we will see is a prerequisite to a successful immune response, and they secrete cytokines that activate and recruit other immune system cells into an immune response. Although macrophages can activate naïve T cells through antigen presentation, they often present antigens to T cells to be activated themselves. Some microorganisms, such as mycobacteria, are intracellular pathogens that grow primarily in the phagosomes of macrophages. Peptides derived from such microorganisms can be presented on the macrophage surface by MHC class II molecules. These complexes are recognized by the T-cell receptor of the TH<sub>1</sub> subset. The T cells synthesizemolecules that stimulate the macrophage and enable it to eliminate the pathogen. This antimicrobial boost to the macrophage is known as <term>macrophage activation</term>.This coordination between T cells and macrophages results in the formation of the immune reaction call <term>granuloma</term>, in which microbes are held at bay within a centralarea of macrophages surrounded by activated T lymphocytes.</p><p id="b88fcd37b0824aa48979c2964dfa3c5e">Dendritic cells have almost all of the innate immunity receptors and are extremelysensitive to the presence of pathogens. Stimulation of innate immunity receptors promotes the ingestion and digestion of the pathogen. As part of innate immunity, dendritic cells produce cytokines that attract other immune cells to sites of infection and interferons that inhibit viral infection. Dendritic cells in the skin are called Langerhans cells.</p><p id="e4c6fd13208143968b7bc7f3c2ec869c">The lymphoid progenitor in the bone marrow gives rise to the antigen-specific lymphocytesof the adaptive immune system and also a type of lymphocyte that responds to the presence of infection but is not specific for antigen, and so it is considered to be part of the innate immune system. These large cells have distinctive granular cytoplasm and are called a <term>natural killer cells</term> (<term>NK cells</term>). These cellsrecognize and kill some abnormal cells, such as tumor cells and cells infected with viruses, and are thought to be important in controlling viral infections until the adaptive immune response has a chance to kick in.</p><wb:inline idref="lymph_roles_wbc_digt2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
