<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_15b"><head><title>Components Aiding Cellular Physiology of Innate Immunity</title><objref idref="lymph_innate_cellular_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_complement_fever_LO" /></head><body><section id="dcf97de68e884b51bef186a407af6738"><title>The Kinin-Kallikrein and Complement Systems</title><body><p id="b77214742b8e4cea9b623090102c8d32">There are two additional systems in the body that aid the inflammatory response to eliminate infection: the kinin-kallikrein and the complement systems. These are the non-specific mechanisms that are part of the innate immune response.</p><p id="adc651da19254d3caabc4bd5f7bc1fb4"><term>The Kinin-Kallikrein System</term></p><p id="f78f87b13f8144e792d4dc00a6945282">When tissues and cells are damaged, the interior components of their cells are released to the external environment. These components are not found outside cells normally, and are therefore recognized by the innate immune response. Specifically, the release of intracellular proteins from damaged tissue stimulates the activation of the kinin-kallikrein system. As a result, a cascade of proteins is activated that ultimately produce a chemical called bradykinin. Within tissues, bradykinin serves as a vasodilator that increases the permeability of the blood vessels. This increased permeability allows the larger leukocytes to leave the blood vessels and enter into the infected area.</p><p id="db036e643816407c8bf9de395380e641"><term>The Complement System</term></p><p id="a71ea03900f94156901c7d736ffc0af9">The second system activated in response to local inflammation is the complement system. This system can be activated through three different pathways: the classical, alternative, and the MB/Lectin pathways. Activation of any of these pathways results in the creation of a membrane attack complex or MAC. The MAC is made up of 9 proteins that assemble in the presence of an infected cell. They form a complex that can bind to the surface of an invading pathogen or infected cell. MACs are a part of the innate immune response that non-specifically recognize pathogen proteins and bind to the cell surface. When bound, the MAC pokes holes in the membrane of the pathogen and lyses it. Therefore, assembly and activation of the MAC destroys an invading pathogen.</p><image id="baeb187f209f4fc2ae7f2ebb3e2e1bc3" src="../webcontent/Lymph_13.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aa6913d5f43ed4575868b2be688e5f728">Complement</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="e1b9eb18b9984b598611b42e09385b9d" src="../webcontent/Lymph_15.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ac0d8da85bea14e87a3065b2facd00e77">Effector Function of Complement Proteins</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="be899a4e51a14feab929ec0df8a8e1fe"><title>Fever</title><body><p id="ce1722fa864842aa8b54257fcd65d913">Fevers usually occur in response to infection or inflammation. Fever is an elevated core body temperature (37.2-37.5 C or 99.0-99.5 F in adults) that occurs because a thermostat in the hypothalamus is reset to a higher setpoint. Many bacterial toxins can elevate body temperature by triggering release of fever-causing cytokines (pyrogens) such as interleukin-1 from macrophages. Positive benefits of this elevated body temperature include, inhibiting the growth of some microbes and speeding up chemical reactions involved in the immune response.</p></body></section><section id="be55c917d6ae4e5daf1fe30012d85ff9"><title>Review of Innate Immunity</title><body><p id="bb329a5114c94fb7a1624799b9b4f8ef">The innate immune response system produces a non-specific response to invading pathogens. Immune cells, such as mast cells, macrophages and dendritic cells, recognize protein patterns called pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) on the surface of pathogens and mount a localized immune response. Local immune cells release chemical mediators, including chemokines, interferon, and other chemicals that increase the permeability of the local capillaries. These chemicals attract leukocytes, such as neutrophils circulating in the blood, and facilitates their transport across the cell membrane into the tissue. As leukocytes enter the infected area, localized swelling, pain, redness, and heat are produced. These are the hallmark signs of inflammation and may also lead to immobilization of loss of function. Macrophages are also recruited. These are phagocytes that engulf pathogenic organisms, in essence eating the invading pathogens. In addition, non-specific signaling cascades, the kinin-kallikrein and the complement system are activated. These produce bradykinin or other chemical mediators to facilitate influx of leukocytes and assemble the membrane attack complex (MAC) that punches holes in the membrane of the pathogen to lyse the cells.</p><image id="dae828b534fb4f5b886d2a4060a15866" src="../webcontent/Lymph_22.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="adaa86ddb6d8d4c2aaec7d9b8305c66bb">Primary Immune Response</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="ef817d1e5929416f8015f99ddebbdd42" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="lymph_innate_cellular_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_innate_cellular_sac" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
