<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_12"><head><title>Organ Level of Organization</title><objref idref="lymph_organs_LO" /></head><body><p id="d93f7bd0a2f94ff6a81261ae0b66cf67">The lymphatic system consists of many different tissues and organs that are found throughout the body. Some organs provide the environment for the development and maturation of leukocytes. Other tissues and organs trap pathogen and are the sites where leukocytes can interact with the pathogen. The circulatory and lymphatic systems interact together to connect these organs and tissues.</p><p id="cc2b2d5e3ed84ad5b264158d6afdd1d6">Several morphologically and functionally diverse organs have various functions in the development of immune responses. These can be distinguished by function as primary and secondary lymphoid organs. The red bone marrow and thymus gland are the primary lymphoid organs, where maturation of B and T lymphocytes occurs. It is in the secondary lymphoid organs and tissues where the immune responses take place. Secondary lymphoid organs include the lymph nodes and spleen.</p><section id="a2447f34ca504193a3c7209f8145fdb3"><title>Bone Marrow</title><body><p id="f5d9c86ec0e4439e952d0db283ecb16f">The <term>red bone marrow</term> is the site where hematopoietic stem cells are found. Hematopoietic stem cells differentiate into the red blood cells (erythrocytes), platelets (thrombocytes) and white blood cells (leukocytes). Leukocytes participate in the immune response and further differentiate into mast cells, granulocytes (neutrophils, eosinophils and basophils), monocytes (macrophages), dendritic cells and lymphocytes (natural killer cells, B-cells and T-cells).</p><p id="d9f31d3bf19348e49409c9e643c92e6b">After birth, generation of mature B cells occurs in the bone marrow. During B cell development, random gene rearrangement produces an immature or pre-B cell expressing a B cell receptor (BCR). Maturation of pre-B cells involves a positive and negative selection process. Pre-B cells capable of an immune response survive positive selection and cells incapable of an immune response undergo apoptosis. Negative selection causes lymphocytes acting against self-antigens to undergo apoptosis or stimulates them to change their receptor specificity (receptor editing).</p></body></section><section id="b62ed68c3abe4c27b18d6e1253748d89"><title>Thymus</title><body><p id="d9126ff459994815909079748676636b">The <term>thymus</term> is located in the chest, just in front of the heart and behind the sternum of the rib cage. The thymus is comprised of two lobes that are further divided into lobules. Structural thymic tissue consists of epithelial cells joined by desmosomes. This framework of cells form small, irregularly shaped compartments filled with lymphocytes. In addition, the network of epithelial cells surrounds capillaries to form a blood-thymus barrier which prevents the entry of foreign antigens into the thymus. Each lobule consists of an outer cortex and an inner medulla. Immature, pre-T cells (thymocytes) migrate from the red bone marrow to the cortex of the thymus where they mature. Thymocytes pass through a series of stages maked by changes in expression of the TCR and cell-surface proteins such as CD4 and CD8. Epithelial cells in the thymus assist in the maturation process of T cells in the thymic cortex in a process called <term>positive selection</term>. In this process immature T cells express T-cell receptors (TCRs) that interact with class I MHC complexed with self proteins on epithelial cells in the cortex. Cells that recognize the MHC part of the complex survive due to <term>self-recognition</term>. T cells that <em style="italic">do not</em> recognize self MHC undergo apoptosis. At the junction of the cortex and the medulla, the development of <term>self-tolerance</term> occurs. The development of self-tolerance occurs in a process called <term>negative selection </term>in which the T cells interact with dendritic cells presenting class I MHC complexed with self proteins. T cells whose TCRs recognize the MHC and <em style="italic">also</em> recognize self proteins undergo apoptosis. This process is referred to as <term>clonal deletion</term>. In this way the surviving T cells recognize self MHC (self-recognition) and lack reactivity to self proteins (self-tolerance). The surviving T cells enter the medulla of the thymus and eventually leave the thymus via the blood and migrate to lymph nodes, the spleen and other lymphatic tissues where they colonize parts of these organs. Functionally the thymus continues to mature until puberty. As a person ages the funtional portion of the thymus gland atrophies considerably. However, before the thymus atrophies, it populates the secondary lymphatic organs and tissues with T cells. Like the spleen and tonsils, it is possible to survive without a thymus since the secondary lymphatic organs have already been populated with mature T cells, but the ability to initiate an immune response is diminished.</p></body></section><section id="c28660b19e2f42abb7c2f41095d6ea2c"><title>Lymph Nodes</title><body><p id="c6f1bf8165514fcb9d97a529fbb64658">As the lymph fluid moves from the capillary beds through the lymphatic vessels, and before it flows back into the general circulation it enters into areas of small swellings in the vessels called <term>lymph nodes</term>. Lymph nodes are oval shaped structures that are enclosed in a fibrous outer capsule. Superficial lymph nodes are in the subcutaneous tissue and include inguinal nodes in the groin, axillary nodes in the armpit and cervical nodes in the neck. Deep lymph nodes are everywhere else in the body where there are lymph vessels. Nodes collect and filter lymph from several afferent vessels, and several efferent vessels carry the lymph out from the node. The lymph fluid enters the lymph node and slowly filters through the cortex and medullary regions. Any microbes that were collected in the lymph are detected by the immune cells in the lymph nodes.</p><p id="a93965dc2be74929b8b29f3eef3c3d27">Lymph nodes are primarily a site for immune system activation. Specialized immune cells, including B lymphocytes, T lymphocytes, and macarophages, leave the bone marrow or thymus gland and reside within the lymph node. Just inside the fibrous capsule is the outer cortex region that contains the lymphatic nodules, a place where the B lymphocytes encounter antigen and the product of B cells, called antibodies, are generated. Memory B cells persist after an initial encounter in the lymphatic node. The inner cortex (paracortex) contains T cells and dendritic cells that enter a lymph node from other tissues. The dendritic cells present antigens associated with MHC class II to Helper T cells causing their proliferation. At the interior of the lymph node is the medulla, where antibody producing B cells (called plasma cells) are located. Antibodies leave the lymph nodes via the lymph.</p></body></section><section id="ec035e00271740a8970ae5f59af86d37"><title>Spleen</title><body><p id="a201ce337dc84467bd0258edcf4a78f0">In addition to lymph nodes, the lymphatic system includes the <term>spleen</term>. The spleen is located in the left, superior corner of the abdominal cavity, just posterior to the stomach, and protected by the rib cage. Although it is about the size of a clenched fist, it is one of the largest immune organ. Shaped like a big lymph node, the spleen similarly contains macrophages and lymphocytes. Instead of lymph flowing through it, the spleen contains blood. In fact, it serves as a reservoir for blood which can be used for a small increase in circulating red blood cells during exercise or emergency situations. Splenic macrophages can phagocytize cellular debris from defective red blood cells. Foreign substances in the blood passing through the spleen can stimulate an immune response because of the presence of lymphocytes.</p><p id="d8c04082f3e24b9f9c247d2da8bb343b">The spleen consists of two different kinds of tissue called white pulp and red pulp. Blood flowing into the spleen through the splenic arteries enters the central arteries of the white pulp. Within this pulp, B and T cells carry out immune functions similar to lymph nodes. White pulp also contains macrophages that can remove blood-borne pathogens by phagocytosis. Within the red pulp, macrophages can remove worn-out red blood cells and platelets.</p><p id="f2f454bac49b431f87a487fb0bca5d4d">It is possible to survive without a spleen if it is damaged. However, removal of the spleen does diminish the ability to mount an immune response.</p></body></section><section id="b796c0253f5547e7a564843cc051f759" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="lymph_organs_digt" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_organs_digt2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_organs_digt3" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
