<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_11"><head><title>Tissue Level of Organization</title><objref idref="lymph_tissues_LO" /></head><body><p id="d6ee4343f8594a1c994735f66e8c7f1d">Recall that the lymph and lymph vessels serve as a means of transporting proteins, lipids and pathogens from intersitial fluid to the lymph tissues. Once mature lymphocytes have been generated they circulate in the blood and migrate to lymph tissues where the leukocytes may interact with the trapped pathogen. Lymphatic tissue surrounded by a connective tissue capsule is said to be encapsulated and include lymph organs such as lymph nodes, spleen and thymus. Nonencapsulated lymphatic tissue includes diffuse lymphatic tissue, lymphatic nodules, and the tonsils. Nonencapsulated lymphatic tissue is found in and beneath the mucous membranes lining the digestive, respiratory, urinary and reproductive tracts. In these locations, the lymphatic tissue is strategically located to intercept pathogens that may enter the body.</p><p id="da47834467fa4b579d99d625ded54684"><term>Diffuse lymphatic tissue</term> has no clear boundary and contains dispersed lymphocytes, macrophages, dendritic cells and other cells. It may be located deep to mucous membranes, around lymphatic nodules and within lymph nodes and spleen.</p><p id="b2098d0ae09a455cbafa9339efc651a2"><term>Lymphoid nodules</term> are denser arrangements of lymphatic tissue organized into spherical structures, ranging in size from a few hundred microns to a few millimeters or more in diameter. Until it is infiltrated by antigen, lymphoid nodules mainly consist of resting B cells and antigen presenting cells (APCs). After antigenic challenge, the nodules consist of antibody-producing B cells (plasma cells) and helper T cells interspersed with macrophages and APCs. Many lymphatic nodules are scattered throughout the connective tissue of mucous membranes lining the respiratory, gastrointestinal, urinary and reproductive tracts. These lymphatic nodules are referred to as <term>mucosa-associated lymphatic tissue (MALT</term>). Although lymph nodules can occur in solitary, many occur in large aggregations. Among these are the <term>Peyer’s patches</term> in the ileum of the small intestine and aggregations in the appendix. Lymphatic nodules may also be located in the lymph nodes and the spleen. In lymph nodes. these nodules receive the name lymphoid follicles, and they contain proliferating B cells called <term>germinal centers</term>.</p><p id="e06e01eae0104dc1884341c79c5c5e9f"><term>Tonsils</term> are large groups of lymphatic nodules located deep to the mucous membranes within the pharynx. They are strategically positioned forming a ring in the pharyngeal and oral cavity where they can stimulate immune responses against inhaled or swallowed pathogens. The adenoid is embedded in the nasopharynx, the two palatine tonsils are on either side of the oral cavity, and the paired lingual tonsils are located at the base of the tongue. When infected, tonsils can become inflamed. It is possible to survive without the tonsils.</p><wb:inline idref="lymph_tissues_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
