<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_16"><head><title>Adaptive Immunity</title><objref idref="lymph_distinguish_LO" /></head><body><p id="b15d44f500b54c21a8c6e781e342e781">Recall that immune cells that are part of the innate immune response have receptors that recognize molecules on the surface of invading pathogens that are common to many different pathogens. Since they are common, they also have not significantly changed over thousands to millions of years. Some pathogens, however, have developed mechanisms to protect the molecules on their outer membranes and shield them from the immune system. For example, some bacteria and viruses have added an extra layer to their outer protein coat. This coating helps the pathogen evade detection by the phagocytic cells of the innate immune system.</p><p id="f24027bac5a14563846d0ecf14176430">Adaptive responses are initiated when antigen and antigen-presenting cells, particularly dendritic cells presenting antigens picked up at sites of infection, enter into secondary lymphoid tissue. Dendritic cells have pattern recognition receptors that recognize molecular patterns common to microorganisms. Binding to receptors stimulates dendritic cells to engulf and degrade the microbe intracellularly. Dendritic cells can also take up extracellular material, including viruses and bacteria in a manner that is receptor-independent. The dendritic cells then migrate to secondary lymph tissue and present this antigen to T lymphocytes. This process will be discussed in more detail in a later module. Free antigen can also stimulate antigen receptors of B cells, but most B cells require help from activated helper T cells. The activation of naïve T lymphocytes is therefore an essential first step in adaptive immune responses. For the adaptive immune response to occur, naïve lymphocytes first have to recognize antigens. After recognition, the naïve lymphocytes divide and differentiate, producing a large number of lymphocytes capable of responding to the antigen.</p><image id="aab8b539b9a64cf4ad11e7961b2cec75" src="../webcontent/Lymph_40.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ad4bbfc3675244ffaaa1b82a2c150e156">Comparison of Antibody Isotype Titer in Primary and Secondary Immune Response</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f52594194db74856b787a498c691694b">The innate and adaptive immune responses have two important differences. First is time. Recall that most components of innate immunity are present before the onset of infection. In contrast, adaptive immunity does not come into play until after the onset of infection. Adaptive immunity responds with a high degree of specificity. Because the adaptive immune response is initiated in response to the recognition of a specific part of a pathogen, it takes 7-10 days to mount an effective response. Contrast this to an innate immune response that is established immediately, and enhanced within minutes to hours. The second difference is the creation of immunological memory. Adaptive immune responses remember that a specific pathogen has been detected before. When the pathogen is encountered again, the immune response that is elicited is both faster and more robust.</p><section id="a1a7f918671441a3a2e1e08b9738ee58"><title>T cells, B cells, and Clonal Expansion</title><body><p id="cf6ca62ef76e46be92aa3b7c605b9349">T and B lymphocytes are the mediators of the adaptive immune response. T and B cells are able to identify a specific pathogen and initiate an immune response. Any molecule that can bind specifically to an antibody or generate peptide fragments that are recognized by a T-cell receptor is called an antigen. Lymphocytes do not recognize an entire antigen. Antigenic determinants, or epitopes, are specific regions of a given antigen to which an antibody or antigen receptor will bind. Because antigens are larger molecules a variety of epitopes could be found on a single antigen. Each T and B cell recognizes only one epitope. All the lymphocytes of a given clone have identical antigen receptors, which combine with a specific epitope. This is like a lock and key system. The pathogen has a protein that is broken down into a protein fragment (peptide). This peptide is the epitope that acts like a key that only fits one lock. That lock is the receptor on the T or B cell. When the epitope (key) is inserted into the matching T cell receptor or B cell receptor (lock) it initiates a series of events (turning the key) which activates the immune response that will affect the microbe expressing that one epitope. Because T and B cells only recognize one antigen, each T and B cell is said to be antigen-specific. In order to recognize all the different antigens, thousands and thousands of different T and B cells are created and circulate in our bodies. If a T or B cell encounters its target pathogen, then that T or B cell becomes stimulated and begins to rapidly divide. Each mitotic division produces an exact copy of the parent cell (clone). Thousands of clones are created in a process called clonal expansion. This produces thousands of daughter cells that all have receptors specific for the same epitope. Adaptive immunity occurs later than innate immunity because the few B cells and T cells specific for the pathogen must first undergo clonal expansion before they differentiate into effector cells and migrate to the site of infection.</p><p id="bf60a8e846504b72a1e727632edbaf33">A naïve lymphocyte is a mature helper T cell, cytotoxic T cell or B cell that has not yet bound to the epitope to which its receptor is specific. Naïve lymphocytes continually pass through peripheral lymphatic tissues where they may encounter an antigen. For example a naïve lymphocytes can pass from one lymph node to blood and be carried to another peripheral lymhatic tissue. Naïve T and B cells continuously circulate in the blood, the tissues, and the lymph vessels and nodes. When they encounter and recognize a pathogen within the lymph system, they stop circulating and begin to clonally expand.</p><image id="a6df67a4832b4d3c81104ce8fffd8eac" src="../webcontent/Lymph_30.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aaca40ff717984c3d889295cd7db4e54d">T Cell Activation and Clonal Expansion</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_distinguish_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_distinguish_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
