<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_15a"><head><title>Cellular Physiology of Innate Immunity</title><objref idref="lymph_innate_cellular_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_phago_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_inflammation_LO" /></head><body><section id="af3b50d4d47343bfb12ad1834e7ab346"><title>Phagocytosis</title><body><p id="de2d4ec179af4c6982a5034860da7892">Phagocytes are specialized cells that engulf and ingest microbes or other particles such as cellular debris. This process is termed <term>phagocytosis</term>. The two main types of phagocytes are neutrophils and macrophages. When an infection occurs, these cells migrate to the infected area. During this migration macrophages enlarge and develop into wandering macrophages. Fixed macrophages stand guard in specific tissues; such as histocytes in connective tissue, Kuppfer cells in the liver and tissue macrophages in the spleen and lymph nodes. In addition to being an innate defense mechanism, phagocytosis by macrophages and dendritic cells plays a vital role in antigen presentation in adaptive immunity.</p><p id="e20b1a4b4083494982ef607fa84c429a">As part of innate immunity, phagocytosis occurs in four phases:</p><ol id="a98a32283084478881d23eccef241c55"><li><p id="e0eea704d60d49159ec80e38c9a141ac"><term>Chemotaxis</term>. Chemicals from invading microbes, damaged tissue cells, leukotrienes from basophils and mast cells or activated complement proteins stimulate movement of phagocytes to a site of damage.</p></li><li><p id="bacd914be17645788bf986c94c564f00"><term>Adherence</term>. Phagocyte attaches to the microbe or other foreign material. Leukotrienes, complement proteins and antibodies bound to the pathogen will enhance adherence (opsonization).</p></li><li><p id="cd02e6af35384cf1b1315db10f79dacb"><term>Ingestion</term>. Plasma membrane extensions (pseudopods) of the phagocyte would engulf the microbe, surround it and internalize the microbe in a sac called a phagosome.</p></li><li><p id="feff4f7ed3384e9b89cee132c4f312eb"><term>Digestion</term>. In the cytoplasm the phagosome and vesicles filled with digestive enzymes and lethal oxidants called lysosomes fuse into a larger vesicle called a phagolysosome. This chemical onslaught quickly kills many microbes.</p></li></ol><image id="ead554ea4c7243b2a7916627fca39bb8" src="../webcontent/Lymph_12.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af1730d81f4ca42038d1562a5b311cc54">Phagocytosis</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="lymph_phago_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="c3f7b20797fa42ed983df68b11b54d92"><title>Inflammation</title><body><p id="b9353374cfc046a9bc852ead2fdf91f3">When pathogens breach the epithelial barrier and enter a tissue, they encounter the resident mast cell, macrophages and dendritic cells. The macrophages and dendritic cells phagocytize the pathogen. The macrophage and mast cells release cytokines that attract neutrophils to the site of infection. This is the beginning of a complex innate immune response called inflammation. Inflammation results in the activation and accumulation of immune cells, the release of inflammatory chemicals and the activation of complement.</p><p id="cafe8f331f74406bb17f300e08ad314c">The four characteristic or cardinal signs and symptoms of inflammation are redness, heat, swelling and pain. Loss of function may also occur at the site depending on the extent of the injury. Inflammation is an attempt to restore tissue homeostasis by removing microbes, toxins or debris at the site of injury and to prepare the site for repair. Inflammation is a normal response to tissue damage and a vital part of tissue repair.</p><p id="b2d2cefde29b4a03a1860438792c9526">Whether the injury was due to abrasion, burns or viral infection, the inflammatory response has three basic stages:</p><ol id="f85470f2e9db4632ab69b0503935dc01"><li><p id="af2f1dbfa602942589515388aeab29c66">Vasodilation and increased permeability of blood vessels. Vasodilation is an increase in blood vessel diameter that allows more blood to flow to the site of injury. Increased permeability permits proteins such as antibodies, clotting factors and complement to enter the injured area because they can leak out of the capillaries.</p></li><li><p id="aeed1987181144cdea686de06c4ea7c70">Emigration of phagocytes. Emigration is the movement of phagocytes from the blood into interstitial fluid. Phagocytes remove pathogens and dead tissue.</p></li><li><p id="adafaa7a7d5924744a26f12a67a879290">Tissue repair. In response to injury, mast cells in connective tissue and basophils in blood release histamine. Neutrophils and macrophages attracted to the site of injury also stimulate the release of histamine, which causes vasodilation and increased permeability of blood vessels. Leukotrienes (LTs) produced by basophils and mast cells increase permeability and are chemotactic agents that stimulate emigration. Other substances that contribute to vasodilation and increased permeability are blood kinins and complement components and prostaglandins released by damaged cells. Prostaglandins also intensify and prolong the pain associated with inflammation.</p></li></ol><image id="a6b16ac788bd45429642745be14aced2" src="../webcontent/Lymph_14.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af41b11dcb7d947b3ac4645ae8be8e516">Inflammation</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_inflammation_digt2_assessment" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/lymph_inflammation_digt2_layout.xml</param></wb:inline><section id="fea940f80520464a9a20626e9a142d44"><title>White Blood Cells and their Functions in Innate Immunity</title><body><table id="d608dc364c474694b99b123e29581ec8" summary="" rowstyle="alternating"><cite id="i0999d85e9ad540e7a91d0cc6e4b908cf" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="ab98d252187d548688316bc5937b9b333">Cell</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="ad894eb443ffc4e759ddc15575cd1043a">Function</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af94c71285f7448a6b4f91dd94930cc92">Mast cell</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad1851f51de4f4b17b6c5a793c25748fd">release chemicals to initiate a allergic inflammation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad904b6deb6294127a905f44bd1682dfe">Neutrophils</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aba25e2856bb54e3a86f5eac5e9f3f706">phagocytosis of infected cells and bacteria</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaeebcc0a746a4fa587083f5bc544313b">Eosinophils</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaa37c3bd96ba4b9097b7f47b140cd5bd">destruction of parasites</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af05eb870ea0a4e0ea4ae4c262d85add4">Basophils</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad8b2e218be214c8b9758ae590eec4576">release chemicals to initiate a allergic inflammation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ada307b00a7404c45bc7639e27d0395f2">Natural Killer cells</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac372b42d2f6b4d1ebd416a759ee7926f">release chemicals to kill tumor or virally infected cells</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af093e778ab7f4641854f461096e48e51">Macrophages</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adc6b886deb734604bef9793db1d95284">phagocytosis and orchestration of immune responses</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adab6d5f6049d46a48602ce78377a4536">Dendritic cells</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="acf641724fd4f4b739358b13e6ef512fa">phagocytosis and antigen presentation</p></td></tr></table></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_inflammation_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
