<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_13"><head><title>System Level of Organization</title><objref idref="lymph_defenses_LO" /></head><body><section id="c0fbb7c1088f4c4eb0dda3e2a2297c66"><title>Overview of the Immune System</title><body><p id="b4973199b00e452badb8bac60957ea82">As you have learned, the lymphatic system and immunity are closely related. Immune responses originate in the lymph organs and tissues. The immune system constantly surveys our body for invading bacteria, viruses, or other foreign pathogens. When it encounters a foreign substance, the immune system is activated to destroy the pathogen. Although fully integrated, the immune response is divided into two categories: the innate immune response and the adaptive immune response. The innate immune response is activated immediately (within hours to days) and is always the same. It responds to non-specific cues from the invading pathogens like highly conserved protein peptides that are expressed by many different types of pathogens, and are not expressed on mammalian cells. For example, each time a bacterial cell enters the body it is recognized and phagocytized with the same speed and efficiency. The innate immune response can be so efficient that signs or symptoms of disease never develop.</p><p id="f9cca863c99d4d21981febabe054b2b5">The adaptive immune response is slow (days to weeks) on first exposure to pathogens, but improves with subsequent exposure. On first exposure, cells of the adaptive immune response identifies a specific pathogen based on the specific proteins in that pathogen and mounts a targeted response to eliminate it. This type of response takes longer to establish and damaged tissues produce signs and symptoms of disease. However, during this time the most important aspect of our adaptive immune response is that it has memory, also called immunological memory. The adaptive immune response produces memory cells so that it is able to recognize foreign substances it has seen before and eliminate the threat both faster and with greater efficiency. Consequently, no signs or symptoms of disease develop and an immunity to that pathogen now exists. Vaccines have been created to take advantage of the immune memory. Because of this, the immune system can be used to prevent many infections and to ward off many diseases, including cancers.</p></body></section><image id="f31dd9bba6374a31bce008b76ddfb966" src="../webcontent/Lymph_22.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aa3e7d8070666411fa5919bb4ae5df63b">Primary Immune Response</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="lymph_defenses_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
