<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_5"><head><title>Molecular Level of Organization</title><objref idref="lymph_molecule_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_interferons_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_histamines_LO" /></head><body><section id="dd3cbe6cba284536a24773d9dda7d9c7"><title>Types of Antimicrobial Proteins</title><body><p id="a454ec9b85e54aa991b107f190767ece">Blood and interstitial fluids contain three main types of antimicrobial proteins that interfere with microbial growth: 1) interferons, 2) complement, and 3) iron-binding proteins.</p><ol id="ffecb0e9d9494c7f96b10cd9278b1bc3" style="decimal"><li><p id="db0887b3d51040ffb3df96ec9bb11cab">Virus-infected cells produce proteins called <term>interferons </term>(<term>IFNs</term>). IFNs diffuse through the interstitial fluid to uninfected neighboring cells. These proteins then cause the uninfected cells to synthesize antiviral proteins that interfere with viral replication. Viruses can cause disease only if they can replicate within body cells. Although IFNs do not prevent attachment and penetration of viruses to host cells, they do stop replication. Some interferons also have important immunoregulatory and anti-tumor effects. There are three families of IFNs; α-, β- and δ-IFN.</p></li><li><p id="ae60273aa52d4fb7a9c9a18bf0c81bc7">The complement system consists of 30 proteins. These proteins are produced by the liver and circulate in the plasma. When activated, the complement proteins collectively can cause cytolysis (bursting) of cells, promote phagocytosis and contribute to inflammation. Most complement proteins are designated by an uppercase letter C and a number; and a few complement proteins referred to as factors B, D and P (properdin). C1-C9 complement proteins act in a cascade. Complement activation may begin by three different pathways: <em style="italic">classical pathway</em> requires antibodies bound to antigen, <em style="italic">alternate pathway</em> involves factors B, D and P interacting with microbial molecules, and the <em style="italic">lectin pathway</em> requires lectin binding on the surface of the microbe. In all three pathways, C3 is activated and splits into fragments C3b and C3a. Although the process of phagocytosis is discussed in another module, C3b enhances phagocytosis by binding to the microbial membrane (<term>opsonization</term>): phagocytic cells have receptors for C3b enhancing the interaction between microbe and phagocyte. C3b fragments together with proteins C5b-C9 initiates a series of reactions that bring about cytolysis through formation of a pore shaped <term>membrane attack complex</term> (<term>MAC</term>) inserted into the microbial membrane. C3a and C5a bind to mast cells and cause histamine release and the resulting increased permeability of blood vessels. C5a also attracts phagocytes to the site of inflammation.</p><image id="c760f577b1cd4c3cba2552570ed7a855" src="../webcontent/Lymph_13.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af16ac3b9fddd417283d05b3d35181b0e">Complement</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></li><li><p id="eb55cf778219489bbd9bbe807706f743">Iron is an important micronutrient most bacteria need to survive. By reducing the amount of iron available, iron-binding proteins called <term>transferrins</term> can inhibit the growth of certain bacteria. </p></li></ol><wb:inline idref="lymph_interferons_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="d0d2dc268101433eaed7b071d5bfc118"><title>Substances that Contribute to Inflammation</title><body><p id="cfddb6b0dc7944fe93dae43392035a0c">Although the process of inflammation will be detailed in another module, two immediate changes occur in blood vessels in the region of tissue damage and/or infection; vasodilation of arterioles and increased permeability of capillaries. Local immune cells release chemical substances that increase the permeability of the local capillaries. Plasma and leukocytes circulating in the blood can now move through the capillary wall and into the interstitial space. Localized swelling, redness, heat and pain are produced. Among the substances that contribute to these cardinal signs of inflammation are: 1) histamine, 2) kinins, 3) prostaglandins (PGs), 4) leukotrienes (LTs) and 5) complement.</p><ol id="df888f7a936645cab5da2c4d25a0bc0d" style="decimal"><li><p id="a83dc60138894304b6521e9e4d022fec"><term>Histamines</term> are released by mast cells found in connective tissue, basophils found in tissues where allergic reactions are occurring and platelets found in blood in response to tissue injury. Histamine promotes vasodilation and increased permeability of capillaries.</p></li><li><p id="d78893c5b2f44908bd4d821d32a81040"><term>Kinins</term> form in the blood from inactive precursor proteins called kininogens. In addition to promoting vasodilation and increased permeability, kinins attract phagocytes into inflamed tissues. Bradykinin is an example of a kinin. Kinins affect some nerve endings causing much of the pain associated with inflammation.</p></li><li><p id="ed529a5f0d8c4ee1b60f917b9d38f78a"><term>Prostaglandins</term> (<term>PGs</term>) are lipids released by damaged cells that intensify the effects of histamine and kinins. PG may also stimulate movement (chemotaxis) of phagocytes through the capillary wall, regulate smooth muscle contraction and intensify and prolong the pain associated with inflammation.</p></li><li><p id="e49a668df91d4e24bbe4b2b4039b64da"><term>Leukotrienes</term> (<term>LTs</term>) are produced by basophils and mast cells and promote increased permeability of capillaries. They also function in chemotaxis and pathogen adherence of phagocytes.</p></li><li><p id="c3a25e9a50cf409abca1e3ab23fa52e7"><term>Complement</term> components (C3b and C5a) stimulate histamine release, function in chemotaxis and phagocytosis.</p></li></ol><wb:inline idref="lymph_histamines_digt_assessment" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="didigetthis"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/lymph_histamines_digt_layout.xml</param></wb:inline></body></section></body></workbook_page>
