<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="digest_homeo_3">
	<head>
		<title>Nerve Control of Digestion</title>
		<objref idref="digest_homeostasis_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>


		<p>Neural innervation of the GI tract is provided intrinsically by the enteric nervous
			system and extrinsically by the autonomic nervous system. The <term>enteric
				nervous system</term> contains around 100 million motor neurons, sensory neurons, and
			interneurons that run from the esophagus to the anus. These neurons are grouped into two
			plexuses. The <term>myenteric plexus</term> (<term>plexus of
				Auerbach</term>) lies in the muscularis externa layer of the intestinal wall while the
				<term>submucosal plexus</term> (<term>plexus of Meissner</term>)
			lies in the submucosal layer. The myenteric plexus is responsible for GI tract <term>motility</term> (spontaneous movement), especially the rhythm and force
			of contractions of the muscularis. The submucosal plexus regulates digestive secretions
			and reacts to the presence of food.</p>
		
		
		<p>The autonomic nervous system provides parasympathetic and sympathetic innervation to the
			GI tract. In general, parasympathetic nerves increase GI secretion and motility by
			stimulating neurons of the enteric nervous system, and sympathetic nerves decrease GI
			secretion and motility by restricting the activity of enteric nervous system neurons.
			When we are angry, frightened, or anxious, sympathetic innervation of the GI tract is
			stimulated, slowing digestive activity. Many people feel ‘butterflys’ in their stomach
			(or regurgitate) when they are nervous.</p>
		<p>Many enteric nervous system neurons are part of the <term>GI reflex pathways</term>
			responsible for controlling secretion and motility in response to GI tract stimuli.
			In these pathways, enteric nervous system sensory neuronal axons synapse with neurons of
			the enteric, central, or autonomic nervous system, either activating or inhibiting the
			activities of GI glands and smooth muscle.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_nervous_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
