<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="digest_homeo_4"><head><title>Dysfunctions of Digestion Homeostasis</title><objref idref="digest_homeostasis_LO" /></head><body><example id="f8a7c0b29c7d4b17b0cb5763b386470b"><title>Homeostasis of Water</title><p id="bcc41262647748af98dba8bd62bffda4">As an example of homeostasis maintained in the digestive system, we will consider the homeostasis of water. In the introductory units, we covered all of the important functions that water plays in our bodies. We get water from drinking liquids and from most of the foods that we eat. Water is necessary for normal functioning of most of our tissue systems including cardiovascular fluids (blood). We lose water by exhalation (respiratory system), urination (urinary system) and through feces in the digestive system. A fraction of water is retained in the digestive system to maintain movement, and water is both absorbed and secreted in the large intestine link to section above on water absorption.</p><p id="b7c86352978646feaf4c7e2f7416171d"><em style="bold">Infections of the gastrointestinal tract leading to diarrhea: </em>Diarrhea is a gastrointestinal disorder characterized by frequent watery stools. Diarrhea can occur secondary to a number of problems, including bacterial or viral infection of the gastrointestinal tract. The most common causes of these infectious diarrheas are infections with the Escherichia coli or Vibrio cholera bacteria or from Rotavirus.. In the large intestine, 98% of digestive system water is reabsorbed along with electrolytes and nutrients. Bacterial or viral infection interferes with the processes that control fluid reabsorption, leading to frequent, watery stools.</p><p id="e1623eca7479487985ed61e513e50aff">Infectious diarrheal disease usually occurs in older infants and children, particularly in situations where safe sources of drinking water are not available. Most children can recover from these gastrointestinal infections; however, diarrhea can lead to loss of substantial body fluids, sodium, chloride and other electrolytes. The loss of just 10% of body fluids can prevent maintenance of blood pressure. Diarrhea leads to 2.2 million deaths per year throughout the world, most in children in developing countries.</p><p id="cc37f781d1ee478c82eaa5362dbafffa"><em style="bold">Cholera </em>is a severe diarrheal disease caused by the Vibrio cholerae bacterium. This bacterium produces a toxin that binds tightly to cells of the large intestine and prevents water absorption. Simply providing water to cholera victims does not prevent dehydration, but adds to the volume of diarrhea. Proper treatment solutions contain water, salts and glucose since all of these are responsible for absorption of fluids.</p></example><wb:inline idref="digest_water_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
