<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_07">
   <head>
      <title>Capillary Exchange</title>
      <objref idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="compare_mechanisms_capillary_exchange_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>The ultimate goal of the cardiovascular and respiratory systems is to deliver
         oxygen-rich and nutrient-rich blood to the capillary networks. Although the amount of blood
         within the capillaries at any given time is only about 5 percent of the total
         volume, it is the most important blood in the body. It is at the level of the
         capillaries that <term>capillary exchange </term>occurs. The thin and porous
         construction of capillary walls provides an avenue for substances such as
         oxygen and glucose to move out of the blood plasma and into the interstitial
         fluids surrounding the tissue cells. The reverse process, uptake of substances
         such as carbon dioxide and wastes from the interstitial fluids into the plasma,
         occurs simultaneously. In addition to the back-and-forth exchange of solutes,
         water also moves between the bloodstream and interstitial fluid in both
         directions within the capillary networks. There are three mechanisms by which
         substances enter and leave capillaries: <term>diffusion</term>,
            <term>transcytosis</term>, and <term>bulk flow</term>.</p>
      
      <section>
         <title>Diffusion</title>
         <body>
            <p><term>Diffusion</term>, the movement of a solute from an area of high concentration to
               an area of low concentration, is a passive process. Diffusion is the
               driving force for the exchange of solutes at the capillary tissue
               interface. Thus, the oxygen and glucose, whose concentrations are high in
               the blood, will move out of the vessels into the interstitial fluids.
               Carbon dioxide levels are high in the interstitial fluid due to diffusion
               from the tissue cells. Carbon dioxide will move across the capillary
               walls into the blood plasma, where the concentration is lower. The
               physical characteristics of each solute determine the route by which that
               solute will diffuse. Small water-soluble molecules, such as glucose and
               amino acids, diffuse primarily through the intercellular clefts between
               the endothelial cells in continuous capillaries or through the
               fenestrations of fenestrated capillaries. Lipid-soluble molecules, such
               as oxygen and steroid hormones, can diffuse through the plasma membranes
               of the endothelial cells. Larger, lipid-insoluble substances must move
               down their concentration gradients via transcytosis.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Transcytosis</title>
         <body>
            <p><term>Transcytosis</term> is a combination of endocytosis and exocytosis that is
               necessary when the substance to be transported cannot be exposed to the
               cytoplasm of an intervening cell. Transcytosis is important in moving
               large lipid-insoluble molecules such as proteins across the capillary
               endothelial cells. A protein, for instance albumin or insulin, which is
               high in concentration in the blood plasma, will be enclosed in tiny
               vesicles formed from the endothelial plasma membrane. This process is
               considered pinocytosis because the molecules dissolved in the blood
               plasma are taken up randomly along with the fluid. These molecules are
               transported within the vesicles across the endothelial cell. At the
               opposite plasma membrane surface, the vesicle merges with the membrane,
               and the molecules are released into the interstitial fluid. In the
               developing fetus, certain plasma proteins and antibodies are moved from
               maternal to fetal circulation via transcytosis.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Bulk Flow</title>
         <body>
            <p><term>Bulk flow</term> is the movement of fluids due to pressure gradients. Fluids
               will move <em style="italic">en masse </em>from an area of high pressure
               to an area of low pressure. While diffusion is most important in the
               transfer of larger solutes, bulk flow controls the movement of fluids
               plus the ions and other small particles that are dissolved within the
               fluid. The movement of fluids from the capillaries into the interstitial
               fluid at the arterial end of the capillary bed is called
                  <term>filtration</term>. The movement of fluids from the interstitial
               fluid into the capillaries at the venous end of the capillary bed is
               called <term>reabsorption</term>.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      
      <wb:inline idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_LBD2-q" purpose="learnbydoing" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
         <param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/describe_function_capillary_exchange_LBD2-q-layout.xml</param></wb:inline>
      
   </body>
</workbook_page>
