<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_15">
   <head>
      <title>Venous Return</title>
      <!--<objref idref="define_venous_return_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="describe_factors_resist_venous_return_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="describe_skeletal_muscles_maintain_venous_returm_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="define_respiratory_pump_maintain_venous_return_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objectives:</p>
				<p>CV2.31 Define venous return.</p>
				<p>CV2.32 Describe factors that resist venous return.</p>
				<p>CV2.33 Describe how skeletal muscles help maintain venous return.</p>
				<p>CV2.34 Define the respiratory pump, and describe how it helps maintain venous return.</p>-->
      <p>The volume of blood in the systemic veins that is flowing back to the heart is called <term>venous return</term>. Blood returns to the heart through veins because of the difference in pressure between venules (approximately 16 mm Hg, on average) and the right ventricle (0 mm Hg). Any pressure increase in the right ventricle or right atrium lessens venous return. A leaky ("incompetent") tricuspid valve raises right atrial pressure, because it allows blood to flow backward ("regurgitate") when the ventricles contract. The resulting reduction in venous return is accompanied by an accumulation of blood in veins of the systemic circulation.</p>
      <p>In the upright individual, return of venous blood from the lower body is particularly challenged. This is because the flow of blood has to overcome the effects of gravity as well as the normal resistance of the vessels. Therefore, in the lower body, two additional factors help force blood toward the heart: the skeletal muscle pump and the respiratory pump. Both mechanisms rely on venous valves to operate.</p>
      <section>
         <title>Skeletal Muscle Pump</title>
         <body>
            <p>The <term>skeletal muscle pump </term>uses muscle contractions in the legs to force venous blood upwards toward the heart. The peripheral veins in the legs have one-way valves that route blood away from the legs and toward the heart. When standing still, these valves prevent the backflow of blood that might otherwise occur due to gravitational pull. When muscles of the legs contract, they tend to “squeeze” the veins of the legs; propelling blood. Because of the one-way valves, blood will only move toward the heart, helping maintain venous return. Lack of use of this skeletal muscle pump contributes to the lower leg edema common in people who are bedridden or confined to a wheelchair. When flow in the legs is not matained the venous system there becomes congested. This leads to increased capillary hydrostatic pressure and resultant edema.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Respiratory Pump</title>
         <body>
            <p>Sequential compression and decompression of veins also drives the <term>respiratory pump</term>, which operates on abdominal and thoracic veins. When you inhale, downward movement of the diaphragm reduces the pressure in the thoracic cavity and increases the pressure in the abdominal cavity. The resulting compression of abdominal veins pushes blood into the decompressed thoracic veins and then into the right atrium. When you exhale, the pressures reverse, and the one-way valves in the veins prevent blood from flowing back to the abdominal veins from the thoracic veins.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
   </body>
</workbook_page>