<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_18">
   <head>
      <title>The Pulmonary Circuit</title>
      <!--<objref idref="describe_features_pulmonary_circuit_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objective:</p>
				<p>CV2.37 Describe the anatomical features of the pulmonary circuit.</p>-->
      <p>The sole function of the pulmonary circuit is to carry blood to the alveoli of
         the lungs so that gases can be exchanged. Flow is matched to ventilatioin so
         that oxygen can move from the alveoli into the bloodstream and carbon dioxide
         can move from the bloodstream into the alveoli. The newly oxygenated blood then
         returns to the left atrium via pulmonary veins.</p>
      <p>The pulmonary circulation receives deoxygenated (or at least less oxygenated)
         blood ejected from the right ventricle. The pulmonary circulation carries this
         oxygen-poor, carbon-dioxide-laden blood to the alveoli of the lungs, where it
         is oxygenated and where some of the carbon dioxide is expelled. The newly
         oxygenated blood is then returned to the left atrium.</p>
      <p>The pulmonary circulation begins at the right ventricle, which pumps
         deoxygenated blood into the large <term>pulmonary trunk</term>. From its origin
         at the right ventricle, the pulmonary trunk takes an upward diagonal course for
         approximately 8 cm (3.1 inches (in.)). It then divides into the <term>right
            pulmonary artery</term> (to the right lung) and the <term>left pulmonary
            artery </term>(to the left lung). With the exception of the fetal
         circulation, the pulmonary arteries are the only arteries that transport
         deoxygenated blood. After entering the lungs, the pulmonary arteries subdivide
         into three <term>lobar arteries </term>in the right lung and two lobar arteries
         in the left lung. Each lobar artery supplies one lung lobe. Further
         subdivisions result in the formation of capillaries around the alveoli. Carbon
         dioxide from the blood is transferred into the alveoli and exhaled. Inhaled
         oxygen is transferred from air in the lungs into the blood.</p>
      <p>Pulmonary capillaries merge, forming venules that unite to become
            <term>pulmonary veins</term>. Two of these veins leave each lung and
         transport oxygenated blood to the left side of the heart. As the left ventricle
         contracts, it pumps out the oxygenated blood into the systemic circulation. It
         is easy to remember which vessels belong to the pulmonary circulation, because
         they all have either the word <em style="italic">pulmonary </em>or <em
            style="italic">lobar </em>in their names <em style="highlight">(Figure 21.18)</em>.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
