<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_13">
   <head>
      <title>Starling’s Law of the Capillaries</title>
      <!--<objref idref="define_starling_law_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objective:</p>
				<p>CV2.29 Define Starling’s Law, and quantify net filtration pressure based on opposing pressures.</p>-->
      <p><term>Starling’s law of the capillaries </term>states that the movement of
         fluid between the capillaries and interstitial fluid is due to the net effect
         of all four of the pressures described. An equation can be used to calculate
         the NFP and determine the direction of the fluid movement.</p>
      <p>NFP = (BHP + IFCOP) – (BCOP + IFHP) <em style="italic">(Equation 6)</em></p>
      <p>BHP and IFCOP promote the movement of fluid out of the capillaries or
         filtration. BCOP and IFHP promote the movement of fluid into the capillaries or
         reabsorption. If the pressures that promote filtration are greater than the
         pressures that promote reabsorption, the NFP will have a positive value. If the
         pressures that promote reabsorption are greater, the NFP will have a negative
         value.</p>
      <p>Under normal physiological conditions, the values of IFHP, BCOP, and IFCOP do
         not significantly vary from the arterial end of the capillaries to the venous
         end. Therefore, in most tissues, the rate of filtration and reabsorption is due
         to BHP. To demonstrate, assume the following pressures at the arterial end of a
         capillary network:</p>
      <p>BHP = 35 mmHg</p>
      <p>IFHP = 0 mmHg</p>
      <p>BCOP = 26 mmHg</p>
      <p>IFOP = 1 mmHg</p>
      <p>NFP = (35 mmHg + 1 mmHg) – (26 mmHg + 0 mmHg)</p>
      <p>NFP = +10 mmHg</p>
      <p>Because the value of NFP is positive, filtration occurs at the arterial end of
         the capillary. Moving along the capillary, the BHP becomes lower as blood moves
         along the pressure gradient of the vascular system, but the other three
         pressures will not fluctuate. At about the midpoint of the capillary network,
         the pressures that promote filtration are equal to the pressures that promote
         reabsorption. Moving away from the midpoint toward the venous end of the
         capillary, the BHP dips below the BCOP. From this point forward, reabsorption
         occurs. Near the junction of the capillaries with the venules, the BHP is about
         16 mmHg.</p>
      <p>NFP = (16 mmHg + 1 mmHg) – (26 mmHg + 0 mmHg) or NFP = –9 mmHg.</p>
      <p>This reabsorption value is close to the initial filtration value at the
         arterial end of the capillary. This means that most of the water that moved
         from the capillaries into the interstitial fluid at the arterial end will be
         returned to the bloodstream at the venous end. In fact, about 85 percent of the
         fluid filtered from the capillaries is reabsorbed. The remaining 15 percent
         flows through the tissues and into the lymphatic capillaries. The lymph system
         returns the excess fluids plus any plasma proteins that escape back into the
         bloodstream. About 22 liters of fluids are filtered from the capillaries each
         day. Of this, approximately 19 liters is reabsorbed back into the venous end of
         the capillaries, with the lymph system picking up the remaining 3 liters of
         non-reabsorbed fluid per day.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
