<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_17_old">
   <head>
      <!--DELETE THIS PAGE-->
      <title>Circulatory Pathways</title>
      <!--<objref idref="contrast_systemic_pulmonary_circuit_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objective:</p>
				<p>CV2.36 Contrast vasculature of the systemic and pulmonary circuits.</p>-->
      <p>Blood vessels are organized into <term>circulatory routes </term>that deliver
         blood to different organs and tissues of the body. The right ventricle pumps
         blood to the lungs via the pulmonary circuit. The left ventricle pumps blood to
         organs and tissues via the systemic circuit. The output of the systemic circuit
         becomes the input of the pulmonary circuit, and vice versa. The pump for the
         systemic circuit is the left side of the heart, which also collects the
         oxygen-rich blood returning from the lungs. The pump for the pulmonary circuit
         is the right side of the heart, which receives deoxygenated blood from the
         systemic circulation.</p>
      <p>There are two important differences between the systemic circulation and
         pulmonary circulation. The first is that blood in the systemic circulation must
         be pumped farther than blood in the pulmonary circulation. The second is that,
         in pulmonary arteries, the diameter is larger, the walls are thinner, and the
         tissue is more elastic than in systemic arteries. Because of the
         characteristics of pulmonary arteries, there is very low resistance to blood
         flow in the pulmonary circuit, and thus pressures do not need to be very high
         to move blood through the lungs. In the right ventricle, the peak systolic
         pressure is typically one-fifth that in the left ventricle.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
