<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_06_old">
   <head>
      <!--DELETE THIS PAGE-->
      <title>Blood Pressure Calculations</title>
     <!-- <objref idref="define_map_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="describe_relationship_arterial_pressure_cardiac_output_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="predict_altered_cardiac_output_bp_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objectives:</p>
				<p>CV2.17 Define mean arterial pressure, and calculate mean arterial pressure from systolic and diastolic pressure.</p>
				<p>CV2.18 Describe the symbolic relationship between mean arterial pressure and cardiac output.</p>
				<p>CV2.19 Predict the effect of altered cardiac output on blood pressure.</p>-->
      <p>Average arterial BP, or <term>mean arterial pressure (MAP)</term>, is about
         one-third of the difference between the systolic and diastolic BP. MAP is
         determined using the following equation:</p>
      <p>MAP = diastolic BP + 1/3 (systolic BP − diastolic BP)</p>
      <p>So someone with a BP of 120/80 mm Hg would have an MAP of approximately 98 mm
         Hg (i.e., 80 + 1/3(120 − 80).</p>
      <p>You have already learned that cardiac output can be calculated by multiplying
         heart rate by stroke volume. Cardiac output can also be estimated by dividing
         MAP by the resistance of the peripheral circulation (i.e. total peripheral
         resistance (TPR), or systemic vascular resistance (SVR)) , using the following
         formula:</p>
      <p>CO = MAP ÷ TPR <em style="italic">(Equation 1)</em></p>
      <p>The same equation can be reconfigured to estimate MAP:</p>
      <p>MAP = CO × TPR <em style="italic">(Equation 2)</em></p>
      <p>This means that if stroke volume or heart rates increases, the subsequent
         increase in cardiac output will result in an increase in MAP, assuming
         resistance does not change. Similarly, reduced cardiac output results in a
         reduced MAP, again assuming a constant amount of resistance.</p>
      <p>The total volume of circulating blood also affects BP. You may recall the the
         total amount of blood in the vascular system contributes to venous return. We
         have learned through the Frank-Starling mechanism that as venous return
         increases, so does stroke volume and therefore cardiac output. A healthy adult
         has about 5 liters (5.3 quarts) of blood. If there is significant bleeding,
         volume decreases. If the blood volume reduction is less than 10 percent,
         homeostatic mechanisms kick in to help normalize BP. If blood volume drops by
         more than 10 percent, the decrease in venous return causes BP to fall.
         Similarly, conditions that increase blood volume (for example, water retention)
         usually result in an increased BP – as long as the individual has a healthy
         heart to pump this extra blood.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
