<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_05">
   <head>
      <title>Blood Pressure and Pulse Measurements</title>
      <objref idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="describe_measurements_pulse_bp_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>Pulse rate and blood pressure are good indicators of the functioning of the
         circulatory system. After every systole of the left ventricle, arteries expand
         and recoil. This creates a moving wave of pressure called the
            <term>pulse</term>. The pulse rate matches the heart rate, which is
         from 70 to 80 beats per minute when the body is at rest. Your pulse can be
         checked in any artery that is close to the skin surface and that can be
         compressed against a solid structure such as a bone. The pulse rate is commonly
         checked at the site of the radial artery at the inner wrist or at the site of
         the carotid artery at the neck. The pulse can also be strongly felt at the
         femoral artery in the groin, at the brachial artery between the bicep and
         tricep, and at the dorsalis pedis artery on the top of the foot. The strongest
         pulse is in arteries near the heart. A rapid resting heart rate, indicated by a
         rapid pulse rate, of over 100 beats per minute is called
            <term>tachycardia</term>. A slow resting heart/pulse rate of less than 50
         beats per minutes is called <term>bradycardia</term>. Bradycardia is normal in
         endurance-trained athletes such as marathon runners.</p>
      
      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-i" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
      
      <p>Blood pressure is typically assessed in the brachial artery of the left arm. An
         inflatable rubber cuff with attached squeezable bulb used to measure BP is
         called a <term>sphygmomanometer</term>. The bulb is squeezed until compression
         stops the flow of blood in the brachial artery. Then the cuff is slowly
         deflated. When the artery reopens, blood spurts through the vein, making a
         sound that corresponds to systolic blood pressure. With continuing deflation,
         the sound of the flowing blood ultimately goes away, which corresponds with
         diastolic blood pressure.</p>
      
      <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_44.jpg" width="500"
         alt="sphygmomanometer shown around upper left arm"><title>Figure 8</title><caption></caption></image>
      
      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_DIGT2-14-23-b" purpose="didigetthis"/>
      
      <section>
         <title>Blood Pressure Calculations</title>
         <body>
            <p>Average arterial BP, or <term>mean arterial pressure (MAP)</term>, is about
               one-third of the difference between the systolic and diastolic BP. MAP is
               determined using the following equation:</p>
            <formula>MAP = diastolic BP + 1/3 (systolic BP − diastolic BP)</formula>
            <p>So someone with a BP of 120/80 mmHg would have an MAP of approximately 98 mmHg (i.e., 80 + 1/3(120 − 80).</p>
            <p>You have already learned that cardiac output can be calculated by multiplying
               heart rate by stroke volume. Cardiac output can also be estimated by dividing
               MAP by the resistance of the peripheral circulation (i.e. total peripheral
               resistance (TPR), or systemic vascular resistance (SVR)) , using the following
               formula:</p>
            <formula>CO = MAP ÷ TPR <em style="italic">(Equation 1)</em></formula>
            <p>The same equation can be reconfigured to estimate MAP:</p>
            <formula>MAP = CO × TPR <em style="italic">(Equation 2)</em></formula>
            <p>This means that if stroke volume or heart rates increases, the subsequent
               increase in cardiac output will result in an increase in MAP, assuming
               resistance does not change. Similarly, reduced cardiac output results in a
               reduced MAP, again assuming a constant amount of resistance.</p>
            
            <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_DIGT2-14-23-c" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            
            <p>The total volume of circulating blood also affects BP. You may recall the the
               total amount of blood in the vascular system contributes to venous return. We
               have learned through the Frank-Starling mechanism that as venous return
               increases, so does stroke volume and therefore cardiac output. A healthy adult
               has about 5 liters (5.3 quarts) of blood. If there is significant bleeding,
               volume decreases. If the blood volume reduction is less than 10 percent,
               homeostatic mechanisms kick in to help normalize BP. If blood volume drops by
               more than 10 percent, the decrease in venous return causes BP to fall.
               Similarly, conditions that increase blood volume (for example, water retention)
               usually result in an increased BP – as long as the individual has a healthy
               heart to pump this extra blood.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      
      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-j" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_DIGT2-14-23-d" purpose="didigetthis"/>
      
   </body>
</workbook_page>
