<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_04">
   <head>
      <title>The Arteries: Blood Flow and Blood Pressure</title>
      <objref idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="define_blood_flow_pressure_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>The volume of blood that moves through any vessel or tissue in a given amount of time is
         called <term>blood flow</term>. Blood flow is commonly measured in milliliters per minute
         (mL/min) or liters per minute (L/min). The amount of blood that moves through either the
         systemic or pulmonary vessels in one minute is the <term>total blood flow </term>or
            <term>cardiac output</term>. Cardiac output is fairly constant when the body is at rest.
         However, the needs of individual organs determine how much blood flows through that organ,
         so if one or more organs needs more flow, cardiac output increases.</p>
      <section>
         <title>Blood Pressure</title>
         <body>
            <p><term>Blood pressure (BP) </term>refers to the force per unit area that blood exerts
               on a vessel wall. It is measured in millimeters of mercury (mmHg). Therefore, the
               pressure from a column of mercury that is 120 mm high is equivalent to a BP of 120
               mmHg. Clinically, such as when your BP is checked by your physician, it refers to
               systemic arterial blood pressure in the biggest arteries close to the heart, where BP
               is similar to that generated by the heart. From these large arteries, blood pressure
               continuously decreases along each path that blood flow can take through the vascular
               system. Once the blood gets back to the heart, it is at a very low pressure (near 0
               mmHg). The heart then gives it a new “boost” of energy, raising BP again. It is this
               pressure gradient that continues moving blood as blood moves from areas of higher
               pressure to areas of lower pressure.</p>
            <p>The highest BP is in the aorta and the bigger systemic arteries. In a healthy young
               adult, BP increases to around 110 mmHg during ventricular systole (contraction) and
               decreases to around 70 mmHg during ventricular diastole (relaxation). The highest
               arterial pressure achieved during systole is called the <term>systolic blood
                  pressure</term>. The lowest arterial pressure reached during diastole is the
                  <term>diastolic blood pressure</term>. The pressure of blood steadily decreases as
               blood travels farther and farther away from the left ventricle. In the blood that
               moves from systemic arteries into systemic arterioles and then into capillaries,
               pressure drops to approximately 35 mmHg. In capillaries, there are no BP
               fluctuations, but pressure falls to around 16 mmHg when blood reaches the venous end
               of capillaries. Because of their distance from the left ventricle, BP in systemic
               venules and veins drops further. By the time blood reaches the right ventricle, its
               pressure is typically 0 mmHg.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_43.jpg" width="450" alt="">
         <title>Figure 7</title>
         <caption/>
      </image>

      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-h" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_DIGT2-14-23" purpose="didigetthis"/>

   </body>
</workbook_page>
