<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_19_old">
   <head>
      <title>The Systemic Circuit</title>
      <!--DELETE THIS PAGE-->
      <!--<objref idref="describe_features_systemic_circuit_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objective:</p>
				<p>CV2.38 Describe the anatomical features of the systemic circuit.</p>-->
      <p>The systemic circuit delivers oxygenated blood and nutrients to the entire body
         and head removes the waste products of metabolism from the same tissues. We
         will review the circuit from previous sections: After blood is pumped from the
         left ventricle into the aorta, it flows into smaller and smaller systemic
         arteries to perfuse all of the body's organs and tissues (except for the
         alveoli of the lungs). Systemic arteries branch off into smaller arterioles
         that lead into extensive networks of systemic capillaries. Nutrients and gases
         are exchanged between blood and systemic tissues through the thin capillary
         walls. After the blood gets rid of oxygen and picks up carbon dioxide, it
         usually travels through a single capillary before entering a systemic venule.
         The venules then transport oxygen-poor (deoxygenated) blood from systemic
         tissues before merging to create the larger systemic veins. All blood in the
         systemic circulation eventually empties into the right atrium.</p>
      <p>The arteries and arterioles of the systemic circulation receive oxygenated
         blood from the left ventricle and transport it to the systemic capillaries. The
         veins and venules of the systemic circulation carry deoxygenated blood back to
         the right atrium. Blood in systemic arteries is bright red in color. Blood in
         capillaries is dark red, because it has lost some oxygen and gained carbon
         dioxide.</p>
      <p>The arteries and veins of the systemic circuit share a number of similarities,
         most notably, the routes and names that many of these vessels share. There are
         also four major differences between arteries and veins. First, all of the blood
         from the heart is pumped into a single systemic artery, the aorta, which
         carries oxygenated blood away from the left ventricle. Deoxygenated blood
         returns to the right atrium via three systemic veins: the superior vena cava,
         inferior vena cava, and coronary sinus. The majority of blood that returns to
         the heart flows through the superior and inferior venae cavae. The names of
         these veins are derived from the location of their tributaries. The
            <term>superior vena cava </term>collects blood from veins located superior
         to (above) the diaphragm, with the exception of the wall of the heart and the
         alveoli of the lungs. The superior vena cava, which delivers blood to the right
         atrium, is formed by the merger of the right and left <term>brachiocephalic
            veins</term>. Each of these veins, in turn, is formed by the union of the
            <term>internal jugular vein </term>and <term>subclavian vein </term>on the
         right or left side of the body. The <term>inferior vena cava</term>, which is
         the largest-diameter blood vessel in the body, collects blood from veins
         located inferior to (below) the diaphragm and delivers it to the right atrium.
         This vein is located directly to the right of the abdominal aorta. Its distal
         end is created by the merger of the paired <term>common iliac veins</term>.
         Blood that drains from the myocardium of the heart empties into cardiac veins
         and returns to the right atrium via the <term>coronary sinus</term>.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
