<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_06">
   <head>
      <title>Factors Influencing Blood Pressure</title>
      <objref idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="contrast_vessel_resistance_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="calculate_vascular_resistance_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <section>
         <title>Vascular Resistance</title>
         <body>
            <p><term>Resistance</term> refers to the factors that oppose the flow of blood.
               Resistance is caused by friction as blood moves through a vessel. The resistance to
               blood flow as it moves from the aorta to the vena cavae is known as <term>total
                  peripheral (i.e., systemic) resistance</term>. This is in contrast to the
               pulmonary vascular resistance that the right ventricle pumps into. Although
               resistance is commonly calculated across the entire circulation, it can also be
               calculated for a particular type of vessel in the body (such as the systemic
               arterioles), an organ, or a single specific blood vessel, as long as the pressure
               drop across the region and the blood flow rate are known. In fact, the previous MAP
               equation (2 on previous page) is a special case of this more general equation:</p>
            <formula>ΔP = Flow x Resistance <em style="italic">(Equation 3)</em></formula>
            <p>where ΔP is the change in pressure, or pressure drop across the region or vessel of
               interest and flow is the flow rate through the same region or vessel. Equation (3)
               can be rewritten in the form</p>
            <formula>Resistance = ΔP ÷ Flow <em style="italic">(Equation 4)</em></formula>

            <section purpose="learnbydoing">
               <title/>
               <body>
                  <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-k" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
                  <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-l" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
               </body>
            </section>
            <p>Although resistance can be calculated by knowing pressure drop and flow (equation
               (4)), resistance of a single vessel can also be determined if we know something about
               the physical characteristics of the vessel and blood. There are three factors that
               influence vascular resistance: lumen size, blood viscosity, and blood vessel length.
               These factors are shown mathematically in the equation, which calculates the
               resistance of a single vessel.</p>
            <formula>R = 8ηl/πr4 <em style="italic">(Equation 5)</em></formula>
            <formula>where η = viscosity of fluid, l = length of the vessel, and r = radius.</formula>
         </body>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Vessel Lumen Size</title>
         <body>
            <p>The smaller the lumen, the greater the resistance. Most of the changes in lumen size
               are due to the vasoconstriction and vasodilation of arteries and arterioles. As a
               vessel constricts, the lumen size decreases. This increases resistance, which is
               inversely proportional to the change in radius to the fourth power.
               <!--indicating-->This means that even small changes in radius can have large affects
               on resistance. And, if the flow rate is kept constant when radius decreases, then the
               pressure change (drop) along the length of the vessel will increase, as indicated by
               equation (3).</p>
            <p>Because our systemic vasculature is made up of millions of vessels, they each
               contribute in some way to the overall resistance of the system, called systemic
               vascular resistance (SVR) or total peripheral resistance. Most of this resistance is
               in the smallest vessels, such as small arteries, arterioles, capillaries, and
               venules. There is little resistance in large arteries and veins. Because of their
               large diameters, only a small amount of blood in large arteries and veins is in
               contact with the vessel wall. Controlling SVR is a chief function of arterioles. They
               regulate SVR—and thus BP and perfusion, or blood flow, to specific tissues—by
               altering their diameter. Even minimal amounts of vasodilation or vasoconstriction in
               arterioles can have significant effects on SVR.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <section purpose="learnbydoing">
         <title/>
         <body>
            <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-m" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-n" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
         </body>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Blood Viscosity</title>
         <body>
            <p><term>Viscosity </term>is a measurement of a fluid's internal resistance (how easily
               the fluid particles can slide past each other), which determines its ability to flow.
               Viscosity depends on the thickness or stickiness of a fluid. A fluid with a low
               viscosity flows quickly; a fluid with a high viscosity flows slowly. When the
               viscosity is high, it is hard to maintain fluid movement, and molecules cannot freely
               slip past each other. The viscosity of blood is mostly dependent on the ratio of red
               blood cells to blood plasma. The more red blood cells in a given volume of blood, the
               more viscous the blood. The amount of plasma proteins in the blood also affects
               viscosity. If blood viscosity increases, resistance increases proportionally as
               indicated by equation (5). If blood flow stays the same, an increased viscosity
               requires that the heart generate more pressure to move the flow through the
               system.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-o" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

      <section>
         <title>Blood Vessel Length</title>
         <body>
            <p>There is a direct correlation between the length of a blood vessel and the amount of
               resistance (Equation 5). As length increases, so does resistance. This may be obvious
               if we consider the pulmonary circulation versus the systemic circulation. Each
               circulation receives the same amount of blood flow, but the pulmonary circulation
               requires much less pressure to maintain this flow rate. A major reason for this is
               that the path length for blood flow is much shorter through the pulmonary circulation
               than it is through the systemic circulation.</p>
            <p>Resistance to blood flow increases in people who are overweight because even a
               kilogram or two of excess fat requires miles of additional small vessels to supply it
               with blood. This increased vessel length dramatically increases the amount of
               peripheral resistance. A common consequence of obesity is hypertension.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_LBD2-p" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
      <wb:inline idref="define_relate_BP_and_MAP_DIGT2-14-23-e" purpose="didigetthis"/>

   </body>
</workbook_page>
