<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_07_old">
   <head>
      <title>Factors Influencing Blood Pressure: Vascular Resistance</title>
      <!--<objref idref="contrast_vessel_resistance_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="calculate_vascular_resistance_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objectives:</p>
				<p>CV2.20 Contrast the total peripheral resistance with resistance through one vessel.</p>
				<p>CV2.21 Calculate vascular resistance from flow and blood pressure; calculate vascular resistance from vessel dimensions.</p>-->
      <p>Resistance refers to the factors that oppose the flow of blood. Resistance is
         caused by friction as blood moves through a vessel. The resistance to blood
         flow as it moves from the aorta to the vena cavae is known as total peripheral
         (i.e., systemic) resistance. This is in contrast to the pulmonary vascular
         resistance that the right ventricle pumps into. Although resistance is commonly
         calculated across the entire circulation, it can also be calculated for a
         vessel order (such as the systemic arterioles), an organ, or a single vessel,
         as long as the pressure drop across the region and the blood flow rate are
         known. In fact, the equation (2) is a special case of the more general
         equation</p>
      <p>ΔP = Flow x Reistance <em style="italic">(Equation 3)</em></p>
      <p>Where ΔP is the change in pressure, or pressure drop across the region or
         vessel of interest and flow is the flow rate through the same region or vessel.
         Equation (3) can be rewritten in the form</p>
      <p>Resistance = ΔP ÷ Flow <em style="italic">(Equation 4)</em></p>
      <p>Although resistance can be calculated by knowing pressure drop and flow
         (equation (4)), resistance of a single vessel can also be determined if we know
         something about the physical characteristics of the vessel and blood. There are
         three factors that influence vascular resistance: lumen size, blood viscosity,
         and blood vessel length. These factors are shown mathematically in the
         equation, which calculates the resistance of a single vessel.</p>
      <p>R = 8ηl/πr4 <em style="italic">(Equation 5)</em></p>
      <p>Where η= viscosity of fluid</p>
      <p>l = length of the vessel</p>
      <p>r = radius</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
