<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_02">
   <head>
      <title>Cardiac Cycles</title>
      <objref idref="describe_phases_cardiac_cycle_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="define_cardiac_cycle_systole_diastole_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="describe_phases_cardiac_cycle_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="relate_heart_sounds_cardiac_cycle_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="explain_atrial_systol_ventricular_filling_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>The <term>cardiac cycle </term>can be divided into two distinct phases, diastole and
         systole. During <term>diastole</term>, the muscles are relaxed and the chambers fill
         passively with blood. Although there is both an atrial and a ventricular diastole, which
         differ slightly in their timing, the word diastole is commonly used in reference to
         ventricular diastole. <term>Systole </term>is when the heart muscles contract. Atrial
         systole helps fill the ventricles while ventricular systole is responsible for pushing the
         blood into the pulmonary artery and aorta.</p>
      <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_40.jpg" width="650"
         alt=""><title>Figure 4</title><caption></caption></image>
      <section>
         <title>Diastole: Relaxation</title>
         <body>
            <p>During atrial diastole blood enters the left atrium from the pulmonary vein and the
               right atrium from the inferior and superior vena cava. As ventricular diastole
               begins, the atria are already well into their diastolic period. The ventricles have
               just finished contracting, so the ventricular pressure is dropping as relaxation
               begins. When the pressure within the ventricles drops below the atrial pressure, the
               AV valves open. Blood passively pours into the atria and flows through the
               open AV valves into the ventricles. As the blood collects in the ventricle, the
               pressure builds. In order to continue filling the ventricle , the SA node
               depolarizes, initiating atrial systole. The contraction of the atrium forces more
               blood into the ventricle in diastole. Nearly 90% of the blood passively flows into
               the ventricles while the remaining 10% enter due to atrial systole.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Systole: Contraction</title>
         <body>
            <p>The increasing volume of blood in the ventricles increases the pressure in the
               ventricles. When this pressure exceeds that in the atria, the AV valves are forced
               closed. The closing of these AV valves creates the <term>first heart sound</term>
               (lub). By this time, the atria have finished systole and have entered their diastolic
               period. There is a delay of about 0.1 sec (100 milliseconds) between the contraction
               of the atria and the contraction of the ventricles. This delay provides enough time
               for the atria to complete their contraction before the ventricles begin their turn
               and prevents the chambers from competing with each other. Imagine if the atria and
               ventricles contracted all at once. The blood flow would not be as controlled or
               efficient.</p>
            <p>The heart contracts in a repeatable sequence. First the atria contracts (as described
               above), then the ventricles. This, along with the heart valves, allows the blood to
               flow in one direction. When the ventricles begin to contract at the onset of systole,
               both the AV and semilunar valves on either side of the ventricles are closed. This is
               called <term>isovolumetric contraction</term>. The volume of blood in the ventricles
               does not change because all the valves are closed, so there is no place for the blood
               to go. As a result, isovolumetric contraction increases the pressure in the
               ventricles. When the ventricular pressures exceed the arterial pressures (pulmonary
               and aortic), the pulmonary and aortic semilunar valves open, ejecting blood into the
               respective blood vessels. Once the ventricles enter diastole, the ventricular
               pressures fall. When these pressures fall below that in their respective arteries,
               the valves close again. This creates the <term>second heart sound</term> (dub).
               Systole is now over and another diastole has begun; the cycle continues again.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
      <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_41.jpg" width="550"
         alt="graph of pressure and volume changes during cardiac cycle"><title>Figure 5</title><caption></caption></image>
      
      <wb:inline idref="describe_phases_cardiac_cycle_LBD2-f" purpose="learnbydoing" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
         <param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/_u9_m02_structure_function_LBD2-f-layout.xml</param></wb:inline>
      
      <wb:inline idref="describe_phases_cardiac_cycle_DIGT2-6-9" purpose="didigetthis"/>
      
   </body>
</workbook_page>
