<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_03">
   <head>
      <title>Heart Calculations</title>
      <objref idref="relate_CO_HR_SV_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="define_cardiac_output_stroke_vol_heart_rate_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="predict_changes_affect_cardiac_output_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="define_EDV_ESV_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="explain_frank_starling_law_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p/>
      <section>
         <title>Cardiodynamics and Cardiac Output</title>
         <body>
            <p>Cardiac output is one measure of the heart's efficiency. It is the amount of blood
               pumped per minute. Heart rate fluctuations are one way for the body to adjust the
               cardiac output so that it can appropriately meet the demands of the body. When
               resting, the body doesn’t have as high of a demand for oxygen because the muscles and
               organs are at a lowered metabolic rate compared to when they are in a state of
               exertion. Therefore, the heart rate is low. Similarly, if the body is actively
               exercising, the demand for oxygen and the need to get rid of carbon dioxide are both
               quite high. The heart rate, and therefore the cardiac output, increases
               accordingly.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Control of Cardiac Output Through a Changing Stroke Volume</title>
         <body>
            <p>Cardiac output is the product of heart rate (beats per minute) and stroke volume
               (volume of pumped blood per beat). Although the heart has the intrinsic ability to
               generate a consistent heart rate, we have already learned that the autonomic nervous
               system exerts significant control over this variable. Similarly, there are factors
               that affect the stroke volume of the heart. The amount of blood that flows into the
               heart is termed <term>preload</term>. Besides preload, the stroke volume of the heart
               can also be affected by myocardial contractility, and, under certain conditions,
               afterload, which is the pressure the ventricle needs to develop to eject blood.</p>
            <p>We have already discussed heart rate. It is the pace the heart beats or the number of
               beats per minute. It is easy to see how an increase or decrease in the number of
               beats can affect the overall cardiac output. If the heart beats more often, more
               blood will be pumped through the heart. If the cardiac output is a function of heart
               rate times the stroke volume, then as the heart rate increases, so does the cardiac
               output. At least this is true up to a point. At very high heart rates the heart may
               not have time to fill appropriately during diastole, which can actually decrease
               cardiac output. This is one of the risks of tachyarrhythmias (tachycardias).</p>
            <p>Preload is the amount of blood in the heart immediately before it contracts (end
               diastolic volume) and is mainly dependent on the flow rate of blood through the veins
               (venous return). Venous return is increased when the systemic venous pressure
               increases. For example, when we run the skeletal muscle in the legs contract,
               pressing against the veins in the leg. This increases the pressure in the veins and
               increases the flow of blood back to the heart. Another method to increase venous
               pressure is through medications that stiffen (decrease compliance) of the veins.
               Because veins can act as a storage space for blood, decreasing the amount of blood
               that they are holding pushes more blood toward the heart, increasing preload. In both
               of these cases (exercise or medications), stroke volume will increase, driving up
               cardiac output. There is a molecular level explanation for this phenomena related to
               the sarcomere structure in the muscle.</p>
            <p>We know that in skeletal muscles, increased stretch in the muscle will increase the
               force of the contraction, but only up to a certain point. Beyond that point, when the
               number of actin-myosin cross bridges decrease, the force generated decreases.</p>
            <!--CONTENT LINK: link to the actin-myosin section in the muscle unit-->
            <p>A similar principle holds true with cardiac muscle. The muscle can be stretched by
               adding more preload. Such stretching will increase the force of contraction by
               providing more optimal overlap for crossbridge generation. The concept that the force
               of heart muscle contraction will increase with an increase in end-diastolic
               ventricular volume is the basis of the <term>Frank-Starling Relationship</term>. This
               relationship was experimentally derived from the work of both O. Frank and E.H.
               Starling (not by one person named Frank Starling). Together, they discovered that the
               heart will adjust to an increase in volume by increasing its force of contraction. If
               the volume decreases, the cardiac output will, likewise, decrease.</p>
            <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_42.jpg" width="550" alt="">
               <title>Figure 6</title>
               <caption/>
            </image>
            <p>Even if preload doesn’t change, SV can either increase or decrease with a change in
               contractility. Contractility differs from the Frank-Starling mechanism in that it
               doesn’t affect the initial overlap of actin and myosin, like adding more preload
               does. Instead contractility changes the force the myocardial cells generate by
               adjusting the amount of calcium in the cytosol. An increase in contractility
               increases the levels of cytosolic calcium, whereas a decrease in contractility has
               the opposite effect. Because calcium is necessary to allow a crossbridge to form
               (overlap isn’t enough), more cytosolic calcium maximizes the number of crossbridges
               that have the potential to form. As a hypothetical example, let’s assume that a
               myocardial cell has the ability to form 1000 crossbridges at its current preload.
               Under normal conditions about 600 crossbridges will actually form because that is how
               much cytosolic calcium is available during systole. If contractility increases, the
               cell may now be able to form 800 crossbridges, increasing its force of contraction
               and increasing its stroke volume.</p>
            <p>Contractility is mainly affected by the sympathetic branch of the autonomic nervous
               system. The greater the number of signals the myocardial cells are receiving from the
               sympathetic nerves, the higher the contractility becomes. If the sympathetic nervous
               system decreases the number of signals sent, contractility will decrease. Various
               heart disorders will also decrease the heart’s contractility.</p>
            <p>The last factor that influences the intrinsic regulation of the heart is the
               afterload. The <term>afterload</term> is the pressure in the aorta that the heart has
               to overcome to eject blood. Afterload is approximated by the mean arterial pressure.
               For most individuals, afterload has little effect on stroke volume until mean
               arterial pressure rises about 50% above normal. But for those with heart disease,
               rising afterload at near normal pressures might decrease their stroke volumes.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <wb:inline idref="relate_CO_HR_SV_LBD2-g" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

      <section purpose="didigetthis">
         <title/>
         <body>
            <wb:inline idref="relate_CO_HR_SV_DIGT2-10-13" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <wb:inline idref="relate_CO_HR_SV_DIGT2-10-13-SC" purpose="didigetthis"/>
         </body>
      </section>

   </body>
</workbook_page>
