<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_08_old">
   <head>
      <!--DELETE THIS PAGE-->
      <title>Factors Influencing Blood Pressure: Vessel Lumen Size</title>
      <!--<objref idref="predict_effects_lumen_size_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objective:</p>
				<p>CV2.22 Using equations of resistance, predict the effects of lumen size.</p>-->
      <p>The smaller the lumen, the greater the resistance. Most of the changes in lumen
         size are due to the vasoconstriction and vasodilation of arteries and
         arterioles. As a vessel constricts, the lumen size decreases. This increases
         resistance inversely proportional to the change in radius to the fourth power,
         indicating that even small changes in radius can have large affects on
         resistance. And, if the flow rate is kept constant when radius decreases, then
         the pressure change (drop) along the length of the vessel will increase, as
         indicated by equation (3).</p>
      <p>Because our systemic vasculature is made up of millions of vessels, they each
         contribute in some way to the overall resistance of the system, called systemic
         vascular resistance (SVR) or total peripheral resistance. Most of this
         resistance is in the smallest vessels, such as small arteries, arterioles,
         capillaries, and venules. There is little resistance in large arteries and
         veins. Because of their large diameters, only a small amount of blood in large
         arteries and veins is in contact with the vessel wall. Controlling SVR is a
         chief function of arterioles. They regulate SVR—and thus BP and perfusion to
         specific tissues—by altering their diameter. Even minimal amounts of
         vasodilation or vasoconstriction in arterioles can have significant effects on
         SVR.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
