<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_14">
   <head>
      <title>Disorders of Capillary Exchange: Edema</title>
      <!--<objref idref="define_edema_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--				<p>Learning Objective:</p>
				<p>CV2.30 Define edema and identify its causes.</p>-->
      <p>The accumulation of excess fluid in the tissues is called <term>edema</term>.
         There are various physiological causes of edema, including standing too long
         without moving your feet and legs, and pregnancy. Edema can also come about as
         a side effect of certain medications and can, in some cases, be a sign of a
         serious underlying medical condition, such as heart failure. Each cause leads
         to an imbalance in the rates of filtration and reabsorption during capillary
         exchange. When fluid is filtered from the capillaries more quickly than it can
         be reabsorbed, or if the lymphatic capillaries cannot remove normal amounts of
         interstitial fluid, the interstitial fluid begins to collect within the
         affected tissue or organ. If the volume of the interstitial fluid exceeds 30
         percent above normal levels, edema can be detected as swelling of the affected
         area.</p>
      <p>Most commonly, edema is caused by venous congestion (increased venous
         pressures) caused by increased resistance to blood flow through major veins,
         reduced pumping ability of the right heart, or excessive fluid levels in the
         body. Pregnancy and liver disease can make it harder for blood to return
         through the venous system from the legs or abdomen, respectively. In each case
         edema will occur in the tissues with impeded flow. Pregnancy commonly causes
         edema in the legs, while liver disease causes abdominal edema, called ascites.
         Right heart failure leads to a more generalized edema, as venous flow from the
         entire body is affected. In each case, BHP is greatly increased within the
         capillaries. Because BHP is the driving force of filtration, the rate of fluid
         leaving the capillaries escalates with increasing BHP. High BHP also opposes
         reabsorption. Despite the rise in IFHP due to extra fluid within the tissues,
         the high BHP results in less fluid reabsorption at the venous end of the
         capillary network. A high BHP also puts uncommon pressure on the walls of the
         capillaries, forcing the epithelial cells apart, and the intercellular gaps
         become wider. Plasma proteins normally confined to the blood vessels spill into
         the interstitial fluid. This causes IFOP to increase and BCOP to decrease,
         causing fluid to accumulate even more rapidly. Edema can only be resolved by
         intervention to prevent the filtration/reabsorption imbalance and time for the
         lymph system to collect the excess fluids.</p>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
