<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m2_structures_01"><head><title>Measuring Heart Electricity</title><objref idref="relate_ECG_waveforms_to_conduction_sys_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="dad35619363a49fb84e2c28e9706a95f">The <term>electrocardiogram</term>, also called an ECG or EKG, measures the electrical activity associated with the heart. By placing a minimum of three electrodes on the skin in three locations—for example, the left arm, the right arm, and left leg—the electrical signals that initiate contraction of the atria and ventricles can be recorded. These recordings, or waveforms, are seen on a monitor and are called a <term>tracing</term>. The resultant waveform consists of <term>P, QRS, and T waves</term>. These deflection waves are indicative of the depolarization electrical activity just before the contraction of the atria (P wave), the depolarization electrical activity stimulating ventricular contraction (QRS complex), and repolarization of ventricles prior to relaxation (T wave). </p><image id="b0ad96f568e14a689134ec2a8482579d" src="../webcontent/C_M3_37.jpg" alt="waveforms of electrical signals associated with different parts of the heart" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="550"><title>Figure 2</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ed2a23460cc446a989f494aa89036fcf">ECG tracings can provide information about the anatomy and placement of the heart in the chest cavity. It provides information about the size of the chambers and the rhythm of contraction. Importantly, ECGs are used to detect changes that have occurred in heart function. Example changes include changes in the rhythm, changes in the conduction pathway of electrical signals, or the development of ischemic areas (areas lacking oxygen) that result from narrowed or occluded coronary arteries.</p><p id="c0c3dfc284e14418a49e315f15358f08">Changes in the tracing can be used to diagnose many diseases. The P-R interval measures the time from atrial to ventricular contraction. Alterations to the length of this interval can be indicative of damage in AV conductance that is caused by inflammation or medications. The QRS wave shows the electrical activity that initiates ventricular contraction or ventricular systole. Lengthening of this interval can indicate problems with ventricular electrical conduction. During the S-T interval, the ventricles are depolarized and contracting. Normally, the EKG reads zero voltage during the S-T interval, and a value higher or lower than this can indicate that underlying ischemic damage to the heart may have occurred. Ischemic damage results when there is a lack of sufficient oxygen to the heart. The duration of the S-T interval varies with heart rate, decreasing at higher rates.</p><image id="ee618ecc481441859b1a1cc48cbed9b4" src="../webcontent/C_M3_38.jpg" alt="ECG trace with the component waves labeled" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><title>Figure 3</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f483101140e64ab09b91a066491d7f86"><em style="bold">Component Amplitute (mV) Duration (sec)</em></p><table id="c16210481ecb4bf5a0f9b4e7bf4df154" summary="" rowstyle="alternating"><cite id="ib41528bb7eb1469a90711566f6ccb9ee" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="cbdabb2425e44478a6bede73f5c5f936"><em style="bold">Component</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="a0a875dfdb444a049081dd0df1569b0f"><em style="bold">Amplitude (mV)</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ea5718c3b17444c69f7c04f0bac2f5c5"><em style="bold">Duration (sec)</em></p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad9c45ed9e59b45858b9d82beca9a0312">P wave</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af807bc60b45547ef8cf39f2f851839ff">0.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af96e160b6dd444019bd3d9c72e55af45">0.10</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af40704f1c59d420a9dc028be945b8804">QRS complex</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="accc2a44c1194460f87cb67e5f4d64f9b">1.0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaecefe7777ce4003b90d05070491d31e">0.08-0.12</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ada99cb1d7b2c49f88d55f74bce09618a">T wave</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae322c47663204ed9b9d4c6e1cd566198">0.2-0.3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afec0f7ffcb9b400bacbd13e3c4fca822">0.16-0.27</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abbadb03d74ca4a10b707ed8f1cb378fa">P-Q interval</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae56384e9ac9a40b8a6ffaad674605327">N/A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abf5c13bd65c145bcacac32d0da3ae8eb">0.12-0.21</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aed2f6213076b4adc8e0bb54035e8ce33">Q-T interval</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abdc8a138013a4493a6e86ecd872274cb">N/A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab878432169a846e194163f563e22f9e6">0.30-0.43</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad54aab395ef8431db3c0988c39a2aa01">T-Q segment</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa73c1ba5d784490faafd0909a8f9ab34">N/A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afa378bfbc929448db4c3564f87092377">0.55-0.70</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac6bc32b2b43d4b86a2bf2840c3038f5c">R-R interval</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab9e7d803ab0e413997542c026dc7ab0f">N/A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae2a8f2b05d5a4a02b0964a5ce68e29c0">0.85-1.00</p></td></tr></table><wb:inline idref="relate_ECG_waveforms_to_conduction_sys_LBD2-d" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/_u9_m02_structure_function_LBD2-d-layout.xml</param></wb:inline><p id="b9fb139a7fa547dab3e9d13c4a7da570">If the SA node fires rapidly, the person has tachycardia. In one form of tachycardia, atrial tachycardia, the atrial rate of contraction might actually be much higher than the ventricular rate of contraction. This can happen because the AV node can limit the number of action potentials that pass from the atria to the ventricles. On an ECG this would be detected as more P waves than QRS complexes. If the ventricles are continuously firing without a consistently preceding P wave, then the person would have <term>ventricular tachycardia</term>. In this case the QRS complexes also look abnormal due to the pathway of conduction having changed. These are just a few examples of the many abnormalities that can be diagnosed using ECG tracings.</p><wb:inline idref="relate_ECG_waveforms_to_conduction_sys_LBD2-e" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="e383742a61ca4ba39a728a83c06a973e"><title>Diseases of the Heart: Arrhythmias</title><body><p id="c0088082db0444b8b2dc09c8d2c82798"><term>Arrhythmias</term> (or dysrhythmias) are the abnormal rhythms in heart rate or conduction pathway. Some tend to be harmless while others can be fatal. Arrhythmias can range from having an occasional extra beat or a skipped beat to having fibrillation of the atria or ventricles. Arrhythmias can also arise when the heart either beats too slowly (bradycardia) or too quickly (tachycardia).</p><p id="ca2b42a2ff754fa281f30863b5948fa2">Arrhythmias are much more serious and deadly when the ventricle beats in an uncontrolled manner. This arrhythmia, called ventricular fibrillation, does not produce a productive heart contraction and will be fatal if not corrected. Atrial fibrillation, on the other hand, is a common arrhythmia arising when multiple cells outside of the SA node spontaneously depolarize at high rates. In this case the atria quiver instead of beat, but because most of the blood in atria move into the ventricles passively due to pressure differences even before the atria contract, it is not nearly as damaging as ventricular fibrillation. People at risk of atrial fibrillation still need to be managed because the condition increases their risk of thromboemboli (blood clots that move to other parts of the body) and stroke. Both atrial and ventricular fibrillation can be diagnosed on an ECG tracing as they will present with either a complete lack of P waves or QRS complexes, respectively.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="relate_ECG_waveforms_to_conduction_sys_DIGT2-4-5" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
