<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_08">
   <head>
      <title>Filtration and Reabsorption</title>
      <objref idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="define_hydrostatic_osmotic_pressure_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="define_compare_pressures_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>Bulk flow follows the same principles as any other type of pressure gradient.
         High pressure in one area promotes movement of fluid to an area of lower
         pressure. Capillary exchange is driven by two types of pressures. Physical or
            <term>hydrostatic pressure </term>is caused by fluid pressing against the
         confining vessel walls or other physical barrier. This is the same as the blood
         pressure measured within the capillary. <term>Osmotic pressure </term>is caused
         by the presence of non-diffusing solutes within the fluid. Nearly all small
         molecules, such as ions, freely diffuse across the capillary wall; as such,
         they don’t contribute to osmotic pressure differences between plasma and
         interstitial space like they do across cell membranes. Instead, it is the large
         plasma proteins that are responsible for the osmotic pressure differences
         across the capillary wall. The name given to the osmotic pressure caused by
         these proteins is <term>colloid osmotic pressure</term>. Depending on the
         location, the sum of the hydrostatic and colloid osmotic pressure, called the
            <term>net filtration pressure (NFP)</term>, can promote filtration or
         reabsorption, or all the pressures can be at equilibrium and neither filtration
         nor reabsorption occurs. There are four pressures to consider when determining
         NFP, two on each side of the capillary wall: <term>blood hydrostatic pressure (BHP)</term>,
         <term>interstitial fluid hydrostatic pressure (IFHP)</term>, <term>blood colloid osmotic pressure
         (BCOP)</term>, and <term>interstitial fluid colloid osmotic pressure (IFCOP)</term>.</p>
      <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_45.jpg" width="550"
         alt=""><title>Figure 9</title><caption></caption></image>
      
      <wb:inline idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_LBD2-r" purpose="learnbydoing" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
         <param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/describe_function_capillary_exchange_LBD2-r-layout.xml</param></wb:inline>
      
      <p>At the arterial end of a capillary network, the BHP is usually about 35 mmHg. A
         high BHP promotes fluids moving from the capillaries into the interstitial
         fluid around the tissues. Alternatively, IFHP is very low throughout the
         tissues surrounding the capillary network. This is because local lymphatic
         vessels are constantly removing fluid from the interstitial space, keeping
         pressure very low. IFHP is so close to zero that it cannot counter the movement
         of fluid into the interstitial fluid under the effects of a high BHP. Due to
         this, IFHP is not typically considered in determining NFP. If there was not
         another force to counteract the hydrostatic pressure difference across the
         capillary wall, there would be a huge outflow of fluid from the capillary into
         the interstitial space. In order to provide balance and prevent this from
         happening, the high colloid osmotic pressure in the capillaries helps retain
         fluid in the vascular space. Most plasma proteins, such as albumin, fibrinogen
         and immune globulins are too large to diffuse from the bloodstream except at
         sinusoid capillaries. Therefore, the concentration of proteins or colloids is
         much greater in the capillaries than in the interstitial fluid. The result of
         this imbalance is an osmotic gradient that moves fluid from the interstitial
         fluid into the capillaries. The osmotic pressures show little variation along
         the length of the capillary network. BCOP holds steady at about 26 mmHg, while
         IFCOP is always close to 1 mmHg.</p>
      
      <wb:inline idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_LBD2-s" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
      <wb:inline idref="describe_function_capillary_exchange_DIGT2-24-29" purpose="didigetthis"/>
      
   </body>
</workbook_page>
