<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m2_structures_00">
   <head>
      <title>The Heart</title>
      <objref idref="describe_conduction_sys_heart_OBJ"/>
      <!--<objref idref="define_automaticity_rhythmicity_heart_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="explain_SA_node_pacing_heart_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="describe_ans_regulation_cardiac_function_OBJ"/>-->
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>The heart pumps continuously to provide tissues and organs with needed oxygen and remove
         cellular waste materials. On average, the heart pumps 70 to 72 beats per minute, every
         minute of every day. It is able to pump close to the entire volume of blood in your body
         every minute. This means that on a daily basis, almost 7200 liters of blood are pumped by
         the heart. This amount increases when you exercise.</p>
      <p>The heart is separated from the lungs inside the thorax by a membranous sack called the
            <term>parietal pericardium</term>. This sack is continuous with the outermost layer of
         the heart called the <term>visceral epicardium</term>. Just deep to the pericardium is the
            <term>myocardium</term>, which is the muscle layer of the heart. It comprises 99% of the
         mass of the heart. The <term>endocardium </term>is the innermost layer of the heart tissue
         that lines the heart chambers and is continuous with the endothelium lining blood
         vessels.</p>
      <section>
         <title>Heart Conduction</title>
         <body>
            <p>The heart’s ability to generate its own beat is an intrinsic quality. Inside the
               superior wall of the right atrium a group of specialized cells called the <term>sinoatrial
               (SA) node</term> spontaneously depolarize, creating a signal that passes to the atria and
               the ventricles, causing their contraction. Because the SA node repeatedly creates
               this signal, it is often called the pacemaker of the heart. These action potentials
               create the rhythmic contraction of the heart that pushes blood through the heart and
               circulatory system. </p>
            <p>If the SA node becomes dysfunctional, the <term>atrioventricular (AV) node</term>,
               found in the septal wall between the atria and ventricles can take over the pacing of
               the heart. Its cells also exhibit the property of spontaneous depolarization, but it
               does so at a slower rate than the SA node; thus the SA node typically “wins” the
               pacing race by generating action potentials at a higher rate. This is called
                  <term>overdrive suppression</term>.</p>

            <wb:inline idref="describe_conduction_sys_heart_LBD2-a" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

            <p>Because of this intrinsic quality, the heart is said to have
                  <term>automaticity</term>, meaning it is able to self-generate a beat. The heart
               also has <term>rhythmicity</term>, which means it can generate its own pace of
               beating. In fact, if a healthy heart is removed from a person or animal, it will
               continue to beat outside of the body as long as it is put in a medium that supplies
               it with energy. This occurs as hearts are transported for transplantation.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <wb:inline idref="describe_conduction_sys_heart_LBD2-b" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

      <image src="../webcontent/C_M3_36.jpg" width="350"
         alt="numbers indicating muscle excitation after S-A impulse">
         <title>Figure 1</title>
         <caption/>
      </image>

      <section>
         <title>Action Potentials and Spontaneous Depolarization</title>
         <body>
            <p>Although the heart can intrinsically generate its own rate of spontaneous
               depolarization (and therefore heart rate), this rate is under significant influence
               by the autonomic nervous system. The sympathetic and parasympathetic branches of the
               autonomic nervous system innervate the SA and AV nodes, adjusting their rates of
               depolarization. The sympathetic nervous system will increase SA node depolarization
               rates, increasing heart rate. The parasympathetic nervous system has the opposite
               effect. At rest, the parasympathetic nervous system exhibits greater control of heart
               rate. If this parasympathetic influence is removed, the heart rate typically
               increases to about 100 beats per minute. Similarly, the pacemaker cells within the AV
               node also spontaneously depolarize, but they do so at a rate of about 50 beats per
               minute.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <wb:inline idref="describe_conduction_sys_heart_LBD2-c" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

      <section>
         <title>Electrical Conductance of the Heart</title>
         <body>
            <p>When the cells in the SA node depolarize, the action potential that is initiated is
               spread throughout the heart. The signal travels through the heart muscle in two ways:
               (1) from node to node along the conducting cells through the <term>internodal
                  conducting pathway </term>and (2) directly by cell–to-cell spread. The internodal
               conducting pathway is actually made up of 3 separate paths of conducting cells that
               connect the SA node with the AV node. Once the signal reaches the AV node, it passes
               through the septum by conducting through the Bundle of His and into the Purkinje
               Fibers. From here the signals are distributed throughout the ventricular myocardium
               in rapid fashion.</p>
            <p>Not only do action potentials travel through the internodal conducting cells from
               node to node, but they also travel directly from cell to cell in the atria and
               ventricles themselves. Therefore, when cells of the SA node depolarize, the cells
               surrounding the SA node also depolarize. Because of the gap junctions between the
               cells, the electrical signal travels quickly throughout all the individual muscle
               cells of the atria.</p>
         </body>
      </section>

      <wb:inline idref="describe_conduction_sys_heart_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"/>

   </body>
</workbook_page>
