<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="PCR" movieroot="">
    
    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-1.swf"  menustep="Polymerase Chain Reaction">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The &lt;b&gt;P&lt;/b&gt;olymerase &lt;b&gt;C&lt;/b&gt;hain &lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;eaction (PCR) is a process by which segments of DNA can be amplified using the rules of replication defined by the mechanism of DNA polymerase. This automated procedure is carried-out in a thermocycler pictured below. This animation will provide a step-by-step illustrated guide through the amplification process.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-2.swf"  menustep="1st Cycle - Denaturing">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;At low temperatures the saturated acyl chains are able to pack close to each other as extended chains. This is very stable configuration because of the favorable van der Waals interactions between the chains. This causes the membrane to be solid-like below the melting temperature. As the temperature rises, clusters of phospholipids melt, followed by melting of the entire bilayer. At temperatures above the melting temperature the acyl-chains are disorder or fluid. The first step in PCR is to create the single stranded template for replication by DNA polymerase. This is accomplished by raising the temperature of the reaction to 90 degrees Celsius or above the Tm for the DNA to be amplified.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-3.swf"  menustep="           Annealing (68 Celsius)">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The second step is to choose primers that define the ends of the DNA fragment to be amplified. The primers are designed to be complementary to a sequence of the template DNA on each strand such that DNA synthesis from the 3’ end of each primer will result in synthesis beyond the position of primer on the second strand. These are referred to as &lt;b&gt;Forward and Reverse Primers&lt;/b&gt;. 

The primers also should to be sufficiently long and rich in GC bases that they will form hydrogen bonded complementary pairing at a temperature above the melting temperature of the original duplex DNA.

The illustration below shows the primers in &lt;b&gt;red&lt;/b&gt; with hybridization (annealing) taking place without re-annealing of the template.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-4.swf"  menustep="           Elongation (72 Celsius)">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The third step is to replicate the template on each strand using DNA polymerase. This step is performed at an elevated temperature (generally 72 degrees Celsius) to maintain the template as single stranded DNA without the use of SSB protein. This replication at elevated temperatures was made possible by the discovery of a thermo-stable DNA polymerase isolated from thermophylic bacteria. An example of this is &lt;i&gt;taq&lt;/i&gt; DNA polymerase I (from the bacteria &lt;i&gt;Thermus aquaticus&lt;/i&gt;) that is optimally active at 70 degrees Celsius.

Replication of the template on each strand proceeds simultaneously from the forward (F-primer) and reverse (R-primer) primers.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-5.swf"  menustep="           Completed">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The DNA polymerase replicates the template as far as it can before dissociating from its substrate. Note that at the end of the first cycle there is new DNA synthesized but none of the new DNA is the length of the fragment defined by the position of the two primers. Each new strand of DNA is synthesized beyond the position of the primer position in the opposite direction.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-6.swf"  menustep="2nd Cycle - Denaturing">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The second cycle repeats the steps of the first. The first step is melting (denaturing) of the double stranded DNA at elevated temperature.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
 
    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-7.swf"  menustep="           Annealing">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The second step is the annealing (binding) of the primers to the singled stranded templates. This is followed by replication by DNA polymerase from the 3’ end of each primer.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-8.swf"  menustep="           Completed">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;DNA polymerase will replicate the DNA on the second and third strands to the ends of the templates. Replication of the first and fourth strands still results in replication beyond the position of the second primer.
   
Note that even after two cycles, there are no duplex (double stranded) fragments of DNA that are equal to the distance from the 5’ end of the forward primer to the 5’ end of the reverse primer.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-9.swf"  menustep="3rd Cycle - Completed">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The third cycle is a repeat of the procedure of the second. Because this is a repetitive cycle of reactions, the process is easily automated.

The positions of the original primers are indicated in red on each duplex product. You will notice that this is the first cycle that has produced fragments (the third and the sixth) that are exactly the length defined by the forward and reverse primers. Thus one fourth of the eight products generated are the desired length.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/PCR-10.swf"  menustep="4th Cycle - Completed">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The fourth cycle continues the repetitive process. There are now 16 products of which 8 (50% of the products) are the desired length defined by the position of the forward and reverse primers. This progression will continue until the fragments of undesirable length are minor components in the mixture of products.

In each case it is worth noting that the primes (highlighted in red) are part of the final product. Thus confirmation of the amplification of the desired sequence by sequencing should generate the original primer sequences. This also means that the forward and reverse primers can be used to initiate the sequencing process on each strand.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    
 </TUTORIAL>
