<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?><TUTORIAL thisTitle="Serine Protease - biochem" movieroot=""><step stepURL="swfs/introduction.swf" menustep=" Introduction "><text>&lt;html&gt;Trypsin is an extracellular protease that hydrolyzes peptide bonds during digestion in the small intestine.  It is a member of a large family of homologous enzymes called "serine proteases".  The chemical mechanism of serine proteases is identical; the various enzymes in the family differ only in their substrate specificity.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/architecture.swf" menustep=" Architecture "><text>&lt;html&gt;The overall architecture of the serine proteases, trypsin, chymotrypsin, and elastase is very similar.  The image shows a backbone model of trypsin.  The three active site residues are shown as Ball & Stick, colored CPK.  The substrate, ArgAla, is shown as Sticks with carbons colored green.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/active.swf" menustep=" Active Site "><text>&lt;html&gt;The close up view of the active site shows the catalytic groups on Asp 102, His 57, and Ser 195.  Together they are referred to as the "catalytic triad".Asp 102 polarizes His 57His 57 acts as a general base to abstract the proton from Ser 195 (Phase 1) or a water molecule (Phase 2). It also acts later in each phase as a general acid.Ser 195 makes a nucleophilic attack on the carbonyl carbon of the scissile peptide bond, to form the acyl-enzyme intermediate (acyl-E).&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/mechanism.swf" menustep=" Mechanism "><text>&lt;html&gt;The mechanism involves the coordinated action of these three features of the enzyme:1. Substrate specificity (or binding) pocket,2. Catalytic triad,3. Oxyanion hole.The reaction can be described in two phases:Phase 1:  From substrate binding to the release of the new amino-terminus and formation of acyl-E.Phase 2:  From the acyl-E to the release of the new carboxyl-terminus and regeneration of free enzyme.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/substrate.swf" menustep=" Phase 1: Substrate Binding "><text>&lt;html&gt;Phase 1: Peptide Bond Cleavage  & Enzyme Acylation.For simplicity, the reaction shown here is the cleavage of the peptide bond in the ArgAla dipeptide.  The substrate binds with the Arg side chain inserted into the complementary binding pocket at the active site of trypsin.  Note the favorable electrostatic interaction between Arg on the substrate and Asp 189 on the enzyme.R1 is  -H3+ in this dipeptide. It would be the amino terminal residues at a longer peptide substrate.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/first.swf" menustep="    First Nucleophilic Attack "><text>&lt;html&gt;The polarized His 57 imidazole acts as a general base to remove the proton from Ser 195.  The increased nucleophilicity of Ser 195 enables it to attack the carbonyl carbon (sp2) of ArgAla.Following nucleophilic attack, the carbon is tetrahedral (sp3) and the carbonyl oxygen becomes an oxyanion (-O-).  This transient state is stabilized by the positive dipoles (d+) of three main chain NH groups that form a hole for the oxyanion.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/bond.swf" menustep="    Bond Cleavage "><text>&lt;html&gt;The tetrahedral intermediate breaks down with His 57 acting as a general acid to donate its H+ to the amino group of the newly-formed N-terminus. (Water has not been used -yet- in this hydrolysis reaction).After formation at the acyl-enzyme intermediate the new amino terminus (Ala in this case) dissociates.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/water.swf" menustep=" Phase 2: Water Entry "><text>&lt;html&gt;Phase 2: Enzyme Deacylation.With the dissociation of the first product, a water molecule can enter the active site near the acyl-E group.  His 57 again acts as a general base to remove a proton from the H2O.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/second.swf" menustep="   Second Nucleophilic Attack "><text>&lt;html&gt;The  water oxygen, as nucleophile, attacks the carbonyl carbon of the acyl-enzyme.The second tetrahedral intermediate is stabilized by the same "oxyanion hole".&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/dissociation.swf" menustep="   Second Product Dissociation "><text>&lt;html&gt;The tetrahedral intermediate breaks down to form the protonated carboxy-terminus.  Dissociation of this product regenerates the free enzyme making it available for another round of catalysis.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/chymo.swf" menustep=" Chymotrypsin "><text>&lt;html&gt;Chymotrypsin cleaves preferentially after Phe, Tyr, and Trp residues.  As in the trypsin animation, a dipepeptide substrate is used for simplicity; in this case, PheAla.  The entire reaction sequence runs without pausing, however, you can stop and restart at any point using the pause buttton.  Note that the chymotrypsin binding pocket does not contain the charged Asp residue that is complementary to the Lys and Arg side chains of trypsin substrates.  Instead the binding pocket is uniformly hydrophobic.  Except for this key difference, all aspects of the mechanism are identical to that shown above for trypsin.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/selected.swf" menustep=" Selected Active Site Interaction "><text>&lt;html&gt;These four animations show enzyme-ligand interactions (or reactions) that highlight features of specificity and catalysis in the serine proteases.&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/DIPF.swf" menustep="   DIPF "><text>&lt;html&gt;The close up view of the active site shows the catalytic groups on Asp 102, His 57, and Ser 195.  Together they are referred to as the "catalytic triad".Asp 102 polarizes His 57His 57 acts as a general base to abstract the proton from Ser 195 (Phase 1) or a water molecule (Phase 2). It also acts later in each phase as a general acid.Ser 195 makes a nucleophilic attack on the carbonyl carbon of the scissile peptide bond, to form the acyl-enzyme intermediate (acyl-E).&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/TPCK.swf" menustep="   TPCK "><text>&lt;html&gt;TPCK reaction with chymotrypsinN-tosyl-phenylalanine chloroketone (TPCK) is shown reacting with the active site His of chymotrypsin.  The reaction products are HCl and the covalently modified enzyme.  In contrast to DIPF, the TPCK reaction is specific to chymotrypsin because the phenylalanine moiety of TPCK directs it to the hydrophobic binding pocket of chymotrypsin .  TPCK is termed an "affinity label" because the labeling reaction depends on the intrinsic enzyme specificity.  What change(s) would you make in TPCK that might convert it into an affinity label for trypsin?&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/pNPA.swf" menustep="   pNPA "><text>&lt;html&gt;Esterase activity of chymotrypsinp-Nitrophenylacetate (pNPA) is an ester substrate for chymotrypsin.  All of the serine proteases catalyze the hydrolysis of esters to varying extents.  The reaction mechanism is similar to that shown above for peptide substrates except that the products are an alcohol and an acid.  In addition, the rate limiting step in ester hydrolysis is phase 2 (acyl-enzyme hydrolysis) instead of phase 1 as in peptide hydrolysis.  The change in rate limiting step produces a "burst" of alcohol product (pNP in this example) prior to the steady state reaction. The p-nitrophenyl moiety makes this substrate specific for chymotrypsin.What change(s) would you make in pNPA that might convert it into an ester substrate for trypsin?&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step><step stepURL="swfs/TSA.swf"menustep="   TSA "><text>&lt;html&gt;Phosphonates as transition state analogsThe charged phosphonate  group mimics the configureation of an ester (or peptide) tetrahedral intermediate.  However, the phosphonate cannot be hydrolyzed or form an acylenzyme intermediate.  Instead, it is a very high affinity (but reversible) inhibitor of the enzyme.  This class of inhibitors is called, "transition state analog (TSA) inhibitors".  The Lys side chain makes it complementary to the trypsin binding pocket.What change(s) would you make in "TSA" that might convert it into a TSA for chymotrypsin?&lt;/html&gt;        </text>    </step></TUTORIAL>