<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="digestion_unit_review"><head><title>Digestive System Unit Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="d1a13c90c1424c17ae85f9141f7fb73d">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="cd4219bee0b942eab49c6a24e95b17e3"><li><p id="ad2a8b9259e3b413385d3dc8f45617808">Describe the major functions of the digestive system.</p></li><li><p id="ab0bb67af02b541cebe86d2c0dfd3b4a4">Identify organs of the digestive system based on position and structure; identify the general function of each.</p></li><li><p id="af4694514ad134691bc3ea9454d9ad3dc">Describe how material moves through the digestive system.</p></li><li><p id="afcafd52163e742879123187d3ed7c9ec">Explain how mechanical and chemical digestion work together to produce absorbable nutrients.</p></li><li><p id="abe5ab0d82225442c9d8935289c233cb1">Explain how nutrients are absorbed in the digestive system.</p></li><li><p id="ab2579b3bdb704ff7b35875734baf47a9">Identify and discuss the histology and functions of the plicae circulares, villi, and microvilli.</p></li><li><p id="af782a11c46074e359fc7888af6a0d256">Integrate the levels of organization in the digestive system and their functional interconnections.</p></li><li><p id="aad58c99d64ef4fc4be70a3854c33a62e">Describe the process of enzymatic hydrolysis for nutritive organic compounds</p></li><li><p id="ae1d65158d60849f7b5970f1a2701f5d0">Describe how secretions from the GI tract, salivary glands, pancreas and the liver work together to digest nutritive molecules in food.</p></li><li><p id="ae46b9b3bf4944b72b948b460e3cd6360">Relate the regional cell-level specializations within the digestive system to changing functions along the length of the GI tract.</p></li><li><p id="aa45cd9947fa54504af0f3a2526c6f858">Identify and describe the histological structure and function of each of the four layers of the GI tract wall.</p></li><li><p id="aa3f4ee3f431b45f0855152f97d3e2bf9">Describe the pathway of the bolus from mouth to stomach, identifying major structures and describing their role in facilitating the process of deglutition (swallowing).</p></li><li><p id="ab7abe44f069a45428907d6be3482f3b2">Explain the process of deglutition, including the changes in position of the glottis and larynx that prevent aspiration and peristalsis.</p></li><li><p id="ab51ed234317b43b9a570191592b7bc85">Describe the pathway of the chyme through the stomach, identifying major structures and describing their adaptations and role in the various digestive activities.</p></li><li><p id="aefdd4c195f5f405fb92fe57a1a7bb6ec">Explain the regulation of gastric secretion in the cephalic phase, the gastric phase and the intestinal phase.</p></li><li><p id="afa5ed28dc118445cb1fe37b144769e07">Describe how the stomach uses a combination of mechanical force and chemicals to digest food.</p></li><li><p id="aca48c0d2fd8f4758a71ba95b6d1417b9">Describe the functions of the different regions of the small intestine.</p></li><li><p id="aa7662e4c2ca94277b4d8a3891b36f62d">List the organs and specific structures involved in the absorption of each nutrient.</p></li><li><p id="afd940c1a77af43739e7d548b29b9f890">Identify and discuss the functions of the large intestine and its structures.</p></li><li><p id="af3fac50075f04177aaa01df29863fd86">Describe the role of bacteria living in the large intestine.</p></li><li><p id="ab565dca8bbcc45bbac233762b79af25a">Describe the defecation reflex and the function of the internal and external anal sphincters.</p></li><li><p id="af7e49d7cb838452ea8be7bbc412a58a1">Describe the location of the parotid, submandibular, and sublingual glands and their respective ducts.</p></li><li><p id="aaba167366b124ed9a82776accf07b728">Identify and discuss the functions of the pancreas and its structures.</p></li><li><p id="ad7398b83e30c42b4907f35d80b1566ff">Identify and discuss the functions of the liver and its structures.</p></li><li><p id="ad8b7a9805e2f40c5b0d7e4567759f602">Identify and discuss the functions of the gall bladder.</p></li><li><p id="acb2935f4caa1441b855c80c4d9132618">Explain how the digestive system relates to other body systems to maintain homeostasis.</p></li></ul><activity idref="Digestion_LOO_Exam" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="Digestion_unit_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
