<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u8_m1_review"><head><title>Digestive Structures and Functions Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="ff1b5b109d794fc78a86f3e1684c399b">The digestive system moves water, nutrients and electrolytes from the external environment to the internal environment. Within the digestive system, the gastrointestinal tract is a continuous hollow tube from the mouth to the anus and is technically contiguous with the external environment.The digestive system is generally divided into two main categories: organs of the alimentary canal (also called the gastrointestinal tract) and accessory digestive organs. Make sure you understand the different organs and their functions.</p><p id="f4e0aa350b2d480c9a18394b763e227e">Both voluntary skeletal muscles and involuntary smooth muscles are involved in propelling food material through the digestive system. The smooth muscle of the GI tract is arranged in two layers: longitudinal along the length of the tube and circular around the diameter of the tube. Coordinated contraction and relaxation of these two layers creates a wave-like propulsion of the food called peristalsis. Controlling the rate of food moving from one organ of the digestive tract to the next are specialized circularly arranged skeletal and smooth muscles called sphincters. Sphincters are typically contracted and relax only to allow food to move from one organ to the next. The majority of sphincters along the length of the GI tract are involuntary smooth muscle structures.</p><p id="cb991145f73a49e7ae789148e15f8e9e">Digestion is accomplished both mechanically and chemically. Mechanical digestion physically breaks food into smaller pieces, increasing surface area for more efficient chemical digestion. Chemical digestion breaks large food macromolecules down into their chemical building blocks, which can then be absorbed through the intestinal wall and into the general circulation.The mechanical and chemical digestive processes that begin in the mouth and continue through the small intestine have one endpoint: to convert food into substances that can be absorbed from the lumen by epithelial cells in the lining of the GI tract and then enter blood or lymphatic vessels. Absorbable substances are the monosaccharides, glucose, galactose, and fructose from carbohydrates; single amino acids, dipeptides, and tripeptides from proteins; and monoglycerides, glycerol, and fatty acids from lipids such as triglycerides.</p><activity idref="_u8_m1_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
