<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u8_m2_review"><head><title>Digestive Levels of Organization Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="b8487968a6fd4dd69bec279e479d0bb5">The digestive system breaks down ingested material into absorbable components (nutrients) that the rest of the body can use to maintain adequate function. We require a diverse set of nutrients to support energy production, carry out metabolism and maintain structure. Chemical digestion generally, breaks down large food molecules into their respective chemical building blocks, called monomers, that can be absorbed. The nutritive organic compounds in our food includes carbohydrates, proteins and lipids. These molecules are digested, then absorbed, and reassembled into macromolecules or used as fuel for metabolism in the body.</p><p id="fdcca3ebb3354cec87c66e360d048308">Some salivary glands are always secreting saliva. Intrinsic salivary glands of the mouth secrete small amounts of saliva, usually just enough to moisten the mucous membranes and clean the mouth and teeth. Bicarbonate and phosphate ions help maintain the pH of saliva as neutral or slightly basic (average 7.4 pH). Gastric glands produce hydrochloric acid (HCl), enzymes, and intrinsic factor. The pancreas produces about 1.2 to 1.5 quarts (1.1 – 1.4 liters) of pancreatic juice each day. This clear, colorless liquid is mostly water, along with some salts, sodium bicarbonate, and several digestive enzymes. Make sure you understand all of the digestive enzymes and their functions. </p><p id="b928cdba3c784c70bbf0344bd109bce6">Bile is another accessory organ contribution to the GI tract lumen. Bile is made by the hepatocytes of the liver, but stored in, concentrated, and released from the gall bladder. Unlike pancreatic juice that is produced and released as needed, bile is produced in small quantities by the liver continuously. The gall bladder stores it for release into the small intestine as needed.</p><p id="f31448c9dc9a4488b01820e41eff29ec">Digestion in the stomach requires a combination of acid and pepsin. In the glands of the stomach, chief cells secrete pepsinogen, which is converted to pepsin, as well as gastric lipase, which is used for digestion of fats. Parietal cells secrete hydrochloric acid (HCl) as well as intrinsic factor. Make sure you understand the different types of stomach cells and the actions they take.</p><activity idref="_u8_m2_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
