<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u3_m3_integrate_01"><head><title>Homeostasis Integration of Systems</title><objref idref="_u3_explain_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="bc9ab8f3a31b489fb89e41c99072debb">Each organ system performs specific functions for the body, and each organ system is typically studied independently. However, the organ systems also work together to help the body maintain homeostasis.</p><example id="water"><title>Water Levels</title><p id="ce07fc2f0363401fac2705d7fabcdc48">For example, the cardiovascular, urinary, and lymphatic systems all help the body control water balance. The cardiovascular and lymphatic systems transport fluids throughout the body and help sense both solute and water levels and regulate pressure. If the water level gets too high, the urinary system produces more dilute urine (urine with a higher water content) to help eliminate the excess water. If the water level gets too low, more concentrated urine is produced so that water is conserved. The digestive system also plays a role with variable water absorption. Water can be lost through the integumentary and respiratory systems, but that loss is not directly involved in maintaining body fluids and is usually associated with other homeostatic mechanisms. </p></example><example id="temp"><title>Internal Temperatures</title><p id="c092dd1d15554657822756937a671d30">Similarly, the cardiovascular, integumentary, respiratory, and muscular systems work together to help the body maintain a stable internal temperature. If body temperature rises, blood vessels in the skin dilate, allowing more blood to flow near the skin&apos;s surface. This allows heat to dissipate through the skin and into the surrounding air. The skin may also produce sweat if the body gets too hot; when the sweat evaporates, it helps to cool the body. Rapid breathing can also help the body eliminate excess heat. Together, these responses to increased body temperature explain why you sweat, pant, and become red in the face when you exercise hard. (Heavy breathing during exercise is also one way the body gets more oxygen to your muscles, and gets rid of the extra carbon dioxide produced by the muscles.) </p><p id="cf0a8fdcb2ca4f5a9d4ba0654967172c">Conversely, if your body is too cold, blood vessels in the skin contract, and blood flow to the extremities (arms and legs) slows. Muscles contract and relax rapidly, which generates heat to keep you warm. The hair on your skin rises, trapping more air, which is a good insulator, near your skin. These responses to decreased body temperature explain why you shiver, get &quot;goose bumps,&quot; and have cold, pale extremities when you are cold.</p></example><section id="a828f77ad018422e808264aad2a39359" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u3_fever_inline" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="_u3_postop_fever_inline" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><example id="b391c748b7f548d6af601210014c4cfe"><title>Fuel for Body Functions</title><p id="ecdf6926c23341fb8e62e107848e5171">As you have learned, blood glucose homeostasis is regulated by two hormones from the pancreas. This glucose provides the fuel for ATP production by all body cells. But the endocrine system is not the only system involved. </p><p id="dd56cb34b1b64852a8025d00580b8e02">Many body cells respond to insulin and glucagon, but the liver of the digestive system plays in important role in ensuring the availability of fuel in-between meals. Under the influence of insulin, the anabolic process of glycogenesis (-genesis means “origin” or “birth”) in the liver converts excess glucose entering liver cells to polymerize into glycogen for storage. Under the influence of glucagon, the reverse catabolic reaction of glycogenolysis (-lysis means “break up”) will convert the glycogen back into glucose for release into the blood stream. The liver cells can also perform gluconeogenesis (-neo means “new”), which creates glucose from non-carbohydrate sources, mainly from specific amino acids.</p><p id="f2e68ea927e641679c63b3fcbcc142b1">The nervous system also plays a role in maintaining blood glucose levels. When the stomach is empty and blood glucose levels are low, the digestive system receptors and the brain respond by making you feel hungry—your stomach may &quot;growl,&quot; and you may feel pain or discomfort in your midsection. These sensations prompt you to eat, which provides new nutrient sources to raise blood glucose levels. The exocrine part of the pancreas is also part of the digestive system. It produces enzymes that help digest the nutrients you have eaten so they can be absorbed by the small intestine into the blood. The circulatory system is important in transporting the glucose and pancreatic hormones in blood to all body cells.</p></example><wb:inline idref="_u3_explain_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></workbook_page>
