<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m3_integrate_02">
    <head>
        <title>Blood Calcium Levels</title>
        <objref idref="_u3_explain_OBJ"/>
    </head>

    <body>

        <p>As you have learned, proper calcium levels are important for normal function of several
            systems. Calcium ions are used for blood clotting, the contraction of muscles, the
            activation of enzymes, and cellular communication. The parathyroid gland of the
            endocrine system is the main receptor and control center for blood calcium levels. When
            the parathyroid glands detect low blood calcium levels, they communicate with several
            organ systems and alter their function to restore blood calcium levels back to normal.
            The skeletal, urinary, and digestive systems all act as effectors to achieve this goal
            through negative feedback. </p>

        <p>The release of parathyroid hormone from the endocrine system triggers osteoclasts of the
            skeletal system to breakdown (resorb) bone and release calcium into the blood.
            Similarly, this hormone causes the kidneys of the urinary system to reabsorb calcium and
            return it to the blood instead of excreting calcium into the urine. Through altered
            function of the kidneys to form active vitamin D, the small intestine of the digestive
            system increases the absorption of calcium.</p>

        <p>When blood calcium levels are elevated, the parathyroid gland senses that as well. But in
            this case, instead of increasing its secretion of parathyroid hormone, it decreases
            secretion of the hormone. This decreases bone resorbtion, increases calcium levels in
            the urine and decreases calcium absorption in the intestines.</p>

        <wb:inline idref="_u3_m3_graves" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>

</workbook_page>
