<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_homeostasis_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>Negative feedback occurs when environmental conditions move the body away from optimal conditions. For example as your body cools below 37 degrees Celsius the control center in your brain signals that actions need to be taken to raise your body temperature. The muscular system will begin to act. The smooth muscle of the blood vessels in the extremities will constrict and shut the blood to the important organs.</p><p>What phenomena does this explain:</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The feeling of hyperthermia in your extremities.</choice><choice value="B">One reason that frost bite occurs on fingers and nose first.</choice><choice value="C">The occurrence of varicose veins in the legs.</choice><choice value="D">The excessive thirst you feel when you are hot.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i3cb3f7aa2984481f96a3a8df7230a922"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hyperthermia is the result of too much heat. The warm blood would be moved to your important organs and away from your extremities.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Your fingers, toes and nose are most likely to experience frost bite from cold first.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Varicose veins are the result of faulty valves in your legs.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Your thirst does not have anything to do with the blood being shunted to your important organs.</feedback></response><hint>You can live without your fingers. Cellular respiration is an aerobic process and the equation is normally written as C <sub>6</sub> H <sub>12</sub> O <sub>6</sub> + 6O <sub>2</sub> yields 6CO <sub>2</sub> + 6H <sub>2</sub> O + ATP. </hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Explain in your own words why the equation for aerobic cellular metabolism C <sub>6</sub> H <sub>12</sub> O <sub>6</sub> + 6O <sub>2</sub> yields 6CO <sub>2</sub> + 6H <sub>2</sub> O + ATP + heat includes both ATP and heat as a product. </body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="i1723f83e1403446792345d19ae772f42"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>This is because no conversion of energy is ever 100% efficient, so not all of the energy in the glucose becomes ATP. The excess energy is released as the by product of heat. So, the heat generated from aerobic cellular metabolism becomes part of your body&apos;s temperature homeostasis, and can be increased from shivering when your body is trying to make heat to warm up.</explanation></part></question></page><page><question id="q3"><body>How is an astronaut like a person with a bone in a cast?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">They are both putting less stress on their muscles and they may atrophy.</choice><choice value="B">They are both putting more stress on their muscles and they may atrophy.</choice><choice value="C">The atrophy of their muscles is irreversible.</choice><choice value="D">The hypertrophy of these muscles is irreversible.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i2f66f6667212435c84c0da4cfe002943"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Muscles can atrophy because of disuse.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In both of these cases the person is putting less stress on their muscles.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The atrophy of muscles through disuse is usually reversible through exercise.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The muscles in these situations would atrophy not experience hypertrophy.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body>A three time Tour de France winner tested positive for a drug that is considered evidence of blood doping. Blood doping increases the amount of red blood cells in the body. Why would this be an advantage to an athlete?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The increase in red blood cells will increase the amount of time it takes the muscles to recover.</choice><choice value="B">The increase in red blood cells will allow the muscles to undergo aerobic respiration longer.</choice><choice value="C">The increase in red blood cells will allow the muscles to undergo anaerobic respiration longer.</choice><choice value="D">The increase in red blood cells will decrease the amount of ATP produced.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i1a1a46601e524906a27196518b2678c7"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in red blood cells will increase the oxygen which will decrease the recovery time.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. An increase in red blood cells will increase the oxygen which can increase the amount of aerobic respiration.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in red blood cells will increase the oxygen which can increase the amount of aerobic respiration.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in red blood cells will increase the oxygen which can increase the amount of ATP produced.</feedback></response><hint>The function of red blood cells is to carry oxygen.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
