<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_homeostasis_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Why will people die if their body temperature increases too much?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The body will under go spontaneous combustion.</choice><choice value="B">The body’s metabolic reactions are interrupted.</choice><choice value="C">The body will not be able to get enough calcium.</choice><choice value="D">The body’s metabolic reactions will begin to go too fast.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="bee5134d78b84e4ea77b939105056085"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The body will not spontaneously burst into flame.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The body’s metabolic reactions depend on proteins, if they get to hot they will lose their shape.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The amount of calcium in the body is not affected by the heat.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the reactions will speed up with the heat once a certain point is reached the proteins will lose their shape and stop working altogether.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>In older people the ratio of SO fibers to FG fiber increases. This may result in:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">An increase in muscle tension.</choice><choice value="B">More motor units being activated</choice><choice value="C">More powerful movements</choice><choice value="D">Less powerful movements</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i578bb76537b54e6c880e69476cb8dfaa"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In older people there may be less motor units activated which will decrease the muscle tension.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In older people there may be less motor units activated not more.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The decrease in FG movements will decrease the power.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The increase in SO fibers results in less powerful movements.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Endurance training can cause angiogenesis which is an example of how structure and function are related because:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">There is an increase in capillaries to decrease the endurance of the muscles.</choice><choice value="B">There is an increase in capillaries to increase the endurance of the muscles.</choice><choice value="C">There is an increase in muscle fibers to to increase the atrophy of the muscle.</choice><choice value="D">There is an increase in adipose tissue to increase the endurance of the muscle.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i78fae8980adb492fb45a35037b43a756"><skillref idref="_u5_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. By increasing the capillaries, there is an increase of oxygen which increases the endurance of the muscle.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. By increasing the capillaries, there is an increase of oxygen which increases the endurance of the muscle.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Atrophy is a decrease in muscle size.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in adipose tissue will decrease the endurance and strength of the muscle.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
