<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m2_structures_wrapup_openfree">
	<head>
		<title>Urinary Structures and Functions Summary</title>


	</head>

	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Let’s summarize</title>

			<body>
				<p>Nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions in urine
					production:</p>
				<ul>
					<li><em style="bold">glomerular filtration</em> where water and solutes in blood plasma pass through
						the wall of glomerular capillaries and filter into the renal tubules about
						one fifth of the plasma that flows through the kidneys.</li>
					<li><em style="bold">tubular reabsorption</em> where cells of the tubule reabsorb almost all water
						some solutes from the filtrate as it flows through the renal tubule and
						collecting duct. These reabsorbed substances are then returned to the blood
						via the peritubular capillaries and vasa recta.</li>
					<li><em style="bold">tubular secretion</em> where cells in the renal tubule and collecting duct
						secrete waste from the blood as it flows through the tubule and duct.</li>

				</ul>
				<p>Three forces affect the rate of glomerular filtration; one enhances filtration,
					and two resist it. Subtracting the opposing pressures from the promoting
					pressure yields the net filtration pressure.</p>
				<formula>Hydrostatic Pressure – Resistance from fluid in the tubule – Osmotic
					Collodial Pressure = Net Filtration Pressure </formula>
				<p>The <em style="bold">glomerular filtration rate (GFR)</em> is the total amount of filtrate formed by
					the two million renal corpuscles in the kidneys divided by time. </p>
				<ul>
					<li>The average GFR is 125 milliliters (4 ounces) per minute, which adds up to
						nearly 140 liters (50 gallons) a day. </li>
					<li>The kidneys must maintain a relatively consistent GFR to maintain
						homeostatic balance in body fluids. </li>
				</ul>
				<p>Reclaimed fluid that is sent back into the bloodstream to maintain water balance
					and ion concentrations occurs through <em style="bold">reabsorption</em> in the tubules. Reabsorption
					returns about 99 percent of filtered water and many filtered solutes to the
					bloodstream.</p>
				<ul style="none">
					<li>Each day, about 180 liters (190 quarts) of water are filtered in the
						kidneys. Only 1–2 liters (1–2 quarts) are excreted in urine; the rest is
						reabsorbed in the kidneys. </li>
				</ul>
				<p><em style="bold">Reabsorption is</em> performed by cells in the proximal convoluted tubule, epithelial
					cells all along the length of the renal tubule, and the collecting duct.</p>
				<p>The majority of solute and water reabsorption occurs in the proximal convoluted
					tubule and sodium ions participate in most solute reabsorption.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Secretion</em> removes the additional solutes from the plasma and actively transports
					them to the tubule.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Tubular secretion</em> occurs mostly in the proximal convoluted tubule and removes
					unwanted substances from filtrate by transferring unwanted substances from the
					blood and tubule cells into the tubular fluid.</p>
				<p>Tubular secretion is important because:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>It removes substances that are not easily filtered</li>
					<li>It disposes of unwanted substances or end products, such as urea, that have
						been passively reabsorbed.</li>
					<li>It eliminates excess potassium ions.</li>
					<li>It regulates blood pH.</li>
				</ul>

				<p>In the urinary system, <em style="bold">osmosis</em> plays a major role in the regulation of urine
					concentration.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Osmotic activity</em> is the ability of the solution to cause osmosis and depends on
					the amount of solute particles that cannot pass through the semipermeable
					membrane.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Osmolarity</em> is defined as the number of solute particles dissolved in one kilogram
					of water. The osmotic activity of a solution is based on the osmolarity of that
					solution.</p>
				<p>Formation of Dilute and Concentrated Urine:</p>
				<ul style="none">
					<li>Dilute urine is produced when the pituitary gland is not secreting the
						<em style="bold">antidiuretic hormone (ADH)</em> and the diluted filtrate goes to the renal
						pelvis. </li>
					<li>When water conservation is required, the kidneys will produce a small amount
						of concentrated urine to preserve water, while still eliminating wastes and
						surplus ions. ADH inhibits urine production. </li>
				</ul>
				<p><em style="bold">Micturition</em> is the process of urination</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Which begins with blood carrying various wastes enters each of the two
						kidneys through the renal artery. </li>
					<li>From there, afferent impulses are sent to the sacral region of the spinal
						cord when the amount of urine in the bladder reaches about 200 milliliters. </li>
					<li>Once afferent impulses are perceived, a reflexive relaxation of the internal
						urethral sphincter is initiated and contraction of the detrussor muscle
						occurs. </li>
					<li>When more than 500 to 600 milliliters (about 20 ounces) of urine accumulate
						in the bladder, involuntary urination will occur. </li>
					<li>Micturition ends when urine exits out of the body through the urethra. </li>
					<li>After micturition, about 10 milliliters (0.33 ounces) of urine will remain
						in the bladder. </li>
				</ul>

			</body>
		</section>

	<!-- 	<section>

			<title><em style="bold">End Questions</em></title>

			<body>


				<p>Before you do the quiz activity, please evaluate your understanding of the
					learning objectives for the Urinary Structures and Functions and use the first
					My Response link below to ask any questions you might have about the material
					that you would like the instructor to address. Your questions can be for
					clarification of the material or further insight. Your self-evaluation will not
					be graded, but will be available for your instructor to read. Answering these
					questions may also shape the discussions in class. </p> 

				<activity idref="_u12_m2_urinary_structures_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>

					<p> If you do not feel ready for the quia, identify the objectives you need to
					review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t
					just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of
					questions that will be in the quiz.</p>
				

				  <activity idref="u2_m3_checkpoint" purpose="checkpoint"/>

				<p> Now that you have finished the quiz, do you have any questions? Your instructor
					will be able to read the questions and comments that you submit. </p>
				<activity idref="_u12_m2_urinary_structures_feedback_post_quiz" purpose="myresponse"/>



			</body>

</section> -->



	</body>
</workbook_page>
