<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m2_structures_07">
	<head>
		<title>Urine Transport, Storage, and Elimination</title>
		<!--  <objref idref="identify_processes_urinary_filtration"/>-->
		
		<objref idref="describe_urine_transport_collection_elimination"/>
		
		<objref idref="describe_micturition_reflex"/>

	</head>

	<body>

		<section>

			<title>Urine Transport</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the last portion of urine transport and collection
					for elimination.</p>-->
				<p>The difference in hydrostatic pressure between the glomerular capsule (10 mm Hg)
					and the renal pelvis (practically no pressure at all) creates a pressure
					gradient that forces filtrate to flow from the glomerular capsule through the
					tubules and into the renal pelvis. In contrast, no pressure gradient exists to
					propel the flow of urine through the ureters and into the urinary bladder.
					Instead, urine flow at this point is controlled by peristaltic contractions in
					the circular smooth muscle of the ureter walls. These peristaltic waves vary in
					frequency from once every few seconds to once every two to three minutes. Their
					frequency is increased by parasympathetic stimulation and decreased by
					sympathetic stimulation.</p>


			</body>
		</section>

		<example title="kidney_stones">
			<title>Kidney Stones</title>
			<p>Kidney stones are one of the most painful urinary system disorders. Also called
				calculi ("little stones"), kidney stones are not a new disorder. Scientists have
				discovered them in 7,000-year-old Egyptian mummies. Kidney stones are formed when
				the uric acid salts, magnesium, or calcium in urine crystallize. Certain types of
				kidney stones run in families and appear to have a hereditary component. Some
				substances in foods may also contribute to the incidence of kidney stones. Most
				calculi are small enough to pass through the urinary tract and be eliminated with
				urine. Stones larger than five millimeters in diameter, however, can prevent urine
				from draining. The backed-up urine exerts increasing pressure in the kidney, causing
				extreme pain in the back and side near the kidney or in the lower abdomen.
				Dehydration can also contribute to the formation of kidney stones. Each year, about
				2.4 million Americans seek treatment for kidney stones. Kidney stones are more
				common in people with a family history of calculi, or who have urine retention or
				frequent bacterial urinary tract infections. The most commonly used treatment for
				kidney stones is a procedure called extracorporeal shock wave lithotripsy. Shock
				waves created outside the body pass through the skin and body tissues and break down
				the stones into small particles that can be eliminated in the urine. In severe
				cases, endoscopic or open surgery may be required to remove the stones.</p>
		</example>
		<wb:inline idref="urinary_urine_flow_control" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<section>
			<title>Urine Storage</title>
			<body>
				<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Relate the anatomy and histology of the bladder to its
					function.</p>-->
				<p>Much more time is spent storing urine than micturating (urinating). When urine
					accumulates in the bladder, distension of the bladder walls activate stretch
					receptors. These receptors transmit signals through visceral afferent fibers to
					the sacral area of the spinal cord. The signals initiate spinal <term>storage
						reflexes</term>, which enhance sympathetic inhibition of the bladder's
					detrusor muscle and maintain the internal sphincter in a closed position. The
					reflexes also stimulate pudendal motor fibers, which cause the external urethral
					sphincter to contract, preventing the urine from escaping.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="urinary_urine_storage" purpose="didigetthis"/>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Urine Elimination</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the micturition reflex. Describe voluntary and
					involuntary neural control of micturition.</p>-->
				<p>As previously noted, micturition (also called urination or voiding) is the
					process of emptying urine from the bladder and is the result of involuntary and
					voluntary muscle contractions. When the amount of urine accumulated in the
					bladder reaches about 200 milliliters (7 ounces) (though this amount varies from
					person to person), afferent impulses are sent to the sacral region of the spinal
					cord that initiate a reflexive relaxation of the internal urethral sphincter and
					contraction of the detrussor muscle. The afferent signals that stimulate the
					urge to urinate are also sent to the brain. This allows the person to relax
					their external uretheral sphincter, made of skeletal muscle, so that micturition
					will occur. If we do not void immediately, the reflexive responses will
					initially weaken, but as more volume is added to the bladder, these responses
					will come back more strongly, creating a more urgent need to void.</p>
				<p>When we are ready to empty the bladder—a decision executed by the cerebral
					cortex—the <term>micturition reflex </term>is set in motion. Afferent impulses
					activate the <term>micturition center </term>of the brain. This signal
					intregrates with parasympathetic signals of the spinal cord to allow the
					external sphincter to relax, thus releasing urine from the bladder.</p>
				<p>If we need to delay micturiition, the reflex bladder contractions will taper off
					and stop within about one minute, and urine will continue accumulating. The
					addition of another 200 to 300 milliliters (7 to 10 ounces) of urine will prompt
					another micturition reflex. If voiding is still not possible, the reflexes will
					again subside. When more than 500 to 600 milliliters (about 20 ounces) of urine
					accumulates, urination will occur whether we want to or not. After micturition,
					about 10 milliliters (0.33 ounces) of urine will remain in the bladder.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<!--  <section>
			<title>Micturition</title>
			<body>
				 <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Define micturition</p>
				<p>Micturition (also called urination or voiding) is the process of emptying urine
					from the bladder. Micturition is the result of a combination of both involuntary
					and voluntary muscle contractions.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="urinary_define_micturition" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>-->

		<wb:inline idref="urinary_define_micturition" purpose="didigetthis"/>


	</body>

</workbook_page>
