<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u12_m2_structures_wrapup"><head><title>Urinary Structures and Functions Review and Assessment</title></head><body><section id="a756678e1df145fb8f1b18738924eae9"><title>Let’s summarize</title><body><p id="c1d6776751f34c8ba720de3e4f8972f6">Nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions in urine production:</p><ul id="a333a810b6134650a64ac5cde4d24c05"><li><p id="be57a20ccf724b7d91a75392fdf0a17d"><em style="bold">glomerular filtration</em> where water and solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of glomerular capillaries and filter into the renal tubules.</p></li><li><p id="d1cc0ed44caa406caf0f213585836805"><em style="bold">tubular reabsorption</em> where cells of the tubule reabsorb almost all water and some solutes from the filtrate as it flows through the renal tubule and collecting duct. These reabsorbed substances are then returned to the blood via the peritubular capillaries and vasa recta.</p></li><li><p id="bb1950de716146beb91cdb5ebaef484e"><em style="bold">tubular secretion</em> where cells in the renal tubule and collecting duct secrete waste from the blood as it flows through the tubule and duct.</p></li></ul><p id="f5dbf77bc40e46b398bc78b98c874d28">Three forces affect the rate of glomerular filtration; one enhances filtration, and two resist it. Subtracting the opposing pressures from the promoting pressure yields the net filtration pressure.</p><formula>Hydrostatic Pressure – Resistance from fluid in the tubule – Osmotic Collodial Pressure = Net Filtration Pressure </formula><p id="cf698226acca4da397702c61c59dbc72">The <em style="bold">glomerular filtration rate (GFR)</em> is the total amount of filtrate formed by the two million renal corpuscles in the kidneys divided by time. </p><ul id="a41bbfd2b2334b8593df0cc8c7aee10e"><li><p id="aa74cba2ad38f4c9a9c62a1bada8264d6">The average GFR is 125 milliliters (4 ounces) per minute, which adds up to nearly 140 liters (50 gallons) a day. </p></li><li><p id="ab0d8ede09428457b8d80801493210b77">The kidneys must maintain a relatively consistent GFR to maintain homeostatic balance in body fluids. </p></li></ul><p id="aeb68e96c0ca4ad0ae540aff5833c083">Reclaimed fluid that is sent back into the bloodstream to maintain water balance and ion concentrations occurs through <em style="bold">reabsorption</em> in the tubules. Reabsorption returns about 99 percent of filtered water and many filtered solutes to the bloodstream.</p><ul id="a5398b44485446f4b0e4c5524cad62a1" style="none"><li><p id="ae90ec4ae024d4a27b52fc4d96698513e">Each day, about 180 liters (190 quarts) of water are filtered in the kidneys. Only 1–2 liters (1–2 quarts) are excreted in urine; the rest is reabsorbed in the kidneys. </p></li></ul><p id="a30d60ee90a648fb89eaf9e6f6400560"><em style="bold">Reabsorption is</em> performed by cells in the proximal convoluted tubule, epithelial cells all along the length of the renal tubule, and the collecting duct.</p><p id="fd8603545d2941dca8253ad0e49edd88">The majority of solute and water reabsorption occurs in the proximal convoluted tubule and sodium ions participate in most solute reabsorption.</p><p id="a5608a2285d0407f862950591f1e0f9c"><em style="bold">Secretion</em> removes the additional solutes from the plasma and actively transports them to the tubule.</p><p id="fcfac12f2ef24288a1a1696b939961b0"><em style="bold">Tubular secretion</em> occurs mostly in the proximal convoluted tubule and removes unwanted substances from filtrate by transferring unwanted substances from the blood and tubule cells into the tubular filtrate.</p><p id="ad4f06368d8b42299ca24b942a97dd04">Tubular secretion is important because:</p><ul id="d72fc8a7dcc64ebebddfd45885f7043e"><li><p id="adfa25d45f68c4dcf9c7675d08527e1eb">It removes substances that are not easily filtered</p></li><li><p id="acfa2ba13d33c4d24a24a2e1a19494b46">It disposes of unwanted substances or end products, such as urea, that have been passively reabsorbed.</p></li><li><p id="ae302797514d84205975af5c38e5cd082">It eliminates excess potassium ions.</p></li><li><p id="ace86ad994ac74cd4ab7832ff3406e816">It regulates blood pH.</p></li></ul><p id="e5bb07f8835f490ea32133feb1ae15ef">In the urinary system, <em style="bold">osmosis</em> plays a major role in the regulation of urine concentration.</p><p id="dcda2cee5db743b896b7be293f833fb1"><em style="bold">Osmotic activity</em> is the ability of the solution to cause osmosis and depends on the amount of solute particles that cannot pass through the semipermeable membrane.</p><p id="c0434c3fdbd64709a96d3c1ca4c00172"><em style="bold">Osmolarity</em> is defined as the number of solute particles dissolved in one kilogram of water. The osmotic activity of a solution is based on the osmolarity of that solution.</p><p id="ff804c88453540fa9fb1d157f4c9cccd">Formation of Dilute and Concentrated Urine:</p><ul id="fb2ef56d869e4f8bac23d4e341f9ac62" style="none"><li><p id="fb756ff912cd49ce96f27ec744d2c0fb">Dilute urine is produced when the hypothalamus (via the posterior pituitary gland) is not secreting the <em style="bold">antidiuretic hormone (ADH)</em> and the diluted filtrate goes to the renal pelvis. </p></li><li><p id="abe133a8681d24bcc956114930c32c292">When water conservation is required, the kidneys will produce a small amount of concentrated urine to conserve water, while still eliminating wastes and surplus ions. ADH promotes production of concentrated urine. </p></li></ul><p id="ddbe7aceb0f240bf8f5a91b71accfba2"><em style="bold">Micturition</em> is the process of urination</p><ul id="cee1455d429f424d82302758f5f948c2"><li><p id="ab9f13a29b4714edd8fce59b54438f635">Urine accumulates and is stored in the urinary bladder.</p></li><li><p id="ac331de4d0e3a416ab4fd1286f3073900">When the amount of urine in the bladder reaches about 200 milliliters, afferent impulses are sent to the sacral region of the spinal cord.</p></li><li><p id="ab3d60146f5d24f50af02c04808effef9">Once afferent impulses are perceived, a reflexive relaxation of the internal urethral sphincter is initiated and contraction of the detrussor muscle occurs. </p></li><li><p id="abb6217db41d74a0988793ad7fe69ea33">When more than 500 to 600 milliliters (about 20 ounces) of urine accumulate in the bladder, involuntary urination will occur. </p></li><li><p id="acfb5150b402a462c9736a501bcebbe5f">Micturition ends when urine exits out of the body through the urethra. </p></li><li><p id="ac2bbae9c106544aba2362c9c2c0a9347">After micturition, about 10 milliliters (0.33 ounces) of urine will remain in the bladder. </p></li></ul></body></section><section id="df461daef5f74486a049d21fcf14b83d"><title> </title><body><p id="a75f617eebb04f95a35efc469fbe4a3d">If you do not feel ready for the quiz, identify the objectives you need to review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of questions that will be in the quiz.</p><activity idref="urinary_structures_functions_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
