<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m2_structures_01">
	<head>
		<title>Urinary Tract Anatomy</title>
		
		<objref idref="identify_describe_gross_micro_anatomy_urinary_track_hist_nephron"/>
	</head>
	<body>


		<section>
			<title>Introduction to the Urinary Tract Anatomy</title>
			<body>
				<p>As noted above, much of the maintenance of proper chemical balance, or
					homeostasis, is the function of the kidneys, which are located towards
					the lower back. The process begins with waste carrying blood entering
					each of the two kidneys through the renal artery. Urine is produced by
					the nephrons in the kidneys. Once filtered, the blood exits through the
					renal vein. Urine leaves each kidney through a ureter. Each ureter
					transports the urine via peristalsis to the urinary bladder (a hollow,
					muscular chamber that collects and stores urine). A single urethra
					transports the urine from the urinary bladder to the outside of the
					body. This process through the smooth muscles is otherwise known as:
					peristalsis. An internal urethral sphincter muscle and an external
					urethral sphincter muscle help keep the urine in the bladder until the
					process of urination. The internal urethral sphincter muscle, surrounds
					the neck of the urinary bladder at the juncture of the bladder with the
					urethra. It opens reflexively when the bladder muscle contracts and
					builds up pressure. The external urethral sphincter muscle is part of
					the urogenital diaphragm and is located at the external opening of the
					urethra. It is under voluntary control, and as a result of the voluntary
					control, urination can be delayed for a time. Micturition is the entire
					process of urination. </p>
				
				<section purpose="didigetthis">
					<title>Urinary Anatomy</title>
					<body>
						
						
						
						<image src="../webcontent/urinary_internal_anatomy.jpg" height="400"
							width="300" alt="internal urinary anatomy">
							<caption>By Jordi March (<link
								href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Monoplace_chamber.JPG"
								>Urinary Systems</link>) <link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"
									target="new">CC-BY-3.0</link>
							</caption>
						</image>
						
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_internal_anatomy" purpose="didigetthis"
							src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
							<param name="interfaceDescription"
								>../webcontent/urinary_internal_anatomy_layout.xml</param>
						</wb:inline>
						
					</body>
				</section>
				
				
				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_urine_produced" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_peristalsis" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_process_urination" purpose="learnbydoing"
						/>
					</body>
				</section>
				
				
				
			</body>
		</section>
		
		
		 <p>The process of urination is known as <term>micturition</term> which
		 	begins with blood carrying various wastes that enter each of the two kidneys
					through the renal artery and ends when urine exits out of the body through the
					urethra.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>

