<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m2_structures_02">
	<head>
		<title>Filtration, Reabsorption, and Secretion</title>

		  <objref idref="identify_processes_urinary_filtration"/>
		<!--  <objref idref="list_transport_mechanisms_nephron_osmosis"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>


		<p> To produce urine, nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions:
			glomerular filtration, tubular reabsorption, and tubular secretion. </p>
		<p>The first step in urine production is <term>glomerular filtration</term>. In this
			process, water and most of the solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of
			glomerular capillaries, first into the glomerular capsule and then into the renal
			tubule. The product of glomerular filtration is referred to as glomerular filtrate.</p>
		<p>During tubular <term>reabsorption</term>, cells of the tubule reabsorb almost all water
			and a variety of solutes from the filtrate as it flows through the renal tubule and
			collecting duct. These reabsorbed substances are then returned to the blood in the
			peritubular capillaries and vasa recta. In contrast to absorption, in which new
			substances enter the body (e.g., through the gastrointestinal tract), reabsorption
			refers to substances that have been removed from the blood being returned to the
			blood.</p>
		<p>In the process of <term>tubular secretion</term>, renal tubule and collecting duct actively transport
			substances (e.g., wastes, drugs, excess ions) from the blood in the peritubular
			capillaries. Secretion, in this case, refers to the removal of substances from the
			blood. In contrast, the secretion of hormones or enzymes, for example, refers to cells
			releasing substances into blood, ducts, and interstitial fluid.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="urinary_urine_formation" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<p>The normal amount of filtrate produced as a result of glomerular filtration is so high
			that the amount of fluid entering the proximal convoluted tubules in 30 minutes is
			greater than the total blood plasma volume. Clearly, some of this fluid must be
			reclaimed and sent back into the bloodstream to maintain water balance and ion
			concentrations. This reclamation process occurs through reabsorption in the tubules.
			Secretion is essentially the opposite of reabsorption. It removes the additional solutes
			from the plasma and actively transports them to the tubule. Many students get confused
			initially with this concept that secretion means end up in the urine and reabsorption
			means ends up back in the blood.</p>


		<!--  <image src="../webcontent/u_m1_16.jpg" height="300" width="350"
					alt="excretion= filtration, reabsorption and secretion"/>-->

		<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_16.jpg" width="450"
			alt="excretion= filtration, reabsorption and secretion">
			<caption>Reabsorption and Secretion. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>


		<wb:inline idref="urinary_reabsorption_secretion" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
