<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m2_structures_03">
	<head>
		<title>Urinary Filtration</title>

		<!--  	<objref idref="identify_processes_urinary_filtration"/>-->
		<objref idref="describe_gfr_state_average_gfr"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<section>
			<title>Glomerular Filtration</title>
			<body>

				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Identify the distinct processes of the urinary system –
					filtration, reabsorption and secretion – and the urinary structures that are
					responsible for each</p>
		<p>To produce urine, nephrons and collecting ducts carry out three basic functions:
			glomerular filtration, tubular reabsorption, and tubular secretion. This follows
			from the structural section of the nephron.
			</p>
		<p>The first step in urine production is <term>glomerular filtration</term>. In this
			process, water and most of the solutes in blood plasma pass through the wall of
			glomerular capillaries, first into the glomerular capsule and then into the
			renal tubule.</p>
		<p>During tubular <term>reabsorption</term>, cells of the tubule reabsorb almost all
			water and a variety of solutes from the filtrate as it flows through the renal
			tubule and collecting duct. These reabsorbed substances are then returned to the
			blood as it travels along the peritubular capillaries and vasa recta. In
			contrast to absorption, in which new substances enter the body (e.g., through
			the gastrointestinal tract), reabsorption refers to returning substances to the
			bloodstream.</p>
		<p>In the process of tubular <term>secretion</term>, cells in the renal tubule and
			collecting duct secrete substances (e.g., wastes, drugs, excess ions) from the
			filtrate as it flows through the tubule and duct. Secretion in this case refers
			to the removal of substances from the blood. In contrast, the secretion of
			hormones, for example, refers to cells releasing substances into blood and
			interstitial fluid.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="urinary_urine_formation" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->


				<section>
					<title>High Pressure Bulk Filtration</title>
					<body>
						<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Explain the anatomical features that create high glomerular
					capillary blood pressure and explain why this blood pressure is significant for
					urine formation.</p>-->
						<p>The glomerular capillaries filter about one fifth of the plasma that
							flows through the kidneys into the renal tubules. Glomerular filtration
							works like any other filtration process. For example, a coffee filter
							prevents large coffee grounds from passing through it, while allowing
							the passage of water and small solutes such as flavor molecules and
							caffeine. In the same way, the glomerular filtration membrane blocks the
							passage of blood cells and proteins, while allowing water and other
							solutes from the blood to pass into the glomerular capsule. These
							substances are forced through the membrane by the higher hydrostatic
							pressure in the glomerular capillary than in the capsular space.</p>
						<p>The glomerulus has the highest rate of filtration of any capillary bed in
							the body for a number of reasons. First, its filtration membrane has a
							very large surface area. In addition, the large
								<term>fenestrations</term> (capillary pores) in glomerular
							capillaries make them at least 50 times more permeable to water and
							solutes than other capillary beds. Finally, the blood pressure
							(hydrostatic pressure) in glomerular capillaries is about three times
							higher than in other capillary beds (around 55 mm Hg versus 18 mm Hg or
							less). This increased blood pressure is due to the relatively small
							pressure drop across the <term>afferent arteriole</term> leading into
							the glomerular capillary and the large pressure drop across the
								<term>efferent arteriole</term>, which leads out of the glomerular
							capillary. Looking at filtrate production, the combined daily output of
							all other capillary beds in the body is about three to four liters
							(three to four quarts). In the kidneys, the daily output is 150 liters
							(158 quarts) in women and 180 liters (190 quarts) in men. Tubular
							reabsorption returns more than 99 percent of the glomerular filtrate
							(the fluid than enters the capsular space) to the bloodstream. This
							means than just one to two liters are eliminated in urine. The
								<term>filtration fraction </term>describes the portion of blood
							plasma in the afferent arterioles that ends up as glomerular filtrate. A
							typical filtration fraction ranges from 16 to 20 percent.</p>
					</body>
				</section>



				<wb:inline idref="urinary_glomerular_filtration" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<section>
					<title>The Filtration Membrane</title>
					<body>
						<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the anatomy of the glomerular filtration membrane
					and describe how the structure contributes to its function.</p>-->
						<p>The porous <term>filtration membrane </term>separates the inside of the
							glomerular capsule from the blood. Water and solutes smaller than about
							three nanometers in diameter (e.g., glucose, amino acids, nitrogenous
							wastes) pass freely across the membrane between the blood and capsule.
							This means there are similar concentrations of these substances in both
							the blood and the glomerular filtrate. Some bigger molecules may find a
							way through the membrane, but molecules larger than five nanometers
							(large proteins and blood cells) do not usually get into the tubule.</p>
						<p>The filtration membrane, three layers serve as barriers to larger
							molecules circulating in the blood. From most permissive to most
							restrictive, these layers are the glomerular capillary endothelium, the
							gel-like basal lamina basement membrane, and the podocyte-formed
							filtration slit. All plasma components (note plasma does not include
							blood cells) can pass through the fenestrations in the endothelium, but
							blood cells cannot. The smallest proteins and most other solutes can
							penetrate the basement membrane. This membrane is composed primarily of
							negatively charged glycoproteins that oppose other macromolecular anions
							and obstruct their entry into the tubule. In other words, the basement
							provides electrical selectivity to the filtration process. Most plasma
							proteins are too large to meet the size restrictions. Moreover, because
							most plasma proteins have a net negative charge, they are repelled by
							the negatively charged glycoproteins of the basement membrane. Any
							macromolecules that do manage to pass through the basement membrane face
							yet another barrier, thin membranes called slit diaphragms that span the
							filtration slits. Specialized cells in the glomerulus, known as
							mesangial cells, will destroy macromolecules that are trapped in the
							filtration membrane. Mesangial cells can also contract and alter the
							capillary surface area available for filtration.</p>
					</body>
				</section>


				<section purpose="didigetthis">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_filtration_membrane" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						<wb:inline idref="urinary_filtration_membrane_1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Net Filtration Pressure</title>
					<body>


						<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Identify the opposing driving pressures of glomerular
					filtration including hydrostatic and osmotic pressures.</p>-->
						<p>Three forces affect glomerular filtration rate (volume filtered per unit
							time); hydrostatic pressure of the blood in the glomerulus, hydrostatic
							pressure of the fluid in the capsular space, and colloid osmotic force
							of the blood in the glomerulus. Hydrostatic pressure within the
							glomerular capillaries promotes or enhances filtration. The other two
							forces oppose filtration and are: back pressure from hydrostatic
							pressure of the fluid within the capsule and colloid osmotic pressure
							caused by the plasma proteins within the glomerular capillaries.
							Subtracting the opposing pressures from the promoting pressure yields
							the <term>net filtration pressure</term>.</p>
						<p>Hydrostatic Pressure – Resistance from fluid in the tubule – Osmotic
							Collodial Pressure = Net Filtration Pressure</p>
						<p><em style="bold">Net Filtration Pressure</em></p>
						<table rowstyle="alternating">
							<tr>
								<td><em style="bold">Pressure</em></td>
								<td><em style="bold">Description</em></td>
								<td><em style="bold">Average</em></td>
								<td><em style="bold">Effect</em></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Glomerular hydrostatic</td>
								<td>Glomerular capillary blood pressure</td>
								<td>55 mm Hg</td>
								<td>Promotes filtration</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Capsular hydrostatic</td>
								<td>Hydrostatic pressure applied to the filtration membrane by fluid
									in the capsular space and renal tubule</td>
								<td>15 mmHg</td>
								<td>Opposes filtration</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Blood colloid osmotic</td>
								<td>Results from proteins present in blood plasma</td>
								<td>30 mmHg</td>
								<td>Opposes filtration</td>
							</tr>
						</table>
						<p>The <term>glomerular hydrostatic pressure</term> (i.e., the blood
							pressure in glomerular capillaries) is the primary force responsible for
							pushing water and solutes from blood across the filtration membrane.
							This unusually high pressure (55 mm Hg) is opposed by two forces that
							resist the influx of fluids: the <term>capsular hydrostatic pressure
							</term>exerted by fluid already in the glomerular capsule and the
								<term>blood colloid osmotic pressure </term>caused by proteins
							present in blood plasma (e.g., albumen, fibrinogen). Net filtration
							pressure averages 10 mm Hg (i.e., 55 mmHg −15 mmHg − 30 mmHg = 10 mmHg).
							This is in contrast to the 0.3 mmHg net pressure found in most
							capillaries of the body.</p>


						<!-- 	<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_15.jpg" height="300" width="350" alt="glomerular filtration process"/> -->

						<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_15.jpg" width="450"
							alt="glomerular filtration process">
							<caption>Glomerular filtration process. This work by Cenveo is licensed
								under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
									>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
						</image>


						<!-- <p><em style="bold">C. Glomerular Filtration Rate</em></p>-->
						<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe glomerular filtration rate (GFR), state the average
					value of GFR, and explain how clearance rate can be used to measure GFR</p>-->
						<p>The <term>glomerular filtration rate (GFR) </term>is the total amount of
							filtrate formed by the two million renal corpuscles in the kidneys
							divided by time. The average GFR is 125 milliliters (4 ounces) per
							minute, which adds up to nearly 140 liters (50 gallons) a day. The
							kidneys must maintain a relatively consistent GFR to prevent homeostatic
							imbalances in body fluids. If the GFR is too high, needed substances
							will rush through the renal tubules too quickly to be completely
							absorbed, and they will be lost in urine. A GFR that is too low will
							allow waste products to accumulate in the plasma, ultimately leading to
							illness and death if not corrected.</p>
					</body>
				</section>

				<wb:inline idref="urinary_glomerular_filtration_pressure" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="urinary_high_gfr" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
