<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m2_structures_06">
	<head>
		<title>Urine Formation</title>
		<!--  <objref idref="identify_processes_urinary_filtration"/>-->
		<objref idref="state_countercurrent_multiplication_relates_urine_formation"/>
		
	</head>

	<body>

		<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Compare and contrast blood plasma, glomerular filtrate, and
					urine and then relate their differences to function of the nephron.</p>-->
		<p>The process of osmosis plays a major role in the regulation of urine concentration.
			Recall that osmosis refers to the flow of a liquid across a semipermeable membrane to
			equalize the solute concentration on both sides of the membrane. The ability of the
			solution to cause osmosis, its osmotic activity, depends on the amount and not the type
			of solute particles that cannot pass through the semipermeable membrane. For example, in
			the same volume of water, the osmotic activity of 10 sodium ions is the same as that of
			10 glucose molecules, and the same as 10 proteins, and so on. Thus, the osmotic activity
			of a solution is based on the <term>osmolarity </term>of that solution, a quality
			defined as the number of solute particles dissolved in one kilogram of water. Osmotic
			activity is frequently measured in units of 0.001 mole of particles, a millismol (mOsm).
			Osmolarity is measured in mOsm/liter.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="urinary_osmosis" purpose="learnbydoing"
			src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
			<param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/urinary_osmosis_layout.xml</param>
		</wb:inline>
		<section>
			<title>Formation of Dilute Urine</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Predict specific factors involved in creating dilute versus
					concentrated urine.</p>-->
				<p>The ratio of water and solutes in glomerular filtrate is the same as that in
					blood, with an osmolarity of around 300 mOsm/liter (one mOsm is translated as a
					milli osmole or one thousandth of an osmole). The osmolarity of the filtrate
					that enters the proximal convoluted tubule is still the same. And when filtrate
					enters the nephron loop's descending limb, its osmolarity is the same as both
					blood plasma and cortical interstitial fluid. Because tubular fluid is already
					dilute as it flows through the ascending limb of Henle's loop, the formation of
					dilute urine is a relatively simple process. When the hypothalamus (via the
					posterior pituitary gland) is not secreting ADH, additional water is not
					reabsorbed in the collecting ducts and dilute urine is produced. Before urine
					enters the renal pelvis, it is further diluted by the removal of ions, including
					sodium ions, in the distal convoluted tubule and collecting duct. As a result,
					the osmolarity of urine can be reduced to nearly one fourth of that in the
					glomerular filtrate or plasma, dropping to as low as 70 mOsm.</p>

				<wb:inline idref="urinary_osmolarity" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		

		<section>
			<title>Formation of Concentrated Urine</title>
			<body>
				<p>If a person does not drink enough water, sweats a lot, or has diarrhea, water
					conservation is required. In such cases, the kidneys will produce a small amount
					of concentrated urine to preserve water, while still eliminating wastes and
					surplus ions. Antidiuretic hormone (ADH), as its name suggests, inhibits
					diuresis (urine production). ADH helps the kidneys generate urine that is up to
					four times as concentrated as glomerular filtrate or blood plasma (up to 1,200
					mOsm/liter for urine versus 300 mOsm/liter for glomerular filtrate). ADH can do
					this only when there is an osmotic gradient of solutes in the renal medulla's
					interstitial fluid, in other words, when the solute concentration in the
					interstitial fluid is higher than that in the tubular fluid. This osmotic
					gradient, coupled with the insertion of aquaporins into the luminal membrane of
					the collecting ducts' principal cells, causes water and urea to pass from the
					filtrate into the interstitial space to equalize osmolarity. At maximum ADH
					secretion, as much as 99 percent of the water in the tubular filtrate is
					reabsorbed, and the kidneys produce about half a liter of highly concentrated
					urine per day. The production of concentrated urine is key to our ability to
					survive for an extended period of time without water.</p>
				<p>The osmotic gradient needed to produce concentrated urine depends on two chief
					factors. First, individual areas of the nephron loop differ in permeability and
					reabsorption characteristics. Second, fluid flows in opposite directions through
					adjacent tubes in different parts of the urinary system. This process is called
						<term>countercurrent flow </term>of fluid. It occurs down and up the
					descending and ascending limbs of the nephron loop. Blood flowing along the
					ascending and descending portions of the vasa recta also follows countercurrent
					flow. Two countercurrent mechanisms operate in the kidneys: countercurrent
					multiplication and countercurrent exchange.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<image src="../webcontent/hypertonic_urine1.png" height="350" width="350" alt="hypertonic urine">
			<caption>By Yosi I(<link
				href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Monoplace_chamber.JPG"
				>Hypertonic Urine 1</link>) <link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" target="new"
					>CC-BY-3.0</link>
			</caption>
		</image>
		<!--  <image src="../webcontent/u_m1_4.jpg" height="400" width="400" alt="collecting ducts">
			<caption>Collecting ducts. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons
				Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->
		<wb:inline idref="urinary_countercurrent_flow" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<wb:inline idref="urinary_antidiuretic_hormone" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section>
			<title>Countercurrent Exchange</title>
			<body>
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Define countercurrent exchange and describe how this relates
					to urine formation</p>-->
				<p>In <term>countercurrent exchange</term>, countercurrent flow enables the passive
					exchange of water and solutes between blood in the vasa recta and the medullary
					interstitial fluid. The osmolarity of blood entering the vasa recta is around
					300 mOsm/liter. In its descending limb, urea and sodium and chloride ions
					diffuse from the increasingly concentrated medullary interstitial fluid into the
					blood, while water diffuses from the blood into the interstitial fluid. Along
					the ascending limb of the vasa recta, the concentration of the interstitial
					fluid steadily decreases. At this point, urea and sodium and chloride ions
					diffuse from the blood back into the interstitial fluid, and water diffuses in
					the opposite direction. Because the osmolarity of blood leaving the vasa recta
					is only a little higher than that of blood leaving it, it can provide oxygen and
					nutrients to the renal medulla without washing out the osmotic gradient. To
					summarize, the osmotic gradient in the renal medulla is created by
					countercurrent multiplication in the nephron loop, and it is maintained by
					countercurrent exchange in the vasa recta.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<image src="../webcontent/hypertonic_urine2.png" height="350" width="350" alt="hypertonic urine">
			<caption>By Yosi I(<link
				href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Monoplace_chamber.JPG"
				>Hypertonic Urine 2</link>) <link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" target="new"
					>CC-BY-3.0</link>
			</caption>
		</image>
		

		<section>
			<title>Countercurrent Multiplication</title>
			<body>
				<!-- 	<p><em style="bold">[Jan -</em>think this section needs to be in with the Loop of
					Henle section above]</p>-->
				<!-- <p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Define countercurrent multiplication and describe how this
					relates to urine formation</p>-->
				<p>The nephron loop is responsible for the <term>countercurrent multiplication
					</term>mechanism that establishes an osmotic gradient within the medullary
					interstitium. This gradient is necessary for the collecting duct to create an
					osmotic gradient. </p>

				<p>Three factors are involved in countercurrent multiplication. First, recall that
					the ascending limb is responsible for the active transport of sodium, chloride
					and potassium out of the tubular fluid and into the interstitium. Because this
					limb is relatively water impermeable, the solutes move into the interstitial
					fluid without additional water, increasing the osmotic pressure of the
					interstitium.</p>


				<p>Second, the descending limb, which is in very close proximity to the ascending
					limb, is solute-impermeable and water-permeable. Because the ascending and
					descending limb share the same interstitial fluid, water moves along the osmotic
					gradient from the descending limb into the interstium, concentrating the tubular
					filtrate in the descending limb. Thus, the osmolarity of the medullary
					interstitial fluid along this limb steadily increases, and water leaves the
					filtrate. The osmolarity of the filtrate is highest (1,200 mOsm) where the
					nephron loop bends, and the filtrate moves from the descending limb to the
					ascending limb.</p>

				<p>The third factor in the countercurrent multiplication is the shift of the fluid
					along the length of the tubule so that fluid that participated in water loss in
					the descending limb, will now participate in solute loss in the ascending limb.
					When the filtrate in the descending limb turns the corner and enters the
					ascending limb, the concentrations of sodium and chloride ions are very high in
					the filtrate The molecules are now actively pumped from the tubule into the
					interstitial fluid to maintain the high osmotic pressure in the interstitium. It
					turns out that this system “traps” high salt concentrations deep in the medulla
					as the ions are most actively pumped out there.</p>
				<p>Losing salt but not water makes the filtrate in the ascending limb increasingly
					more dilute. By the time it reaches the distal tubule, it is at 100 mOsm and
					therefore has a lower osmotic pressure than the blood plasma and interstitial
					fluids in the renal cortex. This is what allows for the generation of a dilute
					urine.</p>
				<p>Another contributor to the high osmolarity of the the medullary interstitium is
					the recycling of urea. Urea from the interstitial fluid diffuses into the
					filtrate in the thin limbs of the nephron loop. Because the thick limb and
					collecting duct are urea-impermeable, by the time the filtrate reaches the
					collecting duct, water reabsorption has created highly concentrated urea that
					diffuses back into the medullary interstitial fluid. The resulting pool of
					urea is a major contributor to the high osmolarity in this region. This urea is
					then recycled back into the thin limbs of the loop, and the cycle starts again.
					The presence of ADH amplifies urea recycling, which, in turn, amplifies the
					osmotic gradient and enables the formation of more concentrated urine.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="urinary_countercurrent_mult_1" purpose="didigetthis"/>


		<wb:inline idref="urinary_countercurrent_mult" purpose="didigetthis"/>






	</body>

</workbook_page>
