<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.1//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="_u01_m01_metacog_LBD_2a_inline">
    <title>Sonya's Learning Strategy</title>
    <page>
        <content>
            <p>Sonya just got to the Information Literacy unit of her C@CM course. Thinking back to
                all the research papers she wrote in high school, she feels confident that she knows
                the material in the unit. Finding, evaluating, and citing sources? No problem. She
                completes the “assess yourself” portion of the pre-assessment, giving herself a high
                rating in all these areas. But when she takes the "assess your performance"
                quiz, she doesn’t do well. “Still,” she concludes, “I know this stuff.” So she skips
                the explanatory content, activities, and exam-readiness quiz, and is confident that she’ll do fine on
                the final exam.</p>
        </content>
        <question id="_u01_m01_metacog_LBD_2a_1">
            <body>Is the strategy Sonya plans to pursue a good one?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" id="ans">
                <choice value="yes">Yes. Why should she waste time going over material she already
                    knows?</choice>
                <choice value="no">No. She thinks she knows the material, but the pre-test shows she
                    may not.</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="yes" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Sonya’s performance indicates that she doesn’t know the
                        material as well as she believes. She is probably not ready to skip ahead to
                        the final exam.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="no" score="1">
                    <feedback>We agree. Sonya is better off trusting the results of the performance
                        assessment and rethinking her self-assessment. </feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>There is a mismatch between how well Sonya believes she knows this material
                    (very well) and how she actually performs when answering questions on the
                    material (not well). Think about whether Sonya’s self-evaluation or her
                    performance is a more accurate measure of her ability.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>

    </page>
</assessment>
