<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.1//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>

<assessment id="_u01_m01_metacog_LBD_2b_inline">
    <title>Joe's Learning Strategy</title>
    <page>
        <content>
            <p>Joe has just started the Safe Computing unit in C@CM. He wants to get through it as
                quickly as possible while still making sure he is prepared for the proctored exam in
                two weeks. He sees a bunch of text with some activities sprinkled throughout and is
                trying to decide how to proceed. </p>
        </content>
        <question id="_u01_m01_metacog_LBD_2b_1">
            <body>Which of the following strategies would likely be most effective and efficient for
                Joe? (Note: More than one strategy may be effective and efficient).</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="false" id="ans">
                <choice value="A">Jump straight to the activities without reading the text. For each
                    activity, select different answer choices to see if they’re right or wrong and
                    read the feedback text that comes up.</choice>
                <choice value="B">Jump straight to the first activity and if he cannot answer it, go
                    back to the beginning of the unit to read the text.</choice>
                <choice value="C">Jump straight to the activities and after realizing that he has no
                    idea how to answer the first few, quit out of the course and plan to attend his C@CM
                    support meeting that week.</choice>
                <choice value="D">Read the unit straight through from the beginning and do the
                    activities as they come up.</choice>
                <choice value="E">Read the unit straight through from the beginning but skip the
                    activities.</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Learning by doing can be a good idea. However, Joe should
                        keep in mind that the feedback for correct and incorrect answers is not as
                        complete as the preceding text, so he might be missing important
                        information. </feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="1">
                    <feedback>Correct. The good thing about this strategy is that Joe uses the
                        activities as a way to assess his own capabilities and then adjusts his
                        approach accordingly. Moreover, by deciding to go back to read the preceding
                        text, Joe is giving himself a chance to practice independent
                        learning.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. This approach is unlikely to be effective, since Joe will
                        not know what questions to ask at the support meeting. It is also not
                        efficient, since going to a support meeting will take more time than simply
                        reading the explanatory content. By seeking help before trying to learn the
                        material himself, Joe misses the chance to practice learning
                        independently.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="1">
                    <feedback>Correct. This is a good approach unless Joe already knows the unit
                        material fairly well, in which case it is inefficient. The pre-assessments
                        could help him recognize whether he needs to work through the text
                        systematically, focus on specific skills, or skip to the next
                        unit.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Although reading the text will provide Joe with the
                        information content of this module, by skipping the activities he misses the
                        chance to practice using this information and check his
                        understanding.</feedback>
                </response>

                <hint>Think about which of these different strategies will be most likely to give
                    Joe (a) all the information he needs for the final exam and (b) opportunities to
                    practice applying that information and check his understanding.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>

    </page>
</assessment>
