<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<!--Created by OLI Author v3.0-->
<assessment id="_u0_reflect_strategies_lbd">
    <title>Strategies: Rudolfo</title>
    <page id="page_0">
        <question id="_u0_reflect_strategies_lbd_0">
            <!--LO:meta-->
            <body>Rudolfo anticipates a very busy semester, so he completes the entire OLI Psychology course in the first month of the semester, passing each Checkpoint easily. While this frees up his time for other courses, he finds that when he goes to take the final exam a few months later, he has forgotten a lot of what he learned. Rudolfo failed to:</body>
            <multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true">
                <choice value="A">properly assess the task</choice>
                <choice value="B">accurately evaluate his own strengths and weaknesses</choice>
                <choice value="C">plan an effective strategy for working through the course</choice>
                <choice value="D">successfully monitor his own performance</choice>
                <choice value="E">adjust his approach</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part id="qpart_0">
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Rudolfo successfully completed the work, so apparently he assessed the task accurately. It was his plan to complete the work too far in advance of the final exam that proved to be ineffective.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It's possible that Rudolfo overestimated his ability to remember material he had studied weeks earlier. However, it was primarily his plan to complete the work so far in advance of the final exam that proved ineffective.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct! Rudolfo’s plan to complete the work so far in advance of the final exam proved ineffective. Because he left five weeks between studying and taking the final exam, the material was not fresh in his mind when he took the final.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Rudolfo’s performance throughout the course was fine, so monitoring his performance was not his problem. It was his plan to complete the work too far in advance of the final exam that proved to be ineffective.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. By the time Rudolfo realized his approach was unsuccessful, it was too late to adjust. This was because his plan to complete the work too far in advance of the final exam proved to be ineffective.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>Look back at the definition for each skill outlined in the section on Metacognition to see if one looks like a match.</hint>
                <hint>Consider, for example, that Rudolfo would have been better prepared for the final exam if he had scheduled regular work on the OLI Psychology course throughout the semester.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="_u0_reflect_strategies_lbd_1">
            <!--LO:meta-->
            <body>Penelope has worked her way through the entire OLI A&amp;P course by skipping the text and jumping straight to the activities, which she enjoys. When she doesn’t get an answer right on one of the activities, she tries the other answers until she discovers the correct one. Unfortunately, she does not pass the final exam and has to retake it. “Oh well,” she sighs. “Back to the drawing board.” Once again, she opens the first unit, skips the text, and goes straight to the activities. Penelope has failed to:</body>
            <multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true">
                <choice value="A">properly assess the task</choice>
                <choice value="B">accurately evaluate his own strengths and weaknesses</choice>
                <choice value="C">plan an effective strategy for working through the course</choice>
                <choice value="D">successfully monitor his own performance</choice>
                <choice value="E">adjust his approach</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part id="qpart_1">
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. From the story, we can’t really know whether Penelope assessed the task inaccurately. What we do know is that she neither learned from her experience nor adjusted her approach the second time around.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. This is possible, but not the best answer. It's true that if Penelope had accurately assessed her strengths and weaknesses the first time she worked through the course, she would have realized that she could not pass the final exam without reading the explanatory text. However, it was her failure to adjust her approach the second time that stands out here.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>This is true, but not the best answer. Penelope did not plan an effective strategy for working through the OLI  A&amp;P course the first time. However, an even bigger mistake was not reflecting on and adjusting her approach after it failed.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. While Penelope clearly did not monitor her performance closely enough to know her initial approach to studying was not effective, her bigger mistake was to employ the same approach the second time around.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. This is the best answer. Penelope is employing the same unsuccessful approach to prepare for the final exam the second time, without learning from her mistakes the first time.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>Look back at the definition for each skill outlined in the section on Metacognition to see if one looks like a match.</hint>
                <hint>Notice that Penelope’s key decision point now is whether or not she will learn from her past mistakes and find a more effective way to go through the unit so she can learn the material.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>