<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u0_lbdtype_lbd"><title>LBD Activity Type</title><page id="page_0"><question id="_u0_lbdtype_lbd_0"><body>One of the most prominent features in our courses are Learn By Doing activities. These activities give you the opportunity to practice a skill or better understand a new concept. Which of the following do you think is true about Learn By Doing question types in this course?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">They may introduce you to new aspects of a concept that you are currently learning.</choice><choice value="B">They can be skipped if you think you already know the answer.</choice><choice value="C">Only the question and correct answer matters in a Learn By Doing.</choice><choice value="D">They are only presented at the end of a chunk of content to evaluate your knowledge of the presented concept.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Often Learn By Doing questions not only test your knowledge of a concept; at the same time they expand that knowledge and/or provide specific examples to practice the concept in context.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Learn by Doing question types should never be skipped because they might offer additional information to be learned or expand on a concept.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. You can learn something by reviewing all of the hints and feedback in the question. Often the list of answer choices for a Learn By Doing are carefully selected based on common misconceptions about the question.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Learn By Doing question types are usually found right after a presented concept, so that you can practice the concept as you learn it, and these question types are scaffolded to give support “as needed” by providing tailored hints and feedback. Did I Get This activity types are usually presented at the end of a chunk of content, so that you can self-assess.</feedback></response><hint>Learn By Doing question types are presented in-context.</hint><hint>The intent of these activities is often to let you explore many different aspects and details of new concepts that you may not have otherwise experienced.</hint><hint>“Learn By Doing” suggests you might learn something at the same time you are doing something.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
