<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<!--Created by OLI Author v3.0-->
<assessment id="_u1_lo_sc">
    <title>Learning Objectives</title>
    <page id="page_0">
        <question id="_u1_lo_sc_0">
            <!--LO:meta-->
            <body>Describe some study techniques that would be especially useful when learning body system terminology and parts at the knowledge and understanding level.</body>
            <short_answer id="qsub_0"/>
            <part id="qpart_0">
                <response input="qsub_0" match="*" score="10"/>
                <no_response><feedback>You need to write your own response before looking at the sample response.</feedback></no_response>
                <explanation>Much of this learning is based on identification of a structure on an image or by description and definition of associated terms.  You could create blank classification charts, similar to the ones in the unit, and see if you can fill them in with your own words after you have studied.  You could also create flashcards for terms in bold in unit or in your textbook, to help learn descriptions and definitions.  Labeling and coloring activities, typically found in lab manuals, can also be useful in learning the organ system structures.  Creating a flow chart that puts structures or events in sequence will help with some processes that occur in steps.  See the next section on Learning Strategies for more ideas.</explanation>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="_u1_lo_sc_1">
            <!--LO:meta-->
            <body>Describe some study techniques that would be best suited to learning objectives at the reasoning level.</body>
            <short_answer id="qsub_1"/>
            <part id="qpart_1">
                <response input="qsub_1" match="*" score="10"/>
                <no_response><feedback>You need to write your own response before looking at the sample response.</feedback></no_response>
                <explanation>This requires you apply what you have learned about the system.  You can create a mind-map that shows relationships among different parts and processes.  Completing a Venn diagram is a good way to compare and contrast two or three related structures or functions and organizational tables help you analyze multiple characteristics.  Watching animated videos of a physiological process and then creating your own outline or drawing of the process can help you learn the important events and how they interact.  Reading case studies can help you predict and evaluate the effects on organ systems.  See the next section on Learning Strategies for more ideas.</explanation>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>