<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_digttype_digt"><title>DIGT Activity Type</title><page id="page_0"><question id="_u1_digttype_digt_0"><body>Which of the following components are usually found in both, a Learn By Doing question type and a Did I Get This question type?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Hints</choice><choice value="B">Detailed Feedback</choice><choice value="C">Ability to rate yourself against the learning outcomes and provide feedback to instructor.</choice><choice value="D">Expository text.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hints are usually found in Learn By Doing questions but not in Did I Get This (although some Did I Get This questions may contain hints if it is a particularly difficult concept).</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Detailed feedback about why a selected answer is correct or incorrect is part of every activity in the course.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. You might encounter other activity types that offer this opportunity, but they will not be Learn By Doing or Did I Get This questions about the content. For example, you will encounter “My Response” activity types in this course where you will have the opportunity to rate yourself, offer feedback, and ask additional questions for your instructor.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Did I Get This activity types will not have expository text offering more information about a concept, but Learn By Doing question types might.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="_u1_digttype_digt_1"><body>When will you be most likely to succeed at a “Did I Get This” activity?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Before having read any of the content on the page</choice><choice value="B">After exploring all of the content on the page, including any Learn By Doings and Walkthroughs</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If you try to complete the DIGT before exploring the page content, you will only be testing yourself on what you knew before you took the course.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. You want to complete a DIGT to check your understanding of the content you just went through.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
