<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="unit0_contenttypes_assessment"><title>Content Types Assessment</title><question id="q1"><body><p>In the below activity, identify possible ways that some of the different types of content can be used to further your understanding of Anatomy &amp; Physiology.</p><custom id="dragDrop" src="../../webcontent/DynaDropHTML.js" type="javascript" width="550" height="650" layout="../webcontent/unit0_contenttypes_assessment_layout.xml" logging="true"><param name="showInputs">false</param></custom></body><fill_in_the_blank id="aa" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="bb" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="cc" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="dd" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i1ce63276963b4585b4b481dd0f8c9682"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response input="aa" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Images are frequently used to both explain concepts and represent processes in anatomy and physiology. </feedback></response><response input="aa" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Although we do display important terms in a visual way by highlighting them in green throughout the course, there is another type of Explanatory Content that better-fits this description. </feedback></response><response input="aa" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Although tables do display comparable objects or ideas in a visual way by organizing and categorizing them around selected criteria, there is another type of Explanatory Content that better-fits this description. </feedback></response><response input="aa" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Although Examples do display information in a visual way, as they are presented differently than the rest of the text on a page, there is another type of Explanatory Content that better-fits this description. </feedback></response><hint>This type of content highlights more than just words.</hint><hint>Is this type of content visual?</hint></part><part id="i7fa0e2fe629b495aa3c17c67e346219c"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response input="bb" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Though this image does point out some words related to the concept, these words are not guaranteed to appear again. </feedback></response><response input="bb" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Here we see the Levels of Organization highlighted in green and organized in a list because we will be examining these levels of organization for every system in the body. You are going to encounter these terms numerous times throughout the course and they are important for building your vocabulary in the domain. </feedback></response><response input="bb" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Though tables do sometimes include important vocabulary terms, there is a broader purpose to using tables in a page - to organize comparable information. </feedback></response><response input="bb" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Though examples do sometimes include important vocabulary terms, there is a broader purpose to include examples in a page - to provide real-world examples.</feedback></response><hint>What about this content &quot;jumps out&quot; at you?</hint></part><part id="ba2fe28cd74f4c8987af33735849bec5"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response input="cc" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Though images serve as a way to organize information, they do not always specifically provide the ability to compare and contrast.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Though reviewing all the terms on a page may help you to organize some information towards a particular learning objective, there is a another type of Explanatory Content that does the work for you!</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Tables organize information to help you to make comparisons, distinctions, and expand your comprehension of a concept.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Examples organize specific information to pay attention to on a page by the way they are displayed, but not in categories of comparable information.</feedback></response><hint>Is there structure to this type of content?</hint></part><part id="i5eef8f593d7848c48b6aae0e6b241171"><skillref idref="meta_plan_SKILL" /><response input="dd" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Images in this course do sometimes depict realistic information and real-life examples, but they usually do not provide in-depth explanation or case information. Another type of Explanatory Content is a better choice. </feedback></response><response input="dd" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Though terms can be related to real-life samples and scenarios, another type of Explanatory Content serves the broader purpose by illustrating ways you can apply the terminology or concept to something you might encounter in real life. </feedback></response><response input="dd" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Tables can provide information related to the real-life samples and cases, but it is not what the real-life sample or case is.</feedback></response><response input="dd" match="d" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Examples point out a specific condition or event in a page that illustrates a concept in context to increase your knowledge of that particular topic, process, or concept.</feedback></response><hint>Take note of parts of content that reappear with frequency, such as headers.</hint></part></question></assessment>
