<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u6_m2_fiber_org">
	<head>
		<title>Muscle Fiber Organization</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_fiber_org"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_24.jpg" alt="Sarcomere detail" width="500"/>
		<p>The fascicles of parallel muscles are arranged parallel to the long axis of the muscle.
			They are equidistant and run in the same direction. The majority of skeletal muscles in
			the body follow this type of organization. With muscles that seem to be plump, the large
			mass of tissue located in the middle of the muscle is known as the central body, but its
			more common name is the belly. When the muscle contracts, the contractile fibers shorten
			into a large bulge. To see this, extend and then flex your biceps muscle. The large mass
			of the muscle is called the belly; tendons emerge from both ends of the muscle. When a
			muscle contracts, it is the pulling on the tendon by the muscle that actually produces
			the movement.</p>
		<p>The fascicles of circular muscles, also called sphincters, are arranged around an opening in
			rings. When the muscle contracts, the size of the sphincter opening decreases. The
			orbicularis oris muscle is a circular muscle around the mouth under the lips. Another
			example is the orbicularis oculi ("ocular" means "eye"), which surrounds each eye. The
			circular muscles expand and contract in a circular way. The circular muscles contract
			and relax in a circular way. Think about how you can contract and shape your lips to
			whistle or pucker.</p>
		<p>In convergent muscle, the fascicles extend from a broad, fan-shape area and converge on single
			attachment site where the muscle interacts with a tendon. .The large muscle on the
			chest, the pectoralis major, is an example of a convergent muscle. Because of the
			arrangement of motor units within a convergent muscle, it can be stimulated in
			different, smaller areas. This can change the direction of the muscle force slightly
			from when the entire muscle contracts at once.</p>
		<p><term>Pennate</term> muscles are feather-shaped and form different fascicle arrangements at an angle
			to the tendon. Contracting pennate muscles pull at an angle and can produce high
			tension, but don’t move tendons very far. There are three subtypes of pennate muscles:
			<term>unipennate</term>, <term>bipennate</term>, and <term>multipennate</term> muscles. In unipennate muscles, such as the
			extensor digitorum in the forearm, the fascicles are located on one side of the tendon.
			A bipennate muscle, such as the rectus femoris in the thigh, has fascicles on both sides
			of the tendon. If the tendon branches within a pennate muscle, as it does in the deltoid
			muscle of the shoulder, the muscle is referred to as multipennate.</p>
		<p>Some parallel muscles are <term>fusiform</term> and have fascicles that are
			spindle-shaped to give the muscle a large belly, such as the biceps brachii, whereas
			triangular muscles can be convergent or multipennate to create triangular shapes. <term>Triangular</term> muscles include the trapezius, which extends
			from the head down the back and out to the shoulder.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_fiber_org_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
