<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u6_m2_levers_movement">
	<head>
		<title>Levers and Movement</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_levers"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>We can consider the mechanisms by which muscles act on bones using descriptions based on
			levers. A lever is a rigid structure, in this case a bone, that moves on a fixed point
			called the fulcrum, in this case an articulation. A lever moves when an applied force or
			effort is sufficient to overcome any load or resistance that would otherwise oppose or
			prevent such movement. In the body, each bone is a lever and each joint is a fulcrum,
			and muscles supply the applied forces. Movement of the skeleton occurs at joints, so
			there has to be sufficient muscle power to move all the bones at these joints.</p>
		<p/>
		<p>Levers can change the direction and effective strength of a force as well as the distance and
			speed of movement produced by the force. Imagine a seesaw in a playground. You and a
			friend could sit on opposite ends of it. You would then take turns pushing off the
			ground with your legs as you each went up in the air. A seesaw is an example of a
			first-class lever, and there are three classes of levers. The fulcrum (F) lies at the
			midpoint of the seesaw, between the applied force (AF) and the load (L). What this means
			is that the seesaw balances you and your friend, as you both provide the applied force
			with the push of your legs and the load with the weight of your bodies.</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_22a.jpg" alt="levers in the body" width="500"/>
		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_22b.jpg" alt="levers in the body" width="500"/>

		<p>The body has only a few <em style="bold">first-class</em> levers. One is involved in head
			flexion (pulling the head down toward the chest) and head extension (pulling the head
			back up into normal position). The fulcrum is where the head moves in the sagittal plane
			on the first cervical vertebrae. The load is the weight of the head, and the applied
			force comes from the muscles. Extension occurs when the muscles pull the head back up.
			Moving your head forward and backward mirrors the action of a seesaw.</p>
		<p/>
		<p>In a <em style="bold"
				>second-class<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T203545-0500" content=" "?></em><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T203546-0500"?>
			<?oxy_insert_end?>lever, the load is located between the applied force and the fulcrum.
			When you move a load in a wheelbarrow, you lift upward on the handle and the wheel acts
			as the fulcrum. The force is further from the fulcrum than the load is, so you can move
			a larger weight with less effort. In the body, you achieve the same effect by standing
			on your toes. The fulcrum is on the ball of the foot, the load is your body weight, and
			the effort comes from the muscles in the back of the leg.</p>
		<p/>
		<p>In <em style="bold"
				>third-class<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T203612-0500" content=" "?></em><?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T203615-0500"?>
			<?oxy_insert_end?>levers the force is applied between the load and the fulcrum. We don’t
			often see these types of levers in artificial machines, but they are the most common
			levers in the body. Speed and distance traveled are increased at the expense of force.
			For the biceps brachii in the arm, the load will be located in or around the hand. The
			biceps muscle applies the force, while the fulcrum is the elbow. For instance, when you
			pick up a full bag of groceries, you can lift it quickly using the third-class lever of
			the biceps brachii and the forearm. However, the location of fulcrum prevents great
			enhancements of load carrying.</p>
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_levers_2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_levers_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
