<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u6_m2_skeletal_muscle_movement">
	<head>
		<title>Skeletal Muscle Movement</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_bursae"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Skeletal muscles, which are the organs of the skeletal muscle system, generally act by
			pulling on bones to produce movement. To pull the bone, muscles need to attach to the
			bone, either directly or indirectly. The epimysium of a muscle can attach directly to
			bone or cartilage to form a direct attachment. An indirect attachment is formed when the
			connective tissue layers, the epimysium, perimysium, and endomysium form a complex at
			the end of the muscle. </p>
		<p>For connections, muscles require either a tendon or a broader sheet of connective tissue called
			an aponeurosis. Muscles connect to muscles via <term>aponeuroses</term>, and muscles attach to bones
			via <term>tendons</term> or aponeuroses. Thus, when a muscle contracts, the force of movement is
			transmitted through the attachment, which pulls on the bone to produce skeletal
			movement.</p>
		<p>Tendons also help to stabilize the joints. Tendons are a common form of attachment
			because the collagen fibers are more resistant to tearing than direct muscle tissue
			attachment to bone would be, and the compact form of the tendon requires a small amount
			of space. Tendons can be easily seen as the hand is flexed, causing the thick, cordlike
			tendons of the forearm to stand out prominently. The calcaneal (Achilles) tendon is
			visible from the heel to the calf. Some tendons are also surrounded by a connective
			tissue layer called a tendon sheath, which protects the tendon as it moves. Fluid-filled
			sacs called <term>bursae</term> also join to tendons to reduce friction as the tendon moves. Bursae
			are present in connective tissue near bone, where tendons experience friction, but they
			occasionally arise in other areas due to stress caused by movement.</p>
		<example title="Bursitis">
			<p>Bursae can become inflamed, a condition known as bursitis. This is usually caused by overuse
				of a joint or by other mechanical stress, which can result in pain and swelling.
				Bursitis is common in knees, elbows, and shoulders.</p>
		</example>
		<p>Keep in mind that the range of motion produced by muscles is restricted by the anatomy of
			the bones and other support structures involved in a particular joint. Consider the
			movements of the hip and shoulder joints, both of which are freely moveable. The hip is
			the attachment point for the thigh and leg. The shoulder is the attachment point for the
			arm and forearm. The shoulder can produce movements that the hip cannot because of the
			anatomy of the bones involved and the ligaments (connective tissue) associated with the
			joint. Hold your arm out to the side and move your thumb around the axis of the arm in a
			360-degree circle. Can you do that with your hip and leg? No, you can’t. There are some
			people who appear to be
			“double-jointed<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T220146-0500"?>"<?oxy_insert_end?>;<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T220148-0500" content="”"?>
			they are able to push their joints past the normal limits of movement. The reason they
			can do this is because the ligaments of their joints are “loose” compared with someone
			who is not “double-jointed.” This ability appears to have a genetic basis.</p>
		<p>For muscles attached to the bones of the skeleton, the location of the connection
			determines the force, speed, and type of movement. These characteristics depend on each
			other and can explain the general organization of the muscular and skeletal systems.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_bursae_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_bursae_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
