<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u6_m2_tissue_function">
	<head>
		<title>Muscle Tissue Function</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_tone"/>
		<objref idref="_u5_isometric"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<section>
			<title/>
			<body>
				<p>Skeletal muscles (organs) are almost never completely relaxed. Even if a muscle is not
					producing movement, some of the muscle fibers (cells) in the organ contract to
					produce muscle tone <extra>
						<anchor><term>muscle tone</term></anchor>
						<meaning>
							<material>
								<p>low levels of muscle contraction</p>
							</material>
						</meaning>
					</extra>. The tension produced by muscle tone prevents the muscle from becoming
					weak, allowing the muscle to stabilize joints and maintain posture. Muscle tone
					is accomplished by the contraction of a small fraction of muscle cells so
					muscles won't fatigue completely; some cells can recover while others are
					active. This can help with stronger movements, as the motor units being used to
					maintain tone can produce a quicker, stronger contraction than the motor units
					that are resting, avoiding the <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120103T220920-0500" comment="I recommend either briefly defining this word, or leaving it out."?><extra>
						<anchor><term>treppe</term></anchor>
						<meaning>
							<material>
								<p>stepwise increase in contraction tension</p>
							</material>
						</meaning>
					</extra><?oxy_comment_end?> that occurs with muscle fibers that are stimulated
					from a state of rest.</p>
				<p/>
				<p>The absence of the low-level contractions that lead to muscle tone is referred to as
					hypotonia. Hypotonia can be caused by nervous system dysfunction or imbalances
					in certain ions in the blood stream. Hypotonic muscles have a flaccid appearance
					and display functional impairments. Conversely, excessive muscle tone is
					referred to as hypertonia. This takes two forms: spasticity, which is a type of
					stiffness related to uncontrolled reflexes, and rigidity, a stiffness not
					associated with reflexes.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
				
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title/>
					<body>
					<wb:inline idref="bloodtest_dysfunction" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_tone_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Isometric and Isotonic</title>
			<body>
				<p>There are two main types of skeletal muscle contractions: isotonic and isometric. When a
					muscle exerts a force, it exerts this force on a load. At the molecular level,
					cross-bridge formation occurs in both isotonic and isometric contractions, but
					the whole muscle acts differently depending on the load and the outcome to be
					achieved. In <term>isotonic</term> (iso- same, tonic - tension)
					contractions, a load is moved as the length of the muscle changes.</p>
				<p/>
				<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_20.jpg" alt="isotonic contraction" width="600"/>
				<p/>
				<p>There are two types of isotonic contraction: concentric and eccentric. <term>Concentric</term> contractions involve the muscle shortening to move a load.
					An example of this is the biceps muscle shortening as a hand weight is brought
					upward and the angle of the elbow decreases. <term>Eccentric</term>
					contractions occur as the muscle lengthens. Eccentric contractions do not
					produce adequate force to move a load but are used for movement, balance, and
					resisting movement. An example of an eccentric contraction is the movement of a
					bicep as it performs the lowering portion of a biceps curl. A concentric
					contraction brings the arm upward, reducing the angle of the elbow, and then an
					eccentric contraction lowers the arm, resisting gravity and increasing the elbow
					angle slowly. The same muscle tension is required whether the muscle is
					shortening or lengthening.</p>
				<p/>
				<p><term>Isometric</term> (iso- same, metric- length) contractions occur as the muscle
					produces tension without changing length. Isometric contractions do not produce
					movement or lift loads; these contractions maintain posture and joint stability.
					For example, pushing against a wall produces no movement because the muscle
					simply cannot produce enough force and thus does not result in changes in muscle
					length. Conversely, holding your head in an upright position occurs not because
					the muscles cannot move the head, but because the goal is to remain stationary
					and not produce movement. In both of these cases, cross-bridge cycling occurs in
					the same manner as it would if the load had been moved. Most actions are the
					result of a combination of isotonic and isometric contractions working together
					to produce a wide range of outcomes.</p>
				<p/>
				<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_21.jpg" alt="isometric contraction" width="600"/>
				<p/>
				<p>All of the contraction that occurs before a load is lifted is isometric. Even when muscles
					carry no load, they must still develop a tension equal to the muscles' own
					weight before they can shorten. When contractile forces exceed the weight of the
					load, muscles begin shortening. Shortening stops when active tension falls to
					the point that it can no longer overcome and move the load. This converts it
					back to an isometric contraction.</p>

				<section purpose="learnbydoing">
					<title/>
					<body>
					<p> It is relatively easy for someone to lift a glass of water. However, holding a glass of
						water at arm’s length for one full minute is difficult.</p>
					<wb:inline idref="_u5_isometric_sc" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
					</body>
				</section>
				
				
				<section purpose="didigetthis">
					<title/>
					<body><wb:inline idref="_u5_tone_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="_u5_isometric_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/></body>
				</section>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
