<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u6_m2_skeletal_muscle">
	<head>
		<title>Skeletal Muscle Organ Anatomy</title>
		<objref idref="_u5_connective_layers"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Skeletal muscles, which are the organs of the skeletal muscle system, include three layers of
			connective tissue that enclose and provide structure to the muscle as a whole. The outer
			layer of each muscle fiber is wrapped with a layer of connective tissue called the
				<term>epimysium</term> ("epi-" means "outside" or "over," and "-mysium" refers to
			"muscle"). The epimysium allows muscle to contract and move powerfully while maintaining
			its structural integrity; it also separates muscle from other tissues and organs. It is
			composed of a thick layer of collagen fibers. The epimysium is surrounded by
				<term>fascia</term>, which is a type of connective tissue that is found around body
			organs. Deep fascia surrounds groups of muscles, sometimes joining with tendons to
			strengthen the bone attachment, whereas superficial fascia lies between muscle and skin.
			Some fascia contain adipose tissue that insulates and protects muscle.</p>

		<p>Inside each skeletal muscle, muscle fibers (a single muscle cell is called a muscle fiber; not
			to be confused with fibers found in connective tissue) are organized into groups called
			fascicles, or bundles of muscle fibers (cells). Some of these fascicles can be seen
			without a microscope when a muscle is cut open. Each fascicle contains many long muscle
			fibers bound by a middle layer of connective tissue called the <term>perimysium</term>
			("peri-" means "around"). Similar to the epimysium, the perimysium contains collagen
			fibers, but the perimysium also contains elastic fibers.</p>

		<p>Inside each fascicle, each individual muscle fiber is encased in a connective tissue
			layer called the <term>endomysium</term> ("endo-" means "inside"). The
			endomysium forms a thinner layer than the dense epimysium and perimysium, and contains
			areolar and reticular tissues which form loose, delicate networks. The endomysium of
			muscle fibers connect to each other to form a loose complex within a fascicle. Small
			blood vessels and motor neurons pass through the endomysium to support and activate each
			muscle fiber.</p>
		<p>The plasma membrane, or sarcolemma, of a skeletal muscle fiber is located just under the
			endomysium. The sarcolemma is the site of action potential conduction, which triggers
			muscle contraction. Within the sarcolemma is the sarcoplasm, the cytoplasm of the muscle
			cell.</p>


		<image src="../../webcontent/Muscle_23.jpg" alt="Muscle anatomy" width="600"/>

		<example title="Muscular Dystrophy">
			<p>Muscular Dystrophy (MD) is a progressive weakening of skeletal muscles. Duchenne’s Muscular
				Dystrophy (DMD), the most common type of MD, is caused by a mutation in the  dystrophin gene. Dystrophin helps the thin filaments of myofibrils bind to the sarcolemma
				and maintains equal force transmission through the muscle tissue. Without sufficient
				dystrophin, muscle contractions cause the sarcolemma to tear, causing an influx of
					Ca<sup>2+</sup>, leading to cellular damage and muscle fiber degradation. Over
				time, muscles are damaged and functional impairments develop.</p>


			<p>DMD is an inherited disorder caused by an abnormal gene found on the X chromosome. It is one
				of many genetic diseases which are referred to as X-linked; X-linked disorders
				affect males since they only carry one copy of the X chromosome, which they
				inherited from their mother. Girls inherit one X chromosome from their mother and
				one from their father, so they are usually not affected. DMD is usually diagnosed in
				early childhood. It usually first appears as difficulty with balance and motion, and
				then progresses to an inability to walk. It continues progressing upwards in the
				body from the lower extremities to the upper body, where it affects the muscles
				responsible for breathing. It ultimately causes death due to respiratory failure,
				and those afflicted do not usually live past their twenties.</p>

		</example>
		
		
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
		<title/>
					
			<body>
				
			<image src="../../webcontent/muscle_structure.png" width="400"/>
			<wb:inline idref="_u5_connnective_layers_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				
			
				
			</body>
			
			
		</section>
		
		
		
		<wb:inline idref="_u5_connective_layers_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>

</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
