<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="binomial3_lbd2">
    <head>
        <title>An Application of the Binomial Random Variable</title>

    </head>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Purpose</title>
            <body>
                <p>The purpose of this activity is to gain experience making probabilistic decisions
                    using binomial random variables. </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Background</title>
            <body>
                <p>In vitro fertilization is becoming more and more common these days. Suppose each
                    embryo that is implanted has a 20% chance of resulting in a pregnancy that
                    results in delivering a baby. Also, assume that each embryo's chance of
                    surviving and resulting in a baby is independent of the others.</p>
                <p>It is an expensive procedure, so we want to do it only once. We wish to try to
                    find the optimum number of embryos to implant so that the probability of at
                    least 1 child being born is high, but the probability of more than 2 children
                    being born is low. In other words, we want a baby, and we're willing to have
                    twins, but we don't want triplets, quadruplets, etc.</p>
                <p>Note that unlike the airline flight example, where we needed to control only one
                    probability, in this case there are two probabilities that we wish to
                    control.</p>
            </body>
        </section>

        <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_binomial3_lbd2_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

        <p>We will let X represent the number of implanted embryos resulting in a baby. It is a
            binomial random variable with n = number of implanted embryos and p = .20 (the
            probability that an implanted embryo results in a baby). </p>
        <p> It is customary to implant between n = 1 and n = 7 embryos. We have provided a table
            that contains the two probabilities mentioned in the previous question, for values of n
            ranging from 1 to 7.</p>
        <table>
            <tr>
                <th># embryos</th>
                <th>P(X ≥ 1)</th>
                <th>P(X > 2)</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>1</td>
                <td>.20</td>
                <td>0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>.36</td>
                <td>0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>.488</td>
                <td>.008</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>4</td>
                <td>.590</td>
                <td>.027</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>5</td>
                <td>.672</td>
                <td>.058</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>6</td>
                <td>.738</td>
                <td>.099</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>7</td>
                <td>.790</td>
                <td>.148</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m3_binomial3_lbd2_tutor2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
