<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_homeostasis_feedback_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Homeostasis and Feedback Loops</title><page id="eb8bd6805b624f72b74144f28495f46d"><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_01" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad9e0910a1b714c5a969becaf9ba45a9b">What phrase best describes homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="dea43ea01049401a879c34c9f3869d68" labels="false"><choice value="equil">equilibrium</choice><choice value="maintain">maintaining a relatively stable environment</choice><choice value="feedback">feedback loops</choice><choice value="disrupt">disruption of processes</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_01_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="equil" score="0"><feedback><p id="af3a4408fea044ad297fcb345f232f029">Incorrect. Equilibrium is a term that means that everything is equal. In fact, things in the body are constantly changing, but generally within appropriate limits. </p></feedback></response><response match="maintain" score="10"><feedback><p id="abf4fc87088864fc998e9bf273ab4d240">Correct. Relatively stable indicates that most of the time, values of the variables are near the set point, and if they vary, they don’t do so enough to cause dysfunction.</p></feedback></response><response match="feedback" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac150af36535048eab2d8111e543ca202">Although homeostasis is most commonly carried out by the many feedback loops, homeostasis is more about the general maintenance of stable conditions rather than the specifics of how that maintenance occurs.</p></feedback></response><response match="disrupt" score="0"><feedback><p id="af8432eed435648eba821bb71118a8e55">Incorrect. Homeostasis maintains processes of the body.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_02" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aba269f0459c14996ba398237698f6a4d">You would expect homeostasis to occur at what level(s)?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="de5bcb2e81084845902e91a74a15c74c" labels="false"><choice value="molec_macro">molecular and macromolecular</choice><choice value="cell_tissue">cell and tissue</choice><choice value="organ_syst">organ and organ system</choice><choice value="all_above">all of these and more</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_02_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="molec_macro" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae47ac166fbdd4330868afb5b754a3f4e">Incorrect. Although homeostasis is maintained at this level, for example many enzymatic pathways have some level of regulation, this is not the best answer for this question.</p></feedback></response><response match="cell_tissue" score="0"><feedback><p id="afdfe4d67c0cf46a29d739d109367bd54">&gt; Incorrect. Although homeostasis is maintained at this level, for example cell metabolism and mitosis is typically regulated, this is not the best answer for this question.</p></feedback></response><response match="organ_syst" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab4ca1c3e6d5a4b7dbb8a05f9e5e3d10a">Incorrect. Although homeostasis is maintained at this level, for example multiple organs work together to regulate blood glucose, this is not the best answer for this question. </p></feedback></response><response match="all_above" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae17213d54ccd4751b3e3b5352393975a">Correct. With a constant influx of new material and changes in environmental conditions, the body works at every level to maintain homeostasis.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_03" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="f62baba53b8b435187e03c94d4a04343">Which of the following would <em style="italic">not</em> be considered part of a homeostatic feedback loop for regulating blood plasma calcium concentration?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a2c3bbffd94f4e2dad92611ff3c515a4" labels="false"><choice value="hormones">hormones sending messages to various organs</choice><choice value="kidneys">kidneys reabsorbing calcium from the filtrate instead of excreting it in urine.</choice><choice value="ingest">ingesting extra calcium from food</choice><choice value="moving">moving calcium from the skeletal system into the plasma</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_03_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="hormones" score="0"><feedback><p id="acc299b5d6e2c417ca58fe1f2dcca8a81">Incorrect. Hormones often help regulate homeostasis.</p></feedback></response><response match="kidneys" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac640c78d08cd42b4ad00f61692651c9c">Incorrect. The conservation of calcium (usually by hormonal regulation of the kidneys) helps maintain homeostasis.</p></feedback></response><response match="ingest" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac59a6bed3ea34d44a0ef8ff1f1364e2c">Correct. This may be confusing, since ingestion can increase the calcium in the body, but there is no internal process of the body that changes ingestion. Most people don’t “crave” calcium products, even if their calcium levels are low. However, regulatory molecules can increase the absorption of calcium in the digestive tract.</p></feedback></response><response match="moving" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab9a86320ccd74a2e85b3e4de27e0912b">Incorrect. Hormonal regulation of bone calcium is the primary mechanism for maintaining blood calcium homeostasis.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_04" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ab74583030b5a483491eb4107583e7da3">Which feedback mechanism is most commonly used to maintain homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="a5b11020ffd54b688fb216ea78a802ce" labels="false"><choice value="neg">negative feedback</choice><choice value="pos">positive feedback</choice><choice value="both">both positive feedback and negative feedback are used equally</choice><choice value="neither">neither positive feedback and negative feedback is used</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_04_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_compare_pos_neg_SKILL" /><response match="neg" score="10"><feedback><p id="af2919938642c4ec9b9251b1d899552a9">Correct. Negative feedback most commonly helps in maintaining homeostasis. As one example, when we are cold, we shiver to increase our temperature. That’s negative feedback: our body responds to oppose the decreased body temperature by increasing heat generation.</p></feedback></response><response match="pos" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae15beeb9562a45b09a38e14684bd67aa">Incorrect. Positive feedbackcycles occasionally occur in normal physiological systems, but they do so in a limited manner, and are not considered a common mechanism.</p></feedback></response><response match="both" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad80739c7e769435e93748d8f42616fbd">Incorrect. While both positive and negative feedback are used to maintain homeostasis, but one occurs more commonly.</p></feedback></response><response match="neither" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad8986b29cfb047c3940a2cbe22f6cc03">Incorrect. Both positive and feedback are used, but one occurs more commonly.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_05" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af16d9001743f40ab8c4b09921b99343d">Which of the following would be an example of a positive feedback mechanism?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a6bf95cc68e04a36b859f78cecfbd143" labels="false"><choice value="normal">control of glucose</choice><choice value="emergency">control of blood pressure</choice><choice value="pathological">only pathological (or disease) processes have positive feedback</choice><choice value="none">cervical pressure during the childbirth process</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_05_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_compare_pos_neg_SKILL" /><response match="normal" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa83bdd1023b9428d8c8aca11bf984910">Incorrect. When blood glucose levels increase or decrease away from the set point, effectors work to bring it back toward the normal set point, which is an example of negative feedback.</p></feedback></response><response match="emergency" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae1d527f88fd54a73b47582eeb91577c6">Incorrect. When blood pressure increases or decreases away from the set point, effectors work to bring it back toward the set point, which is an example of negative feedback.</p></feedback></response><response match="pathological" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab9b35462440544b5b9e825a2c7f52074">Incorrect. Although some pathological conditions can include positive feedback cycles, there are also some examples of these in regulating healthy physiologic processes.</p></feedback></response><response match="none" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae2245991f75144bc99ca269c99c204c0">Correct. During birthing, pressure on the cervix stimulates stretch receptors and causes the effector (uterus smooth muscle) to contract and put more pressure on the cervix for childbirth. This “self-amplifying cycle is an example of positive feedback.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_06" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae652bf71b5c644f9afc1f140bf648685">What would happen if positive feedback were used in the cruise control system in a car?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="fb41f9068b6149399380bfe2adadabd7" labels="false"><choice value="speed_up">you would speed up until the engine failed or you would slow down until you stopped</choice><choice value="maintain">you would maintain a constant speed</choice><choice value="stop_go">you would stop and go alternately</choice><choice value="none">none of these is correct</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_06_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_positive_SKILL" /><response match="speed_up" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa6c34b265041465481579a79f68ae837">Correct. Cruise control usually works via negative feedback to keep a car moving at a constant speed. However, with positive feedback, an increase in speed would cause the cruise control to further increase speed until the engine failed. Similarly, a decrease in speed would cause the cruise control to slow the car down until it stopped if positive feedback were in effect.</p></feedback></response><response match="maintain" score="0"><feedback><p id="acce931dff55b474da06767a98273fb25">Incorrect. Cruise control usually works via negative feedback to keep a car moving at a constant speed. A positive feedback system would respond very differently.</p></feedback></response><response match="stop_go" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa4dff26519274d19a03c696015983b57">Incorrect. Both positive and negative feedback usually occur as a process or series of small steps, not abrupt changes.</p></feedback></response><response match="none" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad61e43236fa849d383d64ec17573c101">Incorrect. One of these would occur if the cruise control worked as a positive feedback mechanism.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page><page id="a2d26bd1b8fc46bdac74c78ada46fa26"><section id="blood_clott"><title> </title><content><p>Consider the following feedback cycle involving platelets and clotting.</p><p>When a blood vessel is injured, platelets adhere to the injured area. These platelets become “activated”, allowing them to adhere to each other in a mass called the platelet plug. They also release several chemicals, including one called thromboxane that causes other platelets to become activated.</p></content><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_07"><body>This scenario will most likely lead to what?</body><input><choice value="every">more and more platelets sticking together until something stops the cycle</choice><choice value="reduce">the platelet plug will continually reduce in size until it is no longer there</choice><choice value="hemorrhaging">the bleeding will continually get worse</choice><choice value="inactivated">platelets will be inactivated</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_07_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_positive_SKILL" /><response match="every" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Positive feedback will continue to amplify the effect until something stops the cycle. Eventually, a blockage of flow prevents any more platelets from reaching the area of the platelet plu. </feedback></response><response match="reduce"><feedback>Incorrect. That would happen if this were a negative feedback cycle, but then the plug would not be able to prevent blood loss.</feedback></response><response match="hemorrhaging"><feedback>Incorrect. The formation of the platelet plug in this positive feedback mechanism decreases blood loss.</feedback></response><response match="inactivated"><feedback>Incorrect. The platelets are transported in plasma in an inactive form, but the chemical being released in this positive feedback mechanism activates them.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_08"><body>What would best represent the variable in the feedback cycle?</body><input><choice value="platelet">platelet</choice><choice value="vessel">integrity of the blood vessel</choice><choice value="thromboxane">thromboxane</choice><choice value="clot">size of the platelet plug</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_08_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_positive_SKILL" /><response match="platelet"><feedback>Incorrect. Platelets would most likely represent the sensor, control center, and effector in this cycle.</feedback></response><response match="vessel" score="10"><feedback>Correct. It is a break in the integrity of the blood vessel that initiates the positive feedback mechanism.</feedback></response><response match="thromboxane"><feedback>Incorrect. Thromboxane is the method of communication between platelets.</feedback></response><response match="clot"><feedback>Incorrect. The size of the platelet plug is not directly monitored to influence the cycle.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_09"><body>What is a potential medical problem associated with formation of the platelet plug?</body><input><choice value="thrombus">clot (thrombus) formation inside blood vessels</choice><choice value="hemorrhaging">fatal hemorrhaging (bleeding to death)</choice><choice value="loss_platelet">loss of platelets</choice><choice value="loss_vessels">vascular damage</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_09_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_positive_SKILL" /><response match="thrombus" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Atherosclerosis (plaque development) of vessels can sometimes initiate platelet plug formation, which can lead to a complete vessel occlusion, leading to a heart attack or stroke.</feedback></response><response match="hemorrhaging"><feedback>Incorrect. The platelet plug counteracts blood loss.</feedback></response><response match="loss_platelet"><feedback>Incorrect. Although platelets are consumed during the process, formation of the platelet plug typically ceases prior to using up too many platelets and the body will produce more platelets by a negative feedback mechanism.</feedback></response><response match="loss_vessels"><feedback>Incorrect. This cycle limits vascular damage and initiate the healing process.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_10"><body>Aspirin reduces the ability of platelets to produce thromboxane. How does this affect the feedback cycle?</body><input><choice value="adhesion">it changes the level of the variable being monitored</choice><choice value="activation">it reduces the number of effectors in the cycle</choice><choice value="signaling">it interrupts the method of communication between platelets</choice><choice value="repairs">it prevents the sensor from detecting a change in the variable</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_10_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_positive_SKILL" /><response match="adhesion"><feedback>Incorrect. Aspirin limits the cycle, but deosn&apos;t interrupt the cycle completely or affect the variable directly.</feedback></response><response match="activation"><feedback>Incorrect. It does not change the platelet numbers, but it does affect the response of the platelets.</feedback></response><response match="signaling" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Thromboxane is used as a method of communication amoung platelets. Aspiring decreases the amount of thromboxane made, limiting activation of more platelets.</feedback></response><response match="repairs"><feedback>Incorrect. Platelets can still detect changes in the integrity of the vessel. </feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice></section></page><page id="a7df0cb6d9ea4ce395fa752b1f884c9c"><section id="match-parts-neg"><title> </title><content><p>To regulate body fluid osmolarity (concentration of solutes in body fluids), osmoreceptors in the hypothalamus monitor this. The hypothalamus will stimulate the posterior pituitary to release the hormone ADH when the plasma osmolarity increases. ADH causes the kidney to retain more water, reducing urine output.</p><p>Match the parts of this feedback loop with the correct terminology. </p></content><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_11"><body>hypothalamus</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">method of communication</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_11_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response match="variable"><feedback>Incorrect. The variable would be the thing that is changing and being monitored.</feedback></response><response match="receptor"><feedback>Incorrect. The receptor is specifically monitoring the variable.</feedback></response><response match="control" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hypothalamus determines if the osmolarity of body fluids is at the set point or if it is above or below.</feedback></response><response match="effector"><feedback>Incorrect. The effector would initiate a change in the variable based on communication from the control center.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_12"><body>kidney retention of water</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_12_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response match="variable"><feedback>Incorrect. The variable would be the thing that is changing and being monitored.</feedback></response><response match="receptor"><feedback>Incorrect.The receptor is specifically monitoring the variable.</feedback></response><response match="control"><feedback>Incorrect. The control center compares input to set point and communicates with the effector.</feedback></response><response match="effector" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The retention of water dilutes the solutes and helps correct the osmolarity.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_13"><body>body fluid osmolarity</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">method of communication</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_13_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response match="variable" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osmolarity change is detected by the receptor, making this the variable. </feedback></response><response match="receptor"><feedback>Incorrect. The receptor is specifically monitoring the variable.</feedback></response><response match="control"><feedback>Incorrect. The control center compares input to set point and communicates with the effector.</feedback></response><response match="effector"><feedback>Incorrect. The effector would initiate a change in the variable based on communication from the control center.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_14"><body>osmoreceptors in the hypothalamus</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_14_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response match="variable"><feedback>Incorrect. The variable would be the thing that is changing and being monitored.</feedback></response><response match="receptor" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osmoreceptors in they hypothalamus monitor osmolarity (solute concentration or saltiness) of the blood. </feedback></response><response match="control"><feedback>Incorrect. The control center compares input to set point and communicates with the effector.</feedback></response><response match="effector"><feedback>Incorrect. The effector would initiate a change in the variable based on communication from the control center.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_15"><body>Which of these other organ systems is <em>not</em> part of the feedback loop described, but would also likely contribute to homeostasis of body fluid osmolarity? </body><input><choice value="digestive">digestive system</choice><choice value="muscular">muscular system</choice><choice value="skeletal">skeletal system</choice><choice value="respiratory">respiratory system</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_15_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response match="digestive" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The digestive system absorbs and/or excretes water and solutes, which can help contribute to a stable body fluid environment.</feedback></response><response match="muscular"><feedback>Incorrect. In some ways the movement of the muscular system can generate heat and may cause a slight loss of water and salts in sweat, but this is an indirect side-effect of a homeostasis mechanisms for a different variable.</feedback></response><response match="skeletal"><feedback>Incorrect. The skeletal system is responsible for support and has little effect on body fluid osmolarity.</feedback></response><response match="respiratory"><feedback>Incorrect. The humidified air that we exhale does cause some loss of water, but this is not something that can be easily regulated, so this system does not generally contribute to maintenance of body fluid osmolarity.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></section></page><page id="cbadd95955304817b72a02a1acd6708b"><multiple_choice id="q1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af4c67ed5e36844408588251c0b9e05f5">Heart rate commonly changes in response to challenges to the body, yet there is no direct sensor for heart rate. This would suggest that heart rate is:</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="f367f052952a473fb6b22de81e4d8019" labels="false"><choice value="A">An input signal to the control center</choice><choice value="B">A communication from the control center</choice><choice value="C">An response of the effector</choice><choice value="D">None of the above</choice></input><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="afddbfdac3d2647508c9c8addae222ab4">Incorrect. There would need to be a receptor monitoring heart rate for there to be input about this change.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac71a1adeb519413ba80f12ad76ccbf19">Incorrect. The heart is not the control center, so this isn’t an appropriate choice here.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="af2fd040b8d944bcfab42335dc3ab269a">Correct. Heart rate is a response of the effector (heart) to change blood pressure. Under normal conditions, if heart rate increases, the blood pressure also increases. If heart rate decreases, blood pressure also decreases.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ade4e029eed3d47559855f7752efb65d9">Incorrect. The control center will communicate with the heart (effector) by chemical or nerve impulse to initiate this response.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q5" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abacf2ed45ed2491090ac9dccf0f00a8d">Which of the following is a control center for the regulation of plasma calcium levels in adults?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="c5b1f63d32d945ecaba7d5de3309dcfe" labels="false"><choice value="A">hypothalamus</choice><choice value="B">parathyroid gland</choice><choice value="C">pancreas</choice><choice value="D">kidney</choice></input><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab2062e2e4d7e4a7e80b10d255d7635bc">Incorrect. The hypothalamus is a control center for many of the homeostatic feedbacks, but not in this case.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aea8f7db853b14d4f8b00da3d41213887">Correct. Plasma calcium levels are regulated by the endocrine system, mainly the parathyroid gland.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac62c8a5309644fa29170f237a0b0be2e">Incorrect. The pancreas is involved in blood glucose homeostasis, not blood calcium levels.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="accd082d3d1344e9585e5056949f24968">Incorrect. The kidneys would be one of the effectors involved in blood calcium levels, not the control center.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q6" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ab22736073cb844d197174f229ce1879b">Which of the following analogies best describes negative feedback homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="bcac0866de6149c9a64f9e4a1870d147" labels="false"><choice value="A">When you apply the brakes on a car and it slows down.</choice><choice value="B">When you turn the key in the ignition and the car starts.</choice><choice value="C">When cruise control is used to maintain the speed of the car, even on hilly terrain.</choice><choice value="D">When the car burns fuel to produce torque.</choice></input><part id="q6_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="af837145316e54ddea219383d2771576a">Incorrect. This would be a change in the variable (car speed), but it is not due to input from a sensor nor a response able to maintain car speed near the set point.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae74710a8cc434c0c96942059c0507dad">Incorrect. This would be necessary for movement of the car, but has nothing to do with monitoring or maintaining the speed of the car.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa92abe0de7c544ee884df67219b484ce">Correct. If your car is on cruise control, the sensor provides input so it can automatically speed up or slow down to maintain the set speed. </p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="acf81574bf55346aba8fa36a6f5e8f654">Incorrect. This would be necessary for movement of the car, but has nothing to do with monitoring or maintaining the speed of the car.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q7" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abd56078c2fad47e3aebfb2091d3858da">The main benefit of using negative feedback instead of positive feedback to control a variable is that:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="e43f57a440df4805bed3cf84540039a9" labels="false"><choice value="A">Negative feedback can respond more rapidly.</choice><choice value="B">Negative feedback doesn’t require the use of nerves.</choice><choice value="C">Negative feedback brings the variable back toward the set point.</choice><choice value="D">Negative feedback uses a sensor, control center and effector(s).</choice></input><part id="q7_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_compare_pos_neg_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="af2c09d4eb6bf430897aa465be0f0b299">Incorrect. Both types of feedback have the potential to react rapidly.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="afb78bbdce79349d8b081a68155c822a9">Incorrect. Many negative feedback loops use nerves to communicate information.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa04dae643d4041a19682fb6cc9e97af1">Correct. Negative feedback brings the body back toward its set point rather than moving it further from it by enhancing the variable change.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="abdd0abe08c3e42eaa2f59433c5a35871">Incorrect. Both types of feedback use all these components.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q9" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af5798c9f7f4146efb5144907a199b980">An example of positive feedback is:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b7f46b16a0c0488e9df1f8fd9aab3df3" labels="false"><choice value="A">The control of plasma glucose.</choice><choice value="B">Maintenance of blood pressure.</choice><choice value="C">The platelet aggregation aspect of hemostasis.</choice><choice value="D">Regulation of plasma osmolarity.</choice></input><part id="q9_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_positive_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad591c26471e042af88295a635886356f">Incorrect. This is an example of negative feedback maintained near a set point, with increase or decrease of blood plasma glucose as necessary.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abbd9c67b8fac41e5a0b30ed7a1b2e0da">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae076f6dba3ac4cccb3922cc4616dc8a0">Correct. A positive feedback cycle contributes to the formation of the platelet plug (aggregation).</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab73ce0a3f3e64ea49758b24405c2092c">Incorrect. This is an example of negative feedback maintained near a set point, with increase or decrease of blood plasma osmolarity as necessary.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
