<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_functions_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="a800b0c73eb34681a2668eec04ec6846"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="af195a390b97f4ce684eadc6633fa1743">The lymphatic system is unique because it serves the body in two very important ways. How? Select the best answer.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="fdca3afd01e848668df3a53944f8670f" labels="false"><choice value="A">The lymphatic system helps the body by fighting against infectious agents and looking for abnormal cells that may cause cancer</choice><choice value="B">The lymphatic system both provides immunity and helps the tissues to keep proper fluid and molecular balance</choice><choice value="C">The lymphatic system drains fats from the intestinal track and it can sometimes cause autoimmune diseases</choice><choice value="D">The lymphatic system helps clean up cellular debris and dead bacteria while defining your own personal tissue type</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac203181d86714cbf99dcfe0fbf4a49e1">Incorrect. These are two functions of the immune system which is part of lymphatic function but ignores the role of the lymphatic vessels in fluid and electrolyte balance.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaf0849c41bf04a07a0a1ea8beba57dea">Correct. This answer describes the big picture of lymphatic function.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aaf1867f6beef402d9623541e51fd09e1">Incorrect. These are two functions of the lymphatic system but do not include all the others.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad7126fa0e4c641d4bf361c4858954c0c">Incorrect. These are two functions of the immune functions of the lymphatic system but do not include the roles of the lymph vessels.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page><page id="d00a98d82d62491e9b9b9e7277631f8d"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q2"><body><p id="c394d94ba7ee4cbeb923f8771c1fabb2">The lymphatic system contributes to the body’s homeostasis by performing which of the following <em style="bold">functions</em>?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="fe7b2735183a4baa932bcfa78ca7e8c0" labels="false"><choice value="A">Providing defense against invading foreign organisms</choice><choice value="B">Surveying for abnormal cells that could cause cancer</choice><choice value="C">Draining fluids away from the tissues and returning them to the blood</choice><choice value="D">Helping to move large molecules around the body</choice><choice value="E">All are corrrect</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae14e19fcee5b4e7c954126a060f215f7">Incorrect. This is only one of the important contributions the lymphatic system makes to homeostasis.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab939658329e84458a7d899a861a882b5">Incorrect. Cancer prevention is only one important function.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aec1a7a9a1ce843fab433445f21dd7ec5">Incorrect. While this function is essential it doesn’t take immunity into account.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aaf5c531fbd394dd982aaf279bcc601a6">Incorrect. This is very important for tissue homeostasis but ignores the rest of the body.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac404c16e5fc24feabf40a693210c22eb">Correct. These are all important functions.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page><page id="ef333a1ddf944137923ff2c171d3e8ab"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q3"><body><p id="af72cef85586944b38eeef3a5c4ed45e0">Sometimes when people have undergone extensive surgical or radiation procedures they experience abnormal levels of swelling and edema in the affected region. This complication is not from the disease but a result of the treatment. What is the best explanation?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="a2a5a43e8a5e40bc9678bb82de786675" labels="false"><choice value="A">The treatment has changed the molecular balance of their tissues and water has entered due to osmosis</choice><choice value="B">The IV that was inserted in their arm during the procedure put too much fluid in their system</choice><choice value="C">The lymph vessels were destroyed during the procedure and they can no longer drain the affected region properly</choice><choice value="D">A parasite has gotten into their body and clogged up a lymphatic vessel</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad45f5ad4da5541fab363a98072417f4b">Both of these treatments are physically disruptive and should not change the molecular content of the remaining healthy tissue</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad0ddc7bff6684346ae33a761d982bae6">Incorrect. If the IV added too much fluid to their system the person would experience overall swelling and edema not just swelling and edema in the affected body part</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac02a31d788624444a47bd5321a7c1568">Correct. If the lymphatic vessels are destroyed they cannot properly drain the tissue</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac3034a0f3fd849e2ad537ddd03bc1d30">Not the best answer. This scenario does actually happen but in this case it is more likely that the procedures destroyed the lymph vessels.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
