<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_diseases_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="c391c5fef0494129a1f9f390d28317ef"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="ab590cf84b55749bda3419f35d38cf0ce">Dysfunction of the lymphatic system seems to occur around one of two basic mechanisms; either the cells of the immune system respond to something which they should not or the cells lose their ability to function as they normally would. Which pairing with disease and mechanisms is correct?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="b6e4535c227d42b5926a488e1f01e9d9" labels="false"><choice value="A">Diabetes results from immune cells no longer making insulin</choice><choice value="B">Allergic reactions happen when the cells of the immune system respond to normal environmental elements</choice><choice value="C">HIV infection causes the immune cells to make too much antibody</choice><choice value="D">Autoimmune diseases happen when T cells divide too rapidly</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="af85bb989db2744e9a34310bcf3e14d08">Diabetes occurs when the cells of the immune system attack the beta cells in the pancreas that make insulin.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac15f9ea294aa4e95aa45798e02cbc780">Allergic reaction occurs when someone responds to something in the environment that should not stimulate a reaction normally</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa99331699a2d4c3688fd7ed3b8b4809f">Incorrect. HIV infection targets a subgroup of T cells and may eventually kill them.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aace900a9a946468986183e9ef9084321">Incorrect. Autoimmune diseases occur when the immune cells in the body attack other parts of the body.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="ab2b2f734c398415699612d3bd04d8811">Rheumatoid arthritis occurs when the immune system of the body attacks some of the structures found in the snynovial joints. It often becomes a downward spiralling circle. The autoimmune attack on the joint leads to degradation of the joint. Degradation of the joint stimulates the immune system even more so there is a further attack on the joint. What approach might be the best for getting this process under control?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="fc93bff2d32b44ae848bac479348d590" labels="false"><choice value="A">Give the patient antibiotics</choice><choice value="B">Look for a suitable donor to do a bone marrow transplant</choice><choice value="C">Give the patient antihistamines</choice><choice value="D">Give the patient some drugs which would temporarily reduce the activity of their immune cells.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="af07bd5158ee24c6abebbd8644ea8521c">. Incorrect. Antibiotics work on bacteria who are foreign invaders. Autoimmune diseases arise from the body attacking itself</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="afec15ccb9fde408c96b7de30a0251dc9">Incorrect. A bone marrow transplant is use to restore immune function if the cells of the immune system have died or can no longer function. It replaces all of the individual’s immune cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae0baf0f0414a47448a61f6a7909d76d3">Incorrect. Antihistamines help to control the inflammatory response associated with and allergic reaction. They will not be much help here.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaf4877aa5e684a7690cc15f093da5fd6">Correct. Giving the patient medicine to reduce the level of their immune response may stop any further damage and give the joint time to heal.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
