<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_dysfunction_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="bf613eee0b5e4160815f535a6876f2f8"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="af86efe4c389a4d9782794aa2fd5f5271">When the lymphatic structures of a limb are blocked due to tumors, what can result?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="c8a3787d26c4482cb8cdf9cbb376d8e2" labels="false"><choice value="A">Abnormally high lymph drainage from the distal region</choice><choice value="B">Severe localized edema distal to the blockage of that limb</choice><choice value="C">Shrinkage of tissues distal in the limb to the blockage, due to inadequate delivery of lymph</choice><choice value="D">Increased pressure in the lymphatics distal to the blockage</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_dysfunction_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abf4157e6922148eab260a095f1502ad5">Incorrect. If the lymph vessel is blocked there would be no drainage.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="af119ea644e324131a10fc626538c9546">Correct. Blockage of lymph vessels provokes edema, which is the accumulation of fluid in the tissues.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="abfdbd7c1a1344efba58eb80cbe7ae665">Incorrect. Tissues would not shrink for inadequate lymph delivery.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac9955bb76c234fbfb553f023cf36b516">Incorrect. Pressures tend to decrease distal to blockages.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="abd089c80be4d4d37bef98296cf01098f">The movements of fluids and molecules out of the blood capillaries and into the interstitial fluid obey the laws of chemistry and physics. High pressure in the capillary would physically force fluid out. Which chemical changes would make it more likely that fluid will leave the blood capillary and enter the tissues?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="e0038040414f48cf887e64ebc1cb2db2" labels="false"><choice value="A">High-salt diet</choice><choice value="B">Drinking too much water while running a marathon</choice><choice value="C">Kidney failure resulting in increased levels of circulating urea</choice><choice value="D">Intake of large amounts of caffeine</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_dysfunction_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aef54d675c9564079ae48be3d98d47ab1">Incorrect. A high-salt diet would increase the level of salt circulating in the blood and fluid would be retained in the vessel.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab0764d15c3514fc7bef3bc36c440c8ca">Correct. Overhydration will result in the blood being more dilute than the tissues, creating an osmotic gradient that allows fluids to leave the blood and enter the tissues.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aeeb888468b4a4214b7b40b4c84688c36">Incorrect. Kidney failure would put more urea and ammonia ( small molecules) in the blood, raising its osmotic pressure. The result is that fluid would leave the tissues and enter the blood.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="af09e65cd377e4370888bcef85eea6a57">Incorrect. Caffeine is a diuretic, causing fluids to leaviethe body and create a potential for dehydration.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
