<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_circulation_digt"><title>tutor</title><page id="c5b53c6966ac444a9c8e1c127343a8e5"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="aab7740d8cb4d4346aa2a71b104778e17">Which of the following is NOT a difference between lymphatic and blood circulation?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="a7fdbdd8dd2e4b19b743ac0908fc9ff2" labels="false"><choice value="A">Lymphatic capillaries are more permeable than blood capillaries.</choice><choice value="B">There is no pump in the lymphatic circulation.</choice><choice value="C">Lymphatic circulation is one-way.</choice><choice value="D">Skeletal muscle contraction helps flow in lymphatic circulation.</choice><choice value="E">All the above are differences between lymphatic and blood circulation.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_circulation_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aaf51d815e43449ffa572d6b2ee8aae6d">Incorrect. Indeed lymphatic capillaries allow passing of proteins while blood capillaries do not.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa2bda80e70484bee967b8c7cfae8e898">Incorrect. That is a difference: blood circulation has the heart as a pump, while lymphatic has no pump.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af85300551d7146b99ccf37e2d5e27ffb">Incorrect. That is a difference.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad9d73aaadc794daabbd6eb20a9546a2e">Correct. In both, contraction of skeletal muscles helps the flow of blood/lymph.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad322d83922ab41e9b55102e29b999d6b">Incorrect. There is one statement that refers to a common characteristic.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p id="aeef6060d253b4c468e421f5c4c92a525">Select the correct statement about lymph transport.</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="c98387702ff041309ab88504d0c6d46b" labels="false"><choice value="A">Lymph transport depends on the movement of adjacent tissues, such as skeletal muscles.</choice><choice value="B">Lymph transport is faster than that occurring in veins.</choice><choice value="C">Lymph transport is only necessary when illness causes tissue swelling.</choice><choice value="D">Under normal conditions, lymph vessels are very high-pressure conduits.</choice><choice value="E">All the above are correct.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_circulation_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac32730a1d8834cf5b8772e99f8b98672">Correct. Lymph transport is helped by the “massaging” action of muscles and the “sucking” action of the movement of the thoracic cage.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="afa7509bab06341ba913bb00dbd2bcc72">Incorrect. Because of its lack of a pump, the lymph transport is very slow.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa57fa2e77def471d9e4b333e6d4358c8">Incorrect. Lymph transport is necessary to return leaked fluids from the tissues to the blood.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="af7735ec0433e427bad0282ed244e70fa">Incorrect. Lymphatic vessels are leaky, low pressure vessels.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="ade885e94b07d491781549350626e70d3">Incorrect. There is only one correct statement.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page><page id="b7bd8b5a2f4c4715bd40d34928278c34"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q3"><body><p id="ae801019f56ce42428aa3f019143a35ed">Capillaries tend to leak. Consequently, the fluid that has leaked out of them needs to be drained away so that it does not accumulate in the the tissues. How is this accomplished?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="b27f64750e7c44feb3e19560755b0aae" labels="false"><choice value="A">The fluid, which is very much like serum, is collected through the blind end if the lymph capillary, then filtered through lymph nodes on the way to being returned to the cardiovascular system.</choice><choice value="B">The fluid leaks back into the capillaries and the proteins end up in the lymph.</choice><choice value="C">The fluid does accumulate, which is why your feet swell on an airplane.</choice><choice value="D">If there is an infection the lymph system picks things up, but otherwise the blood vessels do.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_circulation_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad3d33218c3564d3b910c5f161a1071e8">Correct. The lymph vessels pick up everything except the red and white blood cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aabfc362bf59d46a3ab778d0954afb2d8">Incorrect. Both the fluid and the proteins end up in the lymph.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad8251b7bb7b042e2bc7502fa11919051">Incorrect. Your feet swelling on the airplane is more because of the blood pooling, since venous return requires muscle movement in your legs.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad182b3f8b93d487da9e42dcf7add36cc">The lymph system collects fluid all the time, not just when there is an infection.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
