<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_immunity_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What could have been the “headline” of Edward Jenner’s discovery?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">“Neither innate nor adaptive, but both!”</choice><choice value="B">“Vaccinated individuals produce super-proteins to attack the invaders!”</choice><choice value="C">“The cause of anthrax revealed: it is minuscule!”</choice><choice value="D">“Boy injected with cowpox survives smallpox challenge!”</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_immunity_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In Jenner’s times nothing was known about innate or adaptive immunity.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It was only in the 20th century that the molecular nature of antibodies was discovered.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Koch’s discovery of anthrax&apos;s causative agent came in the late 1800s.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Jenner injected a young boy with cowpox fluid, and then with smallpox fluid. The boy did not get sick and the term &quot;vaccination&quot; was born.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>The lymph system is unique in that it provides an example of how structure and function and different levels of biological organization work together together to promote homeostasis. In terms of general immune function, which statement does not seem to fit?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The white blood cells contribute to innate immunity by attacking microbes in general, as well as contributing to adaptive immunity by making antibodies that specifically attack one antigen.</choice><choice value="B">The molecules inside and outside of the cell membrane contribute to the immune response. The ability to distinguish self from non-self lies on the external surface of the cell membrane. while the molecules needed to synthesize antibody proteins are found inside the cell.</choice><choice value="C">Complement is the name for a group of proteins that actively bind the body’s cells and destroy them.</choice><choice value="D">Activation of the innate and adaptive immune responses is enhanced by activation of the inflammatory response.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_immunity_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Different white blood cells participate in adaptive and innate immunity.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The major histocompatibility antigens are found on the external surface of the cell, while the machinery to synthesize proteins such as antibodies is found outside.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Complement attacks foreign cells; it does not attack the body’s own cells.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The inflammatory process is an integral part of immune response and the way the body maintains homeostasis.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
