<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="DNA Replication" >
    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation1.swf" menustep="Initiation phase: Introduction">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The enzymatic and structural features of DNA replication in all organisms are very similar.  These animations illustrate the processes involved in the replication of the Eschericia coli chromosome.  The names of the DNA sites, enzymes, and other protein factors differ in viruses and in eukaryotic organisms, however, the basic features have been highly conserved in evolution.

In E. coli, DNA replication begins at a single site on the chromosome called "OriC".&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation2.swf" menustep="        DnaA binding">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;A protein, dnaA, with a bound ATP binds to specific DNA sites at the E. coli origin of replication (oriC).&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation3.swf" menustep="        Open Complex formation">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Following ATP hydrolysis, a ~50 base pair region in OriC DNA is melted, i.e. unwound to form a single-stranded region called the "&lt;b&gt;open complex&lt;/b&gt;". &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation4.swf" menustep="        Prepriming Complex">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The region of the DNA at the junction of the unwound, single stranded DNA and the double stranded DNA is the &lt;b&gt;replication fork&lt;/b&gt;. Assembly of the two replication forks begins with the addition of a protein called a &lt;b&gt;helicase&lt;/b&gt; (dnaB).  A second protein (dnaC) acts as a helper protein to load the helicase protein into the "prepriming complex". &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation5.swf" menustep="        Helicase & Gyrase">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Helicase is required to extend the melted region of the open complex.

DNA gyrase is bound at many sites on the E. coli chromosome (only two are shown here). It uses energy from ATP hydrolysis to relieve the tension on the DNA created by the unwinding by the helicase enzyme. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation6.swf" menustep="        SSB protein">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Extension of the melted region requires the binding of single-stranded binding protein (SSB).  Coating the otherwise exposed DNA strands with SSB prevents reformation of the double stranded DNA.  SSB is required at all stages of the replication process.

In the following segments we will depict events at only one of the two replication forks.  The steps at both of the bidirectional forks are identical. 
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/initiation7.swf" menustep="        Replisome at one fork">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The final steps in the assembly of the "&lt;b&gt;replisome&lt;/b&gt;" start with the binding of the enzyme primase (orange) next to the helicase (red ring). RNA primers (red) are then synthesized on both strands at the fork.

Next, &lt;b&gt;DNA Polymerase III (DNA Pol III)&lt;/b&gt;, a large multi-subunit enzyme (blue ring and yellow sphere), binds to the template/primer complex.  The _-subunit (the blue ring) is responsible for maintaining binding of the enzyme to the DNA.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>

    <step stepURL="swfs/elongation.swf" menustep="Elongation of leading & lagging strands">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The RNA primers are extended by addition of new DNA using &lt;b&gt;DNA Pol III&lt;/b&gt; unidirectionally in the 5’ to 3’ direction (continuously on the leading strand and discontinuously on the lagging strand).  Synthesis of the daughter strands requires the unwinding of parental DNA by the helicase enzyme (with ATP hydrolysis).  The positive twists in the DNA that result from replication fork movement are removed by the enzyme DNA gyrase (with ATP hydrolysis).
 
Each DNA Pol III synthesizes DNA at about 500 to 1000 deoxynucleotides per second.  (This animation is a "super-slow motion" version of the real events, i.e. ~15 deoxynucleotides/min.)&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    
    <step stepURL="swfs/later_elongation.swf" menustep="Connecting the Lagging Strand">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;After a segment of DNA has been replicated, the ~1 kbase DNA-RNA fragments (&lt;b&gt;Okasaki fragments&lt;/b&gt;) on the lagging strand are modified by removal of the RNA segments and joining of the fragments to produce a continuous DNA strand.  

The 5'-->3' exonuclease activity of &lt;b&gt;DNA polymerase I (DNA Pol I)&lt;/b&gt; removes the RNA primers. The nucleotide monophosphates are released and recycled. The resulting small gap is filled-in by the 5'-->3' polymerase activity of DNA Pol I. When DNA Pol I dissociates, all complementary base pairs are formed, but there is still an unformed phosphodiester bond, a &lt;b&gt;nick&lt;/b&gt; in the DNA. &lt;b&gt;DNA ligase&lt;/b&gt; binds to this "nick" and "seals" it using energy from ATP hydrolysis.
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
</TUTORIAL>