<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_integumentary_inline01"><title>Function and Structure of the Integumentary System</title><page><question id="I_u1_m2_quest01_immunity_function"><body><p><em>How does the integumentary system contribute to immunity? </em></p></body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="gen_immune_cells">It produces immune cells.</choice><choice value="waterproof">It makes us waterproof.</choice><choice value="microorganisms">It feels when microorganisms are trying to enter.</choice><choice value="barrier">It provides a physical barrier to most microorganisms.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="I_u1_m2_quest01_immunity_function_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_integument_function_SKILL" /><response match="barrier" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The skin might actually be our most important immune organ because of this function. </feedback></response><response match="gen_immune_cells" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. That is the role of red bone marrow. </feedback></response><response match="waterproof" score="0"><feedback>Not quite. The integumentary system does make us waterproof, but that is not an immune function. </feedback></response><response match="microorganisms" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Microorganisms are too small to activate receptors. However, the skin has immune cells located in the epidermis called Langerhans cells. </feedback></response><hint>Open wounds often become infected. </hint></part></question><question id="I_u1_m2_quest02_merocrine"><body><p><em>Which glands are most common in the skin?</em></p></body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="merocrine">Merocrine sweat glands</choice><choice value="apocrine">Apocrine sweat glands</choice><choice value="sebaceous">Sebaceous glands</choice><choice value="digestive">Digestive glands</choice></multiple_choice><part id="I_u1_m2_quest02_merocrine_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_integument_function_SKILL" /><response match="merocrine" score="1"><feedback>Correct. We have merocrine sweat glands over most of our body to aid in the function of cooling when we get too hot. If you produce sweat on a region of your body, you have merocrine glands there. </feedback></response><response match="apocrine" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These glands are located only on specific regions of your body, such as the genital and axillary (armpit) regions.</feedback></response><response match="sebaceous" score="0"><feedback>Not quite. Sebaceous glands secrete sebum (an oily material composed mostly of fat) to help keep our skin and hair moisturized, but they are not as common as certain sweat glands.</feedback></response><response match="digestive" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The skin doesn&apos;t include digestive glands. </feedback></response><hint>Most of our skin has glands that help with thermal regulation, but most areas do not secrete complex materials.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
