<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_urinary_identify_extra_inline"><title>Identifying Urinary System Organs: Extra Questions</title><page><question id="I_u1_m2_urinary_extra_kidney"><body><p>Number 1 in the adjoining image points to the <input_ref input="kidney" />. </p><p>A key organ in the urinary system, this organ <input_ref input="filters" /> the blood and <input_ref input="reabsorbs" /> water, electrolytes, and ions needed to maintain optimal body fluid levels.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="kidney"><choice value="stomach">stomach</choice><choice value="kidney">kidney</choice><choice value="bladder">bladder</choice><choice value="urethra">urethra</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="filters"><choice value="adds_enzymes_to">adds enzymes to</choice><choice value="colors">colors</choice><choice value="filters">filters</choice><choice value="thickens">thickens</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="reabsorbs"><choice value="produces">produces</choice><choice value="reabsorbs">reabsorbs</choice><choice value="removes">removes</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="I_u1_m2_urinary_extra_kidney_p1" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_urinary_structure_SKILL" /><response input="kidney" match="kidney" score="1"><feedback>Correct. There are two kidneys located posterior to the abdominal cavity. The kidneys are the primary organs of the urinary system; they remove waste products from blood plasma and excrete the wastes as urine.</feedback></response><response input="kidney" match="stomach" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The stomach is an organ in the digestive system, and it is anterior to this organ.</feedback></response><response input="kidney" match="bladder" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The bladder stores the urine excreted as waste and is inferior to the organ you are trying to identify. </feedback></response><response input="kidney" match="urethra" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The urethra is the final passageway through which urine flows as it exits the body.</feedback></response><hint targets="kidney">This organ removes waste from blood, forming urine.</hint><hint targets="kidney">This organ looks like a type of bean that is often found in chili.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_urinary_extra_kidney_p2" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_urinary_function_SKILL" /><response input="filters" match="filters" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The kidneys filter waste products from the blood to remove urea and other toxins.</feedback></response><response input="filters" match="adds_enzymes_to" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Enzymes are complex proteins produced by cell metabolism. The main organ of the urinary system, the kidney, removes the waste produced by cell metabolism called urea and eliminates it as urine.</feedback></response><response input="filters" match="thickens" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The kidneys remove waste products resulting from cell metabolism; they do not thicken the blood.</feedback></response><response input="filters" match="colors" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The primary function of the urinary system is to remove waste products and toxins from blood plasma.</feedback></response><hint targets="filters">This process involves sifting through or sanitizing soluble substances in the blood to separate waste products and toxins from the water, ions and electrolytes that are reusable fluids needed by the body.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_urinary_extra_kidney_p3" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_urinary_function_SKILL" /><response input="reabsorbs" match="reabsorbs" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The kidneys filter soluble substances in the blood, discarding waste as urine and reabsorbing water, electrolytes, and ions needed to maintain body fluid levels within the optimal range (called homeostasis) for proper cell functioning.</feedback></response><response input="reabsorbs" match="produces" score="0"><feedback>This is a good guess, but it is not quite right. The water, electrolytes and ions already exist in blood plasma. The kidneys filter and reclaim these reusable fluids while discarding the waste products of cell metabolism.</feedback></response><response input="reabsorbs" match="removes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The kidneys remove waste products as urine, but keep reusable water, electrolytes and ions for optimal body fluid levels.</feedback></response><hint targets="reabsorbs">This process retains fluids needed by the body.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
