<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_endocrine_inline02"><title>Functions of the Endocrine System</title><page><question id="I_u1_m2_quest01_neurons"><body><p><em>How do functions of the endocrine system differ from functions of the nervous systems? </em></p></body><multiple_choice id="ans01" shuffle="true"><choice value="v1">Endocrine glands secrete signaling molecules, neurons do not.</choice><choice value="v2">The molecules secreted by endocrine glands are typically active longer and travel further than those secreted by neurons. </choice><choice value="v3">The endocrine system controls functions of the body. </choice><choice value="v4">Endocrine glands are found outside of the central nervous system, neurons are not. </choice></multiple_choice><part id="I_u1_m2_quest01_neurons_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_endocrine_function_SKILL" /><response match="v2" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Hormones typically have longer-lasting effects than neurotransmitters and by definition hormones travel through the bloodstream to act at a distant site, whereas neurotransmitters act at a very short distance across synapses. </feedback></response><response match="v1" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Neurons release neurotransmitters, which are signaling molecules, while endocrine glands secrete hormones.</feedback></response><response match="v3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Both systems play primary roles in controlling body functionsThis is true of both the endocrine glands and neurons.</feedback></response><response match="v4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some endocrine glands are found within the central nervous system (such as pituitary and pineal), and many neurons are found outside of the central nervous system in peripheral nerves. </feedback></response><hint>Both use chemical signaling, but the way the signaling occurs is different.</hint></part></question><question id="I_u1_m2_quest02_metalbolism"><body><p><em>Which gland secretes the hormones that most directly control metabolism? </em></p></body><multiple_choice id="ans02" shuffle="true"><choice value="pancreas">Pancreas</choice><choice value="parathyroid">Parathyroid</choice><choice value="thyroid">Thyroid</choice><choice value="thymus">Thymus</choice></multiple_choice><part id="I_u1_m2_quest02_metalbolism_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_endocrine_function_SKILL" /><response match="thyroid" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The thyroid hormone leads to many changes that cause cells to produce and utilize more ATP. </feedback></response><response match="pancreas" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Hormones from the pancreas regulate the fuel (glucose) levels in the blood, and have some effect on metabolism, but not as much as another hormone. </feedback></response><response match="parathyroid" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The parathyroid hormone regulates blood calcium levels. However, the gland you want is very close to this one. </feedback></response><response match="thymus" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The thymus is important for immune function.</feedback></response><hint>If you are low on this hormone, you will typically feel cold and lethargic. </hint></part></question></page></assessment>
