<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_cardiovascular_inline01"><title>Organs of the Cardiovascular System</title><page><question id="_u1_m2_cardiov01"><body>Which component of blood is most responsible for transporting oxygen?</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="platelets">platelets</choice><choice value="plasma">plasma</choice><choice value="red_blood_cells">red blood cells</choice><choice value="white_blood_cells">white blood cells</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u1_m2_cardiov01_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response match="plasma" score="0"><feedback>This is not the best answer. It turns out that the plasma does transport a small amount of oxygen, but you still need cells to carry the majority of it.</feedback></response><response match="red_blood_cells" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Red blood cells transport oxygen and carbon dioxide, Red blood cells are also called erythrocytes (&quot;eryth&quot; means &quot;red&quot; and &quot;cyte&quot; means &quot;cell&quot;). </feedback></response><response match="white_blood_cells" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. White blood cells play important roles in immunity; they rid the body of diseased cells.</feedback></response><response match="platelets" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The main role of platelets is to help stop bleeding (to maintain hemostasis).</feedback></response><no_response score="0"><feedback>Please try to answer the question.</feedback></no_response><hint>When oxygenated, these cells take on a red color.</hint></part></question><question id="_u1_m2_cardiov02"><body>Which structure is most responsible for generating the &quot;blood pressure&quot; that is measured in the doctor&apos;s office? </body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="arteries">arteries</choice><choice value="blood">blood</choice><choice value="heart">heart</choice><choice value="veins">veins </choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u1_m2_cardiov02_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response match="heart" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The heart generates the pressure. Measuring blood pressure is a way to determine heart and vascular (artery and vein) function. </feedback></response><response match="arteries" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Arteries and veins carry the pressure; arteries are high-pressure vessels that carry blood away from the heart. </feedback></response><response match="veins" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Arteries and veins carry the pressure; veins typically have low pressure in them.</feedback></response><response match="blood" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood is the fluid that the pressure is exerted upon, but it does not generate the pressure. </feedback></response><no_response score="0"><feedback>Please try to answer the question.</feedback></no_response><hint>This structure performs the most work, which generates pressure.</hint><hint>When your blood pressure is measured, it should be measured at the same level as this structure.</hint><hint>This is the structure that contracts to supply the force to move blood through the systemic circuit.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
