<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_nervousSys_inline01"><title>Functions of the Nervous System</title><page><question id="I_u1_m2_quest01_motorN"><body><p><em>If a motor nerve is cut, which of the following would happen? </em></p></body><multiple_choice id="ans01" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1">The muscle controlled by that particular nerve will not contract.</choice><choice value="v2">The bone the muscle is attached to will not move.</choice><choice value="v3">Certain motor reflexes may no longer function.</choice><choice value="v4">All of the above.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="I_u1_m2_quest01_motorN_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_nervous_function_SKILL" /><response match="v4" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Motor nerves control all of these things.</feedback></response><response match="v1" score="0"><feedback>This is not the best answer. It&apos;s true that the muscle will not be able to contract, but what else will this lead to? </feedback></response><response match="v2" score="0"><feedback>This is not the best answer. It&apos;s true that if the muscle cannot contract, the bone will not move. But that&apos;s not all that will happen. </feedback></response><response match="v3" score="0"><feedback>This is not the best answer. Reflexes do require information to be transmitted on motor nerves, but what else do motor nerves do? </feedback></response><hint>The nervous system controls many things. </hint></part></question><question id="I_u1_m2_quest02_autonomicNerves"><body><p><em>Which of the following functions are controlled by the autonomic nervous system? </em></p></body><multiple_choice id="ans02" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1">[A] Control of your gastrointestinal motility.</choice><choice value="v2">[B] Control of your heart rate.</choice><choice value="v3">[C] Control of your fingers.</choice><choice value="v4">[D] Control of your muscles of ventilation (for breathing).</choice><choice value="v5">Both A and B.</choice><choice value="v6">Both C and D.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="I_u1_m2_quest02_autonomicNerves_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_nervous_function_SKILL" /><response match="v5" score="1"><feedback>Correct. This is the best choice. The autonomic nervous system controls the automatic functions of the internal organs. It is, therefore, also called the involuntary nervous system. </feedback></response><response match="v1" score="0"><feedback>Not quite. This is correct, but there is also another correct answer. </feedback></response><response match="v2" score="0"><feedback>Not quite. This is correct, but there is also another correct answer.</feedback></response><response match="v3" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. You consciously control your fingers. </feedback></response><response match="v4" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is a tricky one. We typically don’t think about our breathing pattern, as it is controlled by some automatic (though not autonomic) nervous circuits. But we can override this automatic function if we decide to hold our breath, etc. </feedback></response><response match="v6" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Movement of the fingers and, to some extent, breathing, are actions consciously controlled with skeletal muscles. The autonomic nervous system controls the involuntary actions of the internal organs.</feedback></response><hint>If the function is carried out by skeletal muscle, it is not autonomic. </hint></part></question></page></assessment>
