<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_describe_skeletal_function_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Anne Smith is a 38 year old Caucasian female who was recently diagnosed with leukemia (cancer of the blood cells). She had undergone 2 rounds of chemotherapy and has to have blood work done to check her levels of red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets. Her last results showed a decrease in her red cells and platelets. Why might this have happened?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">Because the leukemia has destroyed the bone marrow so that it cannot undergo hemopoiesis.</choice><choice value="B">Because the chemotherapy is destroying the cancer and bone marrow so that it cannot undergo hemopoiesis.</choice><choice value="C">Because she is 36 years old and the production of red cells and platelets decreases with age.</choice><choice value="D">Because she has lost calcium salts from her bone and this has made her bones weaker.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="cd7f1c1bd9924dda8369226235528727"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_skeletal_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The bone marrow is damaged and unable to produce the cells, but it is not from the leukemia.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The chemotherapy is also damaging healthy cells and consequently interfering with the production of red blood cells and platelets.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Age doesn’t decrease bone marrow function.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Her bones might be weaker, but not from lost calcium salts; they aren’t producing blood cells.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
