<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m2_cardiovascular_identify_extra_inline"><title>Identifying Circuits of the Cardiovascular System: Extra Questions</title><page><question id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_PulmonaryCiruit"><body><image alt="Diagram of a Cardiovascular Curcuit" src="../webcontent/pulmonary_circuit-3.png" /><p>The above image illustrates the <input_ref input="pulmonary_circulatory_system" />, which transports blood between the heart and lungs. The <input_ref input="pulmonary_arteries" /> carry <input_ref input="oxygen_poor_blood" /> away from the heart to exchange gases in the lungs. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="pulmonary_circulatory_system"><choice value="blood_vessels">blood vessels</choice><choice value="pulmonary_circulatory_system">pulmonary circuit</choice><choice value="respiratory_system">respiratory system</choice><choice value="systemic_circulatory_system">systemic circuit system</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="pulmonary_arteries"><choice value="pulmonary_veins">pulmonary veins</choice><choice value="veins">veins</choice><choice value="pulmonary_arteries">pulmonary arteries</choice><choice value="aorta">aorta</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="oxygen_poor_blood"><choice value="oxygen_poor_blood">oxygen-poor blood</choice><choice value="oxygen_rich_blood">oxygen-rich blood</choice><choice value="oxygen">oxygen</choice><choice value="plasma">plasma</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_PulmonaryCiruit_p1" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_structure_SKILL" /><response input="pulmonary_circulatory_system" match="pulmonary_circulatory_system" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The pulmonary circuit transports blood into the lungs for the exchange of gases; carbon dioxide is removed from the blood and oxygen is added to it.</feedback></response><response input="pulmonary_circulatory_system" match="blood_vessels" score="0"><feedback>This is not the best choice. Blood flows to all tissues and organs of the body through vessels. This circuit of vessels specifically carries blood between the heart and lungs.</feedback></response><response input="pulmonary_circulatory_system" match="respiratory_system" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The respiratory system includes the lungs, where oxygen from the air moves into the blood and carbon dioxide is removed. The respiratory system, though, does not direct the flow of blood. A circuit of vessels controls the flow of blood into and out of the lungs. </feedback></response><response input="pulmonary_circulatory_system" match="systemic_circulatory_system" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The systemic circuit routes the flow of blood between the heart and all organs and tissues of the body except the lungs.</feedback></response><hint targets="pulmonary_circulatory_system">Notice this image shows the heart and lungs.</hint><hint targets="pulmonary_circulatory_system">This circulatory system obtains oxygenated blood for the body.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_PulmonaryCiruit_p2" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response input="pulmonary_arteries" match="pulmonary_arteries" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Pulmonary arteries direct the flow of blood from the heart into the lungs for the exchange of gases: carbon dioxide is removed and oxygen supplied to the blood.</feedback></response><response input="pulmonary_arteries" match="pulmonary_veins" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Pulmonary veins route oxygen-enriched blood from the lungs <em>into</em> the heart.</feedback></response><response input="pulmonary_arteries" match="veins" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Veins carry blood into the heart: Oxygen-depleted blood is transported through veins from the body into the heart. Oxygen-enriched blood flows through the pulmonary veins from the lungs into the heart.</feedback></response><response input="pulmonary_arteries" match="aorta" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oxygenated blood flows through the aorta from the left side of the heart into the body.</feedback></response><hint targets="pulmonary_arteries">These particular vessels carry blood to the lungs to pick up oxygen for the body and release carbon dioxide waste generated by cell metabolism.</hint><hint targets="pulmonary_arteries">These vessels connect to the right side of the heart in order to transport blood away from the heart and into the lungs.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_PulmonaryCiruit_p3" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response input="oxygen_poor_blood" match="oxygen_poor_blood" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Usually arteries carry oxygen-rich blood, but pulmonary arteries carry oxygen-poor blood. Remember that &quot;arteries&quot; go &quot;away&quot; from the heart.</feedback></response><response input="oxygen_poor_blood" match="oxygen_rich_blood" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Usually arteries carry oxygen-rich blood, but pulmonary arteries carry oxygen-poor blood. Remember that &quot;arteries&quot; go &quot;away&quot; from the heart.</feedback></response><response input="oxygen_poor_blood" match="oxygen" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oxygen is exchanged in the lungs. </feedback></response><response input="oxygen_poor_blood" match="plasma" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Plasma is carried also, but oxygen is poorly soluble in water and plasma.</feedback></response><hint targets="oxygen_poor_blood">This is the condition of the blood after it has traveled through the body providing oxygen and nutrients, and accumulating waste from cell metabolism. </hint></part></question></page><page><question id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_SystemicCiruit"><body><image alt="Cardiovascular Circulatory Systems" src="../webcontent/cirulatory_systems_systemic_v2.png" width="300" /><p>The image above illustrates the two major circuits of the cardiovascular system. Please complete the following sentences. </p><p>The heart pumps to send blood <input_ref input="circular_pattern" />. The <input_ref input="systemic_circulatory_system" /> pumps blood between the heart and all organs in the body, except for the lungs. In this circuit of vessels <input_ref input="arteries" /> carry oxygenated blood away from the heart and <input_ref input="veins" /> carry oxygen-depleted blood back to the heart. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="circular_pattern"><choice value="into_tissues">into tissues</choice><choice value="digestive">toward the digestive system</choice><choice value="circular_pattern">through blood vessels</choice><choice value="to_the_skin">to the skin</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="systemic_circulatory_system"><choice value="pulmonary_circulatory_system">pulmonary circuit</choice><choice value="respiratory_system">respiratory system</choice><choice value="digestive_system">digestive system</choice><choice value="systemic_circulatory_system">systemic circuit</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="arteries"><choice value="red_blood_cells">capillaries</choice><choice value="arteries">arteries</choice><choice value="pulmonary_veins">pulmonary veins</choice><choice value="veins">veins</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="veins"><choice value="arteries">arteries</choice><choice value="pulmonary_arteries">pulmonary arteries</choice><choice value="white_blood_cells">white blood cells</choice><choice value="veins">veins</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_SystemicCiruit_p1" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response input="circular_pattern" match="circular_pattern" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Blood in the circulatory system moves through arteries, veins and capillaries. </feedback></response><response input="circular_pattern" match="into_tissues" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The circulatory system is responsible for moving fluids to most of the body tissues, but most blood is contained in vessels. </feedback></response><response input="circular_pattern" match="digestive" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The circulatory system does move blood to the digestive system, but also moves it throughout the rest of the body, and always through vessels. </feedback></response><response input="circular_pattern" match="to_the_skin" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The circulatory system does move blood to the skin, but also moves it throughout the rest of the body, and always through vessels. </feedback></response><hint targets="circular_pattern">These structures carry blood to specific organs.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_SystemicCiruit_p2" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response input="systemic_circulatory_system" match="systemic_circulatory_system" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The systemic circulatory system routes blood flow between the heart and all parts of the body except the lungs, to provide oxygen and collect waste from cell metabolism.</feedback></response><response input="systemic_circulatory_system" match="pulmonary_circulatory_system" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pulmonary circulatory system directs blood flow between the heart and lungs.</feedback></response><response input="systemic_circulatory_system" match="respiratory_system" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The respiratory system includes the lungs, where oxygen from the air moves into the blood and carbon dioxide is removed.</feedback></response><response input="systemic_circulatory_system" match="digestive_system" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The digestive system does not control the flow of blood; it breaks down food and water, providing nutrients for absorption into the blood.</feedback></response><hint targets="systemic_circulatory_system">This circuit of blood vessels covers the entire body except for one organ.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_SystemicCiruit_p3" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response input="arteries" match="arteries" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Arteries transport oxygen-enriched blood from the heart to all organs and tissues of the body except the lungs. </feedback></response><response input="arteries" match="red_blood_cells" score="0"><feedback>Not quite. Red blood cells contain the oxygen obtained during gas exchange in the lungs, but red blood cells are only one of the components of blood. You are asked to identify the blood vessels that transport oxygenated blood and all of its components. </feedback></response><response input="arteries" match="pulmonary_veins" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pulmonary veins carry oxygenated blood from the lungs <em>into</em> the heart.</feedback></response><response input="arteries" match="veins" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Veins return oxygen-poor blood back to the heart after the blood has coursed through the body and accumulated waste from cell metabolism.</feedback></response><hint targets="arteries">Arteries carry oxygenated blood away from the heart and veins carry oxygen-depleted blood back to the heart.</hint></part><part id="I_u1_m2_cardiovascular_extra_SystemicCiruit_p4" score_out_of="1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_cardio_function_SKILL" /><response input="veins" match="veins" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Veins are the vessels that transport oxygen-poor blood back to the heart after the blood has traveled throughout the body providing oxygen and accumulating waste from cell metabolism. </feedback></response><response input="veins" match="arteries" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Arteries transport oxygen-enriched blood away from the heart to the body. </feedback></response><response input="veins" match="pulmonary_arteries" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Pulmonary arteries are the vessels that carry oxygen-poor blood away from the heart and into the lungs for the exchange of gases.</feedback></response><response input="veins" match="white_blood_cells" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. White blood cells are only one component of the blood that travels through all blood vessels.</feedback></response><hint targets="veins">Veins are under lower pressure since they are returning to the heart.</hint><hint targets="veins">Arteries and veins are the major types of blood vessels. Arteries carry blood away from the heart.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
