<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="functions_of_respiratory_system"><title>Tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The respiratory system functions to?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Transport oxygen and carbon dioxide in the blood</choice><choice value="B">Exchange oxygen and carbon dioxide with the environment</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_respiratory_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. the respiratory system does not transport the gasses, that is the role of the cardiovascular system.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="1"><feedback>Correct. When we breath we move air and respiratory gasses in and out of our lungs.</feedback></response><hint>The respiratory system uses pulmonary ventilation or breathing to accomplish this role.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>If there was an obstruction in the trachea, which of the following would you expect?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="A">a decrease in blood carbon dioxide levels</choice><choice value="B">an increase in blood carbon dioxide levels</choice><choice value="C">a decrease in blood oxygen levels</choice><choice value="D">both, a decrease in blood carbon dioxide levels and a decrease in blood oxygen levels</choice><choice value="E">both an increase in blood carbon dioxide levels and a decrease in blood oxygen levels</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_describe_respiratory_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the trachea is blocked carbon dioxide cannot leave the lungs and will accumulate in the blood.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the trachea is blocked carbon dioxide will accumulate becasue it cannot leave but what else?</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Incorrect. If the trachea is blocked, oxygen (air) cannot enter the lungs and will not pass into the blood but what else will occur?</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Remember carbon dioxide and oxygen move in opposite directions.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback>Correct. If there is an obstruction in the trachea air and the oxygen in it cannot enter the lungs nor leave to eliminate carbon dioxide.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the direction oxgyen and carbon dioxide move when we breath.</hint><hint>If the trachea is blocked, can air get in or out of the lungs?</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
