<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_hormone_stimulus"><title>DynaDrop Assessment</title><question id="hormone_stimulus"><body><p><em style="bold">Match the hormone with the stimulus for release.</em></p><custom id="dragDrop" src="../../../webcontent/DynaDropHTML.js" type="javascript" width="600" height="200" layout="../webcontent/urinary_hormone_stimulus_layout.xml" logging="true"><param name="showInputs">false</param></custom></body><fill_in_the_blank id="aldosterone" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Aldosterone</choice><choice value="B">Angiotensin II</choice><choice value="C">Antidiuretic hormone</choice><choice value="D">Atrial natriuretic peptide</choice><choice value="E">Parathyroid hormone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="angiotensin_I_I" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Aldosterone</choice><choice value="B">Angiotensin II</choice><choice value="C">Antidiuretic hormone</choice><choice value="D">Atrial natriuretic peptide</choice><choice value="E">Parathyroid hormone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="antidiuretic_hormone" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Aldosterone</choice><choice value="B">Angiotensin II</choice><choice value="C">Antidiuretic hormone</choice><choice value="D">Atrial natriuretic peptide</choice><choice value="E">Parathyroid hormone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="atrial_natriuretic_peptide" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Aldosterone</choice><choice value="B">Angiotensin II</choice><choice value="C">Antidiuretic hormone</choice><choice value="D">Atrial natriuretic peptide</choice><choice value="E">Parathyroid hormone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="parathyroid_hormone" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Aldosterone</choice><choice value="B">Angiotensin II</choice><choice value="C">Antidiuretic hormone</choice><choice value="D">Atrial natriuretic peptide</choice><choice value="E">Parathyroid hormone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="identify_hormones_control_absorption" /><skillref idref="identify_ADH" /><response input="aldosterone" match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Aldosterone release is directly stimulated by high plasma concentrations of potassium. Aldosterone release is also stimulated by angiotensin II. The insertion of more sodium transporters in the collecting ducts results in increased leakage of potassium to the collecting duct lumen. </feedback></response><response input="aldosterone" match="B"><feedback>Incorrect. Aldosterone does have an effect on blood pressure, but aldosterone release is directly stimulated by high plasma concentrations of potassium. Aldosterone release is also stimulated by angiotensin II. The insertion of more sodium transporters in the collecting ducts results in increased leakage of potassium to the collecting duct lumen. </feedback></response><response input="aldosterone" match="C"><feedback>Incorrect. Antidiuretic hormones act to decrease urine production by increasing the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct. Aldosterone acts to increase plasma potassium concentration which results in increased leakage of potassium to the collecting duct lumen. </feedback></response><response input="aldosterone" match="D"><feedback>Incorrect. Atrial natriuretic peptide is released from the heart in response to large increases in blood volume. Conversely, aldosterone is activated when blood volume and blood pressure decrease. </feedback></response><response input="aldosterone" match="E"><feedback>Incorrect. Aldosterone release is directly stimulated by high plasma concentrations of potassium. Aldosterone release is also stimulated by angiotensin II. The insertion of more sodium transporters in the collecting ducts results in increased leakage of potassium to the collecting duct lumen. B. Angiotensin II </feedback></response><hint>What does each of these hormones regulate?</hint><hint>What do the sensory receptors that initiate the reflexes responsible for the release of each of these hormones respond to?</hint></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="identify_hormones_control_absorption" /><skillref idref="name_atrial_peptide" /><response input="angiotensin_I_I" match="A"><feedback>Incorrect. Angiotensin II production is stimulated by reduced blood volumes, blood pressure, or reduced plasma concentrations of sodium. </feedback></response><response input="angiotensin_I_I" match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Angiotensin II production is stimulated by reduced blood volumes, blood pressure, or reduced plasma concentrations of sodium. </feedback></response><response input="angiotensin_I_I" match="C"><feedback>Incorrect. Antidiuretic hormones are stimulated to act in decreasing urine production by increasing the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct. Angiotensin II production is stimulated by reduced blood volumes, blood pressure, or reduced plasma concentrations of sodium. </feedback></response><response input="angiotensin_I_I" match="D"><feedback>Incorrect. Angiotensin II production is stimulated by reduced blood volumes, blood pressure, or reduced plasma concentrations of sodium. Conversely, atrial natriuretic peptide is released from the heart in response to large increases in blood volume. </feedback></response><response input="angiotensin_I_I" match="E"><feedback>Incorrect. Angiotensin II production is stimulated by reduced blood volumes, blood pressure, or reduced plasma concentrations of sodium. </feedback></response><hint>What does each of these hormones regulate?</hint><hint>What do the sensory receptors that initiate the reflexes responsible for the release of each of these hormones respond to?</hint></part><part id="p3"><skillref idref="identify_hormones_control_absorption" /><skillref idref="name_parathyroid" /><response input="antidiuretic_hormone" match="A"><feedback>Incorrect. ADH is stimulated by increased plasma osmolarity. </feedback></response><response input="antidiuretic_hormone" match="B"><feedback>Incorrect. ADH is stimulated by increased plasma osmolarity. </feedback></response><response input="antidiuretic_hormone" match="C"><feedback>Incorrect. Antidiuretic hormones are stimulated to act in decreasing urine production by increasing the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct. They are not stimulated by an increase in plasma potassium concentration, reduced blood pressure, or by decreased calcium ions. </feedback></response><response input="antidiuretic_hormone" match="D"><feedback>Incorrect. While ADH acts to decrease urine production by increasing the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct, atrial natriuretic peptide is released from the heart in response to large increases in blood volume. </feedback></response><response input="antidiuretic_hormone" match="E"><feedback>Incorrect. ADH is stimulated by increased plasma osmolarity. </feedback></response></part><part id="p4"><response input="atrial_natriuretic_peptide" match="A"><feedback>Incorrect. ANP is stimulated by increased stretch and pressure in the atria due to an increase in blood volume. </feedback></response><response input="atrial_natriuretic_peptide" match="B"><feedback>Incorrect. ANP is stimulated by increased stretch and pressure in the atria due to an increase in blood volume. </feedback></response><response input="atrial_natriuretic_peptide" match="C"><feedback>Incorrect. Antidiuretic hormones are stimulated to act in decreasing urine production by increasing the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct. Atrial natriuretic peptide is stimulated by increased stretch and pressure in the atria due to an increase in blood volume. </feedback></response><response input="atrial_natriuretic_peptide" match="D"><feedback>Incorrect. Where Parathyroid hormone (PTH) reacts in response to a reduced concentration of calcium ions in the blood, atrial natriuretic peptide is released from the heart in response to large increases in blood volume. </feedback></response><response input="atrial_natriuretic_peptide" match="E"><feedback>Incorrect. ANP is stimulated by increased stretch and pressure in the atria due to an increase in blood volume. </feedback></response></part><part id="p5"><response input="parathyroid_hormone" match="A"><feedback>Incorrect. PTH is stimulated by low levels of plasma calcium. </feedback></response><response input="parathyroid_hormone" match="B"><feedback>Incorrect. PTH is stimulated by low levels of plasma calcium. </feedback></response><response input="parathyroid_hormone" match="C"><feedback>Incorrect. Antidiuretic hormones are stimulated to act in decreasing urine production by increasing the permeability of principal cells in the late distal convoluted tubule and the collecting duct. Parathyroid hormones are stimulated by low levels of plasma calcium and acts to reduce blood pressure in response to the reduced concentration of calcium ions in the blood. </feedback></response><response input="parathyroid_hormone" match="D"><feedback>Incorrect. Atrial natriuretic peptides are released from the heart in response to large increases in blood volume.They are not stimulated by an increase in plasma potassium concentration, reduced blood pressure, or by decreased calcium ions. </feedback></response><response input="parathyroid_hormone" match="E" score="10"><feedback>Correct. PTH is stimulated by low levels of plasma calcium. </feedback></response><hint>What does each of these hormones regulate?</hint><hint>What do the sensory receptors that initiate the reflexes responsible for the release of each of these hormones respond to?</hint></part></question></assessment>
