<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_skel_homeostasis_04"><title>Bone Response to Force</title><content><p>Starting an exercise program is an excellent way to improve bone strength and also has beneficial effects on the cardiovascular, immune, and muscular systems. Exercise stresses the bones which causes cells to respond. </p><p>Which is true of the cellular response to stress? </p></content><question id="skel_homeo_02"><body>The cells that sense forces on bone are the _________? <input_ref input="control" />.</body><fill_in_the_blank id="control" shuffle="false"><choice value="osteoblasts">osteoblasts</choice><choice value="osteoclasts">osteoclasts</choice><choice value="osteocytes">osteocytes</choice><choice value="none">chondrocytes</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="skel_homeo_02_p1"><skillref idref="skeletal_homeo_bone_force_SKILL" /><response match="osteoblasts" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteoblasts are important for bone growth and remodeling, but they do not directly sense forces on bone. </feedback></response><response match="osteoclasts" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteoclasts are important for bone remodeling, but they do not directly sense forces on bone.</feedback></response><response match="osteocytes" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osteocytes sense the amount of stress on the bone in their “area”.</feedback></response><response match="none" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.Chondrocytes are important in cartilage, not bone.</feedback></response><hint>Hint: These are a fully mature cell type.</hint></part></question><question id="skel_homeo_03"><body>In regions of bone that are experiencing high levels of force, which cells most directly stimulate bone growth?<input_ref input="effect" />.</body><fill_in_the_blank id="effect" shuffle="false"><choice value="osteoblasts">osteoblasts</choice><choice value="osteoclasts">osteoclasts</choice><choice value="osteocytes">osteocytes</choice><choice value="none">chondroblasts</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="skel_homeo_03_p1"><skillref idref="skeletal_homeo_bone_force_SKILL" /><response match="osteoblasts" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osteoblasts build bone, which is beneficial in areas of bone experiencing high levels of force (stress).</feedback></response><response match="osteoclasts" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteoclasts break down bone. Although they always have some level of activity, it would be less in areas that are adding bone mass.</feedback></response><response match="osteocytes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Osteocytes are mature bone cells that sense forces, but they do not directly build bone.</feedback></response><response match="none" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Chondroblasts are active in cartilage, not bone.</feedback></response><hint>Hint: this cell is not fully differentiated yet, as indicated by its suffix.</hint></part></question></assessment>
