<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u13_homeo_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Lymphatic Homeostasis</title><page id="f53d2ac6ca1f47b18e3df5a746014c8d"><multiple_choice id="q5" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ade63752dbf1942a7a2ca3aa8f3ca97f6">Sometimes the immune system appears to get confused and it starts mount an immune response against the the body&apos;s own tissues. What is this referred to as?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="fe06c4630ec446c78cf6b2b1bdc1f440" labels="false"><choice value="A">Autoimmune disease</choice><choice value="B">Graft-versus-host disease</choice><choice value="C">Lymphedema</choice><choice value="D">Lymphoma</choice></input><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="aee8f4a8db840420ca92e0a02e709e51c">Correct.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac6a9dd24809343fb93cb311da8ff8911">Incorrect. Graft-versus-host disease occurs when the white blood cells found in donor tissue attack the transplant recipient.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af3b68570f5944356966e30438ab8fa65">Incorrect. Lymphedema refers to swelling in a limb or section of the body because the lymph system is not properly draining that tissue.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="acf8264f0d43e430bbefeaf16a06e5d56">Incorrect. Lymphoma is a cancerous condition in which the white blood cells are reproducing out of control.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q24" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aac18e3e9900b467aad00b189136e45a7">One of the results of the inflammatory response is accumulation of fluid in the affected area (edema). This happens in response to tissue injury such as a sprained ankle or an infection caused by a splinter in one’s finger. Select the correct statement from the choices below.</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="fb6ecd8e5aae475ea8bfb84a54384f68" labels="false"><choice value="A">Activation of the inflammatory response does not indicate a disruption of homeostasis. Presence of extra fluid in the tissues directly activates the innate immune response.</choice><choice value="B">The lymph vessels will eventually drain away the excess fluid. The kinin-kallikrein system causes capillary leakage resulting in edema.</choice><choice value="C">Swelling from tissue injury happens because your body makes excess fluid in that area.</choice><choice value="D">The lymph vessels will bring in the cells from the immune system to fight any potential infection.</choice><choice value="E">Tissue edema does not involve the lymphatic system</choice></input><part id="q24_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab14be500627e4919b76cfc5dc99d3cba">Incorrect. The activation of the inflammatory response is an indicator that homeostasis has been disrupted.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="abd01a11db1f140d9a56c43868f3f51ce">Correct. The lymph vessels will eventually drain away the excess fluid.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad9acef778ec74bbeb5aa90e38a887ad3">Incorrect. The body doesn’t make excess tissue fluid it accumulates because of the kinin-kallikrien system stimulates vasodilation and capillary leakage.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa9342f390dbe49a0a8307fcb5aea395b">Incorrect. The main function of lymph vessels is to drain tissues, not cellular transport.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="add25b7a045f34ac08f87122142415aaa">Incorrect. Resolution of tissue swelling requires a fully functioning lymph system.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q35" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="afff010c889724832aba9e61616f66946">T cells come in several varieties. Cytotoxic T cells are important because they can become activated and kill target cells. Which of the following are not needed directly for Cytotoxic T cell activation?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="d279acea6daf4f5393f91e46f5e967e8" labels="false"><choice value="A">Cytokines</choice><choice value="B">Interferons</choice><choice value="C">Complement</choice><choice value="D">Antibodies</choice><choice value="E">All are correct</choice></input><part id="q35_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_CMIR_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa395eea9326e4ec99a9a12dae47e063d">Incorrect. Cytokines do not play a specific role in the activation of Cytotoxic T cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad5416d96d3ec4289beb76f150d409c78">Incorrect. Interferons, are part of a response against viruses.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ada11200b77fa42ab892f2db43368cbeb">Incorrect. Complement does not play a part in the way Cytotoxic T cells kills cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ada7ce744bcf74c7f85e032b18da00bfa">Incorrect. Antibodies do not play a role here either.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac9257f91000b492ea2627b408e47696c">Correct. None of these choices is needed for Cytotoxic T cell activation.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
