<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u13_integration_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Lymphatic Integration of Systems</title><page id="c880c02fcaff4ba99ef47d2fc5017d39"><multiple_choice id="q1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa5653f57a460425f90b02f3e944be4b0">Two clinical laboratory tests often encountered students are an antibody titer for mononucleosis and a PPD to check for tuberculosis. The test for mononucleosis involves taking a sample of blood and looking for antibodies against the Epstein-Barr virus which causes mono. The TB test involves an injection of a small amount of material under the surface of the skin and looking for a reaction 72 hours later. Which kinds of immunity are being assessed in these tests?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="aa1970cb1cfc4ab1ad65a97ca0a0b017" labels="false"><choice value="A">The mono test is humoral and the TB test is an allergy test.</choice><choice value="B">The mono test is looking at interferon levels and the TB test is looking at cell mediated immunity.</choice><choice value="C">The mono test only indicates if you have been exposed to mono. The TB test lets you know if you have an active TB infection.</choice><choice value="D">The mono test is looking at humoral immunity and the TB test is looking at cell mediated memory.</choice></input><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="af8ee8e65dc2e46c0bb034ee2eac0f94a">Incorrect. The mono test is looking at antibody production which is humoral immunity but the TB test is not an allergy since takes days to develop.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="adb5ff3d562d845049ee819dd5e6dad03">Incorrect. Antibody titer is a measure of humoral immunity.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aae51f15e255144118c99910ffabfb459">Incorrect. High levels of antibody would indicate and on-going infection while low levels may indicate previous exposure. The TB test only lets you know if you have been exposed not if you have an active infection.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="acb66a21a1de141189da9568ed1dcccf6">Correct. Antibody titers are indicators of a humoral immune response. The TB test is really only indicates if you cell mediated response has encountered the tuberculosis bacillus before.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa156f356429947fe9a19228ec14cf385">Vaccines are not always effective in patients who are immunocompromised. Why?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="e32a038c6bbc4066b57012e9fc3055ff" labels="false"><choice value="A">You need a fully functioning immune system for a vaccine to be able to stimulate the immune response enough to create memory cells.</choice><choice value="B">Only healthy people have immune responses.</choice><choice value="C">Chemotherapy destroys rapidly dividing cells so the NK cells may not working.</choice><choice value="D">AIDs patients have low levels of B cells so they don’t get a response.</choice></input><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac4130e439ad941ecba05f209d71e281b">Correct. Vaccines require all of the cell types of the immune system to function to be effective.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa6f6de6a0e2a44079fa1acf3701e5ab7">Incorrect. Immunocompromised individuals may have functioning immune systems that just may not be as effective.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af90a3c78fdbd43bcbdaf8237ca00ca76">Incorrect. NK cells are not part of the vaccination process.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="acc933413cf4042f3a7182396bff02d18">Incorrect. AIDs patients have low level of Helper- T cells so they often do not get a good response.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q3" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abefb431e72794122afb82981af94d2f7">The lymphatic and immune systems protect the entire body. Sometimes the protection doesn’t work the way it is supposed to. Many people have had Streptococcus infections such as &quot;strep throat.&quot; In some patients, the antibodies resulting from the immune response to Streptococcus may attack the endothelial cells of the heart, causing life-threatening conditions. What is this an example of?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="bfc0e13cc86c4e0084cf28c67f1a7a3a" labels="false"><choice value="A">Streptococcus toxins attacking the heart tissue</choice><choice value="B">Antibodies triggering a reaction against cells that are not really harmful, much like an autoimmune response</choice><choice value="C">The inflammatory process targeting the cardiovascular system</choice><choice value="D">The cardiovascular system making the heart pump harder because it is under attack</choice></input><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aeb922ab62d754488a4cc50b58663468d">Incorrect. In this situation it is the antibodies that are attacking healthy heart tissue.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="acf8d13b186f2465a982375482649d650">Correct. Even though a pathogen stimulated antibody reaction the antibodies are now attacking healthy cells.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="adc48c92a28de4e54b8773b5709f30b42">Incorrect. It is not the inflammatory response that starts the problem.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac0c24e2ed1804633ae57a735ea5dddce">Incorrect. The heart tissue is being attacked there is no physiological response to stimulate an increased heart rate.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q4" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa81ec150d83943a5825e6727d5859131">The lymphatic system affects the body’s functioning in many ways. Which statement best describes all of the ways the lymphatic system contributes to homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="faacc5b0e3924cad8c0f7da5fb8aca3c" labels="false"><choice value="A">The lymphatic system responds to irritants like poison ivy by initiating allergic reactions and helps to transport lipids from the intestinal system.</choice><choice value="B">The lymphatic system contributes to keeping blood pressure low by draining off excess fluid from the tissues and it helps to keep the tissues free from cellular debris.</choice><choice value="C">The lymphatic system fights off infections from invading foreign organisms.</choice><choice value="D">The lymphatic system helps to control the fluid levels in the tissues by providing a conduit to return the fluids and other dissolved molecules in the blood plus it contributes to our health by providing a defense against pathogens, plus the lymphatic system provides a means for the digestive system to send fats and other large molecules to the liver for processing.</choice></input><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad02fec93af6a4cfb85134e32bbf8a9e1">Incorrect. The allergic reaction does not contribute to homeostasis it disrupts it.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abb67714a6ff944859249f24cfe22ceb7">Incorrect. This answer does not include the digestive system functions.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aecab192b73104795ad62fba2e0c58c16">Incorrect. This answer only includes one aspect of lymphatic function.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="aad7754217c544c05b4cb3c3922c3b3fe">Correct. The three main functions of the lymphatic system are 1) removal of fluid and debris from the interstitial fluid, 2) immune response, and 3) transport of fats.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q36" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abd6894a9e8384561890e8e651cb22630">Infectious mononucleosis (“mono”) is a common disease among adolescents and young adults. It is caused by infection of epithelial cells and B lymphocytes by EBV (Epstein-Barr virus). One way to help diagnose the disease is to test for presence of antibodies against EBV. Which of the following statements referring to antiviral mechanisms is incorrect?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f52091a6f70e403ab0976c89f473bfb9" labels="false"><choice value="A">Presence of anti-EBV IgM antibodies signals a recent infection.</choice><choice value="B">Macrophages produce alpha-interferons as part of the innate immune response.</choice><choice value="C">Complement activation does not always require presence of antibodies.</choice><choice value="D">NK cells can attack virally infected cells without antigenic presentation.</choice><choice value="E">Cytotoxic T cells can kill virally infected cells using perforins and granzymes.</choice></input><part id="q36_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa1e3deb1d05f44aea814f461ea827a6c">Incorrect. Indeed, IgM is the first antibody produced during an infection.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="abf475eef131b4b7e81ac183d76b1e228">Correct. Macrophages do not produce alpha-interferons.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae1a479962d2244ef97c6ae1966692bef">Incorrect. Complement can indeed be activated through 3 pathways, only one involving antibodies.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac0183153585e4b1d89ca236132b33314">Incorrect. NK cells indeed kill virus-infected cells as part of the innate response.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="aec8b180a20fa4c78b3b37998364d102e">Incorrect. Cytotoxic T cells can indeed kill using those mechanisms.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q37" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af282618c9f6846d19d8b22f560ea7908">Tuberculosis is a disease caused by the bacterium Mycobacterium tuberculosis, and can be latent or active. The Mantoux test (PPD) involves the injection of the TB antigen under the skin and waiting 72 hours. The presence of a hard, raised area signals the presence of a cellular immune response. Based on your knowledge of the immune system, which of the following statements best interprets a positive PPD test?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="e5a114a473cd4ddabe262c27a60513e1" labels="false"><choice value="A">The individual is mounting an innate immune response to the TB antigen.</choice><choice value="B">The individual is mounting a primary antibody response to the TB antigen.</choice><choice value="C">The individual has had a previous exposure to the TB antigen reflected in a hypersensitivity reaction.</choice><choice value="D">The individual has had a previous exposure to TB reflected in a high antibody titer.</choice><choice value="E">The individual has an active TB infection.</choice></input><part id="q37_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_integration_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab9095e1da358490ab6600746daf64d61">Incorrect. 72 hours is too long for an innate response.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae9930ae2f1cf4af8877f2a3664a6d7a2">Incorrect. 72 hours is too quick for a primary antibody response.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab918ee353c3044079e27eb0887b02c46">Correct. The induration is a reflection of recruitment of immune cells to the site of injection.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac61dc4d4953a4fca86f8abde1f1ae072">Incorrect. the PPD test does not provide antibody titers.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac317a670739d4790adb0ea3b2a2f1701">Incorrect. There is no way to know this from the PPD test.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
