<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="param_v_statistic_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_param_v_statistic" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>In June 2015, Gallup conducted a poll of a random sample of 14,683 adults to
                determine the well-being of people living in the United States. One question asked,
                “Did you exercise at least 30 minutes for 3 or more days in the past week?” In the
                survey, 58.9% of males and 52.7% of females responded yes to this question. Which of
                the following is true about this scenario? </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">58.9% and 52.7% are both parameters. </choice>
            <choice value="B">58.9% and 52.7% are both statistics. </choice>
            <choice value="C">If we took another random sample of 14,683 adults, we would expect to
                get the exact same results.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Parameters are values that refer to a population. We would need
                    to take a census of all adults in the United States for these values to be
                    parameters. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since the survey results are obtained from the sample, these are
                    all statistics. Due to sampling variability, if we were to take a different
                    sample of the same size we would not expect to get the same sample results.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Due to sampling variability we cannot expect to get the exact
                    same answers from a new poll. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_param_v_statistic" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>In June 2005, a survey was conducted in which a random sample of 1,464 U.S. adults
                was asked the following question: "In 1973 the Roe versus Wade decision established
                a woman's constitutional right to an abortion, at least in the first three months of
                pregnancy. Would you like to see the Supreme Court completely overturn its Roe
                versus Wade decision, or not?" </p>
            <p>The results were: Yes—30%, No—63%,
                Unsure—7% (<em style="italic">Source</em>:
                www.Pollingreport.com) </p>
            <p>Which of the following is true about this scenario? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">30%, 63%, and 7% are all parameters. </choice>
            <choice value="B">30%, 63%, and 7% are all statistics. </choice>
            <choice value="C">If another random sample of size 1,464 U.S. adults were
                to be chosen, we would expect to get the exact same distribution of answers.
            </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. When discussing parameters, we are referring to the actual
                    value of certain variables relating to the population. In this example, if we
                    were able to poll all U.S. adults and have everyone respond to the poll, then
                    these numbers would be parameters.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since the survey results are obtained from the sample, these are
                    all statistics. Due to sampling variability, if we were to take a different
                    sample of the same size we would not expect to get the same sample results.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Due to sampling variability, we cannot expect to get the same
                    sample results from multiple samples.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
