<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="recog_samp_distrib_norm_1_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_recog_samp_distrib_norm_1" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>A political polling agency wants to take a random sample of registered voters and ask
                whether or not they will vote for a certain candidate. One plan is to select 400
                voters, another plan is to select 1,600 voters. </p>
            <p> If the study were conducted repeatedly (selecting different samples of people each
                time), which one of the following would be true regarding the resulting sample
                proportions of "yes" responses? </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Different sample proportions would result each time, but for either
                sample size, they would be centered (have their mean) at the true population
                proportion. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Different sample proportions would result each time, but for sample
                size 1,600 they would be centered (have their mean) at the true population
                proportion, whereas for sample size 400 they would not. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Different sample proportions would result each time, but for sample
                size 400 they would be centered (have their mean) at the true population proportion,
                whereas for sample size 1,600 they would not. </choice>
            <choice value="D">For either sample size, using the same size each time, as long as the
                samples are drawn with replacement, they would be centered (have a mean) at 0.
            </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Due to sampling variability, for different samples we will get
                    different values of p̂. Since the mean of the sampling distribution of p̂
                    is p, the population proportion, whether we take a sample of size 400 or a
                    sample of size 1,600, the resulting values of p̂ will be centered around p in
                    both cases. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the sampling distribution of p̂ will be
                    normally distributed with a mean of p, the population proportion. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the sampling distribution of p̂ will be
                    normally distributed with a mean of p, the population proportion. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the sampling distribution of p̂ will be
                    normally distributed with mean p, the population proportion. Because the
                    sampling distribution is normally distributed, and p̂ cannot take on negative
                    values, it doesn’t make sense to have the sampling distribution centered at 0.
                </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_recog_samp_distrib_norm_1" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>A social scientist wishes to conduct a survey. She plans to ask a yes/no question
                to a random sample from the U.S. adult population. One proposal is to select 100
                people; another proposal is to select 900 people.</p>
            <p>If the study were conducted repeatedly (selecting different samples of people
                each time), which one of the following would be true regarding the resulting
                sample proportions of "yes" responses?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Different sample proportions would result each time,
                but for sample size 900 they would be centered (have their mean) at the true
                population proportion, whereas for sample size 100 they would not. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Different sample proportions would result each time,
                but for sample size 100 they would be centered (have their mean) at the true
                population proportion, whereas for sample size 900 they would not. </choice>
            <choice value="C">Different sample proportions would result each time,
                but for either sample size, they would be centered (have their mean) at the true
                population proportion. </choice>
            <choice value="D">For either sample size, using the same size each
                time, as long as the sampling is done with replacement, their mean would be 0.
            </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the sampling distribution of p̂ will be
                    normally distributed with a mean of p, the population proportion. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the sampling distribution of p̂ will be
                    normally distributed with a mean of p, the population proportion.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Due to sampling variability, for different samples we will
                    get different values of p̂. Since the mean of the sampling distribution
                    of p̂ is p, the population proportion, whether we take a sample of size
                    100 or a sample of size 900, the resulting values of p̂ will be centered
                    around p in both cases.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the sampling distribution of p̂ will be
                    normally distributed with mean p, the population proportion. Because the
                    sampling distribution is normally distributed, and p̂ cannot take on
                    negative values, it doesn’t make sense to have the sampling distribution
                    centered at 0.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
