<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_homeo_maintain_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Blockage of the lymph system can result in which of the following?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">Swelling or edema in the tissues in the area of the blockage</choice><choice value="B">A reduction in the amount of protein returned to the bloodstream</choice><choice value="C">Discoloration of the skin overlying the swollen tissue, and eventually deformity (elephantiasis)</choice><choice value="D">All of the above</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Partially correct. This is true, but another answer is more complete and, therefore, more correct.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Partially correct. This is true, but another answer is more complete and, therefore, more correct.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Partially correct. This is true, but another answer is more complete and, therefore, more correct.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. All those are results of blockage of the lymphatic system.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which of the following is a main symptom of SLE?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Watery eyes, itching nose and cough</choice><choice value="B">Multiple infections and Karposi’s sarcoma</choice><choice value="C">Localized fluid retention and a tissue swelling</choice><choice value="D">Arthritis and butterfly rash</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These symptoms are mainly due to allergies.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These symptoms are often found in AIDS.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These symptoms usually occur during lymphedema.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Which of the following is a viable explanation for how a person can receive a kidney transplant and not reject it?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The kidney has an outer capsule and is located outside the peritoneal cavity, so the person’s immune system does not recognize the kidney as foreign.</choice><choice value="B">The person’s immune system would recognize that the kidney is not their own and mount a response to eliminate the foreign tissues. In order to not reject the transplant, a person needs to take immunosuppressant drugs that suppress their immune system.</choice><choice value="C">Transplant rejection can be prevented by determining the MHC similarities between the donor tissue and the transplant recipient, and matching them as closely as possible to prevent rejection.</choice><choice value="D">The donor kidney is rejected only by the cytotoxic T lymphocytes, so blockage of IL-2 would prevent costimulation and anergy of these lymphocytes.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the kidney has an outer capsule and is retroperitoneal, but the blood supply to the kidney would allow the immune system to recognize and reject the foreign tissue.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It is true that tissue rejection will be lessened by matching donor and recipient MHC, but immune rejection would still occur unless the donor was the identical twin of the recipient.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Rejection is a cellular immune response via cytotoxic T cells. They induce lysis of transplanted cells as well as trigger an antibody mediated response via activated B cells secreting antibodies. The actions of the adaptive immune responses are joined by components of innate immune responses via phagocytes and soluble immune proteins.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
