<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_inflammation_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>We often take over-the-counter anti-inflammatory medicines to help us feel better when we are sick or injured. However, the inflammatory response is important after injury in our fight against infection and tissue repair and recovery. Which statement is NOT true concerning the inflammatory response?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Swelling and edema provide a more fluid environment, which allows white blood cells easier access to the site of infection of injury.</choice><choice value="B">Increasing body temperature via fever makes it difficult for some organisms to grow.</choice><choice value="C">Pain reminds us to get an injured or infected body part immobile so we don’t spread the infection or exacerbate the injury.</choice><choice value="D">Heat and redness indicate that your inflammatory response is out of whack and the tissue will not heal.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_defenses_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_inflammation_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true. Swelling and edema are important for cell motility.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true. Many pathogens have a very limited temperature range where the can grow well. Fever&apos;s increasing the body temperature may impede pathogen growth.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true. Pain does help remind us to immobilize an area, so the body can use the most resources to fight infection and heal.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Heat and redness are part of the increase vasodilation in the affected area. It means the inflammatory response is working.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
