<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_homeo_maintain_digt2"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The T and B cells that differentiate from hematopoietic stem cells recognize as self the MHC markers on the cells of the bodies that they were in when they differentiated into mature cells. Suppose a woman donates hematopoietic stem cells to an unrelated friend who had her stem cells totally destroyed by radiation and chemotherapy during her cancer treatment. Although most of the donor hematopoietic stem cells differentiated into blood cells, some differentiated into cells of the pancreas and liver. Which of the following outcomes is likely?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The T cells from the donor do not attack the pancreas and liver but mount a GVH response against all of the other host cells.</choice><choice value="B">The T cells from the donor mount a GVH response against all of the host cells.</choice><choice value="C">The T cells from the donor attack the pancreas and liver but fail to mount a GVH response against all of the other host cells.</choice><choice value="D">The T cells from the donor do not attack the pancreas or liver and also fail to mount a GVH response against all other host tissues.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_homeo_maintain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is unlikely since the donor hematopoietic cells differentiate into T and B cells in an environment that contains antigens characteristic of both the host and donor, there is tolerance to cells and tissues of both.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Unlikely, T cells arising from the donor hematopoietic stem cells develop in the presence of the host’s cell and tissues and are therefore immunologically tolerant of them.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Unlikely, since the donor hematopoietic cells differentiate into T and B cells in an environment that contains antigens characteristic of both the host and donor, there is tolerance to cells and tissues of both.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This is the likely outcome because since the donor hematopoietic cells differentiate into T and B cells in an environment that contains antigens characteristic of both the host and donor, there is tolerance to cells and tissues of both.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
