<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_diseases_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>The immune system acts by detecting and attacking anything perceived as “non-self.” The innate immune system responds to molecules derived from tissue damage and to common microbial components. The adaptive immune system responds to specific molecules, and those molecules that provoke an immune response, particularly the production of antibodies, are called antigens.</p><p>Sort the following cells and molecules into self and non-self, from the perspective of your own immune system. </p><p>Viral protein<input_ref input="i1" /></p><p>Bacterial cell<input_ref input="i2" /></p><p>Your own MHC molecule<input_ref input="i3" /></p><p>Your identical twin&apos;s cells<input_ref input="i4" /></p><p>Your mother&apos;s cells<input_ref input="i5" /></p><p>Snake venom<input_ref input="i6" /></p><p>Pollen<input_ref input="i7" /></p><p>One of your cells turned cancerous<input_ref input="i8" /></p><p>A baby in utero<input_ref input="i9" /></p><p>A sperm in a testis<input_ref input="i10" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i1" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i2" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i3" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i4" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i5" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i6" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i7" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i8" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i9" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i10" shuffle="false"><choice value="a">self</choice><choice value="b">non-self</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i1" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A molecule from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. A molecule from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><hint>How similar is a virus to you?</hint></part><part id="q1_p2"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i2" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Any cell from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i2" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Any cell from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><hint>Are bacterial cells like human cells?</hint></part><part id="q1_p3"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i3" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Your own MHC molecules are a representation of your genetic identity.</feedback></response><response input="i3" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Your own MHC molecules are a representation of your genetic identity.</feedback></response><hint>MHC antigens are the body’s molecular fingerprints.</hint></part><part id="q1_p4"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i4" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Your identical twin is genetically identical to you, so his/her cells are seens as self by your immune system.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Your identical twin is genetically identical to you, so his/her cells are seens as self by your immune system.</feedback></response><hint>You and your twin share the same genes.</hint></part><part id="q1_p5"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i5" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Any other human who is not your identical twin is genetically different from you. </feedback></response><response input="i5" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Any other human who is not your identical twin is genetically different from you. </feedback></response><hint>Half of your genetic information comes from one of your parents</hint></part><part id="q1_p6"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i6" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A molecule from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i6" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. A molecule from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><hint>This is a protein made by a snake.</hint></part><part id="q1_p7"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i7" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A molecule from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i7" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. A molecule from a different organism is seen as non-self.</feedback></response><hint>This is a substance made by a plant.</hint></part><part id="q1_p8"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i8" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Even if the cancer cell comes from your own cells, it has changed enough that the immune system will recognize it as non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i8" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Even if the cancer cell comes from your own cells, it has changed enough that the immune system will recognize it as non-self.</feedback></response><hint>Cancer cells are transformed (changed).</hint></part><part id="q1_p9"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i9" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Your child has half of his/her genes coming from another person, so he/she is half non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i9" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Your child has half of his/her genes coming from another person, so he/she is half non-self.</feedback></response><hint>Half of your genetic information comes from one of your parents.</hint></part><part id="q1_p10"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response input="i10" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although your sperm cells are your own, they did not develop as such until adolescence. Because they were not included in the “training” of the immune system (negative selection), the immune system would consider them non-self.</feedback></response><response input="i10" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Although your sperm cells are your own, they did not develop as such until adolescence. Because they were not included in the “training” of the immune system (negative selection), the immune system would consider them non-self.</feedback></response><hint>Do pre-adolescent boys produce sperm cells?</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q2"><body>In some of the cases in the previous question, immune response will occur swiftly, such as the cases of a bacterial infection or a viral protein. Cases of mismatched blood transfusions or organ transplants will cause rejection. Pollen, on the other hand, may cause severe reactions in sensitive people but not in others. Cancers do occur in many patients. Most males’ sperm cells are not attacked by the immune system and most babies develop without being rejected by their mothers. Which of the following could NOT explain a way that non-self cells molecules can provoke strong immune responses in some cases but not in others?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Some antigens are stronger than others.</choice><choice value="B">Some individuals have genetically stronger responses than others.</choice><choice value="C">The immune system may be working incorrectly.</choice><choice value="D">The immune system works better in younger people than in older people.</choice><choice value="E">The immune system may not have access to the antigens.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_diseases_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_functions_SKILL" /><skillref idref="lymph_antigens_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Proteins tend to be more immunogenic (“stronger” when provoking an immune response) than other molecules. Also, the more genetically different a cell is, the more immunogenic it is; that’s why transplants are less riskier with organs from family members.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some individuals may have immune reactions to certain antigens that other persons do not- typical case of allergies.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The immune system may be depressed/deficient for many reasons, including congenital immune deficiencies, HIV infections, treatments such as radiations or certain drugs, or even stress. On the other hand, sometimes the immune system may work incorrectly, attacking the body’s own tissues, which leads to autoimmune disorders.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Although there is often a decline of the immune response in older individuals, it is also common for children to have either weaker or exaggerated immune responses due to their immature immune system. Therefore, this does not explain strong responses in some cases but not others.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Certain parts of the body are considered sites of “immune privilege,” such as the placenta containing the fetus, the testicles, and the eye. That explains why sperm cells or the fetus are not attacked by the immune system.</feedback></response><hint>The immune system must balance between immunity and tolerance.</hint><hint>There must be direct contact between antigens and immune system for the response to occur.</hint><hint>The immune system learns what is self and non-self during the first years of life.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
