<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="lymph_histamines_digt_assessment"><title>lymph_histamines Assessment</title><question id="q1"><body><custom id="dragDrop" src="../../webcontent/DynaDropHTML.js" type="javascript" width="550" height="400" layout="../webcontent/lymph_histamines_digt_assessment_layout.xml" logging="true"><param name="showInputs">false</param></custom></body><fill_in_the_blank id="aa" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice><choice value="e">e</choice><choice value="f">f</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="bb" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice><choice value="e">e</choice><choice value="f">f</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="cc" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice><choice value="e">e</choice><choice value="f">f</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="dd" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice><choice value="e">e</choice><choice value="f">f</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="ee" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice><choice value="e">e</choice><choice value="f">f</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="ff" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">a</choice><choice value="b">b</choice><choice value="c">c</choice><choice value="d">d</choice><choice value="e">e</choice><choice value="f">f</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="lymph_histamines_SKILL" /><response input="aa" match="b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Histamine released from intracellular granules is part of the inflammatory and allergic pathways.</feedback></response><response input="aa" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Histamine is released by mast cells or basophiles, not directly by damaged tissue cells.</feedback></response><response input="aa" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Histamine does not freely circulate in the serum and is not a protein.</feedback></response><response input="aa" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Histamine is locally released from the granules of mast cells and basophils.</feedback></response><response input="aa" match="e"><feedback>Incorrect. Histamine is released from mast cells it does not interact with iron.</feedback></response><response input="aa" match="f"><feedback>Incorrect. Histamine has some similar functions but probably does not play a role in pathogen adherence during phagocytosis.</feedback></response></part><part id="q1_p2"><skillref idref="lymph_histamines_SKILL" /><response input="bb" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinins are normally found in their inactive form circulating in the blood.</feedback></response><response input="bb" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinins are found as freely circulating proteins and not contained within mast cell granules.</feedback></response><response input="bb" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinins are plasma-derived signaling molecules that are vasoactive but do not promote phagocytosis.</feedback></response><response input="bb" match="d" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Kinins are are groups of signaling molecules that can stimulate several different responses.</feedback></response><response input="bb" match="e"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinins are signaling molecules that circulate in the blood; they do not interact with iron molecules.</feedback></response><response input="bb" match="f"><feedback>Incorrect. Kinins are circulating molecules and not derived from mast cells and basophils.</feedback></response></part><part id="q1_p3"><skillref idref="lymph_histamines_SKILL" /><response input="cc" match="a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Prostaglandins release is part of the the bodies response to tissue damage and they work with other chemicals to mediate inflammation.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Prostaglandins are lipid derived molecules released by local tissue cells during tissue damage.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Prostaglandins are lipids and not proteins.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Although prostaglandins can contribute to these effects, prostaglandins are not plasma derived.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="e"><feedback>Incorrect. Prostaglandins are lipids and not proteins.</feedback></response><response input="cc" match="f"><feedback>Incorrect. Prostaglandins are not a major chemical released from mast cells or basophils.</feedback></response></part><part id="q1_p4"><skillref idref="lymph_histamines_SKILL" /><response input="dd" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Leukotrienes are signaling molecules that are more commonly generated in response to an allergic reaction, not direct tissue damage.</feedback></response><response input="dd" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Leukotrienes are signaling molecules and are not released by mast cells or basophils.</feedback></response><response input="dd" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Leukotrienes are eicosanoids (lipids) and not proteins.</feedback></response><response input="dd" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Although leukotrienes can produce many similar effects, they are produced by mast cells and are not plasma derived.</feedback></response><response input="dd" match="e"><feedback>Incorrect. Leukotrienes are eicosanoids not proteins.</feedback></response><response input="dd" match="f" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Leukotrienes are signaling molecules that contribute to a variety of functions</feedback></response></part><part id="q1_p5"><skillref idref="lymph_histamines_SKILL" /><response input="ee" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Complement proteins are found in their inactive form circulating in the blood.</feedback></response><response input="ee" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Complement is found circulating in the blood and is not released by mast cells or basophils.</feedback></response><response input="ee" match="c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. These proteins circulate in the blood and are important for opsonization of infections agents, histamine release and the formation of a membrane attack complex. </feedback></response><response input="ee" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Complement can stimulate histamine release and contribute to opsonization, but it doesn’t directly stimulate these effects.</feedback></response><response input="ee" match="e"><feedback>Incorrect. Complement proteins do not transport iron.</feedback></response><response input="ee" match="f"><feedback>Incorrect. Complement is found freely circulating and is not released in direct response to cell signaling.</feedback></response></part><part id="q1_p6"><skillref idref="lymph_histamines_SKILL" /><response input="ff" match="a"><feedback>Incorrect. Transferrins are plasma proteins that bind and transport iron.</feedback></response><response input="ff" match="b"><feedback>Incorrect. Transferrins are found circulating in the blood, they are not released from mast cells or basophils.</feedback></response><response input="ff" match="c"><feedback>Incorrect. Transferrins are transport proteins specialized for carrying iron. They do not have enzymatic function.</feedback></response><response input="ff" match="d"><feedback>Incorrect. Transferrins are proteins the transport iron throughout the body.</feedback></response><response input="ff" match="e" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Transferrins bind iron so they can transport it. If the iron is bound to transferrin it is not available for use by bacteria.</feedback></response><response input="ff" match="f"><feedback>Incorrect. Transferrins are plasma proteins that carry iron.</feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
