<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_olfaction_5">
	<head>
		<title>Olfactory Nerve Impulses</title>
		<objref idref="describe_olfactory_nerves_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The axons of the olfactory neurons extend from the basal surface of the epithelium,
			through an olfactory foramen in the cribriform plate of the ethmoid bone, and into the
			olfactory bulb, located on the ventral surface of the frontal lobe. Collectively the
			axons that pass through the cribriform plate are called the olfactory
				nerve. From the olfactory bulb, axons project to structures within the limbic
			cortex, including the cortex in the temporal lobe associated with long-term memory
			formation.</p> 
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_37.jpg" alt="Central Nervous System Regions that Receive Information from
			the Olfactory Bulb." width="600">
			<caption>Central Nervous System Regions that Receive Information from
				the Olfactory Bulb. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
			
			
			<p>Smell is the one sensory modality that does not require a synaptic
			connection in the thalamus before connecting to the cerebral cortex. Smell can often be
			a potent trigger for memories because of this intimate connection of the olfactory
			system with the cerebral cortex. It can also trigger visceral reflexes through
			connections within the reticular formation. For example, some people will vomit at the
			smell of another person’s vomit.</p>
		
		
		<p>Because of the noxious chemicals that are inhaled into the nasal cavity, these cells need
			to be replaced on a regular basis. The nasal epithelium, including the olfactory cells,
			can be harmed by airborne toxic chemicals. To reduce the risk of olfactory neurons being
			harmed by these toxins, they have a limited lifespan of about 60 days. Because of this
			imposed cell death, stem cells within the nasal epithelial layer differentiate into new
			olfactory cells. In doing so, axons of the new neurons have to find their way to the
			targets in the olfactory bulb. They are able to do this by growing along the axons that
			are already in place in the cranial nerve. This is the only place in the body where we
			continually make new neuronal cells.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_olfactory_nerves_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_olfactory_nerves_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
