<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Reflexes_2"><head><title>Types of Receptors</title><objref idref="classify_receptors_LO" /></head><body><p id="aec4828dc88a479e9741672e5a43997f">Sensory receptors <em style="bold">enable</em> us to learn about the environment around us or about the state of our internal environment. Stimuli from varying sources, and of different types, must be received and changed into the electrochemical signals of the nervous system represented by changes in the membrane potential. The sensory information is relayed to the central nervous system where it is integrated with other sensory information, or sometimes higher cognitive functions, to become a conscious perception of that stimulus. The central integration may then lead to a motor response.</p><section id="cb3c77f569434ca39c85040b87641d88"><title>Sensory Receptors</title><body><p id="ba701b76719d455695d6db79ed0f33dd">Stimuli in the environment activate specialized receptors in the peripheral nervous system. The classification of receptors into types can be based on three different criteria: structure of the receptors, location of the receptors relative to the stimuli they sense, and by the types of stimuli to which they respond. Regardless of type, the function of these receptors is to <term>transduce</term> a stimulus from one form of energy (chemical, physical, etc.) into a change in the cell membrane potential that may or may not create an action potential.</p></body></section><section id="dc94b295f36c49f185127084461505e5"><title>Structural Receptor Types</title><body><p id="bc9beb446e5248258e4eee32a998bb0c">The cells that detect a change in the environment can be neurons with <term>free nerve endings</term>, where the dendrites are exposed to the surrounding tissue; neurons with <term>encapsulated endings</term>, where supporting cells aid in the reception of stimuli; or specialized receptor cells, which have specific structural components for detecting stimuli. Examples of neurons with free nerve endings are the pain and temperature receptors in the dermis of the skin. Also in the dermis are encapsulated nerve endings such as the lamellar corpuscle that senses pressure. The cells in the retina that receive light stimuli are an example of specialized <term>photoreceptor cells</term>, not neurons, that in turn can stimulate an associated sensory neuron.</p><image id="bce0e1c725ac4b98b71fe1f1ca891a4f" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_8.jpg" alt="Receptor cell types can be classified based on their structure. Unipolar      sensory neurons can have either free nerve endings or encapsulated endings.      Photoreceptors are an example of specialized receptor cells that release      neurotransmitter onto a bipolar cell which then connects to the neuron which      connects to the CNS." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af30c1c9ebf14f5f9219949b55e95bfa">Structural Receptor Classification. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d11394f1e7a94ca79ff893500f6847c5">Receptors can also be classified based on their location relative to the stimuli. <term>Exteroceptors</term> are receptors that receive input from the external environment, such as the lameller corpuscles of the dermis and photoreceptors of the eye that have already been mentioned. <term>Interoceptors</term> are those that sense stimuli from the internal organs. Examples would include a stretch receptor in the wall of an organ, such as those that sense the increase in blood pressure in the aorta or carotid artery or detects stretch as the bladder fills with urine. Finally, <term>proprioceptors</term> are widely distributed receptors in muscles, tendons and joint capsules that the body uses to determine position and movement of structures, such as its limbs and fingers. Proprioceptors allow you to touch your finger to your nose, even with your eyes closed.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="classify_receptors_LBD-1" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/classify_receptors_LBD-layout.xml</param></wb:inline><section id="d8e090548dfb4ee78b726a960704e117"><title>Functional Receptor Types</title><body><p id="c3d740ad95b34556b306d2ccce53819c">Lastly, receptors can be classified by the types of signals they transduce into changes in membrane potential.</p><p id="f6ab31af6a724617acfceb0a4509b860"><term>Chemoreceptors</term> sense chemical stimuli, examples being taste, smell and the osmotic pressure of the body’s extracellular fluids (the latter sensed by osmoreceptors).</p><p id="edef61fa489740449dc8e2771e703576"><term>Nociceptors</term> are pain receptors. Although pain is primarily a chemical sense that detects the presence of chemicals released during tissue damage, nociceptors are typically considered in a functional category of their own. Nociceptors are found in most tissues throughout the body, exceptions being the brain and possibly certain internal structures of organs.</p><p id="b149cb0937d64880935def7a23304ea7"><term>Mechanoreceptors</term> sense physical stimuli, such as pressure and vibration, as well as the sensation of sound and pull of gravity. A specific example of a mechanoreceptor is the baroreceptors (pressure receptors) found in the carotid arteries, which sense blood pressure.</p><p id="f4115dbb683d4ed9a9553d01d763fec8"><term>Thermoreceptors</term> are specific to sensing temperature and changes in temperature. Thermoreceptors are found in two forms, those that respond most strongly to temperatures below normal body temperature (cold thermoreceptors), and those that respond most strongly at temperatures above normal body temperature (warm thermoreceptors). At normal body temperature, both types of receptors are active, but there is generally no awareness of cold or warmth.</p><p id="b8045738b1fb4805bc1fefaad8438500"><term>Photoreceptors</term> respond to electromagnetic radiation (light). Humans have the ability to sense electromagnetic waves at wavelengths between 400 and 700 nanometers, with different wavelengths corresponding to different colors.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="classify_receptors_LBD2" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/classify_receptors_LBD2-layout.xml</param></wb:inline><section id="f403babab79f47648cc5a6b35f79e741" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="classify_receptors_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="classify_receptors_DIGT2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
