<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Hearing_1">
	<head>
		<title>Structures and Functions of the Outer and Middle Ear</title>
		<objref idref="identify_ear_structures_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_ear_glands_LO"/>
		<objref idref="describe_auditory_tube_LO"/>-->
		<objref idref="describe_ear_sound_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>Hearing is the transduction of sound waves into a neural signal that relies on the
			structures of the ear. The outwardly visible structure that is often referred
			to as the ear is more correctly referred to as the <term>outer ear</term>
			(external ear), or the <term>auricle</term>. The C-shaped
			curves of the auricle direct sound waves towards the ear canal, which enters into the
			skull through the external auditory meatus of the temporal bone. At the end of the ear
			canal is the <term>tympanic membrane</term>, or ear drum, which vibrates with
			the movement of air in sound waves.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_28.jpg" alt="Anatomy of the Ear. The outer ear is
			the auricle and ear canal through to the tympanic membrane. The middle ear contains
			the ossicles and is connected to the pharynx by the auditory tube. The inner ear is
			the cochlea and vestibule which are responsible for hearing and equilibrium,
			respectively." id="ear1" width="600">
			<caption>Anatomy of the Ear. The outer ear is
				the auricle and ear canal through to the tympanic membrane. The middle ear contains
				the ossicles and is connected to the pharynx by the auditory tube. The inner ear is
				the cochlea and vestibule which are responsible for hearing and equilibrium,
				respectively. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>	
		
		
		<p>Along the length of the ear canal are <term>ceruminous</term> glands that
			contribute to the production of <term>cerumen</term> (earwax). Because cerumen
			is sticky it can help prevent small particles from finding their way to the tympanic
			membrane. Cerumen also helps prevent bacterial growth, waterproofs the auditory canal
			and tympanic membrane, and may be a deterrent to small insects.</p>
		<p>The <term>middle ear</term> consists of a space spanned by three small bones,
			the <term>ossicles</term>, which amplify the movements of the tympanic
			membrane. These small bones are the <term>malleus</term>, <term>incus</term>, and <term>stapes</term>, which are Latin names that roughly
			translate to hammer, anvil, and stirrup. The malleus is attached to the tympanic
			membrane and articulates with the incus, which articulates with the stapes. The stapes
			is then attached to the <term>inner ear</term> where the sound waves will be
			transduced to a neural signal.</p>
		<p>The middle ear is also connected to the pharynx through the <term>auditory
				tube</term> (Eustachian tube) that helps equilibrate air pressure across the tympanic
			membrane. When flying, you may have experienced what happens when the pressures across
			the tympanic membrane are not equal. As the plane climbs, pressure on the outside of the
			membrane decreases. If there is not a corresponding decrease in pressure in the middle
			ear, the pressure difference will cause the eardrum to push outward, causing pain and
			muffled hearing. The auditory tube is normally closed, but will typically open when
			muscles of the pharynx contract during swallowing or yawning. For this reason, chewing
			gum or drinking as the plane climbs will often relieve these symptoms. The auditory tube
			also provides a pathway of drainage for fluids that accumulate during middle ear
			infections (otitis media). Unfortunately, it is also the auditory tubes that play a role
			in causing otitis media, as microorganisms can use this path to move from the pharynx
			into the middle ear. This is especially common in children.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
