<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Vision_1"><head><title>Anatomy of the Eye</title><objref idref="eye_functions_LO" /></head><body><p id="f481f1d7b2534b73b11b02bc8c1b3bb4">The eyes are located within the skull orbits, which provide protection for the eyes, aswell as provide a place to anchor the soft tissues that support the functions of the eye. The eyelids, with lashes at their leading edges, help to protect the eye from abrasions by blocking particles that may get onto its surface. From the inner surface of each lid, a thin mucous membrane known as the <term>conjunctiva</term> folds in andcovers the surface of the eye. Tears are produced by the <term>lacrimalglands</term>, which are superior and lateral to the orbit in each eye, and they flow over theconjunctiva to wash away particles that may have gotten past the lashes and the lids. Tears flow down through the <term>lacrimal ducts</term>, located on the medialside of each orbit, into the nasal cavity.</p><image id="ab63598f24b043689826a031f5f383e8" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_17.jpg" alt="Anatomical features of the tissues surrounding the eye (a) and    lacrimal system (b)." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600"><caption><p id="fa133ad494d94d9c8205cae88a7ede1c">Anatomical features of the tissues surrounding the eye (a) andlacrimal system (b). This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="d1d5f92345454d0e969417c59cbee5af"><title>Components of the Eye</title><body><p id="ac9374bf62df4949a8af4fdbf14cdcb1">The eye itself is a hollow sphere composed of three layers of tissue. The outermost layeris the <term>fibrous tunic</term> which is the white <term>sclera</term>and clear <term>cornea</term>. The two parts of the fibrous tunic arecontinuous, though they have different properties. The sclera accounts for 5/6 of the surface of the eye, most of which is not visible (though humans are unique in having so much of the “white of the eye” visible). The cornea covers the anterior region of the eye and allows light to pass into the eye where it will eventually stimulate photoreceptors. The next layer of the eye is the <term>vascular tunic</term>,which is mostly composed of the <term>choroid</term>, a highlyvascularized connective tissue that provides a blood supply to the adjacent tissue. The choroid is posterior to the <term>ciliary body</term>, a muscular structurethat is attached to the <term>lens</term> by the <term>suspensoryligament</term>. The ciliary body focuses light on the back of the eye. Overlaying theciliary body, and visible in the anterior eye, is the <term>iris</term>, thecolored part of the eye that opens in the center as the <term>pupil</term>. Theinnermost layer of the eye is the <term>neural tunic</term>, which is the <term>retina</term> or the nervous tissue that is responsible forphotoreception.</p></body></section><image id="f4e47f2a36544107be0a3561f35ede9f" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_18.jpg" alt="Anatomical features of the eye." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600"><caption><p id="b4099e9e359c4c45baed341cd72e3a84">Anatomical features of the eye. This work by Cenveo is licensed under aCreative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="eye_functions_LBD2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="b26c00c6e29341e1a854062478f47e55"><title>Chambers of the Eye</title><body><p id="a7ff0941d47e4b559a70e283d669f094">The eye is also divided into two cavities, the anterior and posterior. The anterior chamber, of anterior cavity, is the space between the cornea and iris. The posterior chamber sits between the iris and the lens. Both the anterior and posterior chambers are filled with a watery fluid called the <term>aqueous humor</term>. The posterior vitreous chamber (also posterior cavity) is posterior to the lens and is filled with a more viscous fluid called the <term>vitreous humor</term> (vitreous body).</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="eye_functions_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="f834d17e7dbe4c51b5463e0c2303aea4" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="eye_functions_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="newd95be94ad05d4908966037aae402bdf2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
