<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_olfaction_6">
	<head>
		<title>Olfactory System Dysfunctions</title>
		<!--<objref idref="predict_olfactory_dysfunction_LO"/>-->
		<objref idref="predict_olfactory_impact_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
	
		<p>If any event, such as blunt force trauma of a car accident, leads to the loss of the
			olfactory nerve, the sense of smell can be lost. This condition is known as <term>anosmia</term>. One way this condition can develop is if the brain moves
			relative to the ethmoid bone, which is likely to shear (tear) the axons of the olfactory
			cells. Professional fighters can have anosmia as a result repeated trauma to the head.
			Certain pharmaceuticals, such as antibiotics, can cause anosmia because they can kill
			off all the olfactory neurons at once. If no axons are in place within the olfactory
			nerve, then the axons cannot grow back into the olfactory bulb leaving the person with a
			long-term loss of smell. There are temporary causes of anosmia, as well, usually based
			on inflammatory responses in relation to infection or allergy.</p>
		<p>You have probably noticed that when you have a cold, the associated loss of smell usually
			results in food tasting bland. Since taste is comprised of only a small number of
			sensations, we use the olfactory system to recognize differences between many foods,
			especially in terms of the spices used. If we lack the numerous smells to enrich the
			taste experience, we often add extra seasonings to further stimulate the tongue.</p>
		<p>The ability of olfactory neurons to be replaced by stem cells can be lost with age
			leading to age-related anosmia. When this affects an elderly person, they often turn to
			using increased salt on their food. Unfortunately, increased sodium intake also leads to
			an increase in blood volume and blood pressure.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
