<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Vision_10"><head><title>Processing Visual Information</title><objref idref="eye_retina_nervepath_LO" /></head><body><p id="efc83e899b7a453989be98edab50c03b">The photoreceptors, and other neuronal cells of the retina, send varied types of information to the brain. These include light intensity, colors and the spatial distribution of the information received. All of this information is then carried along the optic nerve and into the optic tract to be distributed to nuclei in the brain. At the point where the optic nerve becomes the optic tract, the optic chiasm is found. At this point, fibers carrying information from the nasal half of the retina on each side decussate (cross over), such that the information from the nasal half of the retina of the left eye crosses over to the right side of the brain and vice versa. In doing so, the left side of the brain receives information from the right visual field of each eye, and the right side of the brain receives information from the left visual field of each eye. This matches the sidedness of the brain to motor control. For example, visual information from the left side of the body, and motor control of the left limbs, are both processed by the right hemisphere of the brain. </p><image id="f583b097e64b47859c2dca7da0da08cf" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_27.jpg" alt="Depiction of how visual information has sidedness in the    brain. The diagram shows how information from the right visual field is    delivered to the left brain and how information from the left visual field is delivered    to the right side of the brain." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption><p id="bfd2c1e9a73d4511874a895b13b19d3a">Depiction of how visual information has sidedness in the brain. The diagram shows how information from the right visual field is delivered to the left brain and how information from the left visual field is delivered to the right side of the brain. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="e20f62a0c1594b938d0db9230074faa0">Visual information from the optic tract is sent to a variety of nuclei in the brain. These nuclei, along with the type of processing they are involved in are summarized in the table below.</p><table id="f6ef5dd211d34f5f9b6bc26eeeca8023" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><title>Brain structures involved in visual processing.</title><cite id="i0d6e543e628940b698aa27892b8c08c8" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab5b53f7ac4784d359f2ac62a6dbf16d9">Nuclei</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac53f4003d05a426689f07d51c2ae1af5">Role</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac2eecf7f40844190a686eab95f52e148">Lateral geniculate nucleus of the thalamus</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa07e8d0f5699443ea3175e15e3f46308">Project to the occipital lobe for processing of visual perception</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae94aac7a464f42fdb53a3e384e353cfe">Superior colliculus</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abacbdc876ab14427b0affc402f6cb59d">Control of eye movements</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad21b712c179e4c9dae7425b9da712c1c">Pretectum</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adc9daa02a3ae4c8eb01705204e7d65b0">Pupillary light reflex</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abfa060543ead46acb7044111e4903129">Suprachiasmatic nucleus of the hypothalamus</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abe5f03a99b70453e835dca17976627c7">Hormonal control</p></td></tr></table><p id="c98a6cfdb6d64f92b64149f3ae9e9a7e">The majority of the visual information flows through the lateral geniculate nucleus of the thalamus into the occipital lobe for perception of vision. From here fibers will carry some information to regions of the parietal and temporal lobes, called the visual association areas. These areas contribute to object recognition (such as recognizing a face) and motion processing (such as catching a moving ball). </p><youtube id="a2f4c8fafe8649d689685853a3740f8a" src="wbVdlIc5DPE" height="315" width="560" controls="true"><title>Educational Video on The Vision System - Diopsys</title><cite id="i93887a5f25a549a6b05099c4886b6664" /><caption><p id="ad9ee45948f014ea3a038d4bc76e8b34c">A transverse section through the brain depicts the visual pathway from the eye to the occipital cortex. The first half of the pathway is the projection from the retinal ganglion cells through the optic nerve to the lateral geniculate nucleus in the thalamus on either side. This first fiber in the pathway synapses on a thalamic cell that then projects to the visual cortex in the occipital lobe where “seeing,” or visual perception, takes place.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube><wb:inline idref="eye_retina_nervepath_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><pullout id="e45969e280324f549f33ddc3f1e82a81" type="observation"><title>Title</title><p id="e16e7b5526744d56950ad300a9f70b09">It is important to recognize when popular media and online sources oversimplify complex physiological processes so that misunderstandings are not generated. This video was created by a medical device manufacturer who might be trying to highlight other aspects of the visual system than retinal processing. The statement they make is not incorrect, it just bundles together several steps, which makes it sound like RGCs are the traducers, rather than photoreceptors.</p></pullout></body></workbook_page>
