<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Reflexes_8">
	<head>
		<title>Categories of Reflexes</title>
		<!--<objref idref="reflex_pairs_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
	
		<p>As mentioned, reflexes can either be visceral or somatic. <em style="bold">Visceral
				reflexes </em>involve a glandular or non-skeletal muscular response carried out in
			internal organs such as the heart, blood vessels, or structures of the GI tract. They
			utilize neurons of the autonomic nervous system to elicit their actions. Visceral
			reflexes have been more fully discussed in the section on the autonomic nervous system.
			In contrast, <em style="bold">somatic reflexes </em>involve unconscious skeletal muscle
			motor responses. In doing so, these reflexes utilize some of the same lower motor
			neurons (alpha motor neurons) used to control skeletal muscle during conscious movement.
			Because reflexes are quick, it makes sense that somatic reflexes are often meant to
			protect us from injury. As examples, reflexes contribute to the maintenance of balance
			and rapid withdrawal of the hand or foot from damaging stimuli.</p>
		<!--Link to section on autonomic nervous system.-->
		<!--link back or remind about introductory “story” with cake pan?-->
		<p>Somatic reflexes can either be intrinsic (present at birth) or learned. We will be
			focusing on <em style="bold">intrinsic reflexes</em>, which occur as the result of
			normal human development. Learned reflexes are much more complicated in their anatomical
			structure and result from repetitive actions, such as athletic training. Reflexes can
			also be categorized by the number of synapses they involve (<em style="bold"
				>monosynaptic reflex </em>versus <em style="bold">polysynaptic reflex</em>) or the
			relative position of the sensory receptors to the responding muscles (<em style="bold"
				>ipsilateral</em> = same side of the body, <em style="bold">contralateral</em> =
			opposite sides of the body).</p>
		<wb:inline idref="reflex_pairs_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="reflex_pairs_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
