<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Vision_2"><head><title>Components of the Eye</title></head><body><p id="e93fbb2a9f0e4d8baccc62c7802c8c62">The eye itself is a hollow sphere composed of three layers of tissue. The outermost layer is the <em style="emphasis">fibrous tunic </em>which is the white <em style="emphasis">sclera </em>and clear <em style="emphasis">cornea</em>. The two parts of the fibrous tunic are continuous, though they have different properties. The sclera accounts for 5/6 of the surface of the eye, most of which is not visible (though humans are unique in having so much of the “white of the eye” visible). The cornea covers the anterior region of the eye and allows light to pass into the eye where it will eventually stimulate photoreceptors. The next layer of the eye is the <em style="emphasis">vascular tunic, </em>which is mostly composed of the <em style="emphasis">choroid</em>, a highly vascularized connective tissue that provides a blood supply to the adjacent tissue. The choroid is posterior to the <em style="emphasis">ciliary body</em>, a muscular structure that is attached to the <em style="emphasis">lens </em>by the <em style="emphasis">suspensory ligament. </em>The ciliary body focuses light on the back of the eye. Overlaying the ciliary body, and visible in the anterior eye, is the <em style="emphasis">iris</em>, the colored part of the eye that opens in the center as the <em style="emphasis">pupil</em>. The innermost layer of the eye is the <em style="emphasis">neural tunic, </em>which is the <em style="emphasis">retina </em>or the nervous tissue that is responsible for photoreception.</p><p id="feb8e678c0e840d6832729d363e66847"><em style="emphasis">Figure 2:Anatomical features of the eye.</em></p><section id="e8acda9b633547bbb700be7e288dd727"><title>Chambers of the Eye</title><body><p id="ecfc6e2779cc4d3293a761eaecb475c3">The eye is also divided into three chambers, the anterior, posterior and vitreous. The anterior chamber, or anterior cavity, is the space between the cornea and iris. The posterior chamber sits between the iris and the lens. Both the anterior and posterior chambers are filled with a watery fluid called the <em style="emphasis">aqueous humor</em>. The vitreous chamber (vitreous body) is posterior to the lens and is filled with a more viscous fluid called the <em style="emphasis">vitreous humor</em>.</p></body></section></body></workbook_page>
