<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_olfaction_3">
	<head>
		<title>Gustatory Nerve Impulses</title>
		<objref idref="describe_taste_nerves_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Once the taste cells are activated by molecules liberated from the things we ingest, they
			release neurotransmitters onto the dendrites of sensory neurons. These neurons are part
			of the facial and glossopharyngeal cranial nerves, as well as a component within the
			vagus nerve dedicated to the gag reflex. The facial nerve connects to taste buds in the
			anterior third of the tongue. The glossopharyngeal nerve connects to taste buds in the
			posterior two thirds of the tongue. The vagus nerve connects to taste buds in the
			extreme posterior of the tongue, verging on the pharynx, which are more sensitive to
			noxious stimuli like bitterness.</p>
		
		<activity idref="NervousSensory_olfaction_3_MSW" purpose="manystudentswonder"></activity>
		
		<p>Axons from the three cranial nerves carrying taste information travel to the medulla.
			From there much of the information is carried to the thalamus and then routed to the
			primary gustatory cortex, located near the inferior margin of the post-central gyrus. It
			is the primary gustatory cortex that is responsible for our sensations of taste. And,
			although this region receives significant input from taste buds, it is likely that it
			also receives information about the smell and texture of food, all contributing to our
			overall taste experience. The nuclei in the medulla also send projections to the
			hypothalamus and amygdalae, which are involved in autonomic reflexes such as gagging and
			salivation.</p>
		
		<!--<p><em style="highlight">Learn By Doing below- still need to resolve questions about it</em></p>-->
		<wb:inline idref="describe_taste_nerves_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_taste_nerves_DIGT2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
