<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Hearing_2">
	<head>
		<title>Structure and Function of the Inner Ear</title>
		<objref idref="describe_ear_sound_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_sound_waves_LO"/>
		<objref idref="explain_ear_pitch_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
	
		<p>The <xref idref="ear1" page="NervousSensory_Hearing_1">inner ear</xref> is entirely enclosed within the temporal bone. It has two
			separate regions, the <term>cochlea</term> and <term>vestibule</term>,
			which are responsible for hearing and balance, respectively. The neural signals from the
			two regions of the inner ear are relayed to the brainstem through separate fiber
			bundles, but which run together as the vestibulocochlear nerve.</p>
		
		<!--Link to cranial nerves?-->
		<p>Sound information is transmitted from the middle ear to the inner ear via the stapes
			attachment to the <term>oval window</term>, which is a membrane at the
			beginning of the cochlea. As the tympanic membrane vibrates from sound waves, the
			ossicles amplify that vibration, and then the oval window moves with the same vibrations. The oval window is at the beginning of a tube that runs the length of the
			cochlea to its tip (<term>helicotrema</term>) and back alongside itself to end
			at another membrane called the <term>round window</term> (<term>secondary tympanic
				membrane</term>).</p> 
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_29.jpg" alt="(a) Simplified Anatomy of the Cochlea. The cochlea can be
			modeled as a long tube running from the oval window, out to the helicotrema, and back.
			(b). Sound Wave Transmitted into the Cochlea. As sound is
			transmitted from air to the cochlea through the oval window, it creates a wave within
			the fluid of the cochlea (often called a standing wave). This wave creates displacement
			in the membranes of the cochlear duct, where sound is sensed." width="500">
			<caption>(a) Simplified Anatomy of the Cochlea. The cochlea can be
				modeled as a long tube running from the oval window, out to the helicotrema, and back.
				(b). Sound Wave Transmitted into the Cochlea. As sound is
				transmitted from air to the cochlea through the oval window, it creates a wave within
				the fluid of the cochlea (often called a standing wave). This wave creates displacement
				in the membranes of the cochlear duct, where sound is sensed. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>	
			
			<p>As the oval window is pushed in by sound waves, fluid within this
			tube is pushed along its length and the round window at its other end can bulge out as a
			result of that movement. Likewise, when the oval window is pulled back, the fluid inside
			this tube is drawn back and the round window can pucker in to compensate. As vibrations
			of the tympanic membrane are transmitted through the ossicles, a wave (often referred to
			as standing wave because of its properties) is created within the fluid in the cochlea that displaces sections of the <term>cochlear partition</term> (<term>cochlear duct</term> and <term>basilar membrane</term>). It is
				these waves that are detected by the sensing cells found attached to the basilar
			membrane.</p>
		
		
		<p>The tube running from the oval to the round window in the cochlea is separated into two
			spaces. From the oval window to the tip of the cochlea the tube is
			referred to as the <term>scala vestibuli</term> and from the tip of the cochlea
			back to the round window it is the <term>scala tympani</term>. These spaces can
			be seen in a cross-section of one turn of the cochlea.</p> 
			
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_30.jpg" alt="Anatomy of the Cochlea. The cochlea is a spiral structure
			(a) divided into three chambers (b). The middle chamber, the cochlear duct, contains the
			spiral organ that has hair cells (c) for sensing the vibrations we perceive as
			sound." width="600">
			<caption>Anatomy of the Cochlea. The cochlea is a spiral structure
				(a) divided into three chambers (b). The middle chamber, the cochlear duct, contains the
				spiral organ that has hair cells (c) for sensing the vibrations we perceive as
				sound. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
			
			
		<p>	The two spaces are on
			either side of the <term>cochlear duct</term>, which is the space that contains
			the structures that transduce sound into the neural signal. Those structures are
			contained within the <term>spiral organ</term> or <term>organ of
				Corti</term>, which lies on top of the <term>basilar membrane</term> that
			separates it from the scala tympani. The spiral organ contains <term>hair
				cells</term> with <term>stereocilia</term> on their apical membrane. The stereocilia bend in response to movement of the basilar membrane relative to
			the partially fixed <term>tectorial membrane</term>. Depending on which
			direction the stereocilia bend, they open or close ion channels, leading to signal
			changes in the cochlear nerve.</p>
		
		<p>As a standing wave is set up within the scala vestibuli and scala tympani in response to
			movement at the oval window, the basilar membrane responds by moving at a specific spot,
			dependent on the frequency of the standing wave. </p>
			
			
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_31.jpg" alt="Frequency Response of the Cochlea. Different frequencies
			are sensed in different regions of the cochlea. High frequencies (high pitch) are sensed
			near the base of the cochlea, whereas low frequencies are sensed near the tip of the
			cochlea." width="500">
			<caption>Frequency Response of the Cochlea. Different frequencies
				are sensed in different regions of the cochlea. High frequencies (high pitch) are sensed
				near the base of the cochlea, whereas low frequencies are sensed near the tip of the
				cochlea. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
			
		
			<p>The cochlea encodes auditory
			stimuli based on frequency between 20 Hz and 20,000 Hz, the range of human hearing.
			Higher frequencies (higher pitch) cause the basilar membrane close to the base of the
			cochlea to move and lower frequencies (lower pitch) cause the basilar membrane closer to
			the tip of the cochlea to move. Loudness, or sound intensity, is determined by the
			number of hair cells in an area that are stimulated. A louder sound produces greater
			displacement of the basilar membrane, leading to a greater number of stereocilia
			responding.</p>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
