<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Vision_7">
	<head>
		<title>The Retina</title>
		<objref idref="eye_structures_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_eye_retina_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
	
		<p>We have already discussed the structures of the eye that deliver and focus light on the
			retina. The retina is composed of a several layers and contains specialized cells for
			the initial processing of visual stimuli, with the rest of the visual processing
			occuring in the central nervous system.</p>
		<p>The photoreceptors are found in the retinal layer closest to the back of the eye
			(outermost layer). When stimulated by light energy, they change their membrane potential
			and alter the amount of neurotransmitter released onto the <term>bipolar
				cells</term>. The bipolar cells connect to the <term>retinal ganglion
				cells</term> (RGC) where <term>amacrine cells</term> also contribute to
			retinal processing such as contrast enhancement and edge detection. The axons of RGCs,
			which are lying at the innermost aspect of the retina, collect at the <term>optic disc</term> and leave the eye as the optic nerve. Because of the axons passing
			through the wall of the eye at the optic disc, there are no photoreceptors resulting in
			a “blind spot” in the retina. The blind spot in either retina falls in the medial retina
			and does not process corresponding regions of the visual field.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_23.jpg" alt="Layers of the retina in stained tissue (a) and as a drawing (b).">
			<caption>Layers of the retina in stained tissue (a) and as a drawing (b). This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
		
		<p>At the exact center of the retina is a point where light is focused by the lens and the
			greatest <term>visual acuity</term> is found. This is known as the <term>fovea</term> and it is a small dimple in the layers of the retina where
			there are no blood vessels, ganglion cells or bipolar cells to interrupt light reaching
			the receptor cells. Because more light passes to the receptor cells at the
			fovea, it is in this region that visual acuity is the greatest. From this central point
			of the retina, visual acuity drops off towards the peripheral retina. This difference is
			easily evidenced by looking directly at a word in the middle of this paragraph. The
			visual stimulus exactly in the middle of the field of view falls on the fovea and is in
			the sharpest focus. Without moving your eyes off that word, notice that words at the
			beginning or end of the paragraph are not in focus. Beyond the words on your computer
			screen, visual stimuli are less sharp to the point where the edges of vision have vague,
			blurry shapes that cannot be clearly identified. A large part of neural function to
			support the visual system is concerned with moving the eyes and head so that important
			visual stimuli are centered on the fovea of the retina.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_24.jpg" alt="Anatomy of the fovea." width="550">
			<caption>Anatomy of the fovea. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
