<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Vision_8"><head><title>Photoreceptor Cells</title><objref idref="eye_structures_LO" /><objref idref="eye_light_LO" /></head><body><p id="c0bc57df88b44fb5b3d17f03f29a70d2">Light falling on the retina causes chemical changes to pigment molecules (called <term>opsins</term>) in photoreceptors, ultimately leading to a change in the activity of the retinal ganglion cells. Photoreceptor cells have two parts, the <term>inner segment</term> and the <term>outer segment</term>. <image id="c075060a287443d399a0cc6ac37f6cb7" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_25.jpg" alt="Structure of the photoreceptor cells." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="d8f368b2024b4bc9bcaf743e6a677fbb">Structure of the photoreceptor cells. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image> The inner segment contains the nucleus and other common organelles of a cell while the outer segment is a specialized region of the cell where photoreception takes place. There are two types of photoreceptors, <term>rods</term> and <term>cones</term>, based on the shape of their outer segment. The rod-shaped outer segments of rod photoreceptors contain a stack of membrane-bound discs that contain a photosensitive opsin pigment called <term>rhodopsin</term>, which is sensitive to a wide bandwidth of light (white light). The cone-shaped outer segments of cone cells contain one of three photosensitive opsin pigments, called <term>photopsins</term>. Each of the three photopsins are sensitive to a particular bandwidth of light, corresponding to the colors of red, green or blue, allowing for the ability to distinguish color.</p><image id="a10ea54877784a9eb6ca65b44d67d09f" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_26.jpg" alt="Sensitivity of rod and cone photoreceptors to wavelengths of    light." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption><p id="b5e49a3af87644ff80b054bf743e7095">Sensitivity of rod and cone photoreceptors to wavelengths of light. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ce952f3039a242be95be0e6ac25ea329">When a photoreceptor cell is activated by a photon near the wavelength it is sensitive to, the energy from the light creates a change in its opsin molecule called <term>photoisomerization</term>. Photoisomerization is the first step in a process that ultimately leads to a change in membrane potential of the photoreceptor. Until the opsin is changed back to its original shape, the photoreceptor cell cannot respond to light energy, which is called <term>bleaching</term>. When a large group of opsins are bleached, vision will be affected until enough opsins can return to the receptive state. You may have experienced this after the bright flash from a camera.</p><section id="a75675b6de9c4ea081bd483a2bbbc4cd"><title>Light and Dark Adaptation</title><body><p id="d5a748fc3cba4ab3ad9f33233ee815f9">Because rhodopsin found in the rod cells is most sensitive to white light while the cone cells are color specific, rods are suited for vision in low-light conditions and cones are suited for brighter conditions. In normal sunlight, rhodopsin will be constantly bleached and the cones are active. In a darkened room, there is not enough light to activate cone opsins, and vision is entirely dependent on rods. Rods are so sensitive to light that a single photon can result in an action potential from the corresponding RGC. The three cone photopsins, being sensitive to different wavelengths of light, can aid in color vision. By comparing the activity of the three different cones, the brain can extract color information from visual stimuli. Since rods are bleached when cones are active and cones cannot react to low-intensity light, rods result in monochromatic vision. In a dark room, everything appears as a shade of gray shadow. If you think that you can see colors in the dark, it is most likely because your brain knows what color something is and relies on that memory. If you are walking through your dark living room and you are certain that the couch appears green, this is because you already know what color it is, not because you perceive it with rod photoreceptors.</p></body></section></body></workbook_page>
