<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_olfaction_1">
	<head>
		<title>Taste (Gustation)</title>
		<objref idref="explain_taste_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_tastebuds_LO"/>
		<objref idref="explain_tastechems_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
	
		<p><term>Taste</term>, or <term>gustation</term>, is a sense that develops
			through the interaction of dissolved molecules with taste buds. Currently five
			sub-modalities (tastes) are recognized, including sweet, salty, bitter, sour, and <term>umami</term> (savory taste or the taste of protein). Umami is the most
			recent taste sensation described, gaining acceptance in the 1980s. Further research has
			the potential to discover more sub-modalities in this area, with some scientists
			suggesting that a taste receptor for fats is likely.</p>
		<p>Taste is associated mainly with the tongue, although there are taste (gustatory)
			receptors on the palate and epiglottis as well. The surface of the tongue, along with
			the rest of the oral cavity, is lined by a stratified squamous epithelium. In the
			surface of the tongue are raised bumps, called <term>papilla</term>, that
			contain the taste buds. There are three types of papilla, based on their appearance: vallate, foliate, and fungiform.</p> 
			
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_35.jpg" alt="Structures Associated with Taste. The tongue is covered
			with papillae (a), which contain taste buds (b and c). Within the taste buds are
			specialized taste cells (d) that respond to chemical stimuli dissolved in the saliva
			and, in turn, activate sensory nerve fibers in the facial and glossopharyngeal
			nerves." width="600">
			<caption>Structures Associated with Taste. The tongue is covered
				with papillae (a), which contain taste buds (b and c). Within the taste buds are
				specialized taste cells (d) that respond to chemical stimuli dissolved in the saliva
				and, in turn, activate sensory nerve fibers in the facial and glossopharyngeal
				nerves. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
			
			<p>The number of taste buds within papillae
			varies, with each bud containing several specialized taste cells
			(<term>gustatory receptor cells</term>) for the transduction of taste stimuli.
			These receptor cells release neurotransmitters when certain chemicals in ingested
			substances (such as food) are carried to their surface in saliva. Neurotransmitter from
			the gustatory cells can activate the sensory neurons in the facial and glossopharyngeal
			cranial nerves.</p>
		<!--Link to cranial nerves?-->
		
		<wb:inline idref="explain_tastechems_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_tastechems_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
