<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Reflexes_5a"><head><title>Characteristics of Pain</title><objref idref="define_pain_characteristics_LO" /></head><body><section id="b56dcd25921e4cc8927f76e43fd4d972"><title>Hyperalgesia and Analgesia</title><body><p id="bb446536e15845c78356b0f4dffde8bc">Notice that because chemical and silent nociceptors are activated after tissue injury has set in, our sensations of pain can change over time. An initial cut will activate mechano-nociceptors, sending the fast pain signals along A-delta fibers to the brain. After inflammation in the area has set in, the chemical and/or silent nociceptors may send information along C fibers, producing a different pain sensation. If these silent nociceptors become sensitized by the inflammatory mediators, then we might experience <term>hyperalgesia</term>, where tissue stretch to an injured area can be sensed as a more intense pain.</p><p id="fecba8c4a1ae4c7bab6c55d7e30b4230">Our ability to provide <term>analgesia</term> (reduce or block pain) is usually directed at inhibiting the local formation of the mediators that activate chemical nociceptors (this is how aspirin and ibuprofen work), blocking the transmission of signals along peripheral pain fibers (local anesthetics), or interrupting the transmission of pain signals in the CNS (endogenous or exogenous opioids as well as general anesthesia). You may have had experience with a local anesthetic during dental work or when stitches were put in. They act by blocking the ability of nerve fibers to conduct action potentials. Local anesthetics block C fibers more easily, but in time the A-delta fibers are also blocked. This is why the dentist waits awhile after giving the local anesthetic before commencing the work that would otherwise cause pain – you want to make sure your A-delta fibers are fully blocked as well!</p></body></section><section id="bcc2a4d2e3914e0084a1974e0070d3e9"><title>CNS Role in Pain</title><body><p id="f82172b0026543fb8e4661c67bcb4b28">Although the focus of this section has been on the peripheral sensation and transmission of resulting action potentials, keep in mind that the processing of pain, such as pain sensation, localization and the physical and emotional responses to pain, are functions of the CNS.</p><wb:inline idref="define_hyperalgesia_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="define_analgesia_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="c660d6284a4c407da15aa7f4e42dbcd4"><title>Receptive Field</title><body><p id="e238bea74d7f49f3ba28dadf44fbcda8">Although the receptors of the somesthetic senses are widely distributed throughout the body, the density of receptors varies from place to place. This often leads to corresponding changes to the sizes of the <term>receptive field</term> for any modality. The receptive field is the area from which a sensory receptor, and its corresponding neuron, can detect a stimulus.</p><image id="be7df4e5ee7644a9bc08a67381c06b87" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_12.jpg" alt="Receptive field areas around a sensory receptor." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="de8ab1651cdb4885af45515c9a5c1b69">Receptive fields. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unitied States (<link href="http://creativecommmons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommmons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ddf7f8aed6c842ccac3d10b6f83d7382">The size of a receptive field might vary from a few square millimeters to tens of square millimeters, depending on receptor type and location. With larger receptive fields, the CNS has less ability to localize stimuli or to differentiate between multiple stimuli. This can be demonstrated by a two-point discrimination test where two thin objects (such as pen tips) are touched to a person’s skin in proximity to one another. If this is done on the upper back, even objects that are a centimeter apart may be interpreted by the individual to be a single object. The same distance between objects on the lips or fingertips is easily interpreted by the CNS as separate objects. Receptor densities and the corresponding size of receptive fields are represented in the CNS as the sensory homunculus with the primary somatosensory cortex.</p><image id="c082b6a6575e4413ae5b954ecdf28237" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_13.jpg" alt="Sensory homunculus. The size of the     body regions depicted indicate the amount of cortical area dedicated to processing     sensory information from that region. For example, the hand and fingers have a large     cortical area devoted to processing information sent from the high density of     sensory receptors found in these structures." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="e67fedd655b346659ebbf82b443a9256">Sensory homunculus. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="define_receptive_field_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="define_receptive_field_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
