<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_olfaction_2">
	<head>
		<title>Primary Taste Sensations</title>
		<objref idref="explain_taste_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_taste_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>As previously mentioned, five different taste sensations are currently recognized. The
			first, salty, is simply the sense of Na<sup>+ </sup>concentration in the saliva. As the
				Na<sup>+ </sup>concentration becomes high outside the taste cells, a strong
			concentration gradient drives their diffusion into the cells. This depolarizes the
			cells, leading them to release neurotransmitter.</p>
		<p>The sour taste is transduced similar to that of salty, except that it is a response to
			the H<sup>+ </sup>concentration released from acidic substances (those with low pH),
			instead of a response to Na<sup>+</sup>. For example, orange juice, which contains
			citric acid, will taste sour because it has a pH value of about 3. Of course, it is
			often sweetened so that the sour taste is masked. As the concentration of the hydrogen
			ions increases because of ingesting acidic compounds, the depolarization of specific
			taste cells increases.</p>
		<p>The other three tastes; sweet, bitter and umami are transduced through G-protein coupled
			cell surface receptors instead of the direct diffusion of ions like we discussed with
			salty and sour. The sweet taste is the sensitivity of taste cells to the presence of
			glucose dissolved in the saliva. Molecules that are similar in structure to glucose will
			have a similar effect on the sensation of sweetness. Other monosaccharides such as
			fructose or artificial sweeteners like aspartame (Nutrasweet™), saccharine, or sucralose
			(Splenda™) will activate the sweet receptors as well. The affinity for each of these
			molecules varies, and some will taste “sweeter” than glucose because they bind to the
			G-protein coupled receptor differently.</p>
		<p>The bitter taste can be stimulated by a large number of molecules collectively known as
				<term>alkaloids</term>. Alkaloids are essentially the opposite of acids,
			they contain basic (in the sense of pH) nitrogen atoms within their structures. Most
			alkaloids originate from plant sources, with common examples being hops (in beer),
			tannins (in wine), tea, aspirin, and similar molecules. Coffee contains alkaloids and is
			slightly acidic, with the alkaloids contributing the bitter taste to coffee. When enough
			alkaloids are contained in a substance it can stimulate the gag reflex. This is a
			protective mechanism because alkaloids are often produced by plants as a toxin to deter
			infectious microorganisms and plant eating animals. Such molecules may be toxic to
			animals as well, so we tend to avoid eating bitter foods. When we do eat bitter foods,
			they are often combined with a sweet component to make them more palatable (cream and
			sugar in coffee, for example).</p>
		<p>The taste known as umami is often referred to as the savory taste. The name was created
			by the Japanese researcher who originally described it. Like sweet and bitter, it is
			based on the activation of G-protein coupled receptors, in this case by amino acids,
			especially glutamine. Thus, umami might be considered the taste of proteins, and is most
			associated with meat containing dishes.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="explain_tastechems_LBD2" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
		<body><wb:inline idref="describe_taste_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_taste_DIGT2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
		</body>
			
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
