<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Reflexes_9">
	<head>
		<title>Examples of Somatic Reflexes</title>
		<objref idref="define_reflex_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="reflex_pairs_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
	<section>
		<title>Stretch Reflex</title>
		<body>
			<p>One of the simplest reflexes is a <term>stretch reflex</term>. In
			this reflex, when a skeletal muscle is stretched, a muscle spindle in the belly of the
			muscle is activated. The axon from this receptor travels to the spinal cord where it
			synapses with the motor neuron controlling the muscle, stimulating it to contract. This
			is a rapid, monosynaptic, ipsilateral reflex that helps to maintain the length of
			muscles and contributes to joint stabilization. A common example of this reflex is the knee
			jerk reflex that is elicited by a rubber hammer striking against the patellar tendon,
			such as during a physical exam. When the hammer strikes, it stretches the tendon, which
			pulls on the quadriceps femoris muscle. Because bones and tendons do not typically pull
			muscles, the muscle “thinks” it is stretching very rapidly, and the reflex acts to
			counteract this stretch. In doing so, the “knee jerk” occurs.</p>
			<!--May want to link to table on somesthetic senses page that lists muscle spindle, or have an activity where students predict what this senses.-->
			<p>Along with the monosynaptic activation of the alpha motor neuron, this reflex also
				includes the activation of an interneuron that inhibits the alpha motor neuron of the
				antagonistic muscle. This aspect of the reflex ensures that contraction of
				the agonist muscle occurs unopposed.</p>
			
			<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_15.jpg" alt="Stretch Reflex.">
				<caption>Stretch Reflex. When a muscle is stretched (1), muscle
					spindles (2) send information to the spinal cord (3) where it synapses on motor neuron
					of the same muscle (4) causing it to contract (5). At the same time, stimulation of an
					inhibitory interneuron (6) prevents contraction of the antagonistic muscle (7 and
					8). This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
					Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
						href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
						>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
			</image>
		</body>
	</section>
		<section>
			<title>Flexor (Withdrawal) Reflex</title>
	<body>
		<p>Recall from the beginning of this unit that when you touch a hot stove, you reflexively
			pull your hand away. Sensory receptors in the skin sense extreme temperature
			and the early signs of tissue damage. To avoid further damage, information travels along
			the sensory fibers from the skin and into the posterior (dorsal) horn of the spinal
			cord. Once in the spinal cord, the sensory fibers synapse with a variety of interneurons
			that mediate the responses of the reflex. These responses included a strong initial
			withdrawal of the flexor muscle (caused by activation of the alpha motor neurons),
			inhibition of the extensor muscle (mediated through inhibitory interneurons), and
			sustained contraction of the flexor (mediated by a spinal cord neuronal circuit). And as
			already discussed, the sensory information will also travel to the brain to develop a
			conscious awareness of the situation such that conscious decision-making can take over
			immediately after the reflex occurs.</p>
		
		<!--<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_14.jpg" alt="Flexor Reflex.">
			<caption>Flexor Reflex. A flexor reflex is typically initiated by
				activation of pain fibers. The information from these fibers is processed at the level
				of the spinal cord to elicit the initial motor response (somatic reflex) that tries to
				protect the tissues from further injury. In time, conscious control takes over our
				actions. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>-->
	
	</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Crossed-Extensor Reflex</title>
			
		<body>
			<p>Imagine what would happen if, when you stepped on a sharp object, it elicited a strong
			withdrawal reflex of your leg. You would likely topple over. In order to prevent this
			from happening, as the flexor (withdrawal) reflex involving the injured leg happens, an
			extension reflex of the opposite (contralateral) leg occurs at the same time, creating a
			crossed-extensor reflex. In this case, the ipsilateral limb reacts with a
			withdrawal reflex (stimulating flexor muscles and inhibiting extensor muscles on same
			side), but the contralateral extensor muscles contract so that the person can
			appropriately shift balance to the opposite foot during the reflex.</p>
		
			<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_16.jpg" alt="Crossed-Extensor Reflex." width="500">
				<caption>Crossed-Extensor Reflex. In this reflex, as withdrawal
					from the damaging stimulus occurs in the ipsilateral leg, extension occurs in the
					contralateral leg as a way of maintaining balance. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
					Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
						href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
						>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
			</image>
		
		</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="define_reflex_DIGT2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
