<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Reflexes_7"><head><title>Reflexes</title><objref idref="define_reflex_LO" /></head><body><p id="e1edd7d99ed74d5793d10ab27eba3f53">So far we have discussed the types and distribution of somesthetic receptors, now let’s consider what the central nervous system might do with the information it is receiving from these receptors. One option is to make conscious decisions about how to react to the information, such as deciding how to change our behavior if we are cold or in pain. As discussed in the section on the autonomic nervous system, another option is to use this sensory information to inform a <term>visceralreflex arc</term>, like those involved in the regulation of blood pressure or body temperature. Here we will consider using sensory information to inform <term>somatic reflexes</term>, where automatic motor responses occur as a result of the sensory stimuli.</p><p id="cd38edbb0c77463ca66b4115d29d414c">No matter which type of CNS mediated reflex or response we are referring to, the general model is the same. Sensory information activates a receptor that sends information to the CNS via an afferent neuron, some level of synaptic or higher level processing occurs, and, if a response is necessary or appropriate, the response is initiated through efferent neurons. You might recognize this as the same model used to maintain homeostasis. Reflexes are a unique category of responses because they do not require the higher centers used for conscious or voluntary responses. Instead reflexes are involuntary, stereotyped (they are repeatable under the same stimulus conditions) responses that occur quickly.</p><wb:inline idref="define_reflex_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="define_reflex_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="b69640969cfc464cbb7e5c5319be241d"><title>Categories of Reflexes</title><body><p id="a1041532abc5455e9be85580bba78043">As mentioned, reflexes can either be visceral or somatic. <term>Visceral reflexes</term> involve a glandular or non-skeletal muscular response carried out in internal organs such as the heart, blood vessels, or structures of the GI tract. They utilize neurons of the autonomic nervous system to elicit their actions. Visceral reflexes have been more fully discussed in the section on the autonomic nervous system. In contrast, somatic reflexes involve unconscious skeletal muscle motor responses. In doing so, these reflexes utilize some of the same lower motor neurons (alpha motor neurons) used to control skeletal muscle during conscious movement. Because reflexes are quick, it makes sense that somatic reflexes are often meant to protect us from injury. As examples, reflexes contribute to the maintenance of balance and rapid withdrawal of the hand or foot from damaging stimuli.</p><p id="bff4153d9c3b46f3b84b4286e1b84154">Somatic reflexes can either be intrinsic (present at birth) or learned. We will be focusing on <term>intrinsic reflexes</term>, which occur as the result of normal human development. Learned reflexes are much more complicated in their anatomical structure and result from repetitive actions, such as athletic training. Reflexes can also be categorized by the number of synapses they involve (<term>monosynaptic reflex</term> versus <term>polysynaptic reflex</term>) or the relative position of the sensory receptors to the responding muscles (<term>ipsilateral</term> = same side of the body, <term>contralateral</term> = opposite sides of the body).</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="reflex_pairs_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="reflex_pairs_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
