<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="NervousSensory_Vision_4"><head><title>Focusing Light on the Retina</title><objref idref="eye_structures_LO" /><objref idref="eye_light_LO" /></head><body><p id="d30d1d502ef54b1886db195cdbc690ff">The retina, where the photoreceptors are found, is located at the posterior aspect of the eye. In order for the retina to transmit the most appropriate information to the brain, the light rays must land on the retinal cells in focus and with appropriate intensity. The cornea, pupil (the center of the iris) and the lens are responsible for meeting these requirements.</p><p id="f67eaf45b7d84ce684e74a2eed6ade90">When light moves from one medium (such as air) into another medium (such as the cornea or lens), any rays not entering at a 90 degree angle will be refracted, or bent. Because both the cornea and lens have curved surfaces, they refract some of the light rays entering the eye. In doing so, they compress the image of what we see so that a large amount of visual information can be processed by a small amount of retinal tissue. The cornea refracts more light than the lens does because its surface is more curved, but the lens has the ability to change its shape, and therefore fine-tune the amount of refraction necessary to focus the light rays on the retina. This process is known as accommodation.</p><image id="f5ac5e986f2f44f786a023e6fc36b658" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_20.jpg" alt="The refraction of light rays as they pass from one medium to    another (a), such as through the cornea and lens (b)." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="fcc91e0d63f04acbb4eb41a0477b5abb">The refraction of light rays as they pass from one medium to another (a), such as through the cornea and lens (b). This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="eye_lightpath_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="eye_lightpath_DIGT1" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../../webcontent/eye_lightpath_DIGT1-layout.xml</param></wb:inline><p id="eb9e14dfeb3d4d139f2fb9c7ce8eae8c">The lens changes its shape in response to changes in tension of the ciliary muscles on the suspensory ligaments (also called zonules) that hold the lens in place. When the ciliary muscles contract, the suspensory ligaments are less taught, causing the lens to become slightly more spherical and refract light more. This is what happens when objects that are being viewed are close, or moved closer. Light coming from objects that are far away do not require as much refraction and are viewed with the ciliary muscles relaxed and more tension on the lens, which makes it more oblong. The relationship between the ciliary muscles and the taughtness of the suspensory ligaments is a counterintuitive one for most individuals, but the eye has a unique anatomy the leads to this relationship. See the following video.</p><youtube id="affe7e9239f94d8c91207cf0bc8c4a5d" src="aQlCnM0TiRY" height="315" width="420" controls="true"><title>Ciliary Muscle Contraction</title><cite id="i677955a208e84932972834e2df71b3e7" /><caption><p id="ab6737e55d6f7404eb65c291609c2d94a">Using drawn models, the narrator explains the relationship between the ciliary muscles and the taughtness of the suspensory ligaments.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube><image id="ae4935c380aa47e3aceda64ecd4740bb" src="../../webcontent/Nerv_21.jpg" alt="Accommodation of the lens with distant and near    vision. As the suspensory ligaments are pulled tight, the lens lengthens and thins, and as the suspensory ligaments relax, the lens shortens and widens." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="f7b5d856f9c74164abc2cfa833e10169">Accommodation of the lens with distant and near vision. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="explain_eye_image_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="a81b9136fca04fd1bc7767b2213ebc33">Along with accommodation of the lens when objects are near, the pupil also tends to constrict to allow less peripheral light to enter the posterior chamber of the eye. In doing so, objects can be viewed more crisply. The pupil will also constrict when conditions are bright and dilate under low light conditions. This way the retina can receive an appropriate amount of light to activate its photoreceptors without bleaching them with too much light.</p><wb:inline idref="explain_eye_image_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
