<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Reflexes_6">
	<head>
		<title>Receptive Field</title>
		<!--<objref idref="define_receptive_field_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Although the receptors of the somesthetic senses are widely distributed throughout the
			body, the density of receptors varies from place to place. This often leads to
			corresponding changes to the sizes of the <term>receptive field</term> for any
			modality. The receptive field is the area from which a sensory receptor, and its
			corresponding neuron, can detect a stimulus.</p>
		<p>The size of a receptive field might vary from a few square millimeters to tens of square
			millimeters, depending on receptor type and location. With larger receptive fields, the
			CNS has less ability to localize stimuli or to differentiate between multiple stimuli.
			This can be demonstrated by a two-point discrimination test where two thin objects (such
			as pen tips) are touched to a person’s skin in proximity to one another. If this is done
			on the upper back, even objects that are a centimeter apart may be interpreted by the
			individual to be a single object. The same distance between objects on the lips or
			fingertips is easily interpreted by the CNS as separate objects. Receptor densities and
			the corresponding size of receptive fields are represented in the CNS as the sensory
			homunculus with the primary somatosensory cortex.</p>
		<!--Provide link to section on brain that discusses homunculus and somatosensory cortex.-->
		<p><em style="bold">Figure 4:Sensory homunculus</em>. <em style="italic">The size of the
				body regions depicted indicate the amount of cortical area dedicated to processing
				sensory information from that region. For example, the hand and fingers have a large
				cortical area devoted to processing information sent from the high density of
				sensory receptors found in these structures.</em></p>
		<wb:inline idref="define_receptive_field_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="define_receptive_field_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
