<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSensory_Hearing_6">
	<head>
		<title>Crista Ampullaris and Dynamic Equilibrium</title>
		<objref idref="distinguish_equilibrium_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_ear_crista_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The semicircular canals are three ring-like extensions from the vestibule (the region
			containing the saccule and utricle). One is oriented in the horizontal
			plane and two are in the vertical plane. The vertical canals are 45<sup>o </sup>off of
			the sagittal plane, one is anterior and one is posterior.</p> 
			
		<image src="../../webcontent/Nerv_34.jpg" alt="Structure and Function of the Semicircular Canals. The
			three canals each have an ampulla containing a crista ampullaris and cupula (a). When
			the head is stationary, the cupula, and embedded stereocilia, are not bent (b). When the
			head rotates in the same plane as one of the canals, the fluid in the canal (endolymph)
			lags, leading to bending of the stereocilia in the cupula, which initiates nerve
			impulses." width="600">
			<caption>Structure and Function of the Semicircular Canals. The
				three canals each have an ampulla containing a crista ampullaris and cupula (a). When
				the head is stationary, the cupula, and embedded stereocilia, are not bent (b). When the
				head rotates in the same plane as one of the canals, the fluid in the canal (endolymph)
				lags, leading to bending of the stereocilia in the cupula, which initiates nerve
				impulses. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
				Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
			
			<p>At the base of each
			semicircular canal, where it meets with the vestibule is an enlarged region known as the
				<term>ampulla</term>, which contains a hair-cell containing structure,
			called the <term>crista ampullaris</term> that responds to rotational movement.
			The stereocilia of the hair cells extend into the <term>cupula</term>, a
				membrane that attaches to the top of the ampulla.</p>
		<!--Add link-->
	
		<p>When the head rotates in a plane parallel to the semicircular canal, the fluid in the
			canal does not move as quickly as the head is moving. This pushes the cupula in the
			opposite direction, deflecting the stereocilia and creating a nerve impulse. Considering
			the semicircular canals on either side of the head, three orthogonal planes are defined,
			the horizontal plane with both horizontal canals, and two vertical planes 90<sup>o
			</sup>to each other with the anterior canal from one side and the posterior canal from
			the other. In each pair, deflection of the cupula on one side of the body causes
			depolarization of the hair cells while the same movement causes hyperpolarization of the
			hair cells on the other side of the body. For example, when the head rotates to the
			right, the horizontal canals are active and the right side depolarizes while the left
			hyperpolarizes, indicating the direction of the movement. By comparing the relative
			movements of all six semicircular canals, the vestibular system can establish movement
			in any direction within three-dimensional space.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
