<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="_u4_m0_relative_frequency1_lbd1">
    <head>
        <title>Relative Frequency</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Background</title>
            <body>
                <p>Recall from the introduction to probability section the birthday problem, which
                    was presented as an example of when probability is counterintuitive. In
                    particular, recall that we asked: "What is the probability that at least 2
                    people out of a group of 60 will have the same birthday?" The answer, a 99.4%
                    chance, was very surprising.</p>
                <p>How about the probability of at least one "birthday match" in a group of 30
                    people?</p>
                <p>At this point in the course, we do not have the tools needed to solve this
                    problem, so the best we can do is estimate this probability using relative
                    frequency.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>As before, to simplify things, we will ignore leap years (i.e., we will assume
                    that all years have 365 days) and we will assume that all days of the year are
                    equally likely to be birthdays.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Plan</title>
            <body>
                <p>Using the activity below, we will generate (with replacement) 30 birthdays. The
                    group of 30 birthdays represents a group of 30 people. We will then observe
                    whether any birthday is repeated (i.e., whether there is at least one birthday
                    match in the group). To use the relative frequency idea, we will then repeat
                    this process 20 times, and count how many of the 20 repetitions had at least one
                    birthday match. This relative frequency will be our estimated probability of at
                    least one birthday match in a group of 30 people.</p>
                <p>To make this process easier, keep a tally of the number of times you have done
                    the simulation. In addition to this tally, keep a tally of the number of times
                    you got at least one birthday match. So, each time you run the simulation, you
                    will update two tallies: the number of runs of the applet and the number of
                    times you got at least one match. The relative frequency will be the ratio of
                    these two tallies. It will be our estimated probability of at least one birthday
                    match in a group of 30 people.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Simulation</title>
            <body>
                <iframe src="../../../webcontent/html_activities/relative_frequency/relative_frequency.html"
                    height="700" width="750"/>
                <!--   <p>Click <link href="http://www-stat.stanford.edu/~susan/surprise/Birthday.html"
                        target="new">here</link> to launch the applet in a separate window.</p>--> 
                <p><em>Step 1:</em> Choose <em>Generate 30 Birthdays</em> and press the
                    <em>Start</em> button.</p>
                <p>Notice that random birthdays are generated, then filed in the appropriate month
                    and day. Look for <!--a red-->an orange square; this indicates a match. <!--There is also a
                    rectangle on the lower right side of the screen that keeps-->Underneath "Generate ____ Birthdays" are Birthdays and Matches labels that keep track of the number
                    of birthdays and the number of matches.</p>
                <p><em>Step 2:</em> Record your results from the first run, then press the
                    <em>Reset</em> button. You have now completed 1 of the 20 runs of the
                    simulation.</p>
                <p><em>Step 3:</em> Press the <em>Start</em> button, then record your results for
                    the second run of the simulation.</p>
                <!--<p><em>Step 4:</em> For the remaining 18 runs, check
                    <em style="bold">Fast Update</em> so that the process is much faster.</p>-->
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_relfreq1_lbd_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <!--<flash src="../../../webcontent/flash/ShortAnswerTutor.swf" width="505" height="369">
<param name="question_file">../../../webcontent/flash/_u4_m1_lbdtutor2b.xml</param>
<param name="problem_name">_u4_m1_lbdtutor2b</param>
</flash>-->
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m0_relfreq1_lbd_tutor2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
