<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="identify_unique_blood_flow_organs_DIGT"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Why is the liver an exception to the general rule that blood flows from the heart to a single organ and back to the heart?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="A">The liver is responsible for processing substance that were absorbed from the GI tract that may be dangerous to the body before they are transported around the rest of the body.</choice><choice value="B">The liver is responsible for filtering the plasma through its nephrons to remove toxins.</choice><choice value="C">The liver produces hormones that need to travel directly to the pituitary to regulate body functions.</choice><choice value="D">It is not an exception, because the functions of the liver are so important it only gets blood straight from the heart.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="identify_unique_blood_flow_organs_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The liver receives blood from the GI tract before it returns to the heart so the hepatocytes can metabolize some of the potentially dangerous substances that entered the blood stream.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The liver contains hepatocytes, not nephrons, that are responsible for helping to remove potentially toxic materials. The kidney contains nephrons.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The liver is not part of the endocrine system. The hypothalmus and pituitary system are an exception to this rule that involve the transport of hormones.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The liver does receive blood straight from the heart, but it also receives blood from the GI tract that contains nutrients and toxins absorbed through the GI tract.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
