<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m5_integration_00">
	<head>
		<title>Blood Flow to Organ Systems</title>
		<objref idref="describe_blood_flow_organ_systems_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="identify_unique_blood_flow_organs_OBJ"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Our cardiac output varies with our level of activity, decreasing when resting and
			increasing when we are more active. For example, cardiac output can increase from the
			typical 5 L/min at rest up to 15-20 L/min during maximal exercise. When we experience
			such changes in cardiac output it is important to realize that not all organs and
			tissues will experience similar changes in blood flow. So when your cardiac output
			triples, you will not experience a tripling of flow to each organ. Instead, flow is
			directed to those tissues that need it most, typically based on their metabolic state.
			If you are sprinting, your cardiac output might triple, but the flow to the muscles in
			your legs might go up six or eight fold, while flow to your digestive organs can
			actually decrease. Thus flow is directed to those capillary beds surrounded by cells
			with the greatest requirement for oxygen and nutrients.</p>
		<p>There are some organs in the body where their level of blood flow is not as dependent on
			their metabolic need, but because they are important in processing and/or interacting
			with blood in other ways. Examples include the kidneys, which process the blood by
			removing metabolic wastes, the lungs, which participate in gas exchange, the liver,
			which processes the substances absorbed in the GI tract, glands, which release hormones
			into the bloodstream, and the skin, which helps regulate body temperature. In the case
			of the liver and the pituitary gland, they interact with the blood through a portal
			system, where the vascular network in these tissues contains two capillary beds along
			the path of blood flow. The kidney blood flow also involves two capillary beds, but
			these are connected by an arteriole. </p>
		<p>The portal system involving the liver plays an important role in processing substances
			absorbed by the capillaries along the intestines. These capillary beds in the intestines
			absorb nutrients and other chemicals. This same blood then travels to the liver where it
			enters the liver sinusoids (a second capillary bed) before returning to the venous
			circulation. Specific functions occurring in the liver include storing glucose as
			glycogen, repackaging lipids into lipoproteins and detoxification of harmful, and even
			useful, chemicals, such as drugs. In fact, when discussing the ability of orally
			administered drugs to distribute throughout the body, the effect of the liver is known
			as the “first pass” effect.</p>
		<p>The kidney actually contains two capillary beds in the same organ, where the first
			capillary bed (the glomerular capillaries) filters the blood and the second (either the
			peritubular or vasa recta capillaries) reabsorbs most of the original filtrate.</p>
		<p>The cells of the anterior pituitary gland respond to chemical signals secreted into
			capillaries of the hypothalamus. Once the blood from the hypothalamus enters the
			anterior pituitary, it enters a second capillary bed so that the cells of the anterior
			pituitary can sense these signals and respond by secreting their own hormones if
			necessary.</p>

		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_blood_flow_organ_systems_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="identify_unique_blood_flow_organs_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>

		<!--<p>We have reviewed the systemic circuit of blood flow throughout the unit. With only three
			exceptions, the circulatory system perfuses one set of capillaries or one organ before
			it returns to the heart. This allows the delivery of oxygen from the lungs and the
			removal of carbon dioxide from the organ tissues. For example, blood leaves the heart
			and travels to the spleen where it ultimately passes into the capillary bed within the
			spleen. Oxygen is delivered and carbon dioxide is removed. Once the blood exits the
			spleen, it is transported by the veins directly back to the heart. It doesn’t perfuse
			another organ system. However, there are three systems that are the exception to this
			rule: the liver, the kidney, and the hypothalamus/pituitary system.</p>
		<p>Once blood has traveled to the gastrointestinal tract, instead of returning to the heart,
			it travels to the liver. Why? The liver processes nutrients and other molecules; some of
			which may be dangerous to the body, that have been absorbed by the GI tract. Some
			substances are metabolized (broken down) and some are untouched. By passing the blood
			through the liver before sending it back to the heart to be distributed to the rest of
			the body, it provides the body an opportunity to remove some of the potentially harmful
			substances. In fact, when discussing the ability of orally administered drugs to
			distribute throughout the body, the effect of the liver is known as the “first pass
			effect”.</p>
		<p>In the kidney, a significant amount of plasma is filtered by the nephrons to be
			processed. The main function of the nephrons is to reabsorb the substances that the body
			wants to keep. This is also done using two capillary networks in series. In the first
			capillary network, the glomerular capillaries, filtration occurs. In the second
			capillary network (the peritubular and vasa recta capillaries, reabsorption occurs.</p>
		<p>The last exception occurs within the brain. Many hormones are produced in the
			hypothalamus (a small region of the brain that regulates bodily functions, such as body
			temperature and hunger), located deep within the brain, and travel to the pituitary
			gland (gland that secretes hormones and controls hormones functions) to regulate hormone
			release from the pituitary. Therefore, blood enters the capillaries of the hypothalamus
			and carry hormones and other chemicals to the capillaries of the pituitary gland. Most
			of the other organs receive blood from the heart and return it to the heart directly
			without passing through another
			organ.<!-All other organs receive blood from the heart and return it to the heart directly 
			without passing through another organ.-></p>-->
	</body>
</workbook_page>
