<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m5_integration_02">
	<head>
		<title>Hormonal Regulation of the Cardiovascular System</title>
		<objref idref="list_local_hormonal_neuronal_factors_peripheral_resist_OBJ"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>A number of hormones are involved in the regulation of blood flow and BP. They work by
			changing cardiac output, systemic vascular resistance, or total blood volume.</p>
		<section id="_u9_m5_renin-angiotension-aldosterone">
			<title>The Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System</title>
			<body>
				<p>The <term>renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system</term> is set in motion when
					decreases in blood pressure or renal blood flow stimulate cells in the kidney to
					secrete <term>renin</term> into the blood. This leads to a pathway that
					ultimately produces the hormone <term>angiotensin II</term>, which increases BP
					in two ways. First, as a vasoconstrictor, angiotensin II increases BP by
					increasing peripheral vascular resistance. Second, it causes the kidney tubules
					to reabsorb sodium. High plasma angiotensin is also a trigger for higher levels
					of <term>aldosterone</term> synthesis by the adrenal cortex. This hormone also
					acts on the kidneys to increase the reabsorption of sodium ions. The increased
					reabsorption of Na+ leads to enhanced water reabsorption at the kidneys, and
					this causes the total blood volume to rise, elevating the BP and leading to an
					increase in venous return. This increase in the amount of blood flowing into the
					heart also increases cardiac output.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section id="_u9_m5_epinephrine_norepinephrine">
			<title>Epinephrine and Norepinephrine</title>
			<body>
				<p>Sympathetic stimulation promotes the release of <term>epinephrine</term> and
						<term>norepinephrine</term> by the adrenal medulla. As described above,
					these hormones (or neurotransmitters) increase the heart rate (chronotropy) and
					force of contraction (inotropy). As the force of contraction increases the
					stroke volume also increases. Because cardiac output (CO) is the product of HR
					and SV, CO increases. The increase is CO will also lead to an increase in
					arterial pressure, as described earlier. Epinephrine (or norepinephrine) also
					has the effect of constricting arterioles and veins in the abdominal organs and
					skin, while dilating vessels in the heart and skeletal muscle. This results in
					increased blood flow to muscles during physical activity.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section id="_u9_m5_antidiuretic">
			<title>Antidiuretic Hormone</title>
			<body>
				<p>Decreased blood volume or dehydration prompts an increased release of
						<term>antidiuretic hormone (ADH)</term> from the posterior pituitary. This
					hormone, which is produced by the hypothalamus and stored in the posterior
					pituitary, causes the kidney to retain water. This retention can lead to an
					increase in blood volume and increasing preload similarly to the
					renin-angiotensin system. At very high levels (such as those released during
					circulatory shock) it also causes peripheral blood vessels to constrict, helping
					to raise the BP. This is why antidiuretic hormone is also known as
						<term>vasopressin</term>.</p>
				<!--<p>ADH is an extremely important hormone in maintaining the proper blood volume
					throughout the day. Although its peptide structure (which is very closely
					related to the oxytocin, another hypothalamic hormone) lends itself to effecting
					smooth muscle contractioncausing peripheral vasoconstriction, its primary mode
					of actionis through its ability to increase the number of water channels
					(aquaporin) in the apical surfaces of the kidney distal tubule cells.
					Vasopressin’svasoconstrictor role is of significance under hypovolemic (low
					blood volume) shock.During acute dehydration, ADHsecretion and release increases
					to effectwater retention as mentioned above. Additionally, under such
					conditions, the permeability of the kidney medulla to urea is also increased
					several fold, allowing further water retention by the medullary collecting
					tubules.</p>-->
			</body>
		</section>
		<section id="_u9_m5_atrial_natriuretic_peptide">
			<title>Atrial Natriuretic Peptide (ANP)</title>
			<body>
				<p><term>Atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP)</term>, which is secreted by the myocytes
					of the atria of the heart, decreases BP in two ways. First, it dilates blood
					vessels. Second, it reduces blood volume by increasing the excretion of salt.
					This is a peptide hormone that is secreted in response to higher blood volume
					that stretches the atrial walls.<!-- To a lesser extent, it is also produced by
					ventricular myocytes. In addtition to atrial distention, ANP is also secreted
					during sympathetic stimulation of beta adrenoreceptors, higher plasma sodium
					concentration, and angiotensin.--> The effect of ANP is to ultimately lower blood
					pressure. To achieve that, ANP facilitates glomerular filtration pressure,
					increases excretion of sodium and urea, inhibits aldosterone secretion, and
					inhibits the renin-angiotensin system. </p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="list_local_hormonal_neuronal_factors_peripheral_resist_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
