<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m5_integration_01">
	<head>
		<title>Neural Regulation of the Cardiovascular System</title>
		<objref idref="explain_role_sympathetic_reg_bp_vol_OBJ"/>

	</head>
	<body>
		<p>As you have learned, homeostasis relies on communication between body systems, which is
			primarily carried out by the nervous and endocrine systems. To convey information, the
			nervous system uses neural impulses, and the endocrine system uses hormones released
			into the blood. Most homeostatic controls involve negative feedback mechanisms, in which
			the output of a process either terminates or lessens the original change.</p>

		<!--[NOTE: link to homesotasis unit]-->

		<section id="_u9_m5_neural_regulation">
			<title>Neural Regulation of Cardiac Output</title>
			<body>
				<p>Both the parasympathetic and sympathetic branches of the <term>autonomic nervous
						system (ANS)</term> alter the cardiac output as necessary. The ANS modulates
					the heart rate and force of contraction (contractility) of the
					myocardium.<!--We will discuss these changes in the homeostasis section.--></p>

				<p>The <term>parasympathetic nervous system</term> decreases the heart rate. The
						<term>vagus nerve</term> (the 10th cranial nerve) innervates the SA and AV
					nodes of the heart. It is the parasympathetic branch of the ANS that sets the
					heart rate under normal resting condition. This is commonly referred to as the
					“vagal tone” as it is the vagus nerve that is responsible for this basal cardiac
					function. The effect of the parasympathetic system is to decrease the rate at
					which action potentials are generated at the SA and AV nodes and also to slow
					down the conduction speed between the SA and the AV nodes. Increasing
					parasympathetic activity increases the P-R interval of the ECG. Because the
					parasympathetic nervous system does not innervate the ventricular cells, it does
					not significantly affect the level of contractility of the ventricular
					myocardium. Conversely, the heart rate is increased through the actions of the
						<term>sympathetic nervous system</term>. The sympathetic nerves run from the
					sympathetic chain ganglia, found along the thoracic region of the spinal cord to
					the SA node, the AV node, and the myocytes of the ventricles. The sympathetic
					nerves increase the heart rate by increasing the spontaneous depolarization rate
					of the SA and AV nodes, and increases the rate of conduction through the AV
					node. Sympathetic innervation of the ventricular myocytes can be used to
					increase the contractility of the heart. </p>
				<p>The rate of action potential generation is called <term>chronotropy</term>. As we
					discussed above, the parasympathetic branch produces negative chronotropy. The
					vagus nerve releases acetylcholine, which binds to muscarinic receptors of the
					SA and AV nodal cells. When engaged, receptors activate a signal transduction
					pathway that ultimately leads to the opening of potassium channels. As these
					potassium channels remain open, potassium moves down its electrochemical
					gradient and out of the cell. This results in hyperpolarization of the nodal
					cells, leading to delayed or slower rate of depolarization. Thus the effect is
					to decrease the heart rate (negative
					chronotropy).<!-- The conduction between the SA
					and the AV node and from the nodes to the contractile myocardiumis called
						<term>dromotropy</term>. The effect of the vagus activation is also negative
					dromotropy.--></p>
				<p>In contrast, the sympathetic nervous system exhibits a positive chronotropic
					effect. Sympathetic nerves release norepinephrine (NE), which is also called
					noradrenaline, that binds Beta1 receptors in the nodal cells and cardiac
					myocytes.
					<!-- It increases
					the closing of the potassium channels. This increases the rate that action
					potentials are generated, thereby increasing the heart rate. -->
					Binding of NE (or circulating epinephrine) to the Beta-1 adrenergic receptors
					activate the signal transduction pathway that ultimately leads to the opening of
					calcium channels, allowing influx of Ca++. Calcium channel activation on the
					nodal cells leads to positive chronotropy. Binding of NE (or circulating
					epinephrine; Epi) to the Beta-1 adrenergic receptors activates the signal
					transduction pathway that ultimately leads to the opening of calcium channels,
					allowing influx of Ca++, which increases the contractility of the cardiomyocytes
					(positive inotropy). Calcium channel activation on the nodal cells also leads to
					positive chronotropy.</p>
				<p>Changing the contractility of the ventricular muscle also influences the overall
					cardiac output. This change in contractility is called the <term>inotropic effect</term>.
					Binding of NE to Beta1 receptors of cardiomyocytes increases the contractility
					(positive inotropy) by allowing a greater calcium concentration in the cytosol,
					leading to a greater number of crossbridges being formed.
					<!-- As mentioned
					before, only the sympathetic nervous system innervates the ventricles to
					regulate the contractility.-->
					Before the sympathetic system may exert its effect, inhibition of the vagus
					nerve is required.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="explain_role_sympathetic_reg_bp_vol_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
