<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_lymphatic_homeo_module_review">

    <head>
        <title>Homeostasis Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>

    <body>

        <p>Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this module.
            Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the
            assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before
            attempting the assessment.</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Explain the role of antigen-presenting cells (APCs). Distinguish and describe the
                processing of exogenous and endogenous antigens and provide examples of APCs. Define
                immunocompetence (maturity) and self tolerance and distinguish between naïve and
                activated immune cells.</li>
            <li>Compare and contrast the sites where the lymphocytes originate and achieve their
                immuocompetence, and the primary location of the immunocompetent (mature) cells in
                the body. Compare and contrast mechanisms of antigen challenge and the clonal
                selection processes. Compare and contrast defense mechanisms.</li>
            <li>Provide specific examples to demonstrate how the lymphatic system responds to
                maintain homeostasis in the body, particularly related to the diseases presented in
                the introduction. </li>
            <li>Describe the mechanisms of lymph formation and circulation. Describe the path of
                lymph circulation. Compare and contrast innate (nonspecific) defenses with adaptive
                (specific) defenses. Analyze ways in which the innate and adaptice immunity
                cooperate to enhance the overall resistance to disease.</li>

        </ul>

        <!--  Cardio Structures and Functions Quiz  -->
        <activity idref="u13_homeo_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
        <!--        <activity idref="_u9_m2_structure_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>-->

    </body>

</workbook_page>
