<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_18"><head><title>Immunological Memory</title><objref idref="lymph_CMIR_LO2" /></head><body><p id="c7b42b13b547437ab0fbd2ccf46db3fc">The most significant difference between an innate and adaptive immune response is immunological memory. This process only occurs with adaptive immunity. Innate responses do not produce any memory cells. Therefore, each and every time an innate immune response is initiated, new cells are recruited and the same degree of response occurs. When an adaptive response is initiated and the T and B cells proliferate, specialized memory cells are created along with the effector cells. Now, present in the tissues, are many long-surviving cells able to recognize the antigen. If the antigen enters the body a subsequent time, a rapid and more robust immune response occurs.</p><p id="d7747215ffbf45c3af1f9db50bde7b17">The first time the adaptive immune system encounters an antigen, the primary response will take 5 –7 days before clonal expansion is complete and the lymphocytes have differentiated into effector cells. During the initial primary exposure IgM is the most prominent antibody secreted. The second and all subsequent times that the adaptive immune system encounters this same antigen, the immune response will only take 1–3 days to reach its maximal level and IgG is the prominent antibody secreted. Memory cells can live for years and even decades. Therefore, as long as memory T or B cells are circulating in the body, a faster, more robust immune response can be established. This helps to eliminate the infection faster and more efficiently.</p><p id="e51a5fb2a6e04abab7d3d93bcaf2e955">It is possible to acquire the immunological memory of adaptive immunity naturally or artificially. Natural immunity results from natural exposure to an antigen. For example, someone sneezes the influenza virus into the air and then it is breathed it into another person’s nasal passageway. Although not always, but symptoms of the exposure usually develop because the person is not immune during the first exposure. In artificial immunity, an antigen is deliberately introduced into an individual to stimulate an immune response. This introduced antigen is a vaccine and the process is vaccination. Both of these immune responses are considered active processes and can persist for weeks to a lifetime because memory cells have been produced. Passive immunity is not long-lasting because the individual does not produce memory cells. Instead, this temporary immunity results from the transfer of antibodies from a donor to a recipient. An example of passive immunity results from a mother to her child as antibodies move across the placenta before birth.</p><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_digt3" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><example id="d2c648e90c4f4c26a09f729a477df2d7"><title>Clinical Connection: Vaccines</title><p id="de34f1b2b3ba43e7a4bb33e888eb05f4">Without immunological memory, vaccines would not work. Vaccines can prevent or decrease the severity of infections. The mechanism underlying vaccination is that exposure of the adaptive immune system to a small dose of an antigen will produce an initial immune response. More importantly, this small dose of antigen establishes a population of memory T and B cells that will live long-term in the body. When that antigen is encountered again, the immune system is already primed. Upon a subsequent exposure, a more robust and faster response is established and the pathogen is destroyed faster. Thereby preventing clinical manifestations of the infection or greatly reducing the clinical manifestations.</p><p id="cc61775d3cd4466e90fae05892c2e7d2">There are two types of vaccines commonly used: live-attenuated (viable) vaccines and killed vaccines. Live-attenuated vaccines are living organisms that have been modified in such a way that they will grow poorly in the human host and will therefore produce immunity but not disease. People who receive the flu vaccine may have mild flu-like symptoms for a few days but do not get the symptoms of disease that may last for two weeks or more. Killed vaccines have been killed, usually by irradiation, prior to administration. Both types of vaccination contain antigenic proteins that will create memory cells to protect the person from future infection.</p><p id="d184133463b64c6e8fb9974f704c693d">Typically, use of live but weakened microorganisms in vaccines produces a more robust immune response than does killed vaccines. Until now, the underlying reason why has remained unknown. Recently, however, it was discovered that immune cells are able to recognize whether a bacterium is live-attenuated or not (Sander et al, 2011). The presence (and detection) of prokaryotic mRNA signals to the immune system that the invading bacteria is live and, therefore, potentially infectious. As a result, a strong immune response is initiated. It is not just presence of prokaryotic mRNA, however, but specifically, the immune cells recognize a lack of the 3’-polyA tail on the prokaryotic mRNA. This means that vaccines that are augmented with prokaryotic mRNA might be able to produce an enhanced immune response in the future. This could have a significant impact on vaccine design and development.</p></example><example id="fa33910ddf33461fad285bd640752cbf"><title>Clinical Connection: Self-Recognition and Self-Tolerance</title><p id="ecab7e45f3b645cfb0d88418c30af034">If cells are created to attack a foreign antigen, how does the immune system avoid attacking itself? The immune system produces a powerful response to foreign pathogens, but does not attack its own cells or molecules. To avoid attacking self, several mechanisms have been established. The phagocytic cells can differentiate between pathogenic organisms (bacteria, viruses, parasites and fungus) and human cells. Pathogens express pathogen-specific signatures (PAMPs) that are not found on mammalian cells. During development, B and T cells that recognize self-proteins are eliminated during a process called clonal deletion. If a T cell does bind to its antigen, but does not receive the proper costimulatory molecule stimulation, the T cell is rendered inactive or tolerant. The T cell is <term>anergic </term> and unable to properly initiate an immune response.</p><p id="d69864d590904629a48c810ec1b01eb7">Both the innate and the adaptive immune responses have mechanisms in place to avoid the destruction of their own tissues. Rarely, these mechanisms go awry and an immune response to self-protein occurs. When they do malfunction, auto-immune diseases arise. These are diseases where the immune system considers one’s own molecules as foreign. Most of these diseases have a genetic component to them (they tend to run in families), but also may require an environmental trigger.</p><image id="ca16f7be57c34e15921ea2b429876791" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_28.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="453" width="670"><caption><p id="aee87fd5d53534689a98957e90dcd15de"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></example><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_lbd3" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_digt4" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="bee977196be1483fa1d0b117645f971f"><title>Review of Adaptive Immunity</title><body><p id="ac62661deb09488a87c89b637c4daba3">Unlike the innate immune response, the adaptive immune response responds to a specific pathogen. During the adaptive response, B cell receptors recognize pathogens free in body fluids. Additionally, these B cells and dendritic cells engulf and digest the pathogen into peptide fragments. These peptides are bound to a cellular protein called the major histocompatability complex (MHC) and carried together to the surface of the phagocytic cell. This process is called antigen presentation. These peptides presented in the context of (bound to) MHC proteins are recognized by helper T cells. The helper T cell receptors bind to the peptide and MHC protein and become activated releasing cytokines. Cytotoxic T cell receptors recognize foreign peptides that were produced in the cell and associated with MHC such as occurs in infected or tumor cells. Activated T cells, called lymphoblasts, and activated B cells, called plasma cells, begin to divide, creating hundreds of clones of the antigen-specific T or B cell. These clones mount a cellular-mediated immune response or an antibody-mediated immune response to rid the body of the pathogen. Memory T and B cells are also created, which remain in the body and initiate an immune response if the antigen is detected again. Vaccines are effective because of memory cells.</p><image id="a5dd304ac8034f27bc50c61d644e0286" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_42.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="1088" width="720"><caption><p id="ab1cf605dc8214bbc916200071b719d19"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section></body></workbook_page>
