<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="lymph_17"><head><title>Cell-Mediated Immune Response</title><objref idref="lymph_CMIR_LO" /><objref idref="lymph_CMIR_LO2" /></head><body><p id="c73b498a20ef45d2a729a39c0470523f">Antigens are brought from infected tissues to peripheral lymphatic tissues by dendritic cells, which capture antigens in two ways. Stimulation of innate immunity receptors on the dendritic cell by the pathogen promotes phagocytosis by the dendritic cell and the display of antigens with MHC class II molecules. It is also possible that the dendritic cell is infected by an intracellular pathogen, such as a virus, which results in antigen display by MHC class I molecules. In response to the antigen display with MHC, dendritic cells become mobile and move along with lymph to the nearest lymphatic tissue, where they present the antigen to naïve lymphocytes.</p><p id="de3168a4f6754208a843e192d679b212">Antigens in lymph and blood can also enter peripheral lymphatic tissues and stimulate the innate immunity receptors of macrophages, which phagocytize the antigens and display epitopes with MHC class II molecules.</p><p id="a31a61298bbf482c9693a59f0d3d3380">Dendritic cells and macrophages expose naïve T cells to their epitopes, resulting in their activation. Activated helper T cells assist in the activation of B cells and cytotoxic T cells.</p><image id="d5a13e1ecce640a9970f0c60efc7aa50" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_20.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="acd1c6adc878647cbb78ca441bb273b95">Activation and Proliferation of B Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="d8a0777f88804a3fb03c9ccd06994cd6"><title>Antigen Processing and Presentation</title><body><p id="ca8586f6e5fd4617bc4cfcc39df3aacf">T cells only recognize fragments of antigenic proteins that are processed and presented by specific immune cells. In antigenic processing, antigenic proteins are broken down into peptide fragments that then associate with MHC molecules . Next the MHC:epitope complex is inserted into the plasma membrane of a body cell. The insertion of the complex into the plasma membrane is called antigen presentation. Antigen processing and presentation occurs in two ways depending on whether the antigen is located intracellular or extracellular.</p></body></section><section id="a2891799591f40e489b67184861a9a79"><title>Processing of Exogenous Antigens</title><body><p id="cb8e34c373cf40eeba82f4a051a2ca13">Foreign antigens present in fluids outside body cells are termed exogenous antigens. Examples include intruders such as bacteria and bacterial toxins, viruses that have not yet infected a cell, parasitic worms, and inhaled pollens. Antigen-presenting cells (APCs) process and present exogenous antigens. They are located in places where antigens are likely to penetrate the innate barriers and enter the body. Such places include the the skin (for example, Langerhans cells are dendritic cells) and mucous membranes that line the respiratory, gastrointestinal, urinary and reproductive tracts. After processing antigen, APCs migrate from tissues via lymphatic vessels to lymph nodes where they will present their MHC:epitope complex to T lymphocytes.</p><p id="a4ed64ab9f8c4af78eac52156e1a710b">The steps in the processing and presenting an exogenous antigen by an APC occur as follows:</p><ol id="e6fc63d4b0e249b4bce7597c74ffbd8c"><li><p id="ac3dadf6fa6374885880d37c5e3577571">Ingestion of the antigen by phagocytosis or endocytosis.</p></li><li><p id="afb300b16d3914d5f8ead5fd3ab69389c">Digestion of antigen into peptide fragments within the phagosome or endosome by protein-digesting enzymes.</p></li><li><p id="ad75ddfbdb0bb4e6b8fbdf2eadcb63c90">Synthesis of class II MHC molecules (MHC-II) in the endoplasmic reticulum.</p></li><li><p id="ac068feaa5cd34b47af7725e064ed6e27">Packaging of MHC-II molecules into vesicles by the Golgi complex.</p></li><li><p id="afc9f0ce231334c53a0f24cba8a13d44e">Fusion of the phagosome or endosome containing the antigen fragments with the vesicle containing the MHC-II.</p></li><li><p id="ad0b3d418d4f0424bbaf9903d0e24343d">Binding of the peptide fragment to MHC-ll molecules.</p></li><li><p id="afc4c9f825b8b49d397d199c6730b3f1c">Insertion of the MHC-II/epitope complex into the plasma membrane of the APC by exocytosis.</p></li></ol><p id="fe6cdfc5e5964f0790805887d849ea35">It is important to note that exogenous antigens are always enclosed in vesicles when they are brought into the cell. In this way normal cellular peptides are not complexed with class II MHC, only foreign peptides. After processing an antigen, the APC migrates to lymphtic tissue to present the antigen to helper T cells. This informs T cells that specific intruders are present in the body and that immune responses should begin.</p><image id="cde112afe266484aa9ef49c252639ad3" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_36.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="b4db31a5eb674699b17c3f4542feaf9c"><title>Processing of Endogenous Antigens</title><body><p id="dce8675e798741c1b2342213279aa014">Antigens that are present inside the body cells are called endogenous antigens. All nucleated cells of the body have the ability to present antigens complexed with a class I MHC molecule. When a peptide fragment comes from a self-protein, T cells ignore the MHC-I/epitope complex. However, if the peptide fragment comes from a foreign protein, T cells recognize the MHC-I/epitope complex and an immune response occurs. Such foreign antigens may be viral proteins produced after a virus infects the cell and takes over the cell&apos;s metabolic machinery, toxins produced from intracellular bacteria, or abnormal proteins synthesized by a cancerous cell.</p><p id="c2bb80d6806942ae8a63200c31d265b2">The steps in the processing and presenting of an endogenous antigen by nucleated cell.</p><ol id="e91fea7dc82548a9b69723e8ed662d08" style="lower-alpha"><li><p id="ad1135ed0ed6846959cc8720a16e7b1ff">Intracellular proteins are degraded into short peptides by a proteasome. A proteosome is a large protein-enzyme complex.</p></li><li><p id="aac3782262979420c93280a35f03eca30">The peptide fragment is transported to the rough endoplasmic reticulum (RER).</p></li><li><p id="adaa6aa03613f409796386a2d98adec56">MHC-I molecule is made in the RER.</p></li><li><p id="ae2dc0281b1234635bb49a249f029336d">In the RER the MHC-I captures the peptide fragment.</p></li><li><p id="af6bbff4cb2b945f190a25d591a7ea2ce">MHC-I/epitope complex is transported from RER to the Golgi complex.</p></li><li><p id="ad44dc01cf7af4389bf5b6bcc0b1b52e0">Insertion of the MHC-I/epitope complex into the plasma membrane of the nucleated cell by exocytosis.</p></li></ol><p id="ff58520d5bf443a4adc7ba316435e28b">Note the difference in antigen processing between exogenous and endogenous peptides. Exogenous peptides and MHC-II complex together in vesicles within the cell. Endogenous peptides complex with MHC-I in the RER in the cell. Most cells of the body can process and present endogenous antigens. The display of an endogenous self-antigen bound to an MHC-I molecule signals that a cell is normal, however, an endogenous foreign antigen bound to a MHC-I signals that a cell has been infected or is abnormal and needs attention. Cytotoxic T cells have receptors for foreign MHC-I/epitope complex.</p><image id="aef5bfa7283a45af9b80006a9e5c6c82" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_27.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="e0bdde0fa9fc46acbd240c079b27e8b9"><title>Activation of T Cells and Immune Responses</title><body><p id="e894636d1f994443a80293364e051a0d">T lymphocytes come in several varieties. They are helper T (Th) cells and cytotoxic T cells (Tc). Each type plays an important role in the adaptive immune response. Helper T cells bind to cells and release cytokines needed for coordinating virtually all immune responses. Cytotoxic T cells bind to cells and lyse them to destroy them. There are several subsets of cytotoxic and helper T cells that employ different techniques to recognize and eliminate pathogens. Ultimately T cells all function to specifically recognize and destroy pathogens associated with a self-cell and by recruitment of immune cells, hence the term <term>cell-mediated responses</term>.</p><p id="f98e1303aa7c4e5fa76f6cfb7a3810a3">Most mature T cells are naïve because they have not yet encountered a pathogen. However, when an antigen enters the body only a select few T cells have T-cell receptors (TCRs) that can recognize and bind to that specific antigen. Recall that TCRs recognize and bind only to foreign antigen fragments that are presented in MHC/epitope complex. Antigen recognition also involves other surface proteins on T cells. Helper T cells have TCR and CD4 glycoproteins that recognize class II MHC on antigen presenting cells (APCs). Cytotoxic T cells have TCR and CD8 glycoproteins that recognize class I MHC found on all nucleated cells of the body (target cells). These CD4 and CD8 glycoproteins help maintain the TCR-MHC/epitope coupling and direct the appropriate immune response. For this reason they are referred as coreceptors. Antigen/MHC recognition by a TCR with CD4 or CD8 glycoprotein is the <em style="italic">first signal</em> in activation of a T cell.</p><p id="f413d4ec2bf74cc1a44a51ff582d7f00">A T cell becomes activated only if it receives the first signal described previously and at the same time receives a <em style="italic">second signal</em>, a process called <term>costimulation</term>. Molecules involved in costimulation include cytokines such as IL-2 and pairs of plasma membrane molecules on the surfaces of the T cell and on the APC. One of the most important costimulators is B7 on APCs, which binds to CD28 on helper T cells. A resting APC expresses very little B7, but after activation by antigen, the APC expressess B7 and increase the MHC/epitope complexes on its surface.</p><p id="dfb8ee6c43ce47078a08eb8fb645b70d">The two signals essential to activate a T cell are similar to starting a car engine and putting it into gear. The correct key (epitope) in the ignition (TCR) turns it on but it will not move forward unless you move the gear shift into drive (costimulation). The need for costimulation helps prevent the immune response from occurring inappropriately. Once a T cell has received these two signals it is <term>activated</term>. An activated T cell then undergoes proliferation and differentiation in a process called <term>clonal selection.</term></p><p id="b9c8283d76ea4fe2ab025fbd7fd504c1">Inactive helper T cells recognize exogenous antigen fragments associated with class II MHC molecules on the surface of APCs. With the aid of the CD4 proteins, a subset of helper T cells becomes activated. Once activated the CD4+helper T cell undergoes mitotic divisions forming identical copies of itself (clones). This proliferation and differentiation of T helper cells produces both active helper T cells and memory helper T cells. Within hours of activation, active T helper cells start secreting cytokines. Cytokines secreted by these helper T cells act as costimulators for resting helper T cells or cytotoxic T cells, and these cytokines also enhance activation and proliferation of B cells, macrophages and natural killer cells. <term>Memory helper T </term>cells are not active during this current immune response, however, if the same antigen enters the body again, many memory helper T cells can rapidly proliferate and differentiate into active helper T cells and memory helper T cells.</p><image id="fc61122d00944bbdbb72a2cf5b0a6500" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_24.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ad4dec3a0aa5941e888e52d68cdd22e20">Activation and Dfferentiation of Helper T Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d1e2508ef86048fd8eed96656344cf84">Most T cells that display CD8 glycoproteins develop into cytotoxic T cells. Cytotoxic T cells are most effective against pathogens that live inside the cells of the body. Cytotoxic T cells recognize endogenous antigen fragments associated with class I MHC molecules displayed on the surface of nucleated cells (target cells) infected with a pathogen, some tumor cells displaying tumor antigens or cells of a tissue transplant.</p><p id="fca64de6ade540c0a04098c72284269c">Only dendritic cells, the most effective APCs, provide sufficient stimulation to activate naïve cytyotoxic T cells. Dendritic cells acquire antigen by being infected or through phagocytosis of an infected cell. The antigen is processed and a class I MHC molecule presents the epitope to a naïve cytotoxic T cell. Recognition requires TCR-MHC-I/epitope and CD8 coupling. In addition to antigen recognition (signal 1), costimulation occurs when IL-2 and when B7 combines with CD28 (signal 2). Once activated, cytotoxic T cells undergo clonal expansion. The cytotoxic T cell divides, resulting in an increased number of cytotoxic T cells. Most of the T cells are fully functional cytotoxic T cells that are capable of killing infected cells. However, a small percentage of these T cells are memory T cells, which can produce a secondary immune response on subsequent exposure to this pathogen.</p><image id="bb5aa893813f4331ae70ce08ec8f2a33" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_34.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af0c7d01eabfb4133b7ab8edf4b4c943c">Effector Function of Cytotoxic T Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ab093c643f034e6d898bb115b96b3717">Stimulation by dendritic cells alone can be insufficient to activate naïve cytotoxic T cells. Helper T cells can provide assistance when they recognize MHC-II/epitope displayed on the same dendritic cell that is activating the cytotoxic T cell. The helper T cell stimulates the dendritic cell to express more B7 molecules, which promotes costimulation. In addition, the helper cell secretes IL-2, which promotes proliferation and differentiation of the cytotoxic T cell.</p><image id="d02d2b2757594f6198b2caf671177522" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_25.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aff12b5078b714ae98644a7cda7e6e216">Killing of Target Cell by Cytotoxic T Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a010c470fcd94a8599a638f1c1689376">Once activated, a cytotoxic T cell recognizes a target cell infected with intracellular pathogens through its TCR, which binds to MHC-I/epitope complexes on the target cell. The cytotoxic T cell binds to the target cell and releases <term>perforin</term> and <term>granzyme</term> proteins on to the surface of the target cell. The perforin inserts into the plasma membrane of the target cell and creates channels in the membrane. This allows extracellular fluid and granulysin to flow into the cell causing bursting of the cell (cytolysis). Additional granzyme molecules released by the cytotoxic T cell activate enzymes in the target cell that cause fragmentation of its DNA and apoptosis. Cytotoxic T cells also secrete gamma-interferon that attracts phagocytes to the site. After detaching from the target cell, a cytotoxic T cell can continue to seek and destroy other target cells. Memory cytotoxic T cells are inactive during this immune response but can proliferate and differentiate into active cytotoxic T cells if the infection returns.</p><image id="cb43b4b0110643b4ad633c0c5eda44d7" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_25.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ab5e7883b08e643188fed78c412c5904b">Activation and Dfferentiation of Cytotoxic T Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="c34cb477808e431baf2c25587ccd07be" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_33.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="adc998cc444934cb6b3897351d6004ae6">Role of Helper T cell in Cellular Immunity</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="d5c1fe678de34d90875729666e2ac75f" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/_u13_m2_LOO/webcontent/Lymph_35.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ac3581d33741a45f7871a0cbd90f072ca">Killing of Target Cell by Cytotoxic T Cell</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="b7c552691dd9463ba8860add378bd553"><title>Antibody-Mediated (Humoral) Immune Response</title><body><p id="b034e2feaed4446fa509444ffc0d1f22">Antibody mediated immunity works mainly against extracellular pathogens, which include any bacteria, fungi or viruses that are in the extracellular fluids of the body. Antibody-mediated immunity involves antibodies that bind to antigens in body fluids. Cytotoxic T cells leave lymphatic tissues to seek out and destroy a foreign antigen, however, B cells remain in lymphatic tissues. In the presence of antigen, B cells in mucous associated lymph tissue (MALT), lymph nodes or spleen become activated.</p><p id="ba9fef27c943409e8851b38234ee46b6">Although B cells can respond to an unprocessed antigen present in lymph or intersitital fluid, their response is more intense if they process the antigen and present it to helper T cells. Some antigens, such as the lipopolysaccharides (LPS) in the cell wall of Gram-negative bacteria, can bind to BCRs as signal 1. The second signal required for activation is provided directly by recognition of a common microbial molecule or by extensive cross-linking of B-cell receptors by repeating epitopes on the bacterial cell. Although this response is rapidly produced, it is relatively weak compared to the response produced when B cells are activated with assistance from helper T cells.</p><image id="cfe14f4b94b846e9912da2b93ff8b7fc" src="../../../_u13_lymphatic/webcontent/Lymph_32.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aad18c7f1e5a44d41a73d7053957db0bc">Role of Helper T cell in Humoral Immunity</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b25bd0fab93a45f99464aba80d1a61b4">The requirement for T-cell help means that before a B cell can be induced to make antibody against the molecules of an infecting microbe, CD4+ T cells specific for peptides from this microbe must be activated to produce helper T cells. This occurs when naïve T cells interact with dendritic cells presenting these peptides. During B cell activation, an antigen binds to the BCR. Most B cell activation begins when a B cell takes in (by B-cell receptor-mediated endocytosis) the same antigen that activated a helper T cell. The antigen is processed, complexed with a class II MHC molecule and presented on the B-cell surface. The TCR and CD4 of an activated helper T cell then binds to the MHC-II/epitope complex. The B7/CD28 costimulation is not necessary because the helper T cell was already activated. The helper T cell secretes interleukins, especially IL-4, which stimulates the B cell to proliferate identical copies of itself (clones) that differentiate into antibody producing <term>plasma cells</term> and <term>memory B cells</term>. Memory B cells that encounter the same antigen in the future results in a rapid proliferation and differentiation of memory B cells into antibody-producing plasma cells and new memory B cells.</p><p id="ce763e5b95854c068a2d68db47a286a9">All of the plasma cells of a particular clone are capable of secreting antibodies specific for the antigen that originally stimulated the BCR of the B cell. IgM is the first antibody secreted by activated B cells, but makes up less than 10% of the immunoglobulin found in plasma; IgG is the most abundant. Much of the antibody in plasma has therefore been produced by plasma cells derived from B cells that have undergone isotype switching. Recall that the isotype refers to the constant region of the antibody and determines the action that the antibody takes to defend the body from this pathogen. So the early stages of the immune response are dominated by IgM antibodies, later IgG and IgA predominate, with IgE contributing a small but important part of the immune reponse.</p><p id="b9df31a3775e4e51905dcb1db8aa63c9">While the underlying mechanism controlling what initiates an allergic response to non-harmful agents is still largely unknown, research increasingly is discovering how allergic responses proceed. It is known that mast cells, eosinophils, and basophils are found in increased levels of activation in allergic reactions. These cells produce histamine, bradykinin and other chemicals that initiate a T cell mediated immune response. The CD4+helper T subset of T cells are found in increased quantities in allergic reactions. Knowledge of mediators of the allergic immune response will aid in developing new therapies to treat or avoid allergic reactions.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="lymph_CMIR_digt2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
