<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="id_sample_space_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_id_sample_space">
        <!--LO:Determine the sample space of a given random experiment.Sub-objective: samplespace    Identifying sample space  -->
        <body>
            <p>A person in a casino decides to play blackjack until he wins a game, but he will not
                play more than 3 games. Let W denote a win and L denote a loss. What is the sample
                space for this random experiment?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">S = {WWW, WWL, WLW, , WLL, LWW, LWL, LLW, LLL}</choice>
            <choice value="B">S = {W, LW, LLW}</choice>
            <choice value="C">S = {W, LW, LLW, LLL}</choice>
            <choice value="D">S = {W, WW, WWW}</choice>
            <choice value="E">S = {W, WL, WWL, WWW}</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops playing when he wins or if he plays three
                    games without winning. So not all of the options in this set are outcomes for
                    this experiment (for example WWW is not possible) and other possibilities are
                    missing (for example W).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. One option is missing. The person could also lose all 3
                    games.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The person stops playing when he wins or if he plays three games
                    without winning.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops playing when he wins a game, so WW and WWW are
                    not outcomes for this random experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops playing when he wins a game, so W is the only
                    outcome in this set that comes from this random experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_id_sample_space">
        <!--LO: Determine the sample space of a given random experiment.
            Sub-objective: samplespace  Identifying sample space  -->
        <body>
            <p>A person in a casino decides to play 3 games of blackjack. Let W denote a win and L
                denote a loss. Define the event A as “the person wins at least one game of
                blackjack.” What are the possible outcomes for this event?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">{W, LW, LLW}</choice>
            <choice value="B">{W, WW, WWW}</choice>
            <choice value="C">{WWW, WWL, WLW, WLL, LWW, LWL, LLW, LLL}</choice>
            <choice value="D">{WWW, WWL, WLW, WLL, LWW, LWL, LLW}</choice>
            <choice value="E">{WWL, LWL, LLW}</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. {W, LW, LLW} does not describe outcomes for this random
                    experiment because the person decided to play 3 games (regardless of whether he
                    wins or losses), so each outcome must show the result for each of the 3
                    games.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. {W, WW, WWW} does not describe outcomes for this random
                    experiment because the person decided to play 3 games, so each outcome must show
                    the result for each of the 3 games.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the entire sample space for the random experiment in
                    which a person plays 3 games of blackjack.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Event A is all outcomes in the sample space except
                    LLL.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. {WLL, LWL, LLW} are the outcomes for the event “wins EXACTLY
                    one game of blackjack”.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_id_sample_space">
        <!--LO: Determine the sample space of a given random experiment.
            Sub-objective: samplespace  Identifying sample space  -->
        <body>
            <p>A person trying to gain access to a bank vault must pass through a series of three
                security doors. If an attempt to pass through a door is a failure, then the person
                will not make any further attempts. Let P denote a successful pass and F denote a
                failed pass. What is the sample space for this random experiment?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">S = {F, PF, PPF, PPP}</choice>
            <choice value="B">S= {F, PF, PPF}</choice>
            <choice value="C">S = {F, FP, FFP, FFF}</choice>
            <choice value="D">S = {P, PP, PPP}</choice>
            <choice value="E">S ={PPP, FPP, PFP, PPF, FFP, FPF, PFF, FFF}</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The person stops going when he fails to access a door or when he
                    passes through all three doors.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Not quite right. One outcome is missing: the person can also pass through
                    all three doors.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops going when he fails to access a door, so FP,
                    FFP, and FFF are not outcomes for this random experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person continues to try the next door if a pass is
                    successful, so P and PP are not outcomes for this random experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops going when he fails to access a door or when
                    he passes through all three doors. So not all of these are possible outcomes for
                    this random experiment. For example, PFP and FFF are not possible, and other
                    possible outcomes, such as F, are missing.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <!-- added, may need to be removed if qa doesn't go through -->
    <multiple_choice id="q4_id_sample_space">

        <body>
            <p>A person must enter a 4 digit code to gain access to his cell phone. He will enter
                codes until he is successful, however he cannot try more than 3 times or the phone
                will lock him out. Let S denote a successful attempt and F denote a failed attempt.
                What is the sample space for this random experiment? </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">{SSS, SSF, SFS, FSS, SFF, FSF, FFS, FFF}</choice>
            <choice value="B">{S, FS, FFS}</choice>
            <choice value="C">{S, FS, FFS, FFF} </choice>
            <choice value="D">{S, SS, SSS} </choice>
            <choice value="E">{S, SF, SSF, SSS}</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops trying when he successfully enters a code. So
                    not all of the options in this set are outcomes for this experiment (for example
                    SSS is not possible) and other possibilities are missing (for example
                    S).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Not quite right. One option is missing. The person could also fail at all
                    3 attempts. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The person stops trying when he successfully enters the code or
                    when he has failed at all 3 attempts.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The person stops trying when he successfully enters the code,
                    so SS and SSS are not outcomes for this random experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect.The person stops trying when he successfully enters the code, so
                    S is the only outcome in this set that comes from this random
                    experiment.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q5_id_sample_space">

        <body>
            <p>A couple decides to have three children. Let A define the event that the couple has
                at least 1 girl. What are the possible outcomes for this event? (G=girl, B=boy) </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">{G, BG, BBG}</choice>
            <choice value="B">{G, GG, GGG} </choice>
            <choice value="C">{BBB, BBG, BGB, GBB, GGB, GBG, BGG, GGG} </choice>
            <choice value="D">{GGG, GGB, GBG, BGG, GBB, BGB, BBG}</choice>
            <choice value="E">{GBB, BGB, BBG}</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. {G, BG, BBG} does not describe outcomes for this random
                    experiment because the couple wants 3 children regardless of whether or not they
                    have a girl, so each outcome must show the result for all 3 births. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect.{G, GG, GGG} does not describe outcomes for this random
                    experiment because the couple wants 3 children regardless of whether or not they
                    have a girl, so each outcome must show the result for all 3 births.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the entire sample space for the random experiment in
                    which a couple has 3 children. Event A is the event that the couple has at <em style="italic">least</em>
                    one girl. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Event A is all outcomes in the sample space except BBB. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. {GBB, BGB, BBG}  are the outcomes for the event “ EXACTLY one girl”.
                </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
