<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="probs_are_equal_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_probs_are_equal">
        <!--LO: Find the probability of events in the case in which all outcomes are equally likely.
		    Sub-objective: probequal        When probabilities are equal-->
        <body>
            <p>A family plans to have 3 children. For each birth, assume that the probability of a
                boy is the same as the probability of a girl. What is the probability that they will
                have at least one boy and at least one girl?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">0.5</choice>
            <choice value="B">0.125</choice>
            <choice value="C">0.75</choice>
            <choice value="D">0.875</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There are 8 equally likely outcomes in this sample space. In
                    two outcomes the gender of all three children is the same (GGG, BBB). The other
                    6 outcomes contain at least one boy and one girl.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The outcomes are equally likely, so the easiest way to work
                    this problem is to write out the 8 outcomes in this sample space. In two
                    outcomes the gender of all three children is the same (GGG, BBB). The other 6
                    outcomes contain at least one boy and one girl.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The outcomes are equally likely, so the easiest way to work this
                    problem is to write out the 8 outcomes in this sample space. In two outcomes the
                    gender of all three children is the same (GGG, BBB). The other 6 outcomes
                    contain at least one boy and one girl.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have calculated P(at least one girl) = 1 − (0.5) ^ 3.
                    The outcomes are equally likely, so the easiest way to work this problem is to
                    write out the 8 outcomes in this sample space. In two outcomes the gender of all
                    three children is the same (GGG, BBB). The other 6 outcomes contain at least one
                    boy and one girl.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_probs_are_equal">
        <!--LO: Find the probability of events in the case in which all outcomes are equally likely.
            Sub-objective: probequal        When probabilities are equal  -->
        <body>
            <p>Four students attempt to register online at the same time for an Introductory
                Statistics class that is full. Two are freshmen and two are sophomores. They are put
                on a wait list. Prior to the start of the semester, two enrolled students drop the
                course, so the professor decides to randomly select two of the four wait list
                students and gives them a seat in the class. </p>
            <p>What is the probability that both students selected are freshmen?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">½</choice>
            <choice value="B">¼</choice>
            <choice value="C">⅙</choice>
            <choice value="D">1/12</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have been thinking that half of the wait list students
                    are freshmen. But you need to think about the sample space of this random
                    experiment. Since order does not matter, the sample space contains six equally
                    likely outcomes. S = {F1F2, F1S1, F1S2, F2S1, F2S2, S1S2}.
                    <!--Only one of the six
                    outcomes is two freshmen. The correct answer is (C).--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have been thinking that there are four possible
                    outcomes, {FF, FS, SF, and SS}, like when we toss a coin two times. But here the
                    sample space contains six equally likely outcomes because there are 2 freshmen
                    and 2 sophomores and the order in which they are chosen does not matter. S =
                    {F1F2, F1S1, F1S2, F2S1, F2S2, S1S2}.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The order that the students are chosen does not matter, so F1F2
                    and F2F1 are the same outcome. Thus, the sample space contains six equally
                    likely outcomes. S = {F1F2, F1S1, F1S2, F2S1, F2S2, S1S2}.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The order that the students are chosen does not matter, so F1F2
                    and F2F1 are the same outcome. Thus, the sample space contains only six equally
                    likely outcomes. S = {F1F2, F1S1, F1S2, F2S1, F2S2, S1S2}.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_probs_are_equal">
        <!--LO: Find the probability of events in the case in which all outcomes are equally likely.
            Sub-objective: probequal        When probabilities are equal  -->
        <body>
            <p>In the last round of a chess tournament the final match is between Alice and Diego.
                The winner is the first player to win three games [sometimes called “best of 5”].
                Assume that they are equally matched, so that each player has an equal probability
                of winning each game. What is the probability that the match will be finished <em style="italic">after the first 3 games are played?</em>
            </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">0.50</choice>
            <choice value="B">0.25</choice>
            <choice value="C">0.20</choice>
            <choice value="D">0.125</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the probability that Alice or Diego will win a game.
                    Consider the results of the first three games that are played. You will find
                    that there are 8 <!--12 -->equally likely outcomes in this sample space. Note
                    that the only way for the match to be finished in these first three games is if
                    Alice wins all three games (AAA) or Diego wins all three games (DDD).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Considering the results of the first three games that are played,
                    we find that there are 8 equally likely outcomes in this sample space (AAA, AAD,
                    ADA, ADD, DDD, DDA, DAD, DAA). The only way for the match to be resolved in
                    these first three games is if Alice wins all three games (AAA) or Diego wins all
                    three games (DDD), so the probability is 2/8 = 0.25.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have focused on the fact that they might play 5 games.
                    For this problem, we only need to consider the results of the first three games
                    that are played. You will find that there are 8 equally likely outcomes in this
                    sample space. Note that the only way for the match to be finished in these first
                    three games is if Alice wins all three games (AAA) or Diego wins all three games
                    (DDD). </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You correctly identified that there are 8 outcomes in the
                    sample space, but this is the probability of one correct outcome. Note that
                    there are two ways that the match can be resolved in 3 games: Either Alice wins
                    all three games (AAA) or Diego wins all three games (DDD). </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_probs_are_equal">
        <!--LO: Find the probability of events in the case in which all outcomes are equally likely.
            Sub-objective: probequal        When probabilities are equal  -->
        <body>
            <p>For a criminal trial, 8 active and 4 alternate jurors are selected. Two of the
                alternate jurors are male and two are female. During the trial, two of the active
                jurors are dismissed. The judge decides to randomly select two replacement jurors
                from the 4 available alternates. What is the probability that both jurors selected
                are female?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">½</choice>
            <choice value="B">¼</choice>
            <choice value="C">⅙</choice>
            <choice value="D">1/12</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have been thinking that half of the jurors are female.
                    But you need to think about the sample space of this random experiment. Since
                    order does not matter, the sample space contains six equally likely outcomes. S
                    = {F1F2, F1M1, F1M2, F2M1, F2M2, M1M2}. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You may have been thinking that there are four possible
                    outcomes, {FF, FM, MF, and MM}, like when we toss a coin two times. But here the
                    sample space contains six equally likely outcomes because there are 2 female and
                    2 males and the order in which they are chosen does not matter, S = {F1F2, F1M1,
                    F1M2, F2M1, F2M2, M1M2}. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The order that the jurors are chosen does not matter, so F1F2 and
                    F2F1 are the same outcome. Thus, the sample space contains six equally likely
                    outcomes. S = {F1F2, F1M1, F1M2, F2M1, F2M2, M1M2}. Only one of the six outcomes
                    is two females. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The order that the jurors are chosen does not matter, so F1F2
                    and F2F1 are the same outcome. Thus, the sample space contains only six equally
                    likely outcomes. S ={F1F2, F1M1, F1M2, F2M1, F2M2, M1M2}. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <!-- added, may need to be removed if qa doesn't go through -->
    <numeric id="q5_probs_are_equal">
        <body>
            <p>A True/False quiz has three questions. When guessing, the probability of getting a
                question correct is the same as the probability of getting a question wrong. What is
                the probability that a student that guesses gets at least 2 questions correct? (Give
                your answer to 2 decimal places)</p>
            <p><input_ref input="A" /></p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A" />

        </input>
        <part>
            <response input="A" match="0.50" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. There are 8 equally likely outcomes in this sample space. Four of
                    the outcomes (CCW, CWC, WCC, CCC) have at least 2 questions correct. So the
                    probability is 4/8 = 0.5 that at least 2 questions are guessed correctly.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" match=".50" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. There are 8 equally likely outcomes in this sample space. Four of
                    the outcomes (CCW, CWC, WCC, CCC) have at least 2 questions correct. So the
                    probability is 4/8 = 0.5 that at least 2 questions are guessed correctly.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" match=".5" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. There are 8 equally likely outcomes in this sample space. Four of
                    the outcomes (CCW, CWC, WCC, CCC) have at least 2 questions correct. So the
                    probability is 4/8 = 0.5 that at least 2 questions are guessed correctly.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The outcomes are equally likely, so the easiest way to work
                    this problem is to write out the 8 outcomes in this sample space. Four of the
                    outcomes (CCW, CWC, WCC, CCC) have at least 2 questions correct. The remaining 4
                    outcomes only have 0 or 1 question correct. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>

    </numeric>
</pool>
