<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_cell_membrane_active1"><head><title>Active Transport</title><objref idref="levels_membrane_active" /></head><body><p id="febb8257f7564110acfb0a126e199575">You have just finished investigating the passive methods of transport, now let’s look at activemethods. In active methods the cell must expend energy (ATP) to do the work of moving
molecules. Active transport often occurs when the molecule is being moved against its
concentration gradient or when moving very large molecules into our out of the cell.
There are 3 main types of active processes.</p><ol id="c72ce0741b5a4eb885bd57db447e4791"><li><p id="aeaef8ddce9234b73bdd6ba86bf45a570">Primary Active Transport or Solute Pumps</p></li><li><p id="aa1793d0ba65b4a51861d2f17efc374dc">Endocytosis and Exocytosis </p></li></ol><section id="c4e0e439b01740feb46ce772124fb6a4"><title>Primary Active Transport or Solute Pumps</title><body><p id="e48135d071b14db2b31d597259d8fc64">One form of active transport involves moving ions from an area of low concentration to anarea of higher concentration. If you need to roll a rock it’s much easier to
roll it downhill rather than uphill right? Active transport is moving the rock
uphill and requires energy to do so. The best example of this involves the
sodium (Na<sup>+</sup>)/potassium (K<sup>+</sup>) exchange pump. The interior of a cell contains a lowNa<sup>+</sup> concentration compared to the extracellular fluid. The interior of the cell(intracellular fluid or ICF) contains more K<sup>+</sup> than the extracellular fluid(ECF). This creates an imbalance in these ions. Na<sup>+</sup> has a concentration gradientto enter the cell since there is more Na<sup>+</sup> in the ECF. K<sup>+</sup> has a concentrationgradient for it to leave the cell. The cell membrane is not impermeable to these
ions and some of them escape following their concentration or diffusion
gradients. You will later study why it is important to maintain these ion
concentrations. The Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> pump is an active transport pump that moves Na<sup>+</sup>“uphill” back out of the cell against it’s concentration gradient and at the
same time moves K<sup>+</sup> back into the cell against it’s concentration gradient. Thispump requires ATP, a membrane protein transporter, and enzymes to function. </p></body></section><wb:inline idref="levels_membrane_active_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="c1e3b82099fa47d496f8f49881a3a6ab">Another form of active transport is termed secondary active transport. While primary activetransport directly uses ATP, secondary active transport relies on the energy from
electrochemical gradients to move molecules against their gradients. Primary active
transport sets this up because it actively pumps ions such as Na<sup>+</sup> out of the cellthereby creating an electrochemical gradient for Na<sup>+</sup> across the cell membrane. Proteintransporters in the cell membrane use the energy from electrochemical gradients to
transport molecules. If the molecules move in the same direction this is known as
cotransport or symport. If they are moved in opposite directions this is known as
countertransport or antiport. One common occurrence in the human body is the Na<sup>+</sup>/glucosetransport protein known as SGLT1 which cotransports 1 glucose and 2 sodium ions into a
cell. The electrochemical gradient for Na<sup>+</sup> into the cell allows glucose to ride with it.When glucose moves into a cell, it rides the energy from the “coat tails of sodium
ions”.</p></body></workbook_page>
