<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_membrane_osmosis1">
	<head>
		<title>Membrane Transport</title>
		<objref idref="levels_membrane_osmosis"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Cells continually encounter changes in their external environment. Most cells have a similar
			blend of solutes within them, but interstitial or extracellular fluid can vary. What
			will happen if there is a strong concentration gradient between a cell's interior and
			the fluid outside? As you know, molecules will tend to move down their concentration
			gradients until equilibrium is reached. You might think that solutes will flow into our
			out of the cell until the solute concentrations are equal across the membrane. However,
			not all molecules can pass through the cell membrane. The plasma membrane (lipid
			bilayer) is significantly less permeable to most solutes than it is to water. Therefore
			the WATER tends to flow in a way that establishes an equal concentration of solutes on
			either side of the membrane. The water flows down its own concentration gradient, with a
			net movement toward the region that has a higher concentration of solutes. This movement
			of water across a semipermeable membrane in response to an imbalance of solute is called
			osmosis. </p>
		<p>The relationship between the solute concentration and amount of water is an inverse
			relationship. The more concentrated a solution is, the less water it contains. The fewer
			solutes, the more water – i.e. it is more dilute. Water follows gradients and moves from
			an area of more water to less water but in reality water is moved to the area with the
			greater number of solutes. This creates a pressure termed osmotic pressure. Cells cannot
			actively move water, it must follow osmotic gradients. Solutions that have a greater
			solute concentration will pull water via osmotic pressure. This depends on the total
			number of solutes, not the type. Note that some water can pass through the cell membrane
			but most water passes through protein membrane channels termed aquaporins</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="levels_membrane_osmosis_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="levels_membrane_osmosis_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
		
		<p>Cells may find themselves in three different sorts of solutions. The terms isotonic,
			hypertonic, and hypotonic refer to the concentration of solutes outside the cell
			relative to the solute concentration inside the cell. In an isotonic solution, solutes
			and water are equally concentrated within and outside the cell. 0.9% NaCl (physiologic saline) and 5% dextrose are two common isotonic solutions used.The cell is bathed in a
			solution with a solute concentration that is similar to its own cytoplasm. Many medical
			preparations (saline solutions for nasal sprays, eye drops, and intravenous drugs) are
			designed to be isotonic to our cells. A hypotonic solution has a low solute
			concentration and a high concentration of water compared to the cell's cytoplasm.
			Distilled (pure) water is the ultimate hypotonic solution. If a cell is placed in a
			hypotonic solution, it will tend to gain water. The solutes will "stay put" within the
			cell, but water molecules will diffuse such that their net flow is toward the area with
			a higher concentration of solutes. A hypertonic solution has a high solute concentration
			(lower water concentration) compared to the cell cytoplasm. Very salty or sugary
			solutions (brines or syrups) are hypertonic to living cells. If a cell is placed in such
			a solution, water tends to flow spontaneously out of the cell. </p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_osmosis_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<wb:inline idref="levels_membrane_osmosis_digt2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
				
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
