<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_cell_membrane_transport">
	<head>
		<title>Membrane Transport</title>

	</head>
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Selective Permeability</title>
			<body>
				<p>The plasma membrane is the boundary of the cell; it determines what enters and
					exits the cell, and how the cell interacts with its environment. The cell
					membrane separates the extracellular and intracellular fluids, and each of these
					fluids contain thousands of substances. These substances often differ between
					the two fluids, or are at least found in very different concentrations. In order
					to maintain these differences, the cells need to be selectively permeable,
					regulating what moves in and out. Therefore cell membranes only allow some
					molecules through. This characteristic is why cell membranes are selectively
					permeable. They are not impermeable (meaning they do not prevent passage of all
					molecules) nor are they freely permeable (meaning they don’t let all molecules
					freely move across the membrane). This quality allows a cell to control what
					enters and exits it. This section of the course will further explore the ways in
					which molecules can pass across the membrane.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Passive and Active Passage Across (Through) the Cell Membrane</title>
			<body>
				<p>There are two categories used to describe the passage of substances through a
					cell membrane. They are categorized as passive (the cell does not have to use
					ATP), but needs some sort of driving force, and active (the cell must use ATP).
					We will investigate both of these next. </p>
				<p>As mentioned, passive processes do not use ATP but do need some sort of driving
					force. It is usually from kinetic energy in the form of a concentration
					gradient. Molecules will tend to move from high to low concentrations by the
					random movement of molecules. There are 2 main types of passive processes that occur across cell membranes.</p>

				<ol>
					<li>Diffusion and facilitated diffusion</li>
					<li>Osmosis and tonicity</li>
					
				</ol>
				
				<p>There is also a passive process that occurs across vessel membranes (such as capillary walls and the walls of lymphatic vessels) that we will cover in this section, but it should be noted that it does not generally occur across cell membranes - filtration.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
