<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m2_cell_membrane_1">
	<head>
		<title>Membrane Lipids</title>
		<objref idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure"/>
		<!--<objref idref="levels_cell_membrane_lipid"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>


		<p>The cell membrane is a dynamic structure composed of lipids, proteins, and carbohydrates.
			It protects the cell by preventing materials from leaking out, controls what can enter
			or leave through the membrane, provides a binding site for hormones and other chemicals,
			and serves as an identification card for the immune system to distinguish between “self”
			and “non-self” cells. We will first investigate the anatomy of the cell membrane and
			then continue on to study the physiology of membrane transport.</p>

		<p>The <term>phospholipid bilayer</term> is the main fabric of the membrane. The bilayer's
			structure causes the membrane to be semi-permeable. Remember that phospholipid molecules
			are amphiphilic (amphipathic), which means that they contain both a nonpolar and polar region.
			Phospholipids have a polar head (it contains a charged phosphate group) with two
			nonpolar hydrophobic fatty acid tails. The tails of different phospholipids face each other in
			the core of the membrane while the polar heads face either the exterior of interior of the
			cell. Having the polar heads oriented toward the external and internal sides of the
			membrane allows them to interact with the polar water molecules found on each side of the membrane. The hydrophobic core
			blocks the diffusion of <term>hydrophilic ions</term> and polar molecules. Small
				<term>hydrophobic</term> molecules and gases, which can dissolve in the membrane's
			core, cross it with ease.</p>
		<p>Other molecules require proteins to transport them across the membrane.
				<term>Proteins</term> determine most of the membrane's specific functions. The
			plasma membrane and the membranes of the various organelles each have unique collections
			of proteins. For example, to date more than 50 kinds of proteins have been found in the
			plasma membrane of red blood cells.</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/cell_membrane.png"/>

		<section>
			<title>Importance of Phospholipid Membrane Structure</title>
			<body>
				<p>What is important about the structure of a phospholipid membrane? First, it is
					fluid. This allows cells to change shape, permitting growth and movement. The
					fluidity of the membrane is regulated by the types of phospholipids and the
					presence of cholesterol. Second, the phospholipid membrane is selectively
					permeable. </p>
				<p>The ability of a molecule to pass through the membrane depends on its polarity
					and to some extent its size. Many non-polar molecules such as oxygen, carbon
					dioxide, and small hydrocarbons can flow easily through cell membranes. This
					feature of membranes is very important because hemoglobin, the protein that
					carries oxygen in our blood, is contained within red blood cells. Oxygen must be
					able to freely cross the membrane so that hemoglobin can get fully loaded with
					oxygen in our lungs, and deliver it effectively to our tissues. Most polar
					substances are stopped by a cell membrane, except perhaps for small polar
					compounds like the one carbon alcohol, methanol. Glucose is too large to pass
					through the membrane unassisted and a special transporter protein ferries it
					across. One type of diabetes is caused by misregulation of the glucose
					transporter. This decreases the ability of glucose to enter the cell and results
					in high blood glucose levels. Charged ions, such as sodium (Na+) or potassium
					(K+) ions seldom go through a membrane, consequently they also need special
					transporter molecules to pass through the membrane. The inability of Na+ and K+
					to pass through the membrane allows the cell to regulate the concentrations of
					these ions on the inside or outside of the cell. The conduction of electrical
					signals in your neurons is based on the ability of cells to control Na+ and K+
					levels. </p>

				<p>Selectively permeable membranes allow cells to keep the chemistry of the
					cytoplasm different from that of the external environment. It also allows them
					to maintain chemically unique conditions inside their organelles. </p>

				<section purpose="didigetthis">
					<title/>
					<body>
						<wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_fluid_mosaics_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						<wb:inline idref="inline_phospholipid_bilayer" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						<wb:inline idref="inline_phospholipid_bilayer2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						<wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_fluid_mosaics_DIGT3" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
					</body>
				</section>


			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
