<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m2_cell_proliferation">
    <head>
        <title>Cell Division and Control of Cell Number</title>
        <objref idref="levels_cell_number"/>


    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Even though we may not feel any changes from day to day, we are constantly repairing and
            replacing cells within our bodies. It’s estimated that approximately 300 million cells
            die every minute in our body! These cells must be replaced by identical functional cells
            for us to survive and maintain homeostasis. The process of cell proliferation or cell
            division is termed mitosis. Mitosis produces two daughter cells that are identical
            (clones) to the parent cell.</p>

        <p>Cell division is a carefully regulated process. There are “check-points” between phases,
            in which the cell “self-checks.” Through molecular interactions, the cell makes sure
            that it is ready to divide; for example, it checks to see that its DNA has not been
            damaged. If all criteria are met, the cell moves forward through the cell cycle. Normal
            cells usually divide only a limited number of times, and usually do so when stimulated
            by certain molecular signals. For example, if you move to higher altitude, your body
            will produce more red blood cells in order to supply enough oxygen despite the thinner
            air. </p>
        <p>Mitosis is also regulated by genes. Some genes become active to stimulate mitosis and
            other genes act as the brakes to turn it off (suppressor genes). If our body loses
            control over mitosis the result would be the production of too many (hyperplasia)
            abnormal cells and would form a tumor. If the tumor is encapsulated it is termed benign.
            If not, the mutated cells can spread and it is known as cancer. Cancer cells, on the
            other hand, have lost the normal cell cycle controls, and therefore can divide
            indefinitely.</p>

        <p>When a cell is performing its normal day-to-day functions it is in a state termed
            interphase. When it is time for that cell to replicate, genes become active and
            stimulate it to begin mitosis. Mitosis is characterized by four phases. Remember if a
            cell is going to form 2 new identical cells it must first replicate it’s DNA and
            organelles. It is during interphase that the DNA is replicated to form 2 identical
            strands. These strands of identical DNA are termed chromatids and are held together with
            a centromere.</p>

        <p>The stages of mitosis occur in sequence with specific events in each one. It is only
            during mitosis that chromosomes are visible. Usually DNA is in its threadlike chromatin
            form. You can identify the stages of mitosis by observing the chromosomes. Remember that
            the DNA is in the nucleus which is surrounded by the nuclear membrane. The DNA needs to
            be free from the nucleus so it can be evenly distributed to two daughter cells. The
            events of mitosis describe the processes of splitting and moving nuclear DNA to opposite
            ends of the parent cell where the nuclear membranes will reform. Then the cell membrane
            can split the cytoplasm and organelles (termed cytokinesis). The two daughter cells will
            each have the same genetic code. When you studied the cell you learned about the
            microtubules of the centrioles. They are the organelles that will move the DNA during
            mitosis.</p>
        <p>The major stages of mitosis are:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>Prophase</li>
                <li>Metaphase</li>
                <li>Anaphase</li>
                <li>Telophase</li>
            </ol>
           
           
        
    </body>
</workbook_page>
