<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_cell_membrane_active2"><head><title>Endocytosis and Exocytosis </title><objref idref="levels_membrane_active2" /></head><body><p id="b63e028aab81400497c8fa829269f596">Facilitated diffusion and active transport are not the only ways that materials can enter or leave cells. Through the processes of endocytosis and exocytosis, materials can be taken up or ejected in bulk, without passing through the cell&apos;s plasma membrane. </p><p id="b570a0c0642840fb9114d7e1ab4c286e">In <term>endocytosis</term>, material is engulfed within an infolding of the plasma membrane and then brought into the cell within a cytoplasmic vesicle. To begin endocytosis, a particle encounters the cell surface and produces a dimple or pit in the membrane. The pit deepens, invaginates further, and finally pinches off to form a vesicle in the cytoplasm of the cell. Note that during the process the inside surface of the newly formed vesicle is the same as the exterior surface of the cell. Thus the integrity of the cytoplasm and the orientation of the plasma membrane are preserved. Once internalized, this new vesicle containing extracellular materials may fuse with a lysosome so that its solid contents are digested. The resulting molecules may be released to the cytoplasm for use within the cell. </p><p id="d23ff6b2f9694edebe4e48d527b7e370">There are two general forms of endocytosis: <term>phagocytosis</term> and <term>pinocytosis</term>. Phagocytosis is the uptake of large solidparticles such as bacteria or cellular debris. Pinocytosis is the uptake of fluid and any small molecules dissolved within it. Cells are also capable of recognizing specific particles and engulfing them in a more targeted way, a process called receptor-mediated endocytosis. In this case, the particle first binds to a membrane protein receptor on the surface of the cell. Binding of the target particle induces the cell to engulf it. </p><p id="b3dbfd691ac84e0ea086fba6a970d79d"><term>Exocytosis</term> is just the reverse of endocytosis. In exocytosis, an internal vesicle fuses with the plasma membrane and releases its contents to the outside. The balance of exocytosis and endocytosis preserves the size of the plasma membrane and keeps the cell&apos;s size constant. </p><p id="a9ca8af13a9243dfb44782ca77207cd4">How are endocytosis and exocytosis important to everyday life? Immune cells protectanimals by recognizing and destroying foreign objects such as bacteria. Disease-causing bacteria are recognized by proteins called receptors on the surface of the immune cell. The phagocytic immune cell will then engulf the bacterial cells (phagocytosis). The vesicle that contains these bacterial cells is called a phagosome (&quot;phago&quot; means &quot;eating&quot; and &quot;-some&quot; refers to &quot;body&quot;). The phagosome next fuses with lysosomes. Finally, the digested bacterial products are excreted through the process of exocytosis.</p><image id="_i_0" src="../../webcontent/image3.png" alt="phagocytosis of a bacterium" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><title>Phagocytosis of a Bacterium</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_transmit_dopamine_DIGT" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></workbook_page>
