<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_m2_cell_membrane_3"><head><title>Membrane Carbohydrates</title><objref idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure" /></head><body><p id="c63509a05cf14afa99b3ff0fc943f7b8">The extracellular surface of the cell membrane is decorated with carbohydrate groups attached to lipids and proteins. Carbohydrates are added to lipids and proteins by a process called glycosylation, and are called glycolipids or glycoproteins. These short carbohydrates, or oligosaccharides, are usually chains of 15 or fewer sugar molecules. Oligosaccharides give a cell identity (i.e., distinguishing &quot;self&quot; from &quot;nonself&quot;) and are the distinguishing factor in human blood types and transplant rejection.</p><section id="e66fbe0f08b7497eac2e46f3b50833d4"><title>The Distribution of Membrane Carbohydrates is Asymmetric</title><body><p id="ca9f71bae3f344069cd8775a01a3496a">As discussed above, the distribution of carbohydrates in the cell membrane is asymmetric. The extracellular face of the membrane is in contact with the extracellular fluid. The extracellular side of the membrane contains oligosaccharides that distinguish the cell as &quot;self.&quot; It also contains the end of integral proteins that interact with signals from other cells and sense the extracellular environment. The inner membrane is in contact with the contents of the cell and tends to have few carbohydrates. Instead, this intracellular side of the membrane anchors to the cytoskeleton and contains the end of integral proteins that relay signals received on the external side.</p></body></section><section id="e908d8860e474047b2f196ed32761971"><title>Summary: Membranes as Mosaics of Structure and Function</title><body><p id="f82cd406fc604cf4a83adb126c6d00b6">The biological membrane is a collage of many different proteins embedded in the fluid matrix of the lipid bilayer. The lipid bilayer is the main fabric of the membrane, and its structure creates a semipermeable membrane. The hydrophobic core impedes the diffusion of hydrophilic structures such as ions and polar molecules, but allows hydrophobic molecules, which can dissolve in the membrane, to cross it with ease. </p></body></section><section id="b8250df82d7d484b941fc448aaa17a15" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure1" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure2" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure3" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure4" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure5" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
