<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_cell_membrane_diffusion1"><head><title>Diffusion</title><objref idref="levels_cell_membrane_diffusion" /></head><body><p id="dba082909f2547f9a7384650205eed9b">Diffusion relies on kinetic energy and a concentration gradient. Kinetic energy is affected by temperature, size of molecules, magnitude (steepness) of the gradient, and the medium (for example, the type of solution) the molecules are in. Anything that increases the kinetic energy of the molecules will increase the rate of diffusion.</p><p id="f33724a2d37a4cc595ff94249e73433b"><term>Diffusion</term> is the movement of molecules from an area of high concentration to an area of lower concentration. When referring to diffusion of molecules across a cell membrane, diffusion can be divided into simple diffusion and facilitated diffusion. In simple diffusion, the molecule passes directly through the phospholipid bilayer without the aid of a protein, whereas in facilitated diffusion a channel or carrier protein is used. Simple diffusion occurs with either very small or lipid soluble molecules that can pass directly through the hydrophobic region of the phospholipid bilayer of the cell membrane. Some examples of substances that use this process are oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>), carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>), and lipids. Facilitated diffusion occurs with molecules such as glucose, which may have a lower concentration inside of the cell than in the extracellular space, but that require the aid of a membrane protein for entry.</p><p id="b3ebc273c4534516986e6ccda59d2cb3">Diffusion will occur as long as there is a concentration gradient and path for movement. Once the concentration gradient no longer exists, it means that equilibrium has been reached and net diffusion ceases. This doesn’t mean that molecules still won’t move, but it does indicate that the movements are balanced in each direction and no more changes in concentration will occur. </p><p id="c4ef6b31e5c74fc88bf638222ad58029">Diffusion most commonly occurs in gasses and liquids. For example, waking up to the smell of coffee or bacon in the morning can occur because the chemicals (odorants) diffuse from the higher concentration in your kitchen to you! In the human body the diffusion of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> are critical for gas exchange. O<sub>2</sub> levels are higher in your arterial blood than your tissue cells so O<sub>2</sub> will diffuse out of the blood into your cells. CO<sub>2</sub> has the opposite concentration gradient. CO<sub>2</sub> levels are highest in your tissue cells (your mitochondria produce CO2 as a waste product from cellular respiration) and CO<sub>2</sub> diffuses out of the cell into the blood. These molecules are small enough to pass through the phospholipid bilayer and therefore are examples of simple diffusion. </p><p id="ab33ec895e8a84edfa5ca9e1e485aba37">The following animation depicts the process of simple diffusion, showing the molecules moving from an area of high concentration to an area of low concentration. In time, the concentration gradient dissipates and equilibrium is reached.</p><youtube id="b3434f14f09a47b3962e26ae9234448f" src="8HXymF1wjIg" height="300" width="500" controls="false"><cite id="i8e96edbaaf814c9784c7692cc6de9e4d" /><caption><p id="aa96c04d2df464ccc8f70a85b54ac4155"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube><section id="b02873bdd334497b9421a856cffd8e88" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_diffusion_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="ddf845bdf5bf41c096dc0f9304e4a0b6"><title>Diffusion Across the Membrane</title><body><p id="c2d8d546db8845c2acd790907e56d2fa">Molecules can be divided into four categories with regard to their ability to cross the plasma membrane. The first category is nonpolar molecules. These hydrophobic molecules can easily cross the membrane because they interact favorably with the nonpolar lipids. Note that these molecules can accumulate in the membrane because they interact so well with the lipids. The second category is small polar molecules. Although they don’t interact with the lipids, their small size allows them to pass through small temporary holes in the membrane. The third category is large polar molecules. These have difficulty crossing the membrane because of their size and poor interaction with the lipids. The last category is ionic compounds. Their charge interacts very unfavorably with the lipids, making it very difficult for them to cross the membrane.</p></body></section><section id="bb9e69646d31476799d2c130719c5e60" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><materials id="a98941999caa4cb78bf9ea255fbb7a5f"><material><image id="_i_0" src="../../webcontent/_u3_m2_cell_membrane-convert/chol_key_v2.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ab8bd121951534421bb990bda9c71d811"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><youtube id="a84a7679e12241bd8b3e170abae66cc6" src="kDsyfBfZo68" height="300" width="500" controls="true"><cite id="i0dfc70d691a44f929daef44bc368e5a4" /><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube></material></materials><p id="e1810d8de44b42069fa8b6968ca93931">In the preceding video, as three different molecules move, they encounter the lipid bilayer depicted by the horizontal membrane across the center of the stage. Notice that one type of molecule passes freely through the lipid bilayer while the second type of molecule only occasionally passes through the membrane, and the lipid bilayer is totally impermeable to the third type of molecule.</p><wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_cross_membrane_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><p id="acf41869ef844989a88bbd7c5a3599e9">The size, polarity, and charge of a substance will determine whether or not the substance can cross the cell membrane by diffusion. For example, even large, nonpolar substances (such as cholesterol) will freely enter the the nonpolar environment of the lipid bilayer, and some will pass through to the other side, while others will stay within the cell membrane. Small amphipathic molecules such as ethanol on the other hand, diffuse through the membrane. The lipid bilayer is much less permeable to ions because the charges are strongly excluded from the hydrophobic regions. As a general rule, charged molecules are much less permeable to the lipid bilayer.</p><section id="db4aafe16ced46c9be4f6d35cc794b45" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_cross_membrane_diffusion_digt" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
