<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_m2_cell_membrane_2"><head><title>Membrane Proteins</title><objref idref="levels_cell_membrane_structure" /></head><body><p id="c9e034c16d3c427891742deff1b107f6">Membranes also contain proteins, which carry out many of the functions of the membrane. Some functions of membrane proteins are:</p><ul id="b5f84124d130463284e373e01e9f930f"><li><p id="e219d2d5fca24e7bb4edabb8d3f4d929"><em style="italic">Transport.</em> Because the plasma membrane provide a barrier to the movement of many molecules, the cell needs a way to transport larger materials and hydrophilic molecules into and out of the cell.</p></li><li><p id="b2fd6f7b717d46e79a60048714b1dae4"><em style="italic">Communication.</em> Because the plasma membrane is the border of the cell, this is where the cell communicates with its environment. Membrane proteins are able to receive signals from outside the cell and begin a chain of events that cause the cell to respond to these signals. </p></li><li><p id="ae5c0bbb019b4b4e9d24e3fb661c9fbd"><em style="italic">Metabolism.</em> Membrane proteins can be enzymes that are involved in the chemical reactions of metabolism. These are the processes that allow the cell to grow, obtain energy, and eliminate wastes.</p></li><li><p id="e19593670f4a40ddaeaaf88ac9586698"><em style="italic">Adhesion.</em> Membrane proteins help cells bind to each other so that they can form tissues. One example of this is skin cells, which must form a tight, waterproof connection between the cells in order to maintain proper integrity of the skin as an organ. Membrane proteins also bind to structural molecules inside and outside the cell so that cellular structure can be maintained.</p></li></ul><p id="cec5b5520fde470baa8da2be9af7ae6e">Membrane proteins are classified into two major categories: integral proteins and peripheral proteins. <term>Integral membrane proteins</term> are those proteins that are embedded in the lipid bilayer and are generally characterized by their solubility in nonpolar, hydrophobic solvents. <term>Transmembrane proteins</term> are examples of integral proteins with hydrophobic regions that completely span the hydrophobic interior of the membrane. The parts of the protein exposed to the interior and exterior of the cell are hydrophilic. Integral proteins can serve as pores that selectively allow ions, nutrients, and wastes into or out of the cell. They can also transmit signals across the membrane.</p><p id="eee33989961c43059fdbcdb9272e27db">Unlike integral proteins that span the membrane, <term>peripheral proteins</term> reside on only one side of the membrane and are often attached to integral proteins. Some peripheral proteins serve as anchor points for the cytoskeleton or extracellular fibers. Proteins are much larger than lipids and move more slowly than phospholipids in the membrane. Some move in a seemingly directed manner, while others drift. Some are glycoproteins which have a carbohydrate group attached to the protein. These are on the outside of the membrane and important for cell recognition, they work like a cellular identification card.</p><image id="c87534ce58164d46bd1783774be873f3" src="../../../webcontent/proteins_mobility.gif" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="afe1dd4a70ea04b9185c2beacf091d355"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="f92dddf350e2403aa0c0062f7249aa1f" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_fluid_mosaics_DIGT1" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_fluid_mosaics_DIGT2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
