<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_m2_cell_apoptosis"><head><title>Mitosis and Apoptosis</title><objref idref="levels_cell_number" /></head><body><section id="ba0363b734cb4ff9a18e2e4900340441"><title>Prophase</title><body><p id="f3e586049a1043ca87dbfcc9ad00622a">Mitosis begins when DNA condenses into chromosomes visible under a light microscope. This packaging of the chromosomes into condensed bundles makes them easier to sort, but it inhibits protein synthesis. Therefore, it is essential that the cell has produced all necessary proteins prior to the start of this process.</p><image id="f6703a15983f4bf4bb9e3f2fd7942d7a" src="../../webcontent/Cell_Replic-Mitosis/Cells_2_prophase.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="da4eb143af4f4d5c98de5602fc093b13">The nucleoli disappear and the nuclear envelope begins to disintegrate. This allows cellular components to act upon the chromosomes (the chromosomes are no longer tucked away inside the nucleus).</p><p id="ad5812d2b08e45ad8042a1224c04a7e2">Centrioles, contained in the centrosomes formed during interphase, are areas where microtubules originate in order to help sort and organize the sister chromatids. The centrioles begin to move to the opposite poles of the cell. This will determine where the chromosomes go when they are sorted.</p><p id="fc849ca10f7a45899e576ecf065ee29e">Microtubules are disassembled from the cytoplasm and reassembled into the mitotic spindle. This structure will move the chromosomes to the proper location.</p><p id="b6727f703c9748509745a7410fdf66df">This stage is called “<term>prophase</term>,” because it is a preparatory stage. “Pro-” means &quot;before;&quot; “phase” means “stage.” So, this is the stage before the process gets into full swing.</p><wb:inline idref="inline_m1_prophase_function_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="e42c6d2e56ee4fd38dbfcda6e2290139"><title>Prometaphase</title><body><p id="d2b53ffe7cfd4895a1592d5510ea895d">Prometaphase is the stage between prophase and metaphase. During this stage, the nuclear envelope is fully broken down. This allows the microtubules to attach to the centromeres of the chromosomes.</p><image id="defbcf903bcf48cdaa0b7cade5cde416" src="../../webcontent/Cell_Replic-Mitosis/Cells_3_prometaphase.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f97b283ea2304f9eb7e009b90661b327">The centromere is the region in the center of the X-shaped chromosomes. Each half of the X is a copy of the same DNA strand. The centromere contains proteins that hold together these two copies and can bind to the microtubules. The proteins on the centromere are called the kinetochore, and the microtubules that attach to them are called kinetochore microtubules. The microtubules that are not attached to the kinetochores are called nonkinetochore microtubules.</p><wb:inline idref="inline_m1_prophase_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="d421e0c2db8c4e308140e34830693989"><title>Metaphase</title><body><p id="dc23f41c39954f6faeb3ad6c084fb17f">Metaphase is so named because the chromosomes line up in the middle of the cell. The root “meta-” means “middle.”</p><image id="ae0a704f939949648ea48243f116ef87" src="../../webcontent/Cell_Replic-Mitosis/Cells_4_metaphase.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b6e14a40d31343bdb5cd30067ebeeafa">The kinetochore microtubules are used to orient the chromosomes in the center of the cell. Each chromosome will be attached to two kinetochore microtubules. Each of these kinetochore microtubules will be attached to one of the two centrioles.</p><wb:inline idref="inline_m2_metaphase_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="b7ab4d8e8c0b4bc696b3dd752e729cab"><title>Anaphase</title><body><p id="e2d87ff755904a08b9a3ae62e02d3d7b">During anaphase, the kinetochore proteins break down the microtubules attached to them and the connections between each copy of the chromosome will be broken down. This causes the individual chromosomes to move to opposite poles of the cell. The root “ana-” refers to “apart”; the chromosomes are moving apart from each other.</p><image id="ec958ba746da443a846537ebe5917ccb" src="../../webcontent/Cell_Replic-Mitosis/Cells_5_anaphase.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f960066e10014cb0a9c5f59ea0e4cceb">The nonkinetochore microtubules from one pole also push on the nonkinetochore microtubules from the other pole. This causes the cell to elongate. By the end of anaphase, each pole of the cell contains an identical set of chromosomes.</p><wb:inline idref="inline_m3_anaphase_function_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="ba1a156b5d62477d919fcd4544a6d4f1"><title>Telophase</title><body><p id="b0cd64ed9df84ac5b9c822bbed8467b6">In telophase, the nuclei at each pole form again. The chromosomes are now separated into two identical nuclei. This is the end of mitosis. </p><image id="fc8199db726a4f0ab09426b6a9d2b5d3" src="../../webcontent/Cell_Replic-Mitosis/Cells_6_telophase.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b9659f4cafd64348a325cbc70d3d7a27">However, the two nuclei are still in a single cell. The next step will separate the cytoplasm into two cells. “Telo” comes from the Greek word for “end.”</p><wb:inline idref="inline_m4_telophase_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="cdf1d236b8cb44eaa1818973fac95603"><title>Cytokinesis</title><body><p id="eb559236d6574a7a99d832dd2dbd19e3">Cytokinesis is the separation of the cytoplasm into two new daughter cells. Animal cells divide when proteins pinch in the center of the cell until it separates into two. This region is called the cleavage furrow. </p><image id="e6d4a5ea467b4f609d2153312356f63f" src="../../webcontent/Cell_Replic-Mitosis/Cells_7_cytokinesis.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="650"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a51537153c2045bfb2dfb04c5aa15533">Plant cells divide when new cell wall components are laid down in the center of the cell. This is called the cell plate.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="inline_mitosis_phases_DIGT" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="c7593948a80740b69ef82dbfde8241d8"><title>Apoptosis</title><body><p id="ce1b2afae7a9446ca3c76438e3e56f9f">How does a single fertilized cell develop into something as marvelous and intricate as the human body? Part of the answer is apoptosis, or programmed cell death. For example, the early hand of an embryo is a stubby appendage. As cells between the fingers selectively die off, they sculpt the hand, leaving behind the separate fingers. In adults, apoptosis is one way that tissues maintain their integrity. Cells selectively die off to allow renewal of tissues such as the stomach, lungs, liver and so on. If apoptosis ceases in the tissue’s cells, a tumor can form, perhaps becoming cancerous. Apoptosis is distinguished from necrosis, which is cell death as a result of injury. Much like proliferation, there is a series of tightly regulated events that lead to apoptosis. Apoptosis is a cellular program that is internally determined, and billions of cells die this way every day. However, external trauma, toxins or infection cause a different type of cell death called necrosis. Even though both mechanisms lead to dead cells, apoptosis is a program to maintain cell number whereas necrosis is a consequence of intense cell damage.</p></body></section></body></workbook_page>
