<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_cell_membrane_filtration"><head><title>Filtration</title><objref idref="levels_membrane_filtration" /></head><body><p id="a6b9abebf8214fbe856b9ecf96822fe5">Filtration is another passive process of moving material through a cell membrane. While diffusion and osmosis rely on concentration gradients, filtration uses a pressure gradient. Molecules will move from an area of higher pressure to an area of lower pressure. Filtration is non-specific. This means that it doesn’t sort the molecules, they pass due to pressure gradients and their size. If molecules are small enough to pass through the membrane, they will. The force that pushes the molecules is termed hydrostatic pressure. </p><example id="b78691aefe9d463c826c62479712a8ae"><p id="bb3b73e4f3a74a669c85345520941bbf">One example of filtration is making coffee. Think of the coffee filter as the cell membrane and the coffee grounds, flavor and caffeine as the molecules. The pressure is exerted by the water from the machine. It forces materials through the coffee filter into the coffee pot. Small molecules like caffeine, water, and flavor pass through the filter but the coffee grounds do not. They are too big. If you poked holes in the filter, the coffee grounds would end up in your coffee! The coffee filter represents the filtration membrane which is typically a layer of cells.</p></example><p id="a325af516b7640d5a3538208bb4b2620">Filtration is one of the main methods used for capillary exchange. Blood pressure provides the driving force or hydrostatic pressure to force materials out of capillaries to cells or to form the filtrate (fluid in the nephron of the kidney). Hydrostatic pressure is countered by osmotic pressure. Remember osmotic pressure is created due to increased solute concentration and will pull water toward the area of higher solutes. These two pressures must be in balance for homeostasis of fluid volumes. In our body large molecules such as plasma proteins and red blood cells should not pass out of the blood through the cell membranes lining the capillaries. If they pass through and end up in in the tissues or in the kidney and later the urine it is abnormal and a sign of disease. </p><section id="feaea963bf7e4c90a6153cdd1c1a36eb" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><youtube id="a294f8133acd405281f510fc23ab668e" src="h40jomrGEz4" height="300" width="500" controls="true"><cite id="i4e071d50f5e346849783c214e6804e21" /><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_filtration_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="a5267d51eb7f4f26983808c67b9991a6" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_filtration_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_cell_membrane_filtration_digt2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
