<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="urinary_calcitriol"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="calcitriol"><body>Kidneys help synthesize calcitriol, an enzyme which is found in the digestive, endocrine, and integumentary systems. Explain how calcitriol benefits the entire body.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Calcitriol is necessary to help regulate volume of lymph and interstitial fluid.</choice><choice value="B">Calcitriol is necessary as it allows for the passage and direction of sperm.</choice><choice value="C">Calcitriol is necessary for the absorption of dietary calcium in the digestive and integumentary systems which promotes bone reabsorption in the endocrine system.</choice><choice value="D">Calcitriol is necessary to prevent abnormal function of enzymatic pathways in the respiratory system.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="calcitriol_p1"><skillref idref="explain_calcitriol_benefits_body" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Kidneys increase/decrease reabsorption of water filtered from blood help regulate volume of lymph and interstitial fluid. This works in conjunction with the lymphatic/ immune system.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In the urinary system, the urethra in males acts as a dual passageway for urine and sperm. Calcitriol is independent of the reproductive system.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Calcitriol is necessary for the absorption of dietary calcium in the digestive and integumentary systems which promotes bone reabsorption in the endocrine system.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Kidneys work with lungs to adjust the pH of body fluid which prevents abnormal function of enzymatic pathways. Calcitriol is independent of the respiratory system.</feedback></response><hint>Calcitriol is form of vitamin D</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
