<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m3_levels_org_wrapup_openfree">
	<head>
		<title>Urinary Levels of Organization Summary</title>


	</head>


	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Let’s summarize</title>
			
			<body>
				<p>Despite major differences in fluid intake on a given day, the total volume of
					fluid within the body usually remains the same. This is due to <em style="bold"
						>homeostasis</em>. For example, if a person with healthy kidneys drinks a
					large volume of fluids, the kidneys will produce a large volume of urine.
					Conversely, if that same person does not drink enough fluids, the kidneys will
					produce a small amount of concentrated urine to preserve water.</p>
				<p>Urine is composed of elements and compounds that include urea, chloride, sodium,
					potassium, creatinine, hydrogen, and bicarbonate. The nephrons help produce
					urine.</p>
				<p>The functional units of the kidneys are called <em style="bold">nephrons</em>,
					which are made up of epithelial cells sitting on top of a non-cellular layer or
					basement membrane.</p>
				
				<p>Each kidney contains about one million nephrons, which are made up of:</p>
				<ul style="disc">
					<li><em style="bold">A renal corpuscle</em> made up of a glomerulus within a <em
						style="bold">glomerular capsule</em></li>
					<li><em style="bold">A renal tubule</em> comprised of a proximal convoluted
						tubule, nephron loop, and distal convoluted tubule.</li>
					<li><em style="bold">Collecting ducts</em> that receive tubular filtrate from
						multiple nephrons and transport the fluid to the calyces and renal
						pelvis.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>The nephrons are involved in three functions: filtration, reabsorption, and
					secretion.</p>
				
				<p>There are six organs in the urinary system: two kidneys, two ureters, the urinary
					bladder, and the urethra.</p>
				<p>The two kidneys, perform the following functions:</p>
				<ul style="disc">
					<li><em style="bold">Remove wastes</em> from the blood.</li>
					<li><em style="bold">Help regulate blood</em> composition and volume.</li>
					<li>Contributing to the <em style="bold">regulation of blood pressure</em>.</li>
				</ul>
				
				
				<p>External Anatomy of the kidneys include:</p>
				<ul style="disc">
					<li>A <em style="bold">renal hilum</em>, renal vein, ureter, and nerves either
						enter or exit the kidney.</li>
					<li>A <em style="bold">renal capsule</em> that preserves the form of the
						kidney.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">perinephric fat</em> that encircles the renal capsule,
						offering another layer of protection.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">renal fascia</em> that tethers each kidney to
						neighboring structures and to the abdominal wall.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">paranephric fat</em> that comprises the outermost
						layer, and provides another layer of protection.</li>
					
				</ul>
				<p>Internal Anatomy of the kidneys include:</p>
				<ul style="disc">
					<li>The<em style="bold">renal medulla</em> that maintains the proper balance of
						salt and water in the blood</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">renal cortex</em> is the outer layer of the kidney. It
						also extends as renal columns between the renal pyramids.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">renal pyramids</em> make up the renal medulla Included
						as part of the functional part of the kidney.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">renal papillae</em> are located at the apex of the
						renal pyramids.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">renal columns</em> are part of the renal lobes.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">renal lobes</em> consist of one renal pyramid with its
						surrounding renal cortex, including one half of both adjacent renal columns.
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>The other organs of the urinary system include:</p>
				<p>The ureters:</p>
				<ul style="disc">
					<li>The <em style="bold">innermost mucosa lining</em> allows the ureter wall to
						accommodate changing volumes of urine.</li>
					<li>The <em style="bold">middle muscularis layer</em> is composed of two layers
						of smooth muscle: an inner longitudinal layer and outer circular layer. The
						muscularis is responsible for moving urine through the ureters and into the
						bladder. </li>
					<li>The outer layer of <em style="bold">adventitia</em>.</li>
					
				</ul>
				<p>The <em style="bold">urinary bladder</em>: </p>
				
				<ul style="disc">
					<li><p>The<em style="bold">trigone</em>.</p></li>
					<li>The internal urethral sphincter At the bladder-urethra junction,
						involuntarily sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of
						urine when you are not voiding.</li>
					<li>The external urethral sphincter at the distal end of the urethra at the
						orifice closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when you
						are not voiding.</li>
					
				</ul>
				
				<p>The <em style="bold">urethra</em> is a small muscular tube that transports urine
					from the bladder out of the body. The urethra is five times longer in males (8
					inches, 20 cm) than in females (1.6 inches, 4 cm). The course of the urethra
					also differs between the sexes. At the bladder-urethra junction, the internal
					urethral sphincter involuntarily sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents
					the leakage of urine when you are not voiding.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<!-- 	<section>

			<title><em style="bold">End Questions</em></title>

			<body>


				 <p>Before you do the quiz activity, please evaluate your understanding of the
					learning objectives for the Urinary Levels of Organization and use the first My
					Response link below to ask any questions you might have about the material that
					you would like the instructor to address. Your questions can be for
					clarification of the material or further insight. Your self-evaluation will not
					be graded, but will be available for your instructor to read. Answering these
					questions may also shape the discussions in class. </p>

				  <activity idref="_u12_m3_urinary_levels_org_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>

				 	<p> If you do not feel ready for the quiz, identify the objectives you need to
					review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t
					just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of
					questions that will be in the quiz.</p>
				
				 <activity idref="u2_m3_checkpoint" purpose="checkpoint"/>

				<p> Now that you have finished the quiz, do you have any questions? Your instructor
					will be able to read the questions and comments that you submit. </p>
				 	<activity idref="_u12_m3_urinary_levels_org_feedback_post_quiz" purpose="myresponse"/>



			</body>

		</section>-->



	</body>
</workbook_page>
