<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u12_m3_levels_org_wrapup"><head><title>Urinary Levels of Organization Review and Assessment</title></head><body><section id="bd0e797c458d4ff48ea5a86a54e98366"><title>Let’s Summarize</title><body><p id="d33ee17aca0242b7998bbb866750da63">Despite major differences in fluid intake on a given day, the total volume of fluid within the body usually remains the same. This is due to <em style="bold">homeostasis</em>. For example, if a person with healthy kidneys drinks a large volume of fluids, the kidneys will produce a large volume of urine. Conversely, if that same person does not drink enough fluids, the kidneys will produce a small amount of concentrated urine to preserve water.</p><p id="c6ec8c7a21ad40869ccab9e33c324284">Urine is composed of elements and compounds that include urea, chloride, sodium, potassium, creatinine, hydrogen, and bicarbonate. The nephrons help produce urine.</p><p id="efedf27c175c4439a1754b7b0ab2d5ad">The functional units of the kidneys are called <em style="bold">nephrons</em>, which are made up of epithelial cells sitting on top of a non-cellular layer or basement membrane.</p><p id="e01f695087d045f3a228bbba33d7cbac">Each kidney contains about one million nephrons, which are made up of:</p><ul id="c0ce18456f454cad83d57dd48c66ef52" style="disc"><li><p id="f5f4168bc336473a92120d2e47abcc40"><em style="bold">A renal corpuscle</em> made up of a glomerulus within a <em style="bold">glomerular capsule.</em></p></li><li><p id="cf095b3cbaa343e981b6fdb45aba9972"><em style="bold">A renal tubule</em> comprised of a proximal convoluted tubule, nephron loop, and distal convoluted tubule.</p></li><li><p id="d56a70e9fb154471a845c79234145483"><em style="bold">Collecting ducts</em> that receive tubular filtrate from multiple nephrons and transport the fluid to the calyces and renal pelvis.</p></li></ul><p id="fe390f69503840e08cd49fcd0b51cb88">The nephrons are involved in three functions: filtration, reabsorption, and secretion.</p><p id="b43ff9103b8149859a7c4d519661de5a">There are six organs in the urinary system: two kidneys, two ureters, the urinary bladder, and the urethra.</p><p id="e74d8b61241049f3928a3b6eca829981">The two kidneys, perform the following functions:</p><ul id="b6885735791f484a99c21c123cf18599" style="disc"><li><p id="f68ae6819a81474d9f0ee120b36e3444"><em style="bold">Remove wastes</em> from the blood.</p></li><li><p id="c2a9e67e4db249a19efae349440d90a4"><em style="bold">Help regulate blood</em> composition and volume.</p></li><li><p id="f3b06f6dfb654b1cba32559974ce405f">Contributing to the <em style="bold">regulation of blood pressure</em>.</p></li></ul><p id="d871d9751833484c9913a2177d6abb23">External anatomy of the kidneys include:</p><ul id="b727bb668c704d42965486457e5f2d0f" style="disc"><li><p id="e2264d4a1cc145eba8f50ea1330184c7">A <em style="bold">renal hilum</em>, renal vein, ureter, and nerves either enter or exit the kidney.</p></li><li><p id="c61291c4796945f490263d0320d565ae">A <em style="bold">renal capsule</em> that preserves the form of the kidney.</p></li><li><p id="ac49ae032d574aeda20257659190a53f">The <em style="bold">perinephric fat</em> that encircles the renal capsule, offering another layer of protection.</p></li><li><p id="c6607aefa72a430ba5928619e2184f9f">The <em style="bold">renal fascia</em> that tethers each kidney to neighboring structures and to the abdominal wall.</p></li><li><p id="dfb720baeb5a4ea0b15a727b9355b453">The <em style="bold">paranephric fat</em> that comprises the outermost layer, and provides another layer of protection.</p></li></ul><p id="d928929db187418b80534e6f471d4981">Internal anatomy of the kidneys include:</p><ul id="a5020a5668324a3b823044518550b717" style="disc"><li><p id="d3ccfb31b64b409c81284364c5cc84e6">The<em style="bold">renal medulla</em> that maintains the proper balance of salt and water in the blood.</p></li><li><p id="bbc5ee6d82c44741a943450b5ecba6fa">The <em style="bold">renal cortex</em> is the outer layer of the kidney. It also extends as renal columns between the renal pyramids.</p></li><li><p id="a12be1adf52c4025ad1f8fe67850900e">The <em style="bold">renal pyramids</em> make up the renal medulla Included as part of the functional part of the kidney.</p></li><li><p id="f46840198a6f4fcab4121df875290fa8">The <em style="bold">renal papillae</em> are located at the apex of the renal pyramids.</p></li><li><p id="e10bdf1bf1964ecab5fd9f5521f9404d">The <em style="bold">renal columns</em> are part of the renal lobes.</p></li><li><p id="ed340ae00d1d4d019e3ffc47f265c05e">The <em style="bold">renal lobes</em> consist of one renal pyramid with its surrounding renal cortex, including one half of both adjacent renal columns. </p></li></ul><p id="b785ded832ce448eb3a7b02107d7ee86">The other organs of the urinary system include:</p><p id="ea9fe50963134bd9855f812da0c7c56f">The ureters:</p><ul id="d7cd41fb80954350a73581f2a6ea43fb" style="disc"><li><p id="cc7d760407084061b9b883f97abe60bd">The <em style="bold">innermost mucosa lining</em> allows the ureter wall to accommodate changing volumes of urine.</p></li><li><p id="c538eefe50b547b0a0d994bb46890146">The <em style="bold">middle muscularis layer</em> is composed of two layers of smooth muscle: an inner longitudinal layer and outer circular layer. The muscularis is responsible for moving urine through the ureters and into the bladder. </p></li><li><p id="ecaa10bb75b04c4585ce4eea6735b63f">The outer layer of <em style="bold">adventitia</em>.</p></li></ul><p id="bef1d2e31b7f4450bc33f4a2ca3b35f0">The <em style="bold">urinary bladder</em>: </p><ul id="d19015722b7c419cbfa59a7b2fc6a75f" style="disc"><li><p id="c79872de1e1a4779bb18b46a554c9534">The <em style="bold">trigone</em>.</p></li><li><p id="ac6354e4448154aa9bca693a260a5becf">The internal urethral sphincter At the bladder-urethra junction, involuntarily sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when you are not voiding.</p></li><li><p id="aca4925a15eac417d8f8d0eada599bd58">The external urethral sphincter at the distal end of the urethra at the orifice closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when you are not voiding.</p></li></ul><p id="e1d381c3f0b347d9a8b0561b443ce71b">The <em style="bold">urethra</em> is a small muscular tube that transports urine from the bladder out of the body. The urethra is five times longer in males (8 inches, 20 cm) than in females (1.6 inches, 4 cm). The course of the urethra also differs between the sexes. At the bladder-urethra junction, the internal urethral sphincter involuntarily sphincter closes off the urethra and prevents the leakage of urine when you are not voiding.</p></body></section><section id="b6f1356649064a2fb2698b562755e13e"><title> </title><body><p id="b1d095ac66be45aaa3af5449f7da17b5">If you do not feel ready for the quiz, identify the objectives you need to review. Go back to those pages. Read the examples and do the activities. Don’t just read the activities, actually do them to get practice with the types of questions that will be in the quiz.</p><activity idref="urinary_levels_org_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
