<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u12_m3_levels_org_03">
	<head>
		<title>The Kidney</title>

		<objref idref="internal_external_kidney_structure"/>
		<objref idref="blood_vessels_kidney"/>
	</head>
	<body>


		<!--	<p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the anatomy of organs of the
						urinary system and relate the structures to the function of the urinary
						system</em></p>
		<p> Males and females differ in anatomical features of the lower urinary tract. The anatomy
			of the urinary system is closely aligned with that of the reproductive system, which is
			why they are sometimes collectively referred to as the urogenital system. The two
			systems share their embryonic development; moreover, in males, the urethra is both a
			urinary and a reproductive organ.</p>-->

		<p>There are six organs in the urinary system: two kidneys, two ureters, the urinary
			bladder, and the urethra.The <term>kidneys </term>are the body's main purification
			system. They remove wastes, some of which are toxic, from the blood. The kidneys also
			help to regulate blood composition and volume. By manipulating blood volume, the kidneys
			contribute to the regulation of blood pressure. The kidneys are about the size of your
			fist and are shaped like beans. The <term>nephron</term>, which we have already covered,
			is the structural and functional unit of the kidney. The average number of nephrons in
			each kidney is about one million, although this number can vary from about half a
			million to two million. Nephrons are so good at what they do that it only takes about
			one fourth of them to be functional to meet the needs of the body. Still, a low number
			of functioning nephrons has been linked to a greater risk of developing kidney disease
			and high blood pressure (hypertension).</p>

		<section>
			<title>Kidney Location</title>

			<body>
				<!--  <p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Locate the kidney with respect to other
						organs and structures of the abdomen</em></p>-->
				<p>The kidneys lie between the parietal peritoneum and the posterior abdominal wall,
					just above waist level. The location posterior to the parietal peritoneum means
					they are <term>retroperitoneal</term>. These reddish, paired organs are offered
					some protection by the eleventh and twelfth rib pairs. The right kidney lies
					slightly lower than the left kidney. This asymmetry occurs due to the increases
					space required by the liver on the right side of the abdominal cavity superior
					to the kidney.</p>



				<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_13.jpg" height="300" width="500"
					alt="inside look at human body with kidney">
					<caption>Inside look at organs. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
						Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
							href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
							>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
				</image>


				<section>
					<title>External Anatomy</title>
					<body>
						<!-- 	<p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the external anatomy of the kidney and the
				functions of the tissues surrounding the kidney</em></p>-->
						<p>In adults, the kidney is approximately four to five inches long, two to
							three inches wide, and one inch thick (10 cm long, 5 cm wide and 2 cm
							thick). On average, each kidney weighs just under five ounces. The
							kidneys have a concave medial border that faces the vertebral column.
							There is a depression near the middle of the concave border called the
								<term>renal hilum</term>, where the renal artery enters the kidney
							and the renal vein, and ureters leave it.</p>
						<p>Each kidney is enshrouded in four tissue layers. The innermost layer, the
								<term>renal capsule</term>, is composed of fibrous connective
							tissue. It preserves the form of the kidney while protecting it from
							damage due to trauma. The <term>adipose capsule </term>or
								<term>perinephric fat</term> is the middle tissue layer. This fatty
							tissue mass encircles the renal capsule, offering another layer of
							protection from trauma and fixing the kidney in place. The <term>renal
								fascia </term>is the third tissue layer. The renal fascia is a slim
							layer of dense irregular connective tissue. This layer tethers each
							kidney to neighboring structures and to the abdominal wall. The
							paranephric fat forms the superficial layerand provides additional
							cushion and support for the kidney.</p>
					</body>
				</section>

				<table>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_7a.jpg" height="400" width="300"
								alt="detailed cross section of kidney">
								<caption>Cross section of kidney. This work by Cenveo is licensed
									under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
										href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
										>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>

							</image>
						</td>
						<td>
							<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_10a.jpg" height="450" width="450"
								alt="detailed cross section of kidney">
								<caption>Cross section of kidney. Image courtesy of Deborah Y. Sillman, Penn State University.</caption>

							</image>
						</td>
					</tr>
				</table>





				<example title="renal_ptosis">
					<title>Renal Ptosis</title>
					<p>The position of the kidneys is in part maintained by the layers of fat
						surrounding them. People who lose a lot of weight in a short period of time
						can also lose some of the fat that surrounds their kidneys. Very thin people
						may not have a sufficient layer of fat around their kidneys. In either case,
						one or both kidneys may drop down into the pelvis when a person stands up, a
						condition called <term>renal ptosis</term> (<em style="italic">ptosis</em>:
						"to fall"). For the majority of cases, people are without symptoms. However,
						in some cases health problems ranging from acute pain and vomiting to
						kinking of the ureter can occur. </p>
					<p>If renal ptosis creates a kink in the ureter, the kink can prevent the
						drainage of urine. Urine can then back up into the kidney, creating pressure
						that may damage renal tissue. </p>
					<p>Diagnosis is controversial but may be confirmed by a patient experiencing
						relief from abdominal pain upon lying in a supine position and/or by imaging
						tests.</p>
					<p> Treatment for severely symptomatic patients usually involves a laproscopic
						surgical procedure called <term>nephropexy</term>. This procedure affixes
						the kidney to the retroperitoneal tissue, closer to its usual position.</p>
				</example>

				<section>
					<title>Internal Anatomy</title>
					<body>
						<!-- <p><em style="bold">LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Describe the gross anatomy of the interior of the
				kidney</em></p>-->
						<p>Two structures dominate the internal anatomy of the kidney: a deep
							reddish-brown area called the <term>renal medulla</term>, and a
							superficial pinkish area called the <term>renal cortex</term>. The renal
							medulla is made up of cone-shaped structures called <term>renal
								pyramids</term> and its primary purpose is to maintain the proper
							balance of salt and water in the blood. The bases of the pyramids border
							the renal cortex, and their apexes (<term>renal papillae</term>) face
							the renal hilum. The smooth-textured renal cortex runs from the renal
							capsule to the renal pyramid bases and extends towards the pelvis in the
							spaces between the pyramids. The renal cortex has an outer cortical zone
							and an inner juxtamedullary zone. The areas of renal cortex lying
							between renal pyramids are called <term>renal columns</term>. A
								<term>renal lobe </term>consists of one renal pyramid with its
							surrounding renal cortex, including one half of both adjacent renal
							columns.</p>
						
						<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_11.jpg" width="500"
							alt="internal structure of kidney">
							<caption>Internal structure of kidney. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a
								Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
									>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
						</image>
						<p>The <term>parenchyma </term>refers to the functional part of any organ.
							In the case of the kidney, the parenchyma includes the renal cortex and
							the renal pyramids. The actual functional units of the kidneys are
							microscopic structures called nephrons. Recall that there are about a
							million of nephrons per kidney. A low nephron number is associated with
							an increased risk of kidney disease and high blood pressure
							(hypertension).</p>
						<p>One of the nephrons' main roles is to create urine. Urine produced by
							nephrons empties into large <term>papillary ducts</term>. These ducts
							run through the renal papillae of the pyramids. From the papillary
							ducts, urine flows into cup-like structures called the <term>minor and
								major calyces</term> (<em style="italic">calyces</em>: "cups"). Each
							kidney contains two or three major calyces and several minor calyces.
							The papillary ducts of one renal papilla drains into a minor calyx. As
							minor calyces join together, they form a major calyx. All major calyces
							join together to form one large chamber called the <term>renal
								pelvis</term>. Urine that collects in the renal pelvis is
							transported out of the pelvis through the ureters and to the urinary
							bladder.</p>
						<p>Within the kidney, the hilum opens up into a cavity called the
								<term>renal sinus</term>, which includes a portion of the renal
							pelvis, the calyces, and renal blood vessel and nerve branches. These
							structures are held in place in the renal sinus by adipose tissue.</p>
					</body>
				</section>






				



				<wb:inline idref="urinary_internal_external_kidney" purpose="learnbydoing"
					src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
					<param name="interfaceDescription"
						>../webcontent/urinary_internal_external_kidney_layout.xml</param>
				</wb:inline>

				<section>
					<title>Blood and Nerve Supply</title>
					<body>
						<!-- 	<p>LEARNING OBJECTIVES: Identify the large vessels and nerves that integrate with the
			kidney</p>-->
						<p>The kidneys' generous supply of blood vessels reflects their roles in the
							removal of wastes from the plasma and regulators of the volume and ionic
							composition of blood. Despite the kidneys accounting for less than 0.5
							percent of total body mass, the right and left <term>renal arteries
							</term>transport approximately one fourth of total cardiac output
							(approximately1.2 quarts or 1 liter) to these organs every minute.</p>
						
						<image src="../webcontent/u_m1_12.jpg" height="300" width="500"
							alt="detailed cross section of kidney arteries and veins">
							<caption>Cross section of kidney arteries and veins. This work by Cenveo is
								licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
									>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
						</image>
						
						<p>The large renal artery divides into several <term>segmental arteries
							</term>within the kidney that supply different areas or segments of the
							kidney. The segmental arteries branch into a number of <term>interlobar
								arteries </term>within the renal column. At the corticomedullary
							junction, the interlobar arteries branch to form the <term>arcuate
								arteries </term>(arcuate means curved). The arcuate arteries divide
							into smaller <term>cortical radiate arteries</term> (also called
								<term>interlobular arteries</term>) that supply the cortical tissue.
							The cortical radiate arteries divide into afferent arterioles, which
							supply nephrons. The renal cortex receives more than 90 percent of the
							renal blood supply.</p>
						<p>Veins generally follow the same courses as arteries, but in reverse. From
							the renal cortex, blood drains first into the cortical radiate
							(interlobular) veins and then the arcuate, interlobar, and renal veins;
							there are no segmental veins. The renal veins drain into the inferior
							vena cava, which is located to the right of the vertebral column.
							Because of the position of the inferior vena cava, the left renal vein
							is about twice as long as the right renal vein.</p>
						<p>Innervation of the kidneys and their ureters is supplied from an
							outgrowth of the celiac plexus called the <term>renal plexus</term>.
							This complex of autonomic nerve fibers and ganglia is primarily supplied
							by sympathetic vasomotor fibers. Their motor function is to adjust the
							diameter of renal arterioles to help regulate renal blood flow. This
							includes regulation of blood flow in the affrent and efferent arterioles
							and thus in the glomerulus. These fibers also innervate the juxtaglomerular apparatus.</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<wb:inline idref="urinary_cardiac_output_kidney" purpose="learnbydoing"/>



				

			</body>
		</section>






	</body>

</workbook_page>
