<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<assessment id="eda_intro_new_digt_3">
    <title>Tutor</title>
   
    <question id="q1">
        <body><p>Which of the following variables is categorical? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <multiple_choice select="multiple" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="iia">Treat</choice>
            <choice value="iib">AcuteT</choice>
            <choice value="iic">Outcome</choice>

        </multiple_choice>

        <part>

            <response match="iia" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that Treat is a categorical variable because
                    the treatment received by the patients is in the form of categories (Lithium,
                    Imipramine, or Placebo). However, there is at least one other variable that is
                    also categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="iib" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. AcuteT is not a categorical variable; rather, it is a
                    quantitative variable because it can take on multiple numerical values to
                    represent a characteristic of the patient.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="iic" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that Outcome is a categorical variable, since recurrence is in the form of two categories (Recurrence or No Recurrence). However, there is at least one other variable that is also categorical.<!--You are correct that Gender is a categorical variable because
                    patients are placed into two distinct categories (1 = Female; 2 = Male) and the
                    numbers have no arithmetic meaning. However, there is at least one other
                    variable that is also categorical.--></feedback>

            </response>
            <response match="iia,iib" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Treat is a categorical variable because the treatment received
                    by the patients is in the form of categories (Lithium, Imipramine, or Placebo).
                    However, AcuteT is not a categorical variable; rather, it is a quantitative
                    variable because it can take on multiple numerical values to represent a
                    characteristic of the patient.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="iia,iic" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Treat is a categorical variable because the treatment received by
                    the patients is in the form of categories (Lithium, Imipramine, or Placebo).
                    Outcome is also a categorical variable, since recurrence is in the form of two categories (Recurrence or No Recurrence).<!--Gender is also a categorical variable because patients are placed into two
                    distinct categories (1 = Female; 2 = Male) and the numbers have no arithmetic
                    meaning.--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="iib,iic" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. <!--You are correct that Gender is a categorical variable, because
                    patients are placed into two distinct categories (1 = Female; 2 = Male) and the
                    numbers have no arithmetic meaning. -->You are correct that Outcome is a categorical variable, since recurrence is in the form of two categories (Recurrence or No Recurrence). However, there is at least one other variable that is also categorical. However, AcuteT is not a categorical
                    variable; rather, it is a quantitative variable because it can take on multiple
                    numerical values to represent a characteristic of the patient.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="iia,iib,iic" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that that both Treat and Outcome are categorical
                    variables. Treat is a categorical variable because the treatment received by the
                    patients is in the form of categories (Lithium, Imipramine, or Placebo). Outcome is also a categorical variable, since recurrence is in the form of two categories (Recurrence or No Recurrence).<!--Gender
                    is a categorical variable, because patients are placed into two distinct
                    categories (1 = Female; 2 = Male) and the numbers have no arithmetic meaning.-->
                    However, AcuteT is not a categorical variable; rather, it is a quantitative
                    variable because it can take on multiple numerical values to represent a
                    characteristic of the patient.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one variable that is categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </question>
  
</assessment>
