<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="explain_cardio_other_systems_homeostasis_LBD"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>You may expect vasodilation due to __________.</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="A">an increase in oxygen concentration in the tissue fluid</choice><choice value="B">a decrease in CO2 in the tissue fluid</choice><choice value="C">an increase in pH of the interstitial fluid</choice><choice value="D">an increase in lactic acid concentration in skeletal muscles</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="identify_role_autoregulation_cardio_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If there is high oxygen, then there will not be a requirement for greater blood flow, which is the result of vasodilation.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If there is low CO<sub>2</sub>, then there will not be a requirement for greater blood flow, which is the result of vasodilation.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in pH indicates lower CO<sub>2</sub> in the tissue fluid. This means that blood flow need to be restricted to raise the CO<sub>2</sub> level.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Increase in lactate means that there is demand for oxygen and fuel. Vasodilation increases the supply of nutrients and oxygen rich blood while at the same time enhancing the rate of waste removal -– in this case lactate.</feedback></response><hint>Think about how blood vessels respond to changes in the properties of tissue fluid and cells being supplied.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>People who experience local injury often take a prostaglandin inhibitor. This is because __________.</body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="A">prostaglandins are local signaling molecules that cause inflammation, and inhibiting them decreases inflammation</choice><choice value="B">prostaglandins inhibit inflammation, blocking them promotes the beneficial effects of inflammation.</choice><choice value="C">prostaglandins inhibit blood flow to the area, inhibiting them increases blood flow, which benefits tissue healing</choice><choice value="D">prostaglandins are releases locally but move to the central nervous system to cause pain. Inhibiting them blocks pain</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="identify_factors_affect_autoregulation_cardio_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Prostaglandins mediate many of the aspects of inflammation, including vasodilation and local pain.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Prostaglandins promote inflammation.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Prostaglandins promote blood flow (possibly excessive) to an area.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although prostaglandins can sensitize pain receptors, they do so locally and not by traveling to the CNS.</feedback></response><hint>Aspirin and ibuprofen are prostaglandin inhibitors.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
