<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="b50100d2979a48e5982a43bc151d2adb"><title>Applying Electronegativity (copy)</title><page id="cf667ea580c3412a80cf107d6ff2cb80"><title>Page 1</title><question id="chemLev_LBD01_Magnesium"><body><p id="b962f3abc4ac43de8da3a48838f7b598">Given the atom Magnesium, in solution, how many electrons will it loose or gain? Would that make it a cation or an anion?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="c7ae1b74a9fd4ce1857c713176ea1b19" labels="false"><choice value="gain_anion">6 electrons gained, anion</choice><choice value="gain_cation">6 electrons gained, cation</choice><choice value="lost_anion">2 electrons lost, anion</choice><choice value="lost_cation">2 electrons lost, cation</choice></multiple_choice><part id="fdc2f74dacf74ee2aea1c6235f4288bf"><response match="gain_anion" score="0"><feedback><p id="afa797eb181104254916657849885673b">That is not quite right. Magnesium has a low electronegativity thsuit will be easier for it to loose its 2 electrons than gain 6 electrons.</p></feedback></response><response match="gain_cation" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab92d41d5f2684f82b51323a0c70099dc">That is not quite right. Magnesium has a low electronegativity thsuit will be easier for it to loose its 2 electrons than gain 6 electrons. Furthermore, a gain of electrons creates an excess of negative charges. A negatively charged ion is referred to as an anion not a cation.</p></feedback></response><response match="lost_anion" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac217bc71d00245a09178dfdefed8171c">That is not quite right. Loss of electrons creates an excess of positive charges. A positively charged ion is referred to a cation, not an anion.</p></feedback></response><response match="lost_cation" score="1"><feedback><p id="af871041b1a004dd183b5f08100263cae">Good Job! Magnesium, with its low electronegativity will tend to loose its 2 outer electrons, thus leaving an excess of protons. Positively charged ions are referred to as cations.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="af1084673a1724833b20f31fbe507892a">Magnesium has 12 electrons, so arrange them in orbital around nucleus with inner most orbital having maximum of 2, whereas subsequent orbitals hold maximum of 8 electrons</p></hint><hint><p id="ac9aa5f382c9d4ec1b43a8ec5c4f21c5b">How many electrons are in the outer most orbital, is easie to loose or gain electrons to obey the octet rule?</p></hint><hint><p id="ae5f213835fbc40be8b8d2caf83d3b6fd">Magnesium has a low electronegativity thus it will be easier for it to lose electrons</p></hint><hint><p id="ba24bf56ba544812b74436d9a9fdbb15">Loss of electrons leads to an excess of positive charges. A positively charged ion called a <em style="italic">cation</em>, where a negatively charged ion is referred to as an <em style="italic">anion.</em></p></hint></part></question><question id="chemLev_LBD01_chlorine"><body><p id="afaf47fea520c4e98ae26cb04f13232d4">Given the atom Chlorine, in solution, how many electrons will it loose or gain? Would that make it a cation or an anion?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="fad7ba01280747f0aab3bb4f68a6ea17" labels="false"><choice value="gain_anion">1 electron gained, anion</choice><choice value="gain_cation">1 electron gained, cation</choice><choice value="lost_anion">7 electrons lost, anion</choice><choice value="lost_cation">7 electrons lost, cation</choice></multiple_choice><part id="f1554636b31d4d178f49a0b6a1c14138"><response match="gain_cation" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac7e553be6b2c40c281e8efc71e4dce03">That is not quite right. Gain of electrons leads to an excess of negative charges. A negatively charged ion is reffered to as an anion, not a cation.</p></feedback></response><response match="gain_anion" score="1"><feedback><p id="ad69433de877745c584d75ed786d9cadd">Good job! Chlorine, with its high electronegativity will tend gain 1 electron, thus filling its outer orbital. This creates an excess of negative charges. A negatively charged ion is referred to as an anion.</p></feedback></response><response match="lost_cation" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa381bcb29b4245ff944a382677e7936b">That is not quite right. Chlorine, having a high electronegativity will tend to gain electrons rather than loose them. Furthermore, gain of electrons leads to an excess of negative charges, forming a negatively charged ion called an anion, not an cation.</p></feedback></response><response match="lost_anion" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa3bf1989cb1c43669549d17ebb01f7cc">That is not quite right. Chlorine, having a high electronegativity will tend to gain electrons rather than loose them.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="abea8eb70ec074278b71bc1c5939efd4a">The atomic number of chlorine is 17. Since as found naturally it&apos;s neutral, it can be implied that it also has 17 electrons.</p></hint><hint><p id="abfcc19e6a8b54e448da4f78eb0ea1c69">How many electrons are in the outer most orbital? Is easier to loose or gain electrons to obey the octet rule?</p></hint><hint><p id="ad604bc5545d248e685fbdd587d08d18c">Chlorine has a high electronegativity thus it will be easier for it to gain than loose electrons.</p></hint><hint><p id="aef03dd0812f748898ef08a9613212b2d">Loss of electrons leads to an excess of positive charges. A positively charged ion is called a cation, wherea a negatively charged on is referred to as an anion.</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
