<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_0.dtd">
<assessment id="chemLev_LBD01_b">
    
  <title>Applying Electronegativity Part 2</title>
    
    <question id="chemLevel_LBD01_b_oxygen">
        <body>Given the atom Oxygen, in solution, how many electrons will it loose or gain? Would that make it a cation or an anion?</body>
        <multiple_choice>
          <choice value="gain_anion">2 electrons gained, anion</choice>
            <choice value="gain_cation">2 electrons gained, cation</choice>
            <choice value="lost_anion">6 electrons lost, anion</choice>
            <choice value="lost_cation">6 electrons lost, cation</choice>
        </multiple_choice>
        
        <part>
            <response match="gain_anion" score="1">
                <feedback>Good Job! Oxygen, with its high electronegativity will tend gain 2 electron, thus filling its outer orbital. This creates an excess of negative charges. A negatively charged ion is referred to as an anion.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="gain_cation" score="0">
                <feedback>That is not quite right. Gain of electrons leads to an excess of negative charges. A negatively charged ion is reffered to as an anion, not a cation.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="lost_anion" score="0">
                <feedback>That is not quite right. Oxygen, having a high electronegativity will tend to gain electrons rather than loose them.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="lost_cation" score="0">
                <feedback>That is not quite right. Oxygen, having a high electronegativity will tend to gain electrons rather than loose them. Furthermore, gain of electrons leads to an excess of negative charges, forming a negatively charged ion called an anion, not a cation.</feedback>
            </response>
       
            <hint>The atomic number of an atom indicates the number of protons. Since as found naturally it's neutral, it can be implied that it also has 8 electrons.</hint>
            <hint>How many electrons are in the outer most orbital? Is easier to loose or gain electrons to obey the octet rule?</hint>
            <hint>Oxygen has a high electronegativity. Will it be easier for it to gain than loose electrons.</hint>
            <hint>Loss of electrons leads to an excess of positive charges. A positively charged ion is called a cation, where a negatively charged on is referred to as an anion.</hint>            
        </part>
    </question>
    
    <question id="chemLevel_LBD01_b_aluminum">
        <body>Given the atom Aluminum, in solution, how many electrons will it loose or gain? Would that make it a cation or an anion?</body>
        <multiple_choice>
            <choice value="gain_anion">5 electrons gained, anion</choice>
            <choice value="gain_cation">5 electrons gained, cation</choice>
            <choice value="lost_anion">3 electrons lost, anion</choice>
            <choice value="lost_cation">3 electrons lost, cation</choice>
        </multiple_choice>      

        <part>
            <response match="gain_anion" score="0">
                <feedback>That is not quite right. Aluminum has a low electronegativity thus it will be easier for it to loose its 3 electrons than gain 5 electrons.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="gain_cation" score="0">
                <feedback>That is not quite right. Aluminum has a low electronegativity thus will easily loose its 3 electrons than gain 5 electrons. Furthermore, a gain of electrons creates an excess of negative charges. A negatively charged ion is referred to as an anion not a cation.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="lost_anion" score="0">
                <feedback>That is not quite right. Loss of electrons creates an excess of positive charges. A positively charged ion is referred to as a cation, not an anion.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="lost_cation" score="1">
                <feedback>Good Job! Aluminum with its low electronegativity will tend to loose electrons. Loss of the electrons leads to an excess of protons, thus positive charges. A positively charged ion is referred to a cation. </feedback>
            </response>
            
            <hint>The atomic number indicated the number of protons. As found in nature, aluminum is neutral.</hint>
            <hint>The inner most orbotal can hold a maxumum of 2 electrons whereas subsequent orbitals can hold a naxumum of 8 electrons.</hint>
            <hint>Aluminum has a low has electronegativity. It it easier for it to loose of gain electrons?</hint>
            <hint>Loss of electrons leads to an excess of positive charges. A positively charged ion called a cation, whereas a negatively charged ion is referred to as an anion. </hint>
            
            
            
        </part>
    </question>
    
    
    </assessment>