<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<!--Created by OLI Author v3.0-->
<assessment id="metacog_submit_compare">
    <title>Metacognative Submit and Compare Follow-up</title>
    <page id="page_0">
        <question id="metacog_submit_compare_0">
            <!--LO:meta-->
            <body>Now compare your answer to our suggested answer. Apply the metacognitive cycle by
                evaluating the current status of your learning process and progress. Select one of
                the following:</body>
            <multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="false">
                <choice value="A"><em>My answer is incorrect or I didn’t know how to answer the question
                    and just hit submit to see the answer.</em> After reading the sample answer, I
                    realize I need to learn more about the basic facts before I can apply and
                    synthesize to explain this concept in my own words.</choice>
                <choice value="B"><em>My answer is incomplete and/or has some inaccurate parts.</em> After
                    reading the sample answer, I realize I need to review this content and use other
                    strategies to understand the concepts before I can apply and synthesize to
                    explain it in my own words.</choice>
                <choice value="C"><em>My answer had some correct information.</em> After reading the sample
                    answer, I feel that I still need to use graphic organizational tools to practice
                    applying and synthesizing the concepts to better explain them in my own words to
                    the teacher or a fellow anatomy &amp; physiology student.</choice>
                <choice value="D"><em>My answer is correct and comparable to the sample answer.</em>I feel
                    confident I can apply and synthesize the information I have learned to explain
                    this concept in my own words to the teacher or a fellow anatomy &amp; physiology
                    student.</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part id="qpart_0">
                <response match="A" score="1">
                    <feedback>Great!  Now that you have evaluated your performance, how might your revise your study happens as a result?</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="1">
                    <feedback>Great!  Now that you have evaluated your performance, how might your revise your study happens as a result?</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="1">
                    <feedback>Great!  Now that you have evaluated your performance, how might your revise your study happens as a result?</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="1">
                    <feedback>Great job!  </feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
