<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_samp_pop_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_describe_samp_pop">
        <!-- LO: describe_samp_pop -->
        <body>
            <p>The faculty senate at a large university wanted to know what proportion of the
                students thought foreign language classes should be required for everyone. The
                statistics department offered to cooperate in conducting a survey, and a simple
                random sample of 500 students was selected from all the students enrolled in
                statistics classes. A survey form was sent by email to these 500 students. </p>
            <p>In this case, which of the following is the population of interest?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">All students at the university</choice>
            <choice value="B">All students enrolled in a statistics class</choice>
            <choice value="C">The 500 students who got the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="D">The students who responded to the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="E">All students who think that foreign language classes should be
                required for everyone</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The faculty senate wanted to know what proportion <em style="italic">of the students</em> supported the proposal. The senate put
                    no restriction on their group of interest, so they want to gauge the opinion of
                    all students at the university.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that only statistics students were <em style="italic">surveyed</em>, that wasn’t the group that the faculty senate
                    wanted information about.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the sample of students that were sent the survey. A <em style="italic">sample</em> isn’t the same thing as a <em style="italic">population</em>. The population is the large group whose opinion the
                    faculty senate wanted to gauge.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the sample of students that completed the survey. A <em style="italic">sample</em> isn’t the same thing as a <em style="italic">population</em>. The population is the large group whose opinion the
                    faculty senate wanted to gauge.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. If the senate only got replies from the students who <em style="italic">support</em> the proposal, there wouldn’t be any way to gauge
                    what fraction of the student body that might be. In that case, every student in
                    the study would be guaranteed to say "yes." But remember that, in any study, the
                    response has to be able to <em style="italic">vary</em> from person to
                    person.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_describe_samp_pop">
        <!-- LO: describe_samp_pop -->
        <body>
            <p>The faculty senate at a large university wanted to know what proportion of the
                students thought foreign language classes should be required for everyone. The
                statistics department offered to cooperate in conducting a survey, and a simple
                random sample of 500 students was selected from all the students enrolled in
                statistics classes. A survey form was sent by email to these 500 students. </p>
            <p>Which of the following is the appropriate sampling frame in this scenario?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">All students at the university</choice>
            <choice value="B">All students enrolled in a statistics class</choice>
            <choice value="C">The 500 students who got the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="D">The students who responded to the email survey</choice>
            <choice value="E">All students who think that foreign language classes should be
                required for everyone</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that the faculty senate <em style="italic">wants</em> information about all students at the university, notice that
                    the study doesn’t select from among that group. The <em style="italic">sampling
                        frame</em> is the list of potential individuals from which the sample gets
                    selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of
                    potential individuals from which the sample gets selected. In this case, that
                    list is restricted to students enrolled in a statistics class. This is an
                    example in which the sampling frame does not match the population that the
                    faculty senate wants information about.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> isn’t the same thing
                    as the <em style="italic">sample</em>. The <em style="italic">sampling
                        frame</em> is the list of potential individuals from which the sample gets
                    selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of
                    potential individuals from which the sample gets selected. In this case, the
                    sampling frame would be the list of students from which the 500 were selected to
                    receive the survey.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of
                    potential individuals from which the sample gets selected. Notice that the
                    survey could be sent to some students who don’t support the proposal.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_describe_samp_pop">
        <!-- LO: describe_samp_pop -->
        <body>
            <p>The city council hired three college interns to measure public support for a large
                parks and recreation initiative in their city. The interns mailed surveys to 500
                randomly selected participants in the current public recreation program. They
                received 150 responses.</p>
            <p>In this case, which of the following is the population of interest?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">All members of the community</choice>
            <choice value="B">All participants in the city’s recreation program</choice>
            <choice value="C">The 500 people who got the survey</choice>
            <choice value="D">The 150 people who responded</choice>
            <choice value="E">The participants who support the initiative</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The council wanted to measure “public support” for the project.
                    They put no restriction on their group of interest, so they want to gauge the
                    opinion of all members of the community.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that only current participants in the
                    recreation program were <em style="italic">surveyed</em>, that wasn’t the group
                    about which the council wanted information.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the sample of community members who were sent the
                    survey. A <em style="italic">sample</em> isn’t the same thing as a <em style="italic">population</em>. The population is the large group whose
                    opinion the city council wanted to gauge.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the sample of voters who completed the survey. A <em style="italic">sample</em> isn’t the same thing as a <em style="italic">population</em>. The population is the large group whose opinion the city
                    council wanted to gauge.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. If the city council only got replies from the voters who <em style="italic">support</em> the initiative, there wouldn’t be any way to
                    gauge what fraction of the community that might be. In that case, every voter in
                    the study would be guaranteed to say yes. But remember that, in any study, the
                    response has to be able to <em style="italic">vary</em> from person to
                    person.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_describe_samp_pop">
        <!-- LO: describe_samp_pop -->
        <body>
            <p>The city council hired three college interns to measure public support for a large
                parks and recreation initiative in their city. The interns mailed surveys to 500
                randomly selected participants in the current public recreation program. They
                received 150 responses.</p>
            <p>Which of the following is the appropriate sampling frame in this scenario?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">All members of the community</choice>
            <choice value="B">All participants in the city’s recreation program</choice>
            <choice value="C">The 500 people who got the survey</choice>
            <choice value="D">The 150 people that responded</choice>
            <choice value="E">The participants that support the initiative</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although it’s true that the city council <em style="italic">wants</em> information about all members of the community, notice that the
                    study doesn’t select from among that group. The <em style="italic">sampling
                        frame</em> is the list of potential individuals from which the sample gets
                    selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of
                    potential individuals from which the sample gets selected. In this case, that
                    list is participants in the city’s recreation program. This is an example in
                    which the sampling frame does not match the population about which the city
                    council wants information.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> isn’t the same thing
                    as the <em style="italic">sample</em>. The <em style="italic">sampling
                        frame</em> is the list of potential individuals from which the sample gets
                    selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> isn’t the same thing
                    as the <em style="italic">individual who responded</em>. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of potential individuals from which the
                    sample gets selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The <em style="italic">sampling frame</em> is the list of
                    potential individuals from which the sample gets selected. Notice that the
                    survey could be sent to some people who don’t support the proposal.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
