<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="id_samp_techniq_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_id_samp_techniq">
        <!-- LO: id_samp_techniq -->
        <body>
            <p>In order to obtain a sample of undergraduate students in the United States, a simple
                random sample of 10 states is selected. From each of the selected states, 10
                colleges or universities are chosen at random. Finally, from each of these 100
                colleges or universities, a simple random sample of 20 undergraduate students is
                selected. Thus, the final sample consists of 2,000 undergraduates. </p>
            <p>This is an example of which type of sampling strategy?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Simple random sampling</choice>
            <choice value="B">Stratified sampling</choice>
            <choice value="C">Multistage sampling</choice>
            <choice value="D">Convenience sampling</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that a <em style="italic">simple</em> random sample of
                    undergraduates would have selected directly from the pool of undergraduates,
                    without first selecting states or colleges.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that <em style="italic">stratified</em> sampling of
                    undergraduates would have initially viewed the nation’s undergrads as being
                    separated into strata according to some feature. It wouldn’t have involved any
                    initial selection of states or universities.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is an example of multistage sampling, because first a sample
                    of a few states was selected, and then in each of those states another sample of
                    a few universities was selected, and finally in each of those universities a
                    sample of a few students was selected. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">convenience</em> sample of undergrads
                    would have selected directly from undergrads (without first selecting states or
                    colleges), and it would have been only from students conveniently nearby (so it
                    would not have involved random selection from the whole nation).</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_id_samp_techniq">
        <!-- LO: id_samp_techniq -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following is an example of stratified sampling?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">A sample of 351 people called a radio show to express their opinions
                about the verdict in a murder trial.</choice>
            <choice value="B">In order to assess students' satisfaction with the food establishment
                on campus, the first 50 students who came out of the student center were
                interviewed.</choice>
            <choice value="C">A poll asked a random sample of 1,112 adults whether they believe that
                the use of marijuana for medical reasons should be legalized.</choice>
            <choice value="D">A health educator wanted to study the sleeping habits of the
                undergraduate students in her university. For her study, the researcher chose a
                simple random sample of size 150 from each of the classes (150 freshmen, 150
                sophomores, 150 juniors, and 150 seniors) for a total of 600 sampled
                students.</choice>
            <choice value="E">The human resources department of a large bank wanted to assess the
                job satisfaction of the bank's workers. The department chose four of the bank's
                branches at random and used all of the workers in those four branches as the
                subjects for the study.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a simple <em style="italic">voluntary</em> sample. There is no indication that the population of
                    listeners was viewed as divided into separate strata according to some
                    feature.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a simple <em style="italic">convenience</em> sample. There is no indication that the population of
                    students was viewed as divided into separate strata according to some
                    feature.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a <em style="italic">simple random</em>
                    sample. There is no indication that the population of adults was viewed as
                    divided into separate strata according to some feature, and no attempt was made
                    to intentionally select a few people from separate strata of adults.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The researcher viewed the students as being divided into four
                    separate strata (freshmen, sophomores, juniors, and seniors), and a few
                    students from each stratum were selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a <em style="italic">cluster</em>
                    sample. In stratified sampling, the population is viewed as divided into
                    separate strata according to some feature, and then a few <em style="italic">people</em> (not strata) are selected from each stratum (not from only some
                    of the strata).</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_id_samp_techniq">
        <!-- LO: id_samp_techniq -->
        <body>
            <p>In order to get people’s opinions about a particular Supreme Court decision a
                reporter interviewed 30 people who have gathered outside the courthouse waiting for
                the announcement. The reporter makes sure to question people who have signs
                expressing a variety of positions on the issue.</p>
            <p>This is an example of which type of sampling strategy?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Simple random sampling</choice>
            <choice value="B">Stratified sampling</choice>
            <choice value="C">Multistage sampling</choice>
            <choice value="D">Convenience sampling</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Simple random sampling involves some formal method of selecting
                    individuals from a population such that each individual has an equal chance of
                    being selected. In this case the sample consists of people who happen to be at
                    the right place at the right time for the person doing the sampling.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Stratified sampling first divides the general population
                    according to characteristics (such as gender or age) that are distinct from the
                    question being addressed and then randomly select individuals from each group.
                    In this case the sample consists of people who happen to be at the right place
                    at the right time for the person doing the sampling.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Multistage sampling works down from a very large group of
                    people by stratifying them into various groups and then doing random sampling at
                    the end. In this case the sample consists of people who happen to be at the
                    right place at the right time for the person doing the sampling.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Convenience samples contain people who happen to be at the right
                    place at the right time for the convenience of the person doing the
                    sampling.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_id_samp_techniq">
        <!-- LO: id_samp_techniq -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following is an example of stratified sampling?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">In order to assess public attitudes on good nutrition the the first 40
                people to leave a large grocery store were interviewed.</choice>
            <choice value="B">A sample of 37 people who came to speak before the city council on the
                proposed water conservation plan were surveyed.</choice>
            <choice value="C">Proponents of a local ballot measure conduct a survey of the city by
                randomly selecting 100 potential voters from each of its 18 zip codes.</choice>
            <choice value="D">The human resources department of a large retail chain wanted to
                assess the job satisfaction of the retail workers. The department chose 25 of the
                company's stores at random, and used all of the workers in those 25 branches as the
                subjects for the study.</choice>
            <choice value="E">A poll asked a random sample of 1,327 adults whether they supported
                stronger gun control measures.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a simple <em style="italic">convenience</em> sample. There is no indication that the population as a
                    whole was viewed as divided into separate strata according to some
                    feature.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a simple <em style="italic">voluntary</em> sample. There is no indication that the population of
                    listeners was viewed as divided into separate strata according to some
                    feature.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The proponents viewed the voters as being divided into 18
                    separate strata, and a few voters from each stratum were selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a <em style="italic">cluster
                    sample</em>. In stratified sampling, the population is viewed as divided into
                    separate strata according to some feature, and then a few <em style="italic">people</em> (not strata) are selected from <em style="italic">each</em>
                    stratum (not from only some of the strata).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This scenario would be a <em style="italic">simple random</em>
                    sample. There is no indication that the population of adults was viewed as
                    divided into separate strata according to some feature, and no attempt was made
                    to intentionally select a few people from separate strata of adults.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
