<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="id_samp_techniq_critiq_validity_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_id_samp_techniq_critiq_validity">
        <!-- LO: id_samp_techniq_critiq_validity -->
        <body>
            <p><em style="italic">Ross Times</em>, the student newspaper of Ross College, printed a
                "What do you think?" column feature asking: "Do you think that the college is doing
                enough to provide student parking?" Anyone could mail in a response or use the
                paper's Web site to respond. In all, 126 answers were received.</p>
            <p>This is an example of what type of sample?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">A voluntary response sample</choice>
            <choice value="B">A multistage sample</choice>
            <choice value="C">A simple random sample</choice>
            <choice value="D">A convenience sample</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The response was voluntary, since the only responses that were
                    recorded were from students who <em style="italic">decided on their own</em> to
                    voice an opinion. This means the survey result could be <em style="italic">biased</em>, because it only represents the opinions of those students who,
                    for whatever reason, bothered to write a response, rather than fairly reflecting
                    the opinion of the whole college.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">multistage</em> sample would be when there
                    was more than one level of selection. In this story, there was only a single
                    level of selection, at the level of individual students (who decided to voice an
                    opinion), rather than, for instance, first selecting certain classrooms-full or
                    first selecting certain types of students, such as athletes, or
                    freshmen.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Notice that the students who voiced an opinion were not
                    selected by the newspaper using any randomized method.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although the survey method was probably relatively convenient
                    for the newspaper, it wasn't a <em style="italic">convenience sample</em>,
                    because the students weren't all selected from any certain location that would
                    have happened to suit the needs of the researcher.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_id_samp_techniq_critiq_validity">
        <!-- LO: id_samp_techniq_critiq_validity -->
        <body>
            <p>Talkshow host “Bull” Loney asked listeners of his to call in to give their opinion on
                a topic that he had just spent most of his program ranting about. The station got
                384 calls.</p>
            <p>This is an example of what type of sample?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">A voluntary response sample</choice>
            <choice value="B">A multistage sample</choice>
            <choice value="C">A simple random sample</choice>
            <choice value="D">A convenience sample</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is a case in which listeners to the show who cared enough
                    about the issue to make the effort to call in were selected.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A multistage sample breaks down the population into
                    successively smaller groups finishing up with a cluster sample or simple random
                    sample. This sample was selected based on listeners to the show who cared
                    enough about the issue to make the effort to call in.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A simple random sample is one in which every member of a group
                    has an equal chance of being selected. This sample was selected based on
                    listeners to the show who cared enough about the issue to make the effort to
                    call in.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A convenience sample is one in which individuals are in the
                    right place at the right time for the convenience of the person conducting the
                    survey. This sample was selected based on listeners to the show who cared
                    enough about the issue to make the effort to call in.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
