<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_homeostasis_integration_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Homeostasis Integration of Systems</title><page id="c6c4bbd5ed4b41929826e46112c633b9"><multiple_choice id="q2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa04f19a2d759414d9060c8512fefed06">There are multiple sensors in different organ systems for detecting changes in blood pressure. This suggests that:</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="fb3fe68546f74b34b894de0535694b08" labels="false"><choice value="A">(A) There are multiple feedback loops for regulating blood pressure.</choice><choice value="B">(B) A control center integrates information from multiple sensors.</choice><choice value="C">(C) The body changes which sensor it uses depending on the conditions the body is experiencing.</choice><choice value="D">Both A and B could be correct.</choice></input><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae927c4d5338347a180973d192ee5e43e">Incorrect. While there may be different feedback loops, they would not each be totally independent, so this is not the best answer.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe7a8838d6b44af3a3b8cf7699a88d38">Incorrect. While a control center may receive input from multiple sensors, there is not just one control center for all the different organ systems involved in blood pressure homeostasis, so this is not the best answer.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad785bed0f5b54a9d8eb119c0d3fa80c6">Incorrect. All of the sensors would normally be functioning at the same time, even though they may provide input to different control centers.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac115a970911948ba85097ecf6cd21d38">Correct. Multiple sensors could mean there are multiple feedback loops involving different organ systems, and a single control center can be integrating information from multiple sensors. . In this way, different organ systems will interact to maintain blood pressure. </p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_16" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aea13d034c50a44bcac4dfbcafa001a5d">What can result from ingestion of unrestricted amounts of water?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d0afec480eb04411a7135f182f173907" labels="false"><choice value="good_health">good health; water is good for you</choice><choice value="positive_feedback">positive feedback loops</choice><choice value="nothing">nothing</choice><choice value="pos_death">possibly death</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_16_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_predict_SKILL" /><response match="good_health" score="0"><feedback><p id="abdf7b8c509f84beab3bb1262f795c93e">Incorrect. Most people don’t consume enough water. However, too much of something can be as harmful as too little of it; that is why homeostasis maintains a &quot;set point.&quot;</p></feedback></response><response match="positive_feedback" score="0"><feedback><p id="aff0c2eb4b2624cd4a384565ee58f887c">Incorrect. The body will have problems, but positive feedback loops will not occur; this is still a negative feedback process, but the effectors cannot keep up with the input.</p></feedback></response><response match="nothing" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad625e3fb0e5f4b6182682a4fae1cafba">Incorrect. Too much of something can be as harmful as too little of it; that is why homeostasis maintains a &quot;set point.&quot; Too much water causes urination initially, but if the urinary system can’t process all of the fluid fast enough, the water will dilute the blood, cause parts of the body to swell, and ultimately inhibit brain function. </p></feedback></response><response match="pos_death" score="10"><feedback><p id="adf3a457e6eae411b8d3b2b308f868935">Correct. Too much of something can be as harmful as too little of it; that is why homeostasis maintains a &quot;set point.&quot; Too much water causes urination initially, but if the urinary system can’t process all of the fluid fast enough, the water will dilute the blood, cause parts of the body to swell, and ultimately inhibit brain function. </p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_17" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ab2a74a585a094fd1abf9deb035df7661">What can happen if cell number in a tissue is not homeostatically maintained?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f8197edcb469437cb6b77e305431a176" labels="false"><choice value="tumor">tumor</choice><choice value="infection">infection</choice><choice value="nerve">nerve damage</choice><choice value="apoptosis">apoptosis (cell death)</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_17_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_predict_SKILL" /><response match="tumor" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab9228262242949a4ad32ccf04e65a79f">Correct. When cells are not able to regulate homeostasis, a tumor can form.</p></feedback></response><response match="infection" score="0"><feedback><p id="afb3f6201bebe4ed98f941ba653dcc3d0">Incorrect. An infection occurs when foreign organisms enter a tissue or cell.</p></feedback></response><response match="nerve" score="0"><feedback><p id="ace77389f685a47f6ae7ec974a8e7ffc3">Incorrect. It’s possible that too much nerve death can lead to a loss of homeostasis, but usually nerve damage occurs from a cut.</p></feedback></response><response match="apoptosis" score="0"><feedback><p id="aedbff862d9614677a1d986ae347046aa">Incorrect. Apoptosis is a programmed cell death that helps maintain homeostasis.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_18b" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac5452402a3f74c4580802b74086c4590">Calcium is critical for so many body functions. Which of the following systems is not directly involved in the homeostatic maintenance of blood calcium levels?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="dbe768c1c2bd4f769972af6ed0b7177a" labels="false"><choice value="A">skeletal system</choice><choice value="B">digestive system</choice><choice value="C">muscular system</choice><choice value="D">urinary system</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_18b_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa2590c69f8ff4c79953ac3dd37eea92d">Incorrect. The osteoclasts in bone, under the influence of parathyroid hormone, play a major role in the release of calcium from bone tissue.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abac0af87becf4e3386e517019affdaff">Incorrect. The small intestine, under the influence of Vitamin D, plays a major role in the absorption of calcium from foods.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac9933107aab04e72bdd283982c82a29c">Correct. The muscular system needs calcium for contraction, but does not play a role in the maintenance of blood calcium levels. Instead, muscles play an important role in temperature homeostasis with the integumentary and cardiovascular systems.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac5670e3cd79d448b9418a97a8c40f03f">Incorrect. The kidney, under the influence of parathyroid hormone, plays a major role in the conservation of calcium rather than excretion in urine.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_19b" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa2111242cb9740798db967d56627318c">As you exercise, many different body systems must work together to adjust and maintain conditions suitable for normal function. Which of the following would NOT be directly involved in the immediate adjustments needed during exercise?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d8f31e75a5ce4314a44f5a12466c1358" labels="false"><choice value="A">cardiovascular</choice><choice value="B">integumentary</choice><choice value="C">digestive</choice><choice value="D">respiratory</choice></input><part id="_u3_quiz_19b_p1"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab73a640670254edc94ca657dd1ef99c1">Incorrect. The heart rate will need to adjust to provide sufficient oxygen to the skeletal muscles during exercise.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aff2afa46a7d74a6d96d20e11bac45132">Incorrect. The sweat glands in the skin will need to adjust to help regulate body temperature during exercise.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="af4f4dfe812764fdc8921204ac865dcfc">– Correct. While the digestive system is the ultimate source of energy for exercise, increased activity is not needed during exercise and, in fact, blood flow may be diverted away from the digestive system to allow more oxygen and nutrients flow to the skeletal muscles.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac1fe49f4b0d94f51b8dda7dc6c459d97">Incorrect. The respiratory rate will need to adjust to provide sufficient oxygen and removal of carbon dioxide during exercise.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
