<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_fever_inline"><title>Fever Activity</title><page><question id="_u03_m01_feedback_fever"><body><p>Development of a fever is an interesting situation. Although it may appear that fever is caused by a disrupted feedback loop, it is actually a situation in which the temperature set point of the body changes and the feedback loop continues to operate normally. This causes body temperature to increase similar to the way that the temperature in your home will increase if you turn up the thermostat.</p><p>In extreme cases, a fever can be a medical emergency; but fever is an adaptive physiological response of our body to certain infectious agents. Pyrogens are molecules that cause the temperature set point to change. These pyrogens can come from microorganisms that infect you, or they can be produced by your body cells in response to an infection of some sort.</p><p>In this case, the pyrogens would be considered <input_ref input="i1" />, because the set point has been increased, you now feel cold at the “normal” body temperature. This produces the “chills” you feel when you get a fever. In response, as the temperature rises, instead of stimulating <input_ref input="i3" /> as effectors to cool off the body, the hypothalamus will start stimulating <input_ref input="i4" /> as effectors to reach the new upper temperature set point.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i1" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1a">a variable</choice><choice value="v1b">the control center</choice><choice value="v1c">information impacting the control center</choice><choice value="v1d">an effector</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i3" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">sweat glands and increased skin blood flow</choice><choice value="v3b">skeletal muscles to shiver and decrease skin blood flow</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i4" shuffle="false"><choice value="v4a">sweat glands and increased skin blood flow</choice><choice value="v4b">skeletal muscles and decreases in skin blood flow</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i9ac2f2448e1c4c06a48b3f5d907cec84"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i1" match="v1a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This feedback loop has the goal of controlling temperature, the variable of a feedback loop would not change whether or not you have a fever.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The hypothalamus is always the control center in this loop.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Control centers use the level of the variable as one piece of information, but sometimes they also use others. In this case the control center is using the pyrogen level to help determine the set point.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Pyrogens impact temperature, but not as directly as effectors would. Pyrogens work somewhere else in the loop.</feedback></response><hint>The components of a feedback loop do not change. Take another look at a feedback loop diagram in this module and pay attention to a source of multiple information input to the control center.</hint></part><part id="i2bdba3b945b244018e7270a49e8794d8"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i3" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. This would normally decrease the body temperature.</feedback></response><response input="i3" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would increase the body temperature.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what would happen if you didn’t have a fever and you were too hot.</hint></part><part id="i5f7c41527e2241e0a14699639d969c4c"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i4" match="v4a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would decrease the body temperature.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="v4b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. This would increase the body temperature.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what would happen if you were too cold.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="_u03_m01_feedback_fever_2"><body><p>Although the evidence is only indirect, fever is believed to enhance the body’s immune response. The increased temperature may actually impair the replication of infecting bacteria and viruses that are adapted to survive best at your normal body temperature. Thus fever can give your immune cells a chance to destroy the microorganisms before they can rapidly multiply and spread in the body. There is also some indirect evidence that increased body temperature slightly modifies several metabolic reactions in ways that also allow the immune system to function more efficiently.</p><p>Once the new higher set point is reached, the temperature receptors (thermoreceptors) send information to the <input_ref input="i1" />. In response, the <input_ref input="i2" /> (effectors) are stimulated to <input_ref input="i3" />. Unfortunately during some infections, pyrogen levels come in &quot;waves&quot;. This adjusts your temperature set point up and down. When pyrogen levels dip, you get the other part of the fever experience: “the sweats” and feeling flushed. As long as the pyrogen levels continue to increase and decrease you will feel like you are swinging back and forth. Once the pyrogen level is reduced because the infection is under control, the set point within the <input_ref input="i4" /> will reset back to normal. This will return your body to oscillating around the normal temperature set point.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i1" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1a">skeletal muscle</choice><choice value="v1b">sweat glands</choice><choice value="v1c">blood vessels</choice><choice value="v1d">hypothalamus</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i2" shuffle="false"><choice value="v2a">sweat glands and blood vessels</choice><choice value="v2b">skeletal muscles and blood vessels</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i3" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">secrete sweat for evaporation and dilate skin vessels for increased heat loss from blood near the surface of the skin</choice><choice value="v3b">shiver to create heat and constrict vessels to conserve heat by keeping blood away from the surface of the skin </choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i4" shuffle="false"><choice value="v4a">thermoreceptors</choice><choice value="v4b">muscles</choice><choice value="v4c">hypothalamus</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i28c5e2ed74b44648ab0b71bb9a61fbaf"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i1" match="v1a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Muscles are effectors; they do not serve as a control center.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sweat glands are effectors; they do not serve as a control center.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood vessels are effectors; they do not serve as a control center.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1d" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The hypothalamus is the control center for body temperature.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the difference between the control center and the effectors that execute the necessary changes to adjust the variable.</hint></part><part id="i7bc5ad4642904d349d49ba38328dd0fe"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i2" match="v2a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The sweat glands will secrete sweat to cool the body and skin blood vessels will dilate to cool down the body. </feedback></response><response input="i2" match="v2b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The skeletal muscles can shiver and increase body temperature.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what would happen if you didn’t have a fever and you were too hot.</hint></part><part id="d375ebceb9dd4dc8a4931ffe19bd9ceb"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i3" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. This will cool the body.</feedback></response><response input="i3" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would warm the body.</feedback></response><hint>What responses would cool off your body?</hint></part><part id="i7ca76631f62341fcaa7c1f7facaa6636"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response input="i4" match="v4a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Thermoreceptors stimulate the control center in response to a change in the variable they monitor, in this case body temperature.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="v4b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Muscles are an effector controlled by the control center.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="v4c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The hypothalamus is the control center for the regulation of body temperature.</feedback></response><hint>Receptors monitor changes in a variable, but only the control center can determine what changes need to be made for proper adjustment of the variable.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
