<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_explain_lbd"><title>_u3_explain_lbd</title><page id="page_0"><question id="_u3_explain_lbd_0"><body>Which of the following organ systems are generally considered to contribute to the regulation of blood glucose levels?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Endocrine, digestive, skeletal, nervous, cardiovascular</choice><choice value="B">Nervous, endocrine, cardiovascular, digestive, muscular</choice><choice value="C">Skeletal, cardiovascular, muscular, integumentary, endocrine</choice><choice value="D">Integumentary, muscular, cardiovascular, skeletal</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="_u3_explain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although many systems contribute to the regulation of blood glucose, the skeletal system is generally not considered to be involved.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The nervous system can drive appetite, the endocrine system releases hormones, the cardiovascular system transports the hormones, the digestive system absorbs sugars and the muscular system responds to the hormones to change their utilization of glucose.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although many systems contribute to the regulation of blood glucose, the integumentary system is generally not considered to be involved.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although many systems contribute to the regulation of blood glucose, the skeletal and integumentary systems are generally not considered to be involved.</feedback></response><hint>The systems involved the regulation of blood glucose can either be components of the negative feedback loop controlled by the endocrine system or they can be systems involved in hunger and fuel absorption and transport.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
