<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u6_factmyth_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>If you eat a lot of protein you will store it in your muscles and they will get bigger.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There is no place in the body that stores excess protein. Excess protein is converted and stored as fat. The only way to make your muscles larger is to exercise.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Eating a lot of protein will only cause your liver to convert it into fat for storage. </feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>It takes more muscles to frown than to smile</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It is commonly stated that it takes 43 muscles to frown and 17 to smile but there aren’t even that many muscles in the face! A serious frown and scowl will require more muscles than a smile but not many people walk around like that! </feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. There are 53 facial muscles and according to David H. Song, MD, FACS, plastic surgeon and assistant professor at the University of Chicago Hospital, 12 of those muscles are involved with smiling and 11 for frowning. Part of the reason for this myth is defining a frown (it is a scowl or just a frown?) However, smiles are contagious – ever see someone smile? We typically imitate it!</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>The muscle (based on weight) that can generate the most pressure in the human body is the tongue.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The tongue is the strongest and most versatile muscle in the human body but not the one that can generate the most pressure. </feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The masseter (chewing) muscle is the strongest muscle and produces the greatest pressure for its size. It is estimated that the masseter can generate 200 pounds of pressure! </feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body>The hardest working muscle in the body is the heart.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The heart, and cardiac muscle contracts 100,000 times every day!</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The heart is really the hardest working muscle, it never gets a chance to rest and pumps 1000 gallons of blood every day!</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q5"><body>Skeletal muscle is 75% water.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>Fact</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Myth</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q5_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_factmyth_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Water is a critical component of many tissues in the human body, skeletal muscle is one of them. Dehydration can cause muscle fatigue and cramps.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Water is extremely important for normal functioning of the human body. Skeletal muscle is just one of several tissues that contain a lot of water.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
