<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u6_components"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>All muscle tissue is formed from muscle fibers and is striated.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A"><p>True</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>False</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While all muscle tissue (smooth, cardiac, and skeletal) is composed of muscle fibers (muscle cells) only skeletal and cardiac muscle cells have a striated appearance.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. All muscle tissue (smooth, cardiac, and skeletal) is composed of muscle fibers (muscle cells), but smooth muscle is not striated; skeletal and cardiac are striated.</feedback></response><hint>The name of the muscle tissue gives important information regarding its appearance</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which ion is necessary for muscle contraction?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A"><p>acetylcholine</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>potassium</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>calcium</p></choice><choice value="D"><p>myosin</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Acetylcholine is a neurotransmitter, not an ion</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While potassium is important in maintaining the voltage in cells it is not the ion that triggers muscle contraction.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Calcium is vital for muscle contraction, it is responsible for allowing the muscle to shorten.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Myosin is a muscle protein not an ion.</feedback></response><hint>This ion is critical for force generation in muscle. </hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Of the following choices, which represents the smallest level of organization in muscle tissue?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A"><p>aponeurosis</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>muscle fiber</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>actin and myosin</p></choice><choice value="D"><p>biceps brachii muscle</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="_u6_components_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An aponeurosis is a broad tendon which helps to hold muscles together.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A muscle fiber is a muscle cell but muscle cells are made up of even smaller structures.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Actin and myosin are the proteins that form muscle cells, in this unit you will further investigate the microscopic anatomy of muscle.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is a muscle which is formed from muscle fibers and even smaller muscle proteins.</feedback></response><hint>think about which of the above is the smallest in size</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
