<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u4_m01_likely_outcomes1">
<head>
<title>Equally Likely Outcomes (1 of 2)</title>
    <objref idref="find_probability_for_equally_likely_outcomes"/>
</head>
<body>
   
<p>In the Introduction to Probability (Module 7), we learned how the relative frequency approach can
            be used to estimate the probability of an event. While sometimes this is the only method
            that can be used to estimate probability (such as when figuring out the probabilities of
            the occurrence of different blood types among the population), this method requires a
            lot of time and effort, especially since in order to get reliable estimates we need to
            repeat the random experiment many times. We are now moving on to a different method,
            which can be applied in cases in which the random experiment produces outcomes that are
            all equally likely. We'll start with a simple example to introduce the idea of the
            method, and then move on to more interesting examples.</p>
<example><title>Rolling a Fair Die</title>

<p>When an ordinary fair die is rolled once, what is the probability that the number rolled is even?  We'll denote this event by E (for even), so we are interested in finding P(E). Let's analyze this problem:</p>
<p>* The random experiment is rolling a fair die once.</p>
<p>* The sample space of all possible outcomes in this case this is S = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6}. </p>
<p>* Since the die is fair, this means that all 6 possible outcomes are <em>equally likely</em>
                (each having a probability of 1/6 of occurring)</p>
<p>* We are interested in a particular type of outcome, which is represented by event
                E&#8212;getting an even number.</p>
<p>Since 3 out of the 6 equally likely outcomes make up the event E (the outcomes {2, 4, 6}),</p>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/image006.gif" alt="The 6 possible outcomes of rolling a die.
These are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6. Of these, 2, 4, 6 are in our event E."/>
<p>the probability of event E is simply P(E) = 3/6.</p>
</example>
<section>
<title>Let's Generalize</title>
<body>
<p>In the special situation where all the outcomes in S are equally likely, we can find the probability of any event A by dividing the number of outcomes in A by the number of outcomes in S:</p>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/image007.gif" alt="P(A) = (number of outcomes in A)/(number of outcomes in S)"/>
</body>
</section>
<!--<activity idref="_u4_m1_lbd3" purpose="learnbydoing"/>-->
    <p>The purpose of the next activity is to give you guided practice on how to find the
            probability of an event in situations in which all the possible outcomes are equally
            likely.</p>
<section purpose="learnbydoing">
    <title>Learn By Doing</title>
    <body>
        <p>A couple is planning to have 3 children. Assuming that having a boy and having a girl are equally likely, and that the gender of one child has no influence on (or, is independent of) the gender of another, what is the probability that the couple will have exactly 2 girls?</p>
        <p>The "random experiment" in this case is having 3 children, as odd as that may sound in
                    this context. The next and most important step is to determine what all of the
                    possible outcomes are, and list them (i.e., list the sample space S). In this
                    case, each outcome represents a possible combination of genders of 3 children
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101108T093608-0500" comment="Is it OK for me to spell this out, or do you want students to know this on their own?"?>(note
                    that examples with the same number of boys and girls but a different birth order
                    must be listed separately)<?oxy_comment_end?>.</p>
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m1_outcomes1_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m1_outcomes1_tutor2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m1_outcomes1_tutor3" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        
    </body>
</section>
    
 </body>
</workbook_page>
