<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_unit_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Homeostasis Unit</title><page id="d81736318022459287dfe5182aa5028d"><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_01" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="adb1f5cee663b42bd99ad586a152ef962">What phrase best describes homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f2a86236f58f47909bec67c6d28515e3" labels="false"><choice value="equil">equilibrium</choice><choice value="maintain">maintaining a relatively stable environment</choice><choice value="feedback">feedback loops</choice><choice value="disrupt">disruption of processes</choice></input><part id="f7d270da577c4422b87a0651834c0c6e"><response match="equil" score="0"><feedback><p id="abbe5c8d754e64b7794452e552218e59b">Incorrect. Equilibrium is a term that means that everything is equal. In fact, things in the body are constantly changing, but generally within appropriate limits. </p></feedback></response><response match="maintain" score="10"><feedback><p id="af71a1ce7d8b6466698a4908ea116fe8e">Correct. Relatively stable indicates that most of the time, values of the variables are near the set point, and if they vary, they don’t do so enough to cause dysfunction.</p></feedback></response><response match="feedback" score="0"><feedback><p id="af94edf1cfe994428878919b86d9ac482">Although homeostasis is most commonly carried out by the many feedback loops, homeostasis is more about the general maintenance of stable conditions rather than the specifics of how that maintenance occurs.</p></feedback></response><response match="disrupt" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae920f37024484e45b7c2417e2c99c83a">Incorrect. Homeostasis maintains processes of the body.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_02" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae315a040e91644979b38b6bb63f6421d">At what levels is homeostasis maintained?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="b0c9ba8d5a634f21a9e3f51dd1ccc782" labels="false"><choice value="molec_macro">molecular and macromolecular</choice><choice value="cell_tissue">cell and tissue</choice><choice value="organ_syst">organ and organ system</choice><choice value="all_above">all of these and more</choice></input><part id="e199441132a34b929fa51d51ac8bcf2b"><response match="molec_macro" score="0"><feedback><p id="ead1ba79a1374a00be8625851655c273">This is not quite right. Homeostasis is maintained at this level. For example, ions, water and other molecules are maintained at homeostasis using the urinary system. But homeostasis is maintained at other levels, too.</p></feedback></response><response match="cell_tissue" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa66d32d311c342a4b6fef8fc368b12cc">This is not quite right. Homeostasis is maintained at this level. For example, if cell number is not maintained, then tumors can form. But homeostasis is maintained at other levels, too.</p></feedback></response><response match="organ_syst" score="0"><feedback><p id="bddf707b85da46e7aff54bc6c3356e3d">This is not quite right. Homeostasis is maintained at this level. For example, after ingesting toxins, the liver can grow to compensate for the additional workload. But homeostasis is maintained at other levels, too.</p></feedback></response><response match="all_above" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae65ee2912bb5400ab219b964aadd7997">Correct. With a constant influx of new material and changes in environmental conditions, the body works at every level to maintain homeostasis.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_03" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad2abd4fbaae84089bd2c503453e192ae">Which of the following would not be considered part of a homeostatic feedback loop for regulating plasma calcium concentration?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ada0d832b51d443c9d136f3840a32c0a" labels="false"><choice value="hormones">hormones regulating free calcium in the bloodstream</choice><choice value="kidneys">kidneys removing extra calcium from the blood</choice><choice value="ingest">ingesting extra calcium from food</choice><choice value="moving">moving calcium from the skeletal system into the plasma</choice></input><part id="bf67cd0dd39046daa2fd7717d4a9c42f"><response match="hormones" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab7fa9ef1866a448f80a93ad1487248ae">Incorrect. Hormones often help regulate homeostasis.</p></feedback></response><response match="kidneys" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac8b90d7cf5b24f6e9241112365eed972">Incorrect. The removal of excess calcium (usually by hormonal regulation of the kidneys) helps maintain homeostasis.</p></feedback></response><response match="ingest" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab6c15e4da5af4464b3135c61c78d5125">Correct. This may be confusing, since ingestion can increase the calcium in the body, but there is no internal process of the body that changes ingestion. Most people don’t “crave” calcium products, even if their calcium levels are low. However, regulatory molecules can increase the absorption of calcium in the digestive tract.</p></feedback></response><response match="moving" score="0"><feedback><p id="af4396b341e4e432999621e601775aa9a">Incorrect. Hormonal regulation of bone calcium is the primary mechanism for calcium homeostasis.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_04" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae872f91e13b042499f27e5728036336c">Which is a common feedback mechanism to maintain homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="d80786d8ad4e44bd90b673a956ea8689" labels="false"><choice value="neg">negative feedback</choice><choice value="pos">positive feedback</choice><choice value="both">both are used equally</choice><choice value="neither">neither is used</choice></input><part id="cc1ba9cdaec24dc0ad0dcf10984caf56"><response match="neg" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa80811ea7b04484aa5ca3270101136f7">Correct. Negative feedback regulates most homeostasis. As one example, when we are cold, we shiver to increase our temperature. That’s negative feedback: we work to “undo” the cold by increasing heat generation.</p></feedback></response><response match="pos" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab5dfedbdb1f04d3e91107802146ce3eb">Incorrect. Positive feedback can help maintain homeostasis, but only in emergency situations. Negative feedback regulates most homeostasis. As one example, when we are cold, we shiver to increase our temperature. If this situation were regulated by positive feedback, we would be cold and then our body would regulate to make us colder. </p></feedback></response><response match="both" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa285ad93c9304b50af64200b9f5440f7">Incorrect. While both positive and negative feedback are used to maintain homeostasis, positive feedback is typically only used in emergency situations and is therefore less common.</p></feedback></response><response match="neither" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa5ffd920eca54b81bd0eb7bfe85fa187">Incorrect. Homeostasis is most often maintained with negative feedback. Occasionally, in emergency situations, positive feedback is used.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_05" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af5c3cfe6464f41489ee3643a508bedfb">What physiological processes are regulated by positive feedback?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d20f127796c04d429bad56e9a0d73db2" labels="false"><choice value="normal">normal physiological processes</choice><choice value="emergency">emergency or transitional processes</choice><choice value="pathological">only pathological (or disease) processes have positive feedback</choice><choice value="none">there are no biological examples of positive feedback</choice></input><part id="e3aafa80e47c436a82dd148fd66c5edf"><response match="normal" score="0"><feedback><p id="a6994a10e1964c5d82c9c209f8e45806">Incorrect. Normal physiological processes are usually regulated by negative feedback.</p></feedback></response><response match="emergency" score="10"><feedback><p id="af49cdb25719840dba275f71c38aca747">Correct. Normal physiological processes are usually regulated by negative feedback, but some emergency processes, such as blood clotting, are regulated by positive feedback.</p></feedback></response><response match="pathological" score="0"><feedback><p id="abc048ec77c4c4836aee98627ee2aa723">Incorrect. Many pathological processes have positive feedback, but not all positive feedback processes are pathological, for example, lactation and other aspects of birth.</p></feedback></response><response match="none" score="0"><feedback><p id="bd1752c260b14f9b9586d55bce95a768">Incorrect. There are many examples of positive feedback in biology.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_06" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aebdd871f8d194cbcb59366b401a3ce78">What would happen if positive feedback were used in the cruise control system in a car?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="c7811fa0d17f41f38c20adeba37eb246" labels="false"><choice value="speed_up">you would speed up until the engine failed or you would slow down until you stopped</choice><choice value="maintain">you would maintain a constant speed</choice><choice value="stop_go">you would stop and go</choice><choice value="none">none of these is correct</choice></input><part id="bb30d3d29b7d403999963d79d3f39291"><response match="speed_up" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab87e115314ab4511906e4ae09efa0a69">Correct. Cruise control usually works via negative feedback to keep a car moving at a constant speed. However, with positive feedback, an increase in speed would cause the cruise control to further increase speed until the engine failed. Similarly, a slight decrease in speed would cause the cruise control to slow down the car until it stopped.</p></feedback></response><response match="maintain" score="0"><feedback><p id="afe43cb635d604240bcab8ec758b527de">Incorrect. Cruise control usually works via negative feedback to keep a car moving at a constant speed. However, with positive feedback, an increase in speed would cause the cruise control to further increase speed until the engine failed. Similarly, a slight decrease in speed would cause the cruise control to slow down the car until it stopped.</p></feedback></response><response match="stop_go" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac72bc29da0034cecb6242bff8c5947d3">Incorrect. Both positive and negative feedback usually occur as a process or series of small steps, not abrupt changes.</p></feedback></response><response match="none" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae764bfed4e11452db6e9efe82f3d817c">Incorrect. Cruise control usually works via negative feedback to keep a car moving at a constant speed. However, with positive feedback, an increase in speed would cause the cruise control to further increase speed until the engine failed. Similarly, a slight decrease in speed would cause the cruise control to slowdown the car until it stopped.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page><page id="c493bde30309417d9449d174c24d432e"><section id="blood_clott"><title> </title><content><p>Consider the following positive feedback loop of platelets and clotting:</p><p>Blood clotting (or coagulation) begins with damage to the lining of blood vessels. Platelets flowing in the blood stick to the vessels to form a clot and become activated. Then platelets release serotonin, adenosine diphosphate (ADP), and thromboxane, which attract other platelets to the wound.</p></content><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_07"><body>What will ultimately occur if this cascade continues uninterrupted?</body><input><choice value="every">every platelet in the body will go to the clot or the vessel will become occluded</choice><choice value="reduce">the clot will reduce in size over time</choice><choice value="hemorrhaging">fatal hemorrhaging (bleeding to death)</choice><choice value="inactivated">platelets will be inactivated</choice></input><part><response match="every" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Positive feedback will continue to amplify the effect until &quot;failure.&quot;</feedback></response><response match="reduce"><feedback>Incorrect. That is what would happen if this were a negative feedback loop.</feedback></response><response match="hemorrhaging"><feedback>Incorrect. The opposite would happen; entire vessels would be occluded by clots.</feedback></response><response match="inactivated"><feedback>Incorrect. The opposite would happen; every platelet would be activated.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_08"><body>What is a cell type involved in the clotting process?</body><input><choice value="platelet">platelet (a minicell)</choice><choice value="vessel">vessel</choice><choice value="thromboxane">thromboxane</choice><choice value="clot">clot</choice></input><part><response match="platelet" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Platelets are called minicells.</feedback></response><response match="vessel"><feedback>Incorrect. A blood vessel is a tissue.</feedback></response><response match="thromboxane"><feedback>Incorrect. Thromboxane is a lipid secreted by platelets.</feedback></response><response match="clot"><feedback>Incorrect. A clot is an aggregate of cells and proteins. </feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_09"><body>What is a potential medical problem associated with this positive feedback cycle?</body><input><choice value="thrombus">clot (thrombus) formation inside blood vessels</choice><choice value="hemorrhaging">fatal hemorrhaging (bleeding to death)</choice><choice value="loss_platelet">loss of platelets</choice><choice value="loss_vessels">loss of vessels</choice></input><part><response match="thrombus" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Cardiovascular disease can cause a clot, or a thrombus, inside blood vessels, leading to a complete blockage or occlusion.</feedback></response><response match="hemorrhaging"><feedback>Incorrect. The opposite is true; a thrombus can lead to a complete vessel blockage or occlusion.</feedback></response><response match="loss_platelet"><feedback>Incorrect. Thrombus formation is the problem.</feedback></response><response match="loss_vessels"><feedback>Incorrect. This is possible, after complete blockage or occlusion, but thrombus formation is the problem.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_10"><body>Aspirin reduces the ability of platelets to produce thromboxane. How does this impede clot or thrombus formation?</body><input><choice value="adhesion">it prevents platelet adhesion to vessels</choice><choice value="activation">it prevents platelet activation</choice><choice value="signaling">it prevents platelet signaling to other platelets</choice><choice value="repairs">it repairs the wound</choice></input><part><response match="adhesion"><feedback>Incorrect. Platelets will still adhere, but the positive feedback cascade is inhibited.</feedback></response><response match="activation"><feedback>That is not quite right. Initial platelets will still activate and adhere, but the positive feedback cascade to other platelets is inhibited.</feedback></response><response match="signaling" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Initial platelets will activate and adhere, but the positive feedback cascade to other platelets is inhibited.</feedback></response><response match="repairs"><feedback>Incorrect. Thromboxane signals platelets. </feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice></section></page><page id="d9ffb0a6b5c3412eb3ad00fe87466491"><section id="match-parts-neg"><title> </title><content><p>To maintain the homeostasis of fluids, dehydration (decrease in blood volume or increase in solute concentration) in the blood stimulates the osmoreceptors in the hypothalamus, which signal the brain to make you feel thirsty. </p><p>Match the parts of this negative feedback loop with the correct homeostasis terminology.</p></content><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_11"><body>brain</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part><response match="variable"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="receptor"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="control" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hypothalamus in the brain is nicknamed the &quot;thermostat&quot; because one of its main functions it thermoregulation. It is an important control center for body temperature.</feedback></response><response match="effector"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_12"><body>behavior pattern of thirst</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part><response match="variable"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="receptor"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="control"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="effector" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The feeling of thirst causes us to get a drink and replace lost fluids in our blood. This is stimulated by the hypothalamus and is an effect from the dehydration.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_13"><body>fluid pressure or solute concentration</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part><response match="variable" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Fluid pressure and or solute concentration varies as blood becomes more concentrated or more dilute as a result of water loss or gain. </feedback></response><response match="receptor"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="control"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="effector"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_14"><body>osmoreceptors in the hypothalamus</body><input><choice value="variable">variable</choice><choice value="receptor">receptor</choice><choice value="control">control center</choice><choice value="effector">effector</choice></input><part><response match="variable"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="receptor" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Osmoreceptors in they hypothalamus monitor osmolarity (solute concentration or saltiness) of the blood. They are receptors for fluid balance.</feedback></response><response match="control"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="effector"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><no_response><feedback>You did not submit an answer.</feedback></no_response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_15"><body>What other organ system strongly contributes to total body fluid homeostasis? </body><input><choice value="urinary">urinary system</choice><choice value="muscular">muscular system</choice><choice value="skeletal">skeletal system</choice><choice value="respiratory">respiratory system</choice></input><part><response match="urinary" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The urinary system helps regulate total body fluid by monitoring excretion.</feedback></response><response match="muscular"><feedback>Incorrect. In some ways the movement of the muscular system can generate heat and may cause a slight loss of water, but this is indirect.</feedback></response><response match="skeletal"><feedback>Incorrect. The skeletal system is responsible for support.</feedback></response><response match="respiratory"><feedback>Incorrect. The humidified air that we exhale does cause some loss of water, but the urinary system is the primary regulator.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_16"><body>What can result from ingestion of unrestricted amounts of water?</body><input><choice value="good_health">good health; water is good for you</choice><choice value="positive_feedback">positive feedback loops</choice><choice value="nothing">nothing</choice><choice value="pos_death">possibly death</choice></input><part><response match="good_health"><feedback>Incorrect. Most people don’t consume enough water. However, too much of something can be as harmful as too little of it; that is why homeostasis maintains a &quot;set point.&quot;</feedback></response><response match="positive_feedback"><feedback>Incorrect. The body will have problems, but positive feedback loops will not occur; this is still a negative feedback process, but the effectors cannot keep up with the input.</feedback></response><response match="nothing"><feedback>Incorrect. Too much of something can be as harmful as too little of it; that is why homeostasis maintains a &quot;set point.&quot; Too much water causes urination initially, but if the urinary system can’t process all of the fluid fast enough, the water will dilute the blood, cause parts of the body to swell, and ultimately inhibit brain function. </feedback></response><response match="pos_death" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Too much of something can be as harmful as too little of it; that is why homeostasis maintains a &quot;set point.&quot; Too much water causes urination initially, but if the urinary system can’t process all of the fluid fast enough, the water will dilute the blood, cause parts of the body to swell, and ultimately inhibit brain function. </feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="_u3_quiz_17"><body>What can happen if cell number in a tissue is not homeostatically maintained?</body><input><choice value="tumor">tumor</choice><choice value="infection">infection</choice><choice value="nerve">nerve damage</choice><choice value="apoptosis">apoptosis (cell death)</choice></input><part><response match="tumor" score="10"><feedback>Correct. When cells are not able to regulate homeostasis, a tumor can form.</feedback></response><response match="infection"><feedback>Incorrect. An infection occurs when foreign organisms enter a tissue or cell.</feedback></response><response match="nerve"><feedback>Incorrect. It’s possible that too much nerve death can lead to a loss of homeostasis, but usually nerve damage occurs from a cut.</feedback></response><response match="apoptosis"><feedback>Incorrect. Apoptosis is a programmed cell death that helps maintain homeostasis.</feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></section></page><page id="de783dc950154081a24cd6c0b9569cb7"><multiple_choice id="q1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ad55736c2b3244ca2870d40c1056fc570">Heart rate commonly changes in response to challenges to the body, yet there is no direct sensor for heart rate. This would suggest that heart rate is:</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="c26836c4f59c42b09737863ae5bb218c" labels="false"><choice value="A">An input signal</choice><choice value="B">A control center</choice><choice value="C">An effector</choice><choice value="D">None of the above</choice></input><part id="a48b40ff10034bb7bb4b36e384e7c582"><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab07fa6e6e9bf4ace976fbf29d89f7543">Incorrect. </p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="af6d6241eaa2b4513abb7fa1aeb2a20be">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="af132d999660f4026adf8b9f2f0213ae1">Correct. Heart rate is a response the brain uses to control blood pressure. If heart rate increases, the blood pressure also increases. If heart rate decreases, blood pressure also decreases.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="af5843c6fa059475f962657bb98082c3b">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af7b7c7e355544603af64af790b3be19a">There are multiple sensors for measuring blood pressure. This suggests that:</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="cada5b7bdbf64232bb94a7031cc7968e" labels="false"><choice value="A">(A) There are multiple feedback loops for regulating blood pressure.</choice><choice value="B">(B) The control center integrates information from all sensors.</choice><choice value="C">(C) The body changes which sensor it uses depending on the conditions the body is experiencing.</choice><choice value="D">Both A and B could be correct.</choice></input><part id="e8dbef9e09f440cba880abe8cfcf5790"><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aef204f23efb043a6a093801f0697e280">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae352e61adb3249eda57f85cbfb97ccf5">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af7a3f818e445466e9765cc864faef485">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="abfd0540d431a4cb884b82d3ae08f75f4">Correct. Multiple sensors mean there are more than one mechanism to regulate blood pressure. Blood pressure is affected by heart rate, blood volume, and blood vessel diameter.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q5" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ab4fc16267b6049ff90e23b83910b7bd8">which of the following is a control center for the regulation of plasma calcium levels in adults?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a2b96985a5a24a4aa9e253ecb21715ea" labels="false"><choice value="A">hypothalamus</choice><choice value="B">parathyroid gland</choice><choice value="C">adrenal gland</choice><choice value="D">pituitary gland</choice></input><part id="dcf8e96687204ac98128ef70e691c378"><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="abe1170bf30c342819084a54b7cb53af7">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac50a5a054a634a6aa4f046dd491f063a">Correct. Plasma calcium levels are regulated by the endocrine system, mainly the parathyroid and thyroid endocrine organs.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac178b968925743dfb482fffb78843ed3">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aea452901b4c84cbda312673c29bf3106">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q6" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af60d0aaa30e6418e93d5895fcd163760">Which of the following analogies best describes homeostasis?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="dc066019774c495e8d183505e7904979" labels="false"><choice value="A">When you apply the brakes on a car and it slows down.</choice><choice value="B">When you turn the key in the ignition and the car starts.</choice><choice value="C">When cruise control is used to maintain the speed of the car, even on hilly terrain.</choice><choice value="D">When the car burns fuel to produce torque.</choice></input><part id="a6b57a3f0e0142d9adf7398a2228c458"><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad3c43ff38cd84d92b30f836fe542241e">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aac06699b22e84d00823ba934728ce009">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab451470368a440c0ac12208c0afda46c">Correct. Remember if your car is on cruise control it automatically speeds up or slows down to maintain the set speed. </p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aec7c8025ac9e4105bd9a3e75656eb5cf">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q7" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af38b5b5625f240eb89abc1c8c6bff2fd">The main benefit of using negative feedback instead of positive feedback to control a variable is that:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="c51f5a196a3348a3903917ebfafa4014" labels="false"><choice value="A">Negative feedback can respond more rapidly.</choice><choice value="B">Negative feedback doesn’t require the use of nerves.</choice><choice value="C">Negative feedback brings the variable back toward the set point.</choice><choice value="D">Negative feedback uses a sensor, control center and effector(s).</choice></input><part id="baffa7b230d54b1c902ab6914741a515"><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae7902fa0dcee4481b852068118c5371e">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="af00ed7c3b50c40419d41a6dbd5403452">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa43efcc3cf4a42bb93205304b8e3e137">Correct. Negative feedback brings the body back to its set point rather than moving it further from it by enhancing the change.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab9001e30f3d14aa693b7e82ac7d454cf">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q8" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ab63a798294b148a6afd4f02e28caae6e">In comparison to negative feedback loops, positive feedback loops are more likely to:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d098bb3a7aeb4bf2813ca3f681273ba9" labels="false"><choice value="A">Lead to a disease or a worsened condition.</choice><choice value="B">Respond more quickly.</choice><choice value="C">Use nerves as a mechanism of sending information.</choice><choice value="D">Be utilized to correct for large changes in a variable.</choice></input><part id="cf7ac95225714ff8916b9874bfa13894"><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa3dbda445ceb41818990c0b97775287f">Correct. Positive feedback loops which brings the body away from its set point. They are important for certain conditions but generally would cause disease and illness.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="abd9e343c9b9e421e81ed3edb3b491e80">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac78e24b435c04476bb63677b8ec38f16">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac400fed08f494b1bb61993c032109bfa">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="q9" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="accb0a57d299944b2993adc4731baa96d">An example of positive feedback is:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a94ac93421e94d31bdbf04a6cfe907d7" labels="false"><choice value="A">The control of plasma glucose.</choice><choice value="B">Maintenance of blood pressure.</choice><choice value="C">The platelet aggregation aspect of hemostasis.</choice><choice value="D">Regulation of plasma osmolarity.</choice></input><part id="e0380666763942f09f101fe3203b65a4"><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aef9b82ff37474e51a18eaf05cb0c4659">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="af3edc41dd38e405aafa28757b16ec6f2">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac38315d648094f7aabe9b5225fe79638">Correct. Positive feedback is critical in forming the platelet plug (aggregation) and blood clot which prevents excessive blood loss due to injury. Blood pressure, osmolarity and blood glucose levels are regulated by negative feedback loops.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="abdfe3bc323cc45b4b2ab7206ca58edc1">Incorrect.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
