<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u4_endUnit4_review"><head><title>Unit Review and Assessment unused</title></head><body><p id="daa26d03640b48fbaec75c0263e237a8">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit on vital functions, body systems, body planes, and directional terms. Could you demonstrate your knowledge of each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="e526350761fd46529d7dd59d633bb46d"><li><p id="aba48537523b2409384501b313652076a">List several conditions or that lead to decreased or altered function of the skeletal system.</p></li><li><p id="aec2ebc99e34841efae61d6a227eaade3">Compare and contrast the bones and the functions of the Axial and Appendicular divisions of the skeleton.</p></li><li><p id="acb0c1cfc70a447c899dfefcbf3d705fb">Identify and label the bones of the axial skeletal system.</p></li><li><p id="aec8b1a130cfb4ea0b7f280f11f792041">Identify and label the bones of the appendicular skeleton.</p></li><li><p id="ad505f64c3a8d4d13869b1df8784e6ad8">Integrate the functions of the different skeletal system components to the system functions.</p></li><li><p id="ac38fef40e1304de4aac53527d495046d">Describe bone anatomy in terms of axial and appendicular skeletons. List bones from both functional groups and compare functions based on group.</p></li><li><p id="ae97e7a0eb3d5487791f7a0587470d3e0">Compare intramembranous and endochondral (intracartilagenous) bone formation.</p></li><li><p id="ac90b0d8234434080bd7bdb74fd1d65bb">Compare and contrast Compact (cortical) bone with Spongy (cancellous) bone.</p></li><li><p id="aedbee1cdc92b493a84b7304b66c9aa99">Describe the classification of bone based on shape.</p></li><li><p id="aec3f408cd78e4066827d990c1c0a49a8">Describe the three main components of a long bone.</p></li><li><p id="af45bec8a29df4c20a54baab3be0d8ae0">Describe the functional classification of articulations, based on degree of movement allowed—synarthrotic, amphiarthrotic, and diarthrotic—and provide examples of each type.</p></li><li><p id="abf849b42b0344e0da87106c12409907f">Integrate the levels of organization in the skeletal system and their functional interconnections.</p></li><li><p id="abbacd37804f94e43adb5d60b25743b9f">Describe the functions of the inorganic extracellular matrix components in osseous (bone) tissue. </p></li><li><p id="abe8a0c4f7374477fa39a75c05bb81cf4">Describe the functions of the organic extracellular matrix components in osseous (bone) tissue.</p></li><li><p id="ab2066bc8ed3f4a819bb22da026d0cb80">Predict how loss of a molecular component could lead to altered skeletal structures. </p></li><li><p id="adae18e1958bd477d951c4ed6d81631e2">Discuss the how the components of bone relate to its mechanical function. Describe how bone resists tension and compression. </p></li><li><p id="adc60c1e42945421caa46820f2db15537">Describe the steps of bone formation, resorption and repair including the cellular contributions. </p></li><li><p id="ae2e8de5ff01b4bb38e55a6423a53f409">Describe fracture types and fracture repair mechanisms. </p></li><li><p id="aa6f3f059bdad4ab3b72e23358f93a157">List the cell types and extracellular matrix components in the skeletal system and describe their function.</p></li><li><p id="aca58dd7d529c4c2a9e0b528f827423e3">Compare the structure and function of extracellular matrix components, and describe how cells alter the extracellular matrix.</p></li><li><p id="adbd5536296de4eab81b5c2c18c2acf18">Visually identify microscopic and macroscopic bone structures.</p></li><li><p id="af30f0936e65d460cb1cfa8c3d1e90576">Describe the effects of a fracture and the most common types of fractures.</p></li><li><p id="aa6236cfd7f824268b58486f7cb5d1c65">Describe the mechanics of bone repair and aging.</p></li><li><p id="afc554e80691a4619a2bbfc9b0ec65fd2">Provide specific examples to demonstrate how the skeletal system and articulations respond to maintain homeostasis in the body.</p></li><li><p id="af3df026da38b4ee9b33565efc2dae802">Explain how the skeletal system and endocrine system interact for calcium homeostasis.</p></li><li><p id="ad42b1bde53054ba6ab30a524967b3979">Describe two disorders of the skeletal system that can result from calcium deficiency.</p></li><li><p id="aa2c55bcb12624e72900f2dc386244e0b">Predict changes in the skeletal system due to altered homeostasis. </p></li><li><p id="ae4fe890a6cc74e1081cac1a3e42368c4">Describe the cellular and extracellular matrix reorganization that occurs in response to stress (force) on bones.</p></li><li><p id="ad993975da1c7494593dc8072f2c5ad4e">Predict changes in bone structure homeostasis with altered force.</p></li><li><p id="af49115996b3548b08270a7c79eb1b668">Describe the passive and active responses that occur in cartilage when stress (force) on the tissue changes.</p></li><li><p id="afd75409181f74dfe972147a6bce71542">Describe the impact of arthritis on the skeletal system.</p></li><li><p id="aac4beaa115184fc9a610c2b5c1e057be">Discuss ways in which other body systems integrate with the skeletal system.</p></li></ul><activity idref="u4_endofunitquiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
