<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bonding_wbk"><head><title>Chemical Bonding and Molecules</title><objref idref="levels_molecules_bonds" /></head><body><section id="b54bf84891ac45a495c071b2b2895097"><title>Chemical Bonding and Molecules</title><body><p id="fef7bb5f6f6c438d811ec00ec3e32b42">Chemical bonds result when atoms of the same element (e.g., C-C) or different elements (e.g., C-O, C-N, O-H) combine into relatively strong, commonly neutral, structures. There are two major types of chemical bonds: ionic and covalent. Covalent bonds can further be divided into polar covalent and nonpolar covalent bonds. A polar covalent bond is a type of covalent bond that results in unique interaction between <term>molecules</term>. These polar bonds will interact with other polar bonds through an intermolecular attraction known as hydrogen bonding, such as that found between water molecules. Both the strong ionic and covalent chemical bonds and the weaker intermolecular forces are important in the functioning of the cell. </p></body></section><wb:inline idref="levels_molecules_bonds_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="ee8048eded53447db94baa9032894f6a"><title>Ionic Bonds</title><body><p id="b0d2b694b5f74bd1821b3b5ee58d7ad5"><term>Ions</term> form when an atom or group of atoms gains or loses one or more electrons. When an atom gains electrons, it becomes a negatively charged ion, called an <term>anion</term>. When an atom loses electrons, it becomes a positively charged ion called a <term>cation</term>. Atoms with higher electronegativities tend to gain electrons and become anions, whereas those with lower electronegativities tend to lose electrons and become cations. The electrostatic attraction between a positively charged ion and a negatively charged ion is the basis of an ionic bond. </p><p id="c2a8b3655a714a4ab749b0ce0d4ba9b6">An ionic bond generally forms between an atom of low electronegativity and an atom of high electronegativity. In many cases this will be between a metal and a nonmetal. In this situation, one or more electrons is transferred from the atom with low electronegativity, which readily “gives away” its electrons, to the atom with high electronegativity, which strongly attracts those electrons. </p><example id="f2cc88b0b12d496f8114e6316dbe37ec"><p id="f632fde28e144be4ab94961336056dfb">For example, a sodium (Na) atom will transfer its one valence electron to a chlorine (Cl) atom, resulting in the formation of a sodium cation, Na<sup>+</sup>, and a chloride anion, Cl<sup>-</sup>. Because these are oppositely charged particles, they are attracted to each other and form table salt which is stable in air. When an ionic compound, like table salt, is put into water, it dissolves. This happens because the polar water molecule pulls these oppositely charged ions apart, as will be discussed further in the next module.</p></example></body></section><section id="dea6dc6d38064af58bfe11acb25604ec"><title>Covalent Bonds</title><body><p id="d280ea0230c140b7be536d0f65ce9344">After single elemental atoms, we can think of small molecules as the next level in chemistry’s hierarchy. Molecules result from the covalent bonding of two or more elements’ atoms.</p><p id="bf4862dbc2864c7c813de9f28dc16f31">Covalent bonds are strong bonds in which electrons circling the atomic nucleus are shared. The nature of the covalent bond is determined by the number of electrons shared and the nature of the two elements sharing the bond. Two or more atoms held together by covalent bonds in a specified arrangement is called a molecule. The diagram below illustrates the covalent bond that forms between two hydrogen atoms to form a molecule of hydrogen. Nonpolar covalent bonds form between atoms of the same or similar electronegativities, most often two nonmetals. </p><p id="d5d5d52a9209409b90d12ca13ba11c9a">Each atom typically forms a specific number of covalent bonds when in a molecule with other atoms. The number of bonds that a particular atom will form is based on the atom’s valence electrons. Carbon for instance, which has four valence electrons, will form four bonds when it is in a molecule, as you can see from the diagram of methane below. Nitrogen, which has five valence electrons, will form three bonds, as seen in the ammonia molecule. The number of covalent bonds that a nonmetal will typically form is provided in <xref idref="atomic_mass" target="self" page="reference_tables">this table</xref> for the biologically important elements. </p><p id="ce7c1fb104d34aaf9c2dbaef91097707">The number of bonds between two atoms, such as single bonds, double bonds or triple bonds, helps determine the stability of the atomic interactions. Double bonds, which share two pairs of valence electrons between two atoms, are very strong. The strong bond of carbon double bonded to oxygen is found in amino acids (these will be discussed later). The number of valence electrons shared also controls the &quot;shape&quot; of the atomic interactions. Carbon double bonded to oxygen forms a &quot;flat&quot; (planar) bond that does not rotate. This limits the shapes that the larger macromolecule, with repetitive double bonds, can form. </p><image id="e47e2c25753148c6a80e2fd0e4ddb5fd" src="../../webcontent/bonds/hydrogenmolecule.png" alt="diagram of 2 hydrogen atoms forming a hydrogen molecule" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><title>Formation of Hydrogen Molecule</title><caption><p id="ad9435b8cb45f4e68b3e7a917b18c40d2">A covalent bond is formed between two hydrogen atoms.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="bf74274ce7ae4b14b32cfd7a0c722770" src="../../webcontent/bonds/covalentBond2.jpg" alt="diagram of carbon and hydrogen forming a methane molecule and nitrogen and hydrogen forming an ammonia molecule" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><title>Formation of Methane and Ammonia Molecules</title><caption><p id="af2235c7d338c40d686d63e3ed6269495"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><wb:inline idref="levels_molecules_bonds_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="levels_molecules_bonds_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="e73f5ab24cf2464e8fd933f508799bf1"><title>Polar Covalent Bonds</title><body><p id="a215714285604ba19b1244e493cdaaf4">In a molecule such as hydrogen, the electrons are shared equally because each atom has the same electronegativity. However, in some molecules one atom is more electronegative than another, in which case the electrons are not shared equally. For example, in a water molecule, one oxygen atom is covalently bonded to two hydrogen atoms. Because an oxygen atom is more electronegative than a hydrogen atom, the oxygen atom draws the electrons being shared toward itself and away from the less electronegative hydrogen. When electrons in a covalent bond are shared in an unequal manner it is termed a polar, or polar covalent, bond. This unequal sharing of electrons results in the more electronegative element, in this example the oxygen atom, having a slightly negative charge and the less electronegative element, in this example the hydrogen atom, having a slightly positive charge. Molecules with polar bonds have characteristics of both ionic and covalent bonds. Whether or not a molecule is polar has significant implications on how that molecule interacts with other molecules and ions in biological systems. </p></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
