<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="carbo_intro">
	<head>
		<title>Carbohydrates</title>
		<objref idref="levels_chem_carb"/>
		<objref idref="levels_chem_carb_function"/>
	</head>
	
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Carbohydrates</title>
			<body>
				<p>The simplest of the macromolecules are carbohydrates, also called saccharides. The name is
					descriptive of the character of this class of molecules, since they all have the
					general formula of a hydrated carbon.</p>
				<p><formula>(C(H<sub>2</sub>O))<sub>n</sub></formula></p>
				<p> This represents a 2:1 ratio of hydrogen to oxygen atoms(as in water)but in this case, they are attached to a carbon backbone. the constituent
					atoms of carbohydrates can be configured in virtually endless configurations, so
					carbohydrate molecules come in a multitude of different shapes and sizes.</p>

				<p>Monosaccharides are the most basic units of carbohydrates. These are simple sugars, including
					glucose, fructose, and others. They contain between three and seven carbon
					atoms, have a sweet taste and are used by the body for energy. </p>
				<p> Polysaccharides are long polymers of monosaccharide sugars that are covalently bonded
					together. Polysaccharides are often used to store the energy of the
					monosaccharide. These include starch (in plants) and glycogen (in humans and animals). Polysaccharides can also be
					used for structure in plants and other lower organisms. For example, cellulose
					is a large polysaccharide that is found in plant cell walls. People can't digest
					cellulose into monosaccharides, but it is important in our diets as "roughage"
					or "insoluble fiber." Carbohydrates are also critical components in the backbone of DNA, with one monosaccharide found in each nucleotide. With 3 billion DNA nucleotides per cell, that is a lot of monosaccharides in the body.</p>

				<p>Polysaccharides can be conjugated with other macromolecules. For example, complex
					carbohydrates can be linked with proteins or lipids to form glycoproteins and
					glycolipids, respectively. Very different structures can be made from a few
					monosaccharides arranged in different patterns and with different bonding. This
					flexibility in structure can therefore be used for identification of individual
					cell types, since the structure of each cell type is unique. More than half of
					the proteins in the body, which we will discuss later in this module, have
					glycosylations or carbohydrate modifications. The outside of cells are covered
					in carbohydrates from modifications of lipids that make up the membrane; we will
					cover lipids in the last chapter of this section. </p>

				<p> Carbohydrates are best know as energy storage molecules. Their primary function is as a
					source of energy. Cells readily convert carbohydrates to usable energy. You will
					recall that molecules are a collection of atoms connected by covalent bonds. In
					general, single covalent bonds can be represented as having approximately 100
					kcal/mol of energy associated with the force that holds the two atoms together.
					Table sugar, or sucrose, is the best-known carbohydrate. The most common
					carbohydrate in nature is glucose, which has the general formula
							<formula>(C(H<sub>2</sub>O))<sub>6</sub></formula>and which is a common
					source of energy for many living organisms. If a mole of glucose is completely metabolized
					("burned") for its energy in a cell, it has the following chemical reaction: </p>
				
				<p><formula>(C(H<sub>2</sub>O))<sub>6</sub> + 6 O<sub>2</sub>
					&lt;-------------&gt; 6 CO<sub>2</sub> + 6 H<sub>2</sub>O + 673 kcal
					(energy)</formula></p>
			
				<p> While the overall reaction represents a coupled oxidation/reduction process, on balance this
					process involves the breaking of five carbon-to-carbon bonds per glucose molecule, with the release of
					673 kcal/mol of energy. </p>

				<p>However, the body does not need dietary carbohydrates for energy. Proteins and fats can meet
					the body's needs, and the body can convert molecules into carbohydrates needed
					for energy and other cellular functions. But carbohydrates require minimal processing for
					use as energy. For example, a simple enzymatic reaction converts sucrose into
					blood sugar, which can be used directly as a source of cellular energy. The
					trick for the cell is to convert the 673 kcal/mol of energy to a useful form so that
					it can do work for the cell or organism. The metabolic fate of the carbohydrate
					will be discussed later in the course.</p>
				<!--  <p>
			<em> If the only bonds broken were the carbon-carbon bonds, how much energy on average
				is contained in each of those carbon-carbon bonds? </em>
		</p>-->
				<!--<question_answer>
			<question>If the only bonds broken were the carbon-carbon bonds, how much energy on average
  			is contained in each of those carbon-carbon bonds? </question>
		</question_answer>
		<feedback idref="carbo_intro_1_rhe" type="x-oli-feedback"/>-->
				<wb:inline idref="introCarbs_response" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				<wb:inline idref="introCarbs2_response" purpose="didigetthis"/>

				<p> A second function performed by carbohydrates is structure. For example, cellulose is a linear polymer of glucose
					that interacts with other cellulose polymers to form fibers that interact to
					form the basic structure of the cell wall of plants. These cellulose polymers
					are undigestable and constitute the roughage. </p>
				<image src="../../webcontent/carbo_images/celluloseMatrix.jpg"
					alt="cellulose matrix"/>
				<!--<p> Another example is the peptidoglycan that makes up the cell wall structure of a bacterium.
					"Peptido" refers to a peptide, which is a fragment of a protein or a short
					polymer of amino acids, and "glycan" refers to a polysaccharide, a polymer of
					carbohydrates. In this case, the polymer of carbohydrates includes building
					blocks other than glucose, but the end result is the formation of a matrix. In
					both cases, the resulting fibers and matrices provide scaffolding that gives
					rigidity (structure) and protection to the bacteria. Gram staining used to
					identify bacteria is based on the staining property of this peptidoglycan and
					some antibiotics work by destroying this protective layer so bacteria are killed
					by water rushing into the cell by osmosis.</p>
				<image src="../../webcontent/carbo_images/peptido-glycan1.jpg"
					alt="peptido-glycan that makes up the cell wall structure of a bacterium"/>
				<p>Carbohydrates are also the structural basis for nucleic acids, which we will cover later. </p>-->
				<p>A third function of carbohydrates is cell recognition and signaling.
					This typically occurs with carbohydrates conjugated to other molecules, such as those found in glycoproteins (carbohydrates linked to proteins) and glycolipids
					(carbohydrates linked to lipids). Because a very large number of structures can
					be made from a few monosaccharides (simple carbohydrates), a very large number
					of different structures can also be made from a few simple carbohydrates, as
					will be seen later. This large number of different structures can therefore be
					used for identification of individual cell types. </p>
				<p>Carbohydrate modifications (called glycosylations) are present on lipid membranes and
					proteins for specialized function and recognition. Unique carbohydrate
					<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120322T111420-0400" comment="is my chane correct? Or should this be &quot;conjugations&quot;?"?>formations<?oxy_comment_end?>
					allow even more specificity to a protein, beyond just the amino acid code. The
					outer membrane of the cell is dotted with carbohydrate chains, which differ
					according to cell type. These carbohydrate glycosylations provide a "signature"
					of the cell and can also act as a signal. Thus, glycosylations are important in
					immune response and general cell-to-cell communication. </p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<!--<section>
			<title>Video Lecture</title>
			<body>
				<p>Click the link below for a video lecture. The download is 81 MB and the video runs for 33
					minutes.</p>
				<activity idref="carbo_intro_msw" purpose="learnmore"/>
							
			</body>
		</section>-->
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
