<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<!--
<workbook_page id="functional_groups_wbk" created="10/18/2004" modified="$Date: 2009/07/22 18:37:49 $" version="$Revision: 1.23 $">
-->
<workbook_page id="functional_groups_wbk">
	<head>
		<title>Functional Groups</title>
		<objref idref="levels_functional_groups"/>
		<!--
		<author>
			<name first="James" last="Burnette"/>
			<email>jbfc@andrew.cmu.edu</email>
			<institution>Carnegie Mellon University</institution>
			<department>Biological Sciences</department>
		</author>
-->
		<!--<objectives>

			<!-\-   <objective id="obj5" title="Importance of Water">
Be able to describe properties of water that make it the most suitable for supporting living systems.
            </objective>
	        <objective id="obj6" title="Hydrophobic Effect">
Be able to describe the hydrophobic effect, which is the interaction of hydrophobic molecules to the exclusion of water.
	        </objective> -\->

			<objective id="obj7" title="Relevant Functional Groups">After delving into the
				functional grouping of molecules, students will be able to identify different
				functional groups, and characterize each, by category (i.e. polar, non polar,
				neutral, or charged). </objective>
		</objectives>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p><em style="highlight">FIXME: What do students need to do with this information?  Describe the concept of a functional group.  How would they do that?</em></p>
	<!--	<flash src="../../../webcontent/why_boxes/functional_groups_WhyBox.swf" height="180"
			width="540"/>-->
		<p> Biological systems use only a small part of the total chemical repertoire. This is due
			to the number of chemical reactions that can occur under physiological conditions, and
			to the small number of chemical, or <extra>
				<anchor><term>functional groups</term></anchor><p>There are a number of functional groups used to describe the particular bonds and chemical reactions of molecules.</p></extra>, compatible in biological systems.
			The physical properties of these groups define how molecules behave in biological
			systems at physiological pH and temperature. By learning the properties of these groups,
			you will be able to predict how various molecules will function, as well as which
			functional groups can be converted to others during metabolism </p>
		<p> The functional groups fall into three broad categories:
			non<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120229T105645-0500" content="-"?>polar,
			polar neutral, and polar charged. The molecules in each group all have common
			properties. </p>
		<section>
			<title>Functional Group Tutorial</title>
			<body>
				<p> The "Learn By Doing" link below will open the Functional Groups Glossary. We will use this
					glossary extensively. It contains the functional groups organized based on
					properties and is rich with information and examples about each of the groups.
					Click on "Learn By Doing"  to enter the tutorial. The functional groups are
					listed. You can click on each group to see the chemical properties, as well as
					several examples of molecules associated with that group. The three-dimensional
					structure viewer is interactive; click and drag the structure to rotate it. You
					can also use radio buttons to select groups of molecules to explore how the
					groups are related
					<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120229T114926-0500" comment="Here is a list of corrections in the functional groups interactive file (I can&apos;t find it, and in the past using track changes on complicated animated files resulted in problems, so I don&apos;t want to touch it ...):

--Nonpolar should be one word, no hyphen, in column at left, at top of center column, and in definition (title and within).

--in definition of nonpolar, remove extra colon

--in definition of &quot;neutral,&quot; remove hyphen from non-polar, and change 7 to 7.0

--in definition of &quot;charged,&quot; change 7 to 7.0, and remove phrase at bottom &quot;illustration from textbook&quot; (there is no illustration)

--in definition of &quot;hydrophilic,&quot; change bold definition text to &quot;Hydrophilic&quot; literally means &quot;water-loving.&quot; in my brownser, the word &quot;EXAMPLE&quot; and everything with it is covered up by the animation. Also, there is not time to read the line of text in the last section of the animation before it disappears.

--In hydrophobic definition: hyphenate entropy-driven. Change bold defintition text to &quot;Hydrophobic&quot; literally means &quot;water-fearing.&quot;

--In the &quot;info&quot; section: change &quot;when you&apos;ll click&quot; to &quot;when you click.&quot; remove space between &quot;selected&quot; and period.

--aspirin is included as an example in both the methy and phenyl groups.

--in the carbonyl examples, NutraSweet should be one word, capital N, capital S. Nutrasweet is in both carbonyl and amino groups. (If it belongs in both, please also fix spelling in amino group list).

--in carboxyl examples, Nutrasweet (fix spelling) and aspirin are both included here, too (I guess they&apos;re supposed to be in multiple categories?). In last two examples, change &quot;animo&quot; to &quot;amino&quot;

--Is &quot;AMP&quot; correct for the phosphate group example? (text mentioned ATP)

--In explanatory text: Explain &quot;pKa values.&quot; Also, first two groups&apos; text doesn&apos;t start with &quot;Family:&quot; but others do.

--in amino explanatory text, insert space after amines. Comma after conditions.

--in carboxyl explanatory text, comma after conditions.


"?>functionally.<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
				<activity idref="func_groups_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing">
					<image src="../../webcontent/functional_groups/functionalgroups.jpg"
						alt="functional groups activity"/>
				</activity>
				
				<p><em style="highlight">FIXME: need activities about the point of functional groups.</em></p>
			<!--	<p>The following link is a video in which Dr. Bill Brown explains the various
					functional groups. You can open the Learn by Doing above and watch the video
					simultaneously. </p>
				<video src="http://telstar.ote.cmu.edu/biology/movies/fg.mov" width="320"
					height="257" type="video/quicktime"/>
				<p> If you need a reminder of chemical structures or how to view molecules in 3-D,
					use the link below.</p>
				<activity idref="chemical_structure" purpose="manystudentswonder"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Practice</title>
			<body>
				<p> This exercise uses the Functional Group Glossary to let you test your knowledge
					of the properties of the functional groups. </p>
				<activity idref="func_groups_quiz" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>My Questions</title>
			<body>
				<p> Using the My Response button below, record two questions you have about this
					lesson. Due by by 9 a.m. of the day the lesson will be discussed. These
					questions will be used to shape the classroom discussion. </p>
				<activity purpose="myresponse" idref="my_questions_func_group"/>
				<composite_activity title="Functional Group Practice Quiz">
					<materials>
						<material>
							<applet codebase="../../../webcontent/jmol-11.8.21" id="formamide"
								archive="../OLIMessaging.jar,JmolApplet0.jar"
								code="edu.cmu.oli.messaging.applet.jmol.JmolAppletWrapper"
								height="200" width="200">
								<param name="progressbar">true</param>
								<param name="progresscolor">blue</param>
								<param name="boxmessage">Downloading JmolApplet ...</param>
								<param name="boxbgcolor">white</param>
								<param name="boxfgcolor">white</param>
								<param name="ReadyCallback">_jmolReadyCallback</param>
								<param name="load"><wb:path
										href="../../../webcontent/jmol-11.8.21/pdbs/formamide.pdb"
									/></param>
								<param name="script">set background white;wireframe 0.2;spacefill
									0.3;color cpk;</param>
							</applet>
						</material>
						<material>
							<wb:inline idref="inline_func_groups" purpose="didigetthis"/>
						</material>
					</materials>

				</composite_activity>-->
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
