<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 2.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_2_0.dtd">
<workbook_page created="08/09/2006" id="intro_DNA_transcription" modified="$Date: 2007/02/24 10:14:27 $" version="$Revision: 1.11 $" xmlns:ask="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/assessment/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">
  <head>
    <title>DNA is transcribed to RNA is translated to Protein
    </title>
    
 
    
    <author>
      <name first="William" last="Brown"/>
      <email>wb02@andrew.cmu.edu</email>
      <institution>Carnegie Mellon University</institution>
      <department>Biological Sciences</department>
    </author>
    </head>
  <body>
    <p>DNA replication: Every time a cell divides, all of the DNA of the genome 
      is duplicated (called replication) so that each cell after the division 
      (called a daughter cell) has the same DNA as the original cell (called the 
      mother cell).
      
    </p>
    <image src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/DNA-Transcription.jpg"/>
    
    <p>DNA transcription: For the genetic code to become protein it goes through 
      a transcription step. DNA is transcribed into RNA (a single 
      strand nucleic acid). The RNA is then shuttled away from the DNA to the 
      region of protein synthesis.
      
    </p>
    
    
    <image src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/CD-Transcription.jpg"/>

   
    <p>RNA translation: RNA is translated 
      from a nucleic acid code into a protein.
    </p>
    
    <image src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/CD-Translation.jpg"/>
    
    <p>Thus, the DNA gene code is able to duplicate to maintain consistency 
      throughout the persons body and throughout the person's life. DNA is also 
      used to make proteins through the use of an RNA intermediate.
      
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>The organization of the gene expression system into Operons,</li>
      <li>The initiation of transcription at special sequences called Promoters,</li>
      <li>The unidirectional RNA sythesis using RNA polymerase and how it differs from replication, and</li>
      <li>The post-transcriptional processing of the end products of transcription</li>
    </ul>
  </body>
</workbook_page>
