<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<!--
<workbook_page created="02/20/2006" id="intro_proteinsynthesis" modified="$Date: 2007/02/20 22:06:29
	$" version="$Revision: 1.53 $" xmlns:ask="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/assessment/"
	xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">
-->
<workbook_page id="intro_proteinsynthesis" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"
    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<head>
		<title>Protein Synthesis</title>
<!--
		<author>
			<name first="William" last="Brown"/>
			<email>wb02@andrew.cmu.edu</email>
			<institution>Carnegie Mellon University</institution>
			<department>Biological Sciences</department>
		</author>
-->
		<objectives>
			<objective id="obj560" title="Translation">
Describe what post-transcriptional modification must take place before
					translation.
			</objective>
			<objective id="obj561" title="Translation">
Define the role of each RNA molecule used in translation.
			</objective>
			<objective id="obj562" title="Translation">
Distinguish between prokaryotic and eukaryotic
				translation.
			</objective>
			<objective id="obj563" title="Translation">
Define the genetic code.
			</objective>
			<objective id="obj564" title="Translation">
Describe the process of translation as a step-wise
				process.
			</objective>
		</objectives>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>
			<em>The Code</em>
		</p>
		<p>Translation involves the conversion of a sequence of RNA to a corresponding sequence of
			amino acids. To perform the conversion a code is needed to translate from the four
			nucleotides (AUGC) of mRNA to the 20 naturally occurring amino acids. The question then
			is what combination of nucleotides can code for at least twenty different amino acids?
			Four nucleotides taken two at a time would generate 16 possible unique sequences. Not
			enough to code for 20 different amino acids. However, four nucleotides taken 3 at a time
			would generate 64 different unique sequences. Clearly this is enough to code for the 20
			naturally-occurring amino acids. In fact, the abundance of codes means that there is
			redundancy or degeneracy in the code with more than one triplet code representing a
			single amino acid.</p>
		<p>Through experimentation it was found that the universal start code or codon is AUG and
			three stop codons (UAG, UGA and UAA) were identified. The remaining 60 codons
			represented the 20 amino acids. Having elucidated the entire code it was found that for
			many of the amino acids, the first two nucleotides in the sequence defined the amino
			acid with the third nucleotide being any of the four nucleotides. For example the codon
			for the amino acid leucine is CUX where the X represents any one of the four
			nucleotides, and the codon for the amino acid valine is GUX. This third base then became
			known as the wobble base signifying the flexibility the system has in identifying the
			third base. This also demonstrates the fact that a single amino acid can be coded by
			several triplet codes but a triplet code only represents a single amino acid. This
			triplet code for converting the sequence of mRNA to a sequence of amino acids is
			referred to as the <em>Genetic Code</em>.</p>
		<p>
			<em>The Starting Materials</em>
		</p>
		<p>Having identified a code to perform the translation, it is now necessary to describe the
			process by which the genetic code is used. Four major ingredients are necessary to carry
			out translation: m-RNA, t-RNA, the ribosome and the initiation factors.</p>
		<p><em>Messenger RNA (mRNA)</em> 
			This RNA is the message that is transcribed from the 
			DNA which contains the code for the amino acids.
			
			
			 </p>
		<p><em>Transfer-RNA (tRNA)</em>The transfer RNA contains a region to recognize 3 
			nucleic acids in the triplet on the mRNA and also carries the specific 
			amino acid. There is a tRNA for every amino acid.
			
		</p>
		<figure orient="horizontal" title="tRNA Structures" >
			<title>tRNA Structures</title>
	<material>
		
					<image height="160" src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/primary_image.jpg"
						width="160">
						<caption>Primary Sequence</caption>
					</image>
		</material>
				<material>
					<image height="160"
						src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/secondary_image.jpg" width="160">
						<caption>Secondary Sequence</caption>
					</image>
				</material>
			<material>
					<image height="160"
						src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/tertiary_image.jpg" width="160">
						<caption>Tertiary Sequence</caption>
					</image>				
	</material>
	<material>
		<applet archive="JmolApplet0.jar" code="JmolApplet"
			codebase="../../../webcontent/jmol/jmol" height="155" width="155">
			<caption>t-RNA Double Helix</caption>

			<param name="progressbar">true</param>
				<param name="progresscolor">blue</param>
				<param name="boxmessage">Downloading JmolApplet ...</param>
				<param name="boxbgcolor">white</param>
				<param name="boxfgcolor">white</param>
				<param name="ReadyCallback">_jmolReadyCallback</param>
				<param name="load">
					<wb:path href="../../../webcontent/jmol/jmol/pdbs/4TRA.pdb"/>
				</param>
				<param name="script">set specular 60; set specpower 100; set ambient 20;
					set diffuse 80; rotate x 90; rotate z 150; rotate y 60; zoom 120;
					spacefill ON</param>

		</applet>
	</material>
</figure>

		<p>The Following Learn by Doing contains an animation describing the tRNA structures.</p>
		<activity idref="protein_synthesis_structures_lbd"
			purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<flash id="charging" src="../../../webcontent/animation/stage.swf" height="417" width="600">
			
				<param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../../webcontent/CommLoggingLibrary.swf</param>
				<param name="mypath">../../../webcontent/animation/</param>
				<!-- use path from top to the animation folder-->
				<param name="TutorialPath">ProteinSynthesis/</param>
				<!-- use path from top to the animation folder-->
				<param name="TutorialData">charging.xml</param>
				<!-- use the unit folder as path to this tutorial-->
				<param name="UseAudio">yes</param>
				<!-- tell stage to display audio-->
			
		</flash>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<em>Ribosomes</em> Ribosomes are complexes of ribosomal RNA (rRNA) and proteins.
				This two subunit complex that holds the mRNA in place and allows the t-RNA 
				to recognize the code and translate the code into an amino acid complex.
				
			</li>
		</ul>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<image src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/50S_30S.jpg" width="160"
						height="160">
						<caption>50S and 30S subunits</caption>
					</image>
				</td>
				<td>
					<image src="../../../webcontent/DNATranscription/70S.jpg" width="160"
						height="160">
						<caption>70 S Initiation Complex</caption>
					</image>
				</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<em>Initiation Factors</em> are a set of proteins used to facilitate the specific 
				binding of mRNA to the small subunit of the ribosome.
				
			</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p><em>Protein Synthesis</em></p>
		<ul>
			
			
				<li>1. mRNA is transcribed from the DNA</li>
				<li>2. mRNA is held within a ribosome and tRNAs enter the complex</li>
			<li>3. the correct tRNAs match up with the code on the mRNA and the attached 
				amino acids are combined to make a protein</li>
		</ul>
			<p>
			The following detailed animation describes the production of a 
			protein from the formation of the initiation 
			complex, 
			the elongation of the peptide during synthesis and the termination of the 
			synthesis at the termination or stop codon.
			
			
		
		
			
			
		</p>
		<flash height="417" id="protein_synthesis" src="../../../webcontent/animation/stage.swf"
			width="600">
			
				<param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../../webcontent/CommLoggingLibrary.swf</param>
				<param name="mypath">../../../webcontent/animation/</param>
				<!-- use path from top to the animation folder-->
				<param name="TutorialPath">ProteinSynthesis/</param>
				<!-- use path from top to the animation folder-->
				<param name="TutorialData">synthesis.xml</param>
				<!-- use the unit folder as path to this tutorial-->
				<param name="UseAudio">yes</param>
				<!-- tell stage to display audio-->
			
		</flash>
		<p>
			<em>The Consequence or Error</em>
		</p>
		<p> During both replication and transcription errors can be made in the incorporation of the
			correct bases during the complementary copying of the DNA. In a previous section a
			discussion of the methods used by the system to minimize these errors has been
			presented. However, even with editing functions, some errors are generated and result in
			changing of the reading code used during translation to a protein sequence. These
			changes are referred to as mutations and can be categorized into four different
			categories described by the end result of the mutation or change.</p>
		<ul><!--I think we should illustrate these four consequences - Diana-->
			<li><em>Silent mutation</em> – Because of the degeneracy of the genetic code, multiple
				triplet codes represent the same amino acid. Thus, a change in the sequence for a
				code may not result in a change in amino acid. This particularly applies to the
				wobble or third base in a triplet code sequence. Thermophylic bacteria that operate
				optimally at high temperatures have optimized the use of the degeneracy to include
				codons with high G and C content to increase the thermal stability (higher melting
				temperature) of the resulting duplex DNA. </li>
			<li>
				<em>Missense mutation</em> – Some mutations result in the changing of a codon to
				represent a different amino acid. Missense mutations that change the amino acid can
				have no effect on the structure of a protein or may have a dramatic effect on the
				folding of a protein causing loss of function.</li>
			<li>
				<em>Nonsense mutation</em> – Another class of mutations may result in the changing
				of a codon to one of the three termination or stop codons. This will result in
				premature stop in the translation of a protein. Such a mutation at the beginning of
				the translation sequence will generally result in total loss of function which some
				nonsense mutations near the normal termination of the coding sequence may have
				little or no effect on the function of the resulting protein.</li>
			<li>
				<em>Frame-shift mutations</em> – Occasionally a mutation will occur that results in
				either the insertion or deletion of an extra base in the coding sequence. This type
				of mutation results in a shifting of the “reading” frame for the triplet codes after
				the insertion or deletion and production of a meaningless sequence of protein after
				that point. Again depending on where the insertion or deletion occurs, the effect
				can vary on the final product. It should also be noted that this reading frame shift
				will also change the position of the termination codon giving either a premature
				termination of the translation or an extended coding sequence.</li>
		</ul>
<!--
		<activity idref="a2_digit-Protein-Synthesis" purpose="didigetthis" type="x-ims-assessment"/>
-->
		<activity idref="a2_digit-Protein-Synthesis" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		<section>
			<title>End of Lesson Questions</title>
			<body>
				<activity purpose="myresponse" idref="proteinsynthesis_feedback"/>
			</body>
		</section>
<!--		 <section>
			<title/>
			<body>
				<image src="../../../webcontent/HS_Stop.gif"/>
			</body>
		</section>-->
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
