<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m1_lipids">
    <head>
        <title>Lipids</title>
<!--        <objref idref="levels_chemistry"/>
        <objref idref="levels_chem"/>-->
       <!-- <objref idref="levels_chem_water"/>-->
        <objref idref="levels_chem_lipids"/>
<!--        <objref idref="levels_molecules_bonds"/>-->
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Lipids include fats and waxes. Several vitamins, such as A, D, E and K, are lipid
            soluble. Perhaps the most important role of lipids is in forming the membranes of cells
            and organelles. In this way, lipids enable isolation and control of chemical processes.
            They also play a role in energy storage and cell signaling.</p>
        <p>Lipid molecules forming cell membranes are comprised of a hydrophilic “head” and
            hydrophobic “tail”  (<activity_link idref="levels_m1_molecules" target="new"
                >remember</activity_link>, "hydro" means water and "philos" means love; "hydro"
            means water, "phobic" means fear). A phospholipid bilayer is formed when the two layers
            of phospholipid molecules organize with the hydrophobic tails meeting in the middle.
            Scientists believe that the formation of cell-like globules of lipids was a vital
            precursor to the origin of cellular life, since membranes physically separate
            intracellular components from the extracellular environment. Thus, lipid membranes
            enclose other macromolecules, confine volumes to increase the possibility of reaction,
            and protect chemical processes. Proteins with hydrophobic regions float within the lipid
            bilayer. These molecules govern transport of charged or lipophobic molecules in and out
            of the cell, such as energy molecules and waste products. Some of these lipids also have attached carbohydrate molecules jutting
            out of the membrane are important for cell recognition as mentioned previously.</p>
        <p>Lipids are also vital energy storage molecules. Carbohydrates can be used right away, and
            lipids provide long-term energy storage. Lipids accumulate in adipose cells (fat cells)
            in the body. As part of the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120330T143951-0400" comment="Should this term be defined?"?>catabolic<?oxy_comment_end?>
            process, from the days when humans had to forage for food, excess carbohydrates can be
            converted into lipids, which are then stored in fatty tissue. Ultimately, too many
            ingested carbohydrates and lipids lead to obesity. </p>
        
        <wb:inline idref="levels_chem_lipids_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
        
        </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
