<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m1_water">
    <head>
        <title>Water</title>
<!--        <objref idref="levels_chemistry"/>
        <objref idref="levels_chem"/>-->
        <objref idref="levels_chem_water"/><!--
        <objref idref="levels_chem_ions"/>
        <objref idref="levels_molecules_bonds"/>-->
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Water is the basis of life. Without it, life is not possible. Up to 75 percent of
            our body weight comprises water. Water provides a relatively stable medium in
            which chemical reactions can take place. Water’s unique chemical properties (as
            a solvent, with a high boiling point and high heat capacity) make it essential
            for homeostasis. The body’s thermoregulation relies on water’s high heat
            capacity to buffer it against swings in external temperature. Cooling of the
            body is carried out by evaporative water loss – perspiration. Water is vital as
            a transport medium. Oxygen is carried by red blood cells suspended in water.
            Nutritional substances are dissolved in water and transported to cells. Water
            transports waste materials for processing and excretion. If the body goes
            without water for any length of time, death soon follows.</p>
        <p>Some of the many amazing aspects of water were covered in the 'Motivation and
        Introduction to Body Systems' section.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Learning Activities</title>
            <body>
               <p> Recall the
                functions of water. Which is NOT a function of water.</p>
                <p>Answers: flows through the body and caries nutrients; helps regulate temperature;
                    solubilizes materials inside the body; is a hormone for endocrine regulation</p>
                <p>Clues: in the endocrine system, hormones are small carbon-based molecules or
                    peptides</p>
                <p>Where we get water:</p>
                <p>List of many functions, possibly a "do you remember" from the previous
                    section.</p>
                <p>flows easily and allows transport of material throughout the body</p>
                <p>holds heat and allows good temperature regulation</p>
                <p>solubilizes many materials and allows their transport and movement </p>
                <p>All of these functions are made possible by the unique bent structure of water
                    and the fact that it forms bonds between water molecules.</p>
                <p>Water - nutritive sources and necessary for life over food...</p>
                <p>Water - into the body through the digestive system and out by digestive system
                    and urinary system</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        
        <p>Similar pages for each of:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Amino Acids</li>
            <li>Simple sugars</li>
            <li>Nucleic acids</li>
        </ul>
        <p>...to be included at a later date.</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
