<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m1_macro">
    <head>
        <title>Macromolecules</title>
        <objref idref="levels_chem_macro"/>
        <!--<objref idref="levels_chem_protein"/>
        <objref idref="levels_chem_nucleic"/>
        <objref idref="levels_chem_carbo"/>
        <objref idref="levels_molecules_lipids"/>-->
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Macromolecules are giants of the atomic world. The prefix “macro-” means "very large
            scale." Indeed, macromolecules dwarf other molecules involved in life’s chemistry, such
            as table salt (NaCl) or water (H<sub>2</sub>O). Macromolecules are typically comprised
            of at least 1,000 atoms, with repeated structures of smaller components. The process of
            polymerization links together the smaller components (monomers). It’s the extent of
            repetition that leads to large size.</p>
        <p>It’s the large size of macromolecules that dictates their importance in
            living systems. They are the basis of complex cellular life. Macromolecules are
            not intrinsically stable. They are not created in the absence of life, nor can
            they persist for long outside living systems.</p>
        
        <p>Essentially, a macromolecule is a single molecule that consists of many covalently linked subunit molecules. A
                        polymer is a single molecule composed of similar monomers. In physiology,
                        the four major macromolecules are: </p>
                        <ol>
                            <li>nucleic acids - made of nucleotide subunits linked through their phosphate
                                backbone.</li>
                            <li>proteins - made of amino acid subunits linked between carbon and
                    nitrogen.</li>
                            <li>lipids - typically large molecules comprised of nonpolar bonds, making them hydrophobic. Some lipids contain covalently attached polar groups, which may act as attachment points for multiple hydrophobic lipid molecules.</li>
                            <li>carbohydrates - have covalently linked sugar groups.</li>
                        </ol>
        
        <p>So far, we have discussed the major elements and types of bonds that are important in
            the functioning of a cell. Together these elements and bonds define the
            major properties of the four classes of macromolecules that make up a cell:
            carbohydrates, proteins, lipids and nucleic acids. In this module, we will explore these
            ma<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20120322T102420-0400" content="r"?>cromolecules.</p>
        
        <p>Carbohydrates, proteins and nucleic acids are all examples of polymers. <term>Polymers</term>
            are very large molecules composed of smaller units joined by covalent bonds using a
            common set of chemical reactions. Proteins are linear polymers of amino acids all joined
            by peptide bonds. Polysaccharides are
            the carbohydrates joined through glycosidic bonds in sometimes quite complex branched
            structures. DNA and RNA are polymers of nucleic acids linked by phosphodiester bonds. This module includes
            a discussion of the structures of these organic macromolecules. </p>
      
        
        
    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
