<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m1_carbs">
    <head>
        <title>Carbohydrates</title>
     <!--   <objref idref="levels_chem_protein"/>
      <objref idref="levels_chem_nucleic"/>-->
        <objref idref="levels_chem_carbo"/>
        <!--   <objref idref="levels_molecules_lipids"/>-->
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Carbohydrates, also called saccharides, are the simplest macromolecules. All
            carbohydrates are comprised of carbon, hydrogen and oxygen atoms, with the
            chemical formula C<sub>m</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub> (hence carbon plus
            hydrate). This represents a 2:1 ratio of hydrogen to oxygen atoms (as in water), but in this case, they are attached to a carbon backbone.
            The constituent atoms of carbohydrate can be configured in virtually endless
            configurations, so carbohydrate molecules come in a multitude of different
            shapes and sizes. Carbohydrate modifications (called glycosylations) are present
            on lipid membranes and proteins for specialized finction and recognition. Unique
            carbohydrate conformations allow even more specificity to a protein, beyond just
            the amino-acid code. The outer membrane of the cell is dotted with carbohydrate
            chains, which differ according to cell type. These carbohydrate glycosylations
            provide a "signature" of the cell and, whe expressed transiently, can also act
            as a signal. Thus, glycosylations are important in immune response and general
            cell-cell communication.</p>
        <p>Carbohydrates are best known as energy storage molecules. Cells readily convert
            carbohydrates into usable energy. Table sugar, or sucrose, is the best-known
            carbohydrate. However, the body does not need dietary carbodydrates for energy.
            Proteins and fats can meet the body’s energy needs, and the body can convert
            molecules into carbohydrates needed for other cellular functions. But
            carbohydrates require minimal processing for use as energy. For example, a
            simple enzymatic reaction converts sucrose into blood sugar, or glucose, which
            can be used directly as a source of cellular energy.</p>
        <p>** insert Kreb's here from Bio unit**</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
