<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="levels_m1_protein">
    <head>
        <title>Proteins</title>
        <objref idref="levels_chem_protein"/>
        <objref idref="levels_chem_protein_function"/>
        <!--    <objref idref="levels_chem_nucleic"/>
        <objref idref="levels_chem_carbo"/>
        <objref idref="levels_molecules_lipids"/>-->
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>After nucleic acids, proteins are the most important macromolecules. Structurally,
            proteins are the most complex macromolecules. A protein is a linear molecule comprised
            of amino acids. Twenty different amino acids are found in proteins. The sequence of a
            protein's amino acids is determined by the sequence of bases in the DNA coding for the
            synthesis of this protein. A single protein molecule may be comprised of hundreds of
            amino acids. This sequence of amino acids is a protein's <term>primary structure</term>.
            The protein's size, shape and reactive properties depend on the number, type and
            sequence of amino acids. The amino acid chain can remain in its primary linear
            structure, but often it folds up and in on itself to form a shape. This <term>secondary
                structure</term> forms from localized interactions (hydrogen bonding) of amino acid
            side chains. These include alpha helix and beta sheet structures. The alpha helix is
            dominant in hemoglobin, which facilitates transport of oxygen in blood. Secondary
            structures are integrated along with twists and kinks into a three-dimensional protein.
            This functional form is called the <term>tertiary structure</term> of the protein. An
            additional level of organization results when several separate proteins combine to form
            a protein complex—called <term>quaternary structure</term>.</p>
        <image src="../../webcontent/amino_acids/protein_structures.jpg"
            alt="illustrations that represent the basic
            structures of primary, secondary, tertiary and quaternary proteins"/>


        <p>Proteins perform numerous essential functions within the cell. Many proteins serve as
            enzymes, which control the rate of chemical reactions, and hence the responsiveness of
            cells to external stimuli. An enzyme can fast-forward a reaction that would take
            millions of years under normal conditions and make it happen in just a few milliseconds.
            Enzymes are important in DNA replication, transcription and repair. Digestive processes
            are also largely facilitated by enzymes, which break down molecules that would otherwise
            be too large to be absorbed by the intestines. Enzymatic proteins also play a role in
            muscle contractions.</p>
        <p>Other proteins are important in cell signaling and cell recognition. Receptor proteins
            recognize substances as foreign and initiate an immune response. Through cell signaling,
            proteins mediate cell growth and differentiation during development. Several important
            proteins provide mechanical support for the cell, scaffolding that helps the cell
            maintain its shape. Other proteins comprise much of the body’s connective tissue and
            structures such as hair and nails.</p>
        <p>For protein production in cells the body needs amino acids, which we ingest. It seems a
            bit inefficient, but we eat proteins, break them down into amino acids, distribute the
            amino acids inside the body and then build up new proteins. Our cells can synthesize
            some amino acids from similar ones, but essential amino acids must be obtained from the
            diet, since they cannot be synthesized. Deficiencies of protein in the diet result in
            malnutrition diseases such as kwashiorkor, which is common in developing countries. In
            cases of kwashiorkor, protein deficiency causes edema (swelling) which leads to a
            distended abdomen. Proteins are eventually metabolized into ammonia and urea, which are
            excreted by the kidneys. Kidney disease can cause these waste products to accumulate in
            the body, causing someone to become very ill, ultimately leading to death. A low protein
            diet can help those whose kidneys have a low level of function.</p>
        <p>Unlike nucleic acids, which must remain unchanged in the body for the life of the
            organism, proteins are meant to be transient—they are produced, do their functions and
            then are recycled. Proteins are also readily denatured (unfolding of the secondary and tertiary structures) by extremes of heat or pH. When
            you boil an egg, the yolk and white stiffen and change color. When you cook meat, the
            flesh changes color and becomes firm. These changes arise because the constituent
            proteins denature, changing the properties of the tissues.</p>
        
        <wb:inline idref="levels_chem_protein_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
