<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="levels_m1_nucleic"><head><title>Nucleic Acids</title><objref idref="levels_chem_nucleic" /><objref idref="levels_chem_dna_express" /></head><body><p id="c1e1b27a5edb45ac95048a2c89af0078">Primarily located in the cell nucleus (hence the name) <term>nucleic acids</term> are replicating macromolecules. The most important are DNA and RNA. Without them, cells could not replicate, making life impossible. These molecules store the cell’s “software”—the instructions that govern its function, processes and structure. The code is comprised of sequences of four bases—adenine, cytosine, guanine and thymine (uracil in RNA). These are arranged in sets of three called triplets. Each triplet specifies an amino acid, which in turn is a component of a protein macromolecule. All the intricate complexity of the human body arises from the information encoded by just four chemicals in a single long DNA macromolecule.</p><p id="a592d74573bb4af3a1f3c815b40b47a9">In humans, mistakes in the structures of DNA and RNA cause diseases, including sickle cell anemia, hemophilia, Huntingdon&apos;s chorea and some types of cancer. Even a small error can result in a dramatic effect. Sickle cell disease is caused when just one amino acid in the DNA base sequence is changed. Through directing chemical processes, nucleic acids instruct cells how to differentiate into various organs. During development, whole sets of DNA sequences are shut down or activated to drive specific processes. These processes lead to different kinds of cells that form organs such as the heart, liver, skin and brain.</p><p id="c15a0c0b11ff4d1e9012199ff0488936">Within the cell, nucleic acids are in turn organized into higher-level structures called chromosomes. You can see chromosomes with a light microscope, using an appropriate stain. Early study of chromosomes helped scientists discover and understand the role of nucleic acids in cellular reproduction. Errors in chromosomal structure lead to malfunctions of life processes. For example, in humans, an extra chromosome 21 results in Down Syndrome.</p><section id="ca07765de424497c9a9e42058254f29e"><title>The Backbone</title><body><image id="d159607d87a24b64bb903ce2956e845e" src="../../../webcontent/DNA_1.png" alt="structures of RNA and DNA with molecular                      representations of the bases." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="e91d4940bb1144248785cc35820bc747"><em style="italic">Structure of RNA and DNA</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f0e2b395c9d84d0d93b1edb519303d38">Our genetic code is determined by only four bases in DNA (G, C, A, T), which are repeated and arranged in a special order. For example, </p><p id="de37a90971d8498a85c154bdf0e7f739">1 agccctccag gacaggctgc atcagaagag gccatcaagc agatcactgt ccttctgcca </p><p id="ba324831dab9465db8c07ae6af732182">61 tggccctgtg gatgcgcctc ctgcccctgc tggcgctgct ggccctctgg ggacctgacc </p><p id="d120fa24bf534585ae64543fe2a12243">121 cagccgcagc ctttgtgaac caacacctgt gcggctcaca cctggtggaa gctctctacc </p><p id="cb35d3efd9c948b3b62b8b5d0e405966">181 tagtgtgcgg ggaacgaggc ttcttctaca cacccaagac ccgccgggag gcagaggacc </p><p id="d3c3883c956d45e59c3196e2fa03fb8f">241 tgcaggtggg gcaggtggag ctgggcgggg gccctggtgc aggcagcctg cagcccttgg </p><p id="c1d04cb15d8e4d7da81a35539ae39c30">301 ccctggaggg gtccctgcag aagcgtggca ttgtggaaca atgctgtacc agcatctgct </p><p id="ab63f097f97d4f3899e19f5a1f660ae4">361 ccctctacca gctggagaac tactgcaact agacgcagcc cgcaggcagc cccacacccg </p><p id="bedcd18fef614c0983d535a26b402f1e">421 ccgcctcctg caccgagaga gatggaataa agcccttgaa ccagcaaaa </p><p id="ec04ca3529e74b8ea1550ef70c181f50">This may seem like a random string of G, C, A, T, but this DNA codes for human insulin. DNA is organized into a linear polymer in a double helix and maintains the inherited order of bases or genetic code. The &quot;steps&quot; of the DNA ladder have the code that ultimately directs the synthesis of our proteins. This linear polymer of genetic code is maintained when double strand DNA is transcribed to single strand RNA. </p><image id="b304f1d392bf47769cc1b6eacee48213" src="../../../webcontent/nucleotide.png" alt="structure of a nucleotide highlighting                      the phosphate group, the furanose sugar group and the nitrogenous base." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="b8107081f7a044fda4031f3c23381909"><em style="italic">Structure of a nucleotide</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f9c6358e031b4b01a04b58cc98a6cd6c">The fundamental unit of DNA is the nucleotide. The nucleotide contains a phosphate group (shown in orange), which will eventually give the DNA polymer its charge and interconnect nucleotides on the backbone. The furanose sugar group is a five-sided sugar (shown in purple). The nitrogenous base (shown in yellow) determines the type of nucleotide formed. </p><p id="bbe2518472dd4116b192d8317d941d00">The numbering of the positions on the sugar furanose rings of DNA and RNA follow a convention that uses &apos; (the prime symbol) to denote the sugar positions. Thus, the ribose has a nitrogenous base connected to the 1&apos; position and hydroxyl groups (OH) on the 2&apos;, 3&apos; and 5&apos; positions. Using this nomenclature, deoxyribose is formally called 2&apos;-deoxyribose (2 prime deoxyribose) to denote the loss of the hydroxyl at the 2&apos; position of ribose.</p><p id="ea962aae7d4645dea2a322e8bb83e0a4">The major difference in the polymer backbones between DNA and RNA is the sugar used in the formation of the polymer. In DNA (<em style="italic">D</em>eoxyribo<em style="italic">N</em>ucleic <em style="italic">A</em>cid) the 2&apos; position of the furanose has a hydrogen. In RNA (<em style="italic">R</em>ibo<em style="italic">N</em>ucleic <em style="italic">A</em>cid), the 2&apos; position of the furanose has an OH (hydroxyl) and the sugar is the monosaccharide ribose in the furanose conformation. </p><image id="f951b443a0a34d61a8d5a8d83c9f6c76" src="../../webcontent/DNAstructures/Sugars.jpg" alt="structural representations of                      deoxyribose and ribose, highlighing the difference between the two." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="c1ac8ed65d914a6d81f02ff8b006ac36"><em style="italic">Furanose sugars</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f521af2c100e4adbbca6495456777f15">The linkage of individual nucleotides is made by a bridging phosphate molecule between two hydroxyl groups, one on each furanose ring. The resulting polymer is a string of furanose molecules linked by phosphodiester bonds in one very long macromolecule.</p><image id="ac1bf1562bb04e4b8f3c12884d0171c9" src="../../../webcontent/backboneofDNA_1.png" alt="backbone of DNA, showing the sugar and                      phosphate group on the backbone and the bases between the backbone with hydrogen bonding between the                      bases." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="b892713a8d184f2b9fcd1a6763055035"><em style="italic">Backbone of DNA</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b0a5bc4ed6c544e5b3623f12dd645060">The following is a list of structural characteristics of the DNA/RNA polymer backbone.</p><ul id="b260466f5411456fb99231790c5bad7a"><li><p id="aa532eb6b597446c6abba3b00fd4b511a">Phosphate-ribose(deoxyribose)-phosphate-ribose(deoxyribose) sequence</p></li><li><p id="aa2bf430f573142f1860e6669cbf63456">Linked by phosphodiester covalent bonds</p></li><li><p id="ac103ff54d57c4946be03129422ee3c41">3&apos; position on one ribose(deoxyribose) linked to 5&apos; position of adjacent ribose(deoxyribose) through phosphodiester bridge</p></li><li><p id="ae6daaadbdede4923b71cdf2bff887c0d">Chain has 3&apos; end and 5&apos; end</p></li></ul></body></section><section id="f7f2cd364ba6405784ae6892a36b2b2d"><title>Hydrogen Bonding Between Bases</title><body><p id="a70b99fa99e4452eaab17d99e5639256">The DNA double helix is held in place with the hydrogen bonding of purines to pyrimidines.</p><image id="d80f366fdcda4ac1bb1a637aa205d9dc" src="../../webcontent/purine-pyrimidine_bases.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="a6ce4c9eac614bf9864eb1708fb226ad">Example purines and pyrimidines. <link href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nucleobase" target="new" internal="false">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nucleobase</link></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f15b557ba3074ac9a73ad7d50802f752">Recall that hydrogen bonds are weak interactions, not like the covalent bonds of the phosphate-furanose backbone. Thus, DNA is held together, but can be pulled apart for transcription to RNA or for DNA replication.</p><p id="dc7d4bd5d77f4665aa0db581036dd265">To maintain equal distance between the two strands of DNA, the larger purines must bind with the smaller pyrimidines, so the size of the base pair is conserved. Specifically, A always binds with T and G always binds with C in DNA. A useful memory device is that A and T are angular letters and G and C are both curvy.</p></body></section><section id="cf63f605fee84a7b99ec89b046f20cc3"><title>DNA Transcription</title><body><p id="c97a1c2c6f98460e93a659de2d7f8182"><em style="bold">DNA replication</em>: Every time a cell divides, all of the DNA of the genome is duplicated (called replication) so that each cell after the division (called a daughter cell) has the same DNA as the original cell (called the mother cell). </p><image id="cd4f5d09d7c44734b804d21243404c7e" src="../../webcontent/DNATranscription/DNA-Transcription.jpg" alt="process of DNA replicatioin.  DNA arrow to                      DNA" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="aa844946b1c26487a9a1df7f289e03648"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b67eab3ac36c49b3897f06c23d2cf328"><em style="bold">DNA transcription</em>: For the genetic code to become a protein, it goes through a transcription step. DNA is transcribed into RNA (a single-strand nucleic acid). The RNA is then shuttled away from the DNA to the region of protein synthesis. </p><image id="a57e4e806d724dd6a1c66ae6afc37fd6" src="../../webcontent/DNATranscription/CD-Transcription.jpg" alt="process of transcription.  DNA arrow to RNA." style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="af7670ad6abad4e0d954af8bfef3dc310"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="eff5e19c8e404a70b949ee337bbc61cf"><em style="bold">RNA translation</em>: RNA is translated from a nucleic acid code into the amino acid sequence of a protein. </p><image id="eb48115015ed4f2c804108e2aadf1851" src="../../webcontent/DNATranscription/CD-Translation.jpg" alt="process of translatioin. RNA arrow                      to Protein" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ae4dbe03b3dd640478bfa9354dada37f6"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="fb778bb2629844f0b3261298c5dbae8e">Thus, the DNA gene code is able to duplicate to maintain consistency throughout the person&apos;s body and throughout the person&apos;s life. DNA is also used to make proteins through the use of an RNA intermediate. </p></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
