<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ph_wbk_mod_ml"><head><title>Electrolytes and pH</title><objref idref="levels_chem_ph" /></head><body><section id="b0c25965efda4ac99f81c7f128f968bb"><title>Electrolytes</title><body><p id="d1c6c29ba7c848cb934a57dbf7a4ac11">An electrolyte is any fluid that contains free ions. You have already learned about ions and ionic properties. Important ions in physiology include sodium, potassium, calcium, chloride and phosphate. These ions are used in maintaining protein structure and in cell communication, and generally can help maintain water balances throughout the body. We get electrolytes through ingestion. Drinks with “electrolytes” have salts (sodium and potassium) that help maintain ion levels for athletes that lose ions through sweat. Electrolytes are essential for life, but many people get too much (like too much sodium from salt in processed food), which can also disrupt proper physiological function.</p></body></section><section id="e4ee5528c9634dfdb4e20fbf873ef6fd"><title>pH</title><body><p id="c3f316efd41b42e2ba51d56f14cbaf4b">The hydrogen ion concentration (H<sup>+</sup>) of a solution is an important property, because biological systems contain functional groups whose properties are changed by changes in the hydrogen ion concentration.</p><p id="df2592e00280497ba2256a60123d65ef">Since the hydrogen ion concentrations are usually much less than one, and can vary over many orders of magnitude, a different scale is used to describe the hydrogen ion concentration—the pH scale. The pH is the negative logarithm (-log) of the proton concentration:pH = - log (H<sup>+</sup>). The log conversion reduces a tenfold change in hydrogen ion concentration to a one unit change in pH. The minus sign changes the negative numbers that would be obtained from log(H<sup>+</sup>) to positive ones. Since the pH scale is an inverse scale, the concentration of protons is high at low pH and low at high pH. A solution is said to be acidic if the pH is less than 7.0, and basic if the pH is more than 7.0. A solution is neutral if its pH is equal to 7.0.</p><p id="d3626b52b15449fe933affd0bb37349b">The image below shows the pH of a number of common fluids. </p><image id="ph_scale_img" src="../../webcontent/pH_Scale.jpg" alt="Diagram of common substances placed on pH scale" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="550"><title>pH of various compounds</title><caption><p id="dcc093ba73c0495f8e5162b74ded786a">Examples of solutions with their pH listed, and concentration of Hydrogen ions compared to distilled water. For comparison, other biologically relevant solutions include the pH of pancreatic juice, which is 8.8, and seminal fluid, which has a pH of 7.8. By ChemEd DL (<link href="http://chemteacher.chemeddl.org/services/chemteacher/images/stories/pH_Scale.jpg" target="new" internal="false">pH Scale</link>)/<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="new" internal="false">CC-BY-SA</link>.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="b8d95e12c07f455aa3cc9a038df4ad38" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="electrolytes_concentration" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="electrolytes_concentration_digt2" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="d42b9d5437dc49b18bfed2dfc676d15d"><title>Acid Dissociation and pH</title><body><p id="da9f9eed7ba8459fb11cf9080777e668">For our studies, the Bronsted definition of an acid will be used. Here, we will define an <term>acid</term> as a proton donor and a <term>base</term> as a proton acceptor. Hydrochloric acid, like sodium chloride, is a strong electrolyte because it completely dissociates in aqueous solution into charged ions. Hydrochloric acid is also a strong acid, because when it completely dissociates it also completely donates all of its protons. </p><p id="fb7be4b59aa7443d931e6dbbc5454ca1">Many molecules are weak electrolytes and exist in an equilibrium (indicated by <m:math xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><m:mo lspace="3px" rspace="3px">&amp;rlhar;</m:mo></m:math> in the general equation below) between the starting molecule and its dissociated parts. Thus dissociation can be seen as an <term>acid</term> (HA) in equilibrium with a <term>proton</term> (H<sup>+</sup>) and the corresponding <term>conjugate</term> base (A<sup>-</sup>). </p><p id="e2f64a922bda404f976ff4a3d62fd02e">In general:HA <m:math xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><m:mo lspace="3px" rspace="3px">&amp;rlhar;</m:mo></m:math> A<sup>-</sup> + H<sup>+</sup></p><p id="c84f69cd9580417a8b2ed61bd4ff0d78">Specifically for acetic acid: CH<sub>3</sub>COOH <m:math xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><m:mo lspace="3px" rspace="3px">&amp;rlhar;</m:mo></m:math>CH<sub>3</sub>COO<sup>-</sup> + H<sup>+</sup></p></body></section><wb:inline idref="levels_chem_ph_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="levels_chem_ph_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
