<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="water_wbk"><head><title>Water and Hydrogen Bonding</title><objref idref="levels_chem_water" /></head><body><p id="dd4750934bdd4198ba521c8ec87d5925">Water is the basis of life. Without it, life is not possible. Water accounts for up to 75 percent of the weight of the human body. Water provides a relatively stable medium in which chemical reactions can take place. Water’s unique chemical properties (as a solvent with a high boiling point and high heat capacity) make it essential for homeostasis. The body’s thermoregulation relies on water’s high heat capacity to buffer it against swings in external temperature. Cooling of the body is carried out by evaporative water loss—perspiration. Water is also vital as a transport medium. Oxygen is carried by red blood cells suspended in serum, which is mostly water. Nutritional substances are dissolved in water and transported to cells. Water is used to dissolve and dilute waste molecules. If the body is deprived of water for very long, death will result. </p><p id="ee0c7f036baf454ea0b83345fd7cce8a">Water has several properties that contribute to its suitability to support life as we know it. One of these properties is that water is a <term>polar molecule</term>. Oxygen is more electronegative than hydrogen and draws the electrons that it shares in the covalent bond towards itself. Because water is polar, the partial positive end of one water molecule will be attracted to the partial negative end of a neighboring water molecule. This attraction is called a <term>hydrogen bond</term>. <term>Hydrogen bonding</term> occurs between partially negatively charged atoms with high electronegativity—oxygen, nitrogen or fluorine—and partially positively charged hydrogen atoms that are bonded to oxygen, nitrogen or fluorine atoms. </p><p id="a2574125791645ffb2a195c3c6a426fb">Hydrogen bonding, which is referred to as an intermolecular attraction, is a critical interaction within the cell. It is the principal force that holds the tertiary structure of proteins, carbohydrates and nucleic acids together and the overall stability of these molecules is due in part to the cumulative effect of the large number of hydrogen bonds found in the functional structures. Hydrogen bonds are found in and between a variety of molecules. For example, the enormous number of hydrogen bonds between strands of plant cellulose provide the strength and structure of the plant cell wall. As another example, wool (sheep hair) has lots of proteins with an enormous number of hydrogen bonds that provide the curly structure of individual wool fibers. These curly fibers trap air spaces which makes wool such a good insulator. When washed at high temperatures, these hydrogen bonds are broken and the wool fibers will lose their shape, probably damaging any wool clothing.</p><image id="c68e23ddd9434946b2a288e8685b165c" src="../../../webcontent/biochem_bonding_water.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="ad9c9ccf7377840038acee118571555df">The electronegative oxygen (red) draws electrons to it, creating the partial negative charge on oxygen and partial positive charge on hydrogen. δ- and δ+ represent a partial negative and partial positive charge, respectively. </p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a5eddb1483a74008b2282953c87d8141">A water molecule attracts four other water molecules towards itself. One molecule to each of the two free pairs of electrons in the oxygen atom valence shell, and one to each of the hydrogen atoms covalently bonded to the oxygen. As the water molecules associate with each other they have a defined structure dictated by the tetrahedral geometry of the electrons around the oxygen atom as seen in the figure below. The partially positive hydrogen atoms are attracted to the free electron pairs from other water molecules while the partially negative charge on the oxygen&apos;s free electron pairs are attracted to the partially positive hydrogen atoms from another water molecule. </p><wb:inline idref="water_1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><example id="c0eb729f93104d7b8d7e344c73d39b9e"><p id="bce913f76bb640d491425cbd0d5a56d4">One excellent illustration of the hydrogen bonding is the change in hydrogen bonding of water in ice. These stabilized bonds give ice its crystal-like appearance due to the network-like formation of weak bonds between molecules. This type of hydrogen bonding also helps large protein structures stabilize.</p></example><section id="cd20665757e94b89a59829e6bb628d58" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="levels_chem_water_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_chem_water_digt2" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="levels_chem_water_digt3" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
