<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="compu_median_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_compu_median" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to trauma
                (accidents and homicides) that occurred in a certain hospital during a week. </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif" />
            <p>Which of the following is a possible value of the median in this example?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">23</choice>
            <choice value="B">45</choice>
            <choice value="C">50</choice>
            <choice value="D">33</choice>
            <!--    <choice value="E">It is impossible to answer without seeing all of the
                data. </choice>-->
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. Only 21 people
                    out of 50 could be younger than age 23, as represented by the total height of
                    the two left bars on the display. So 23 is too low to be the median.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the middle value. Only 10 people
                    out of 50 could be older than age 45, as represented by the total height of the
                    four bars on the right side of the display. So 45 is too large to be the
                    median.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the median is the value of the middle person, not
                    the middle of the range. Only 10 people out of 50 could be older than age 50, as
                    represented by the total height of the four bars on the right side of the
                    display. So 50 is too large to be the median.</feedback>
            </response>
            <!--    <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The median is the middle value. There are 50 people in the data,
                    so the median must be the age between the 25th youngest person and the 26th
                    youngest person. These people will both be represented in the third bar from the
                    left on the display. Since that bar represents ages from 25 to 35, the median
                    could be any value between those ages.</feedback>
            </response>-->
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>




    <multiple_choice id="q2_compu_median" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an animal
                behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png" />
            <p>Which of the following is a possible value of the median in this example?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">3.3 </choice>
            <choice value="B">3.9 </choice>
            <choice value="C">4.6 </choice>
            <choice value="D">5.5 </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="bold">median</em> is the middle
                    value. There are 25 observations (odd number) and therefore the median is the
                    13th ranked observation. Only 11 observations fall below 3.5, so 3.3 is too low
                    to be the median.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. There are 25 observations (odd number), and therefore the median
                    is the 13th ranked observation. If we look at the histogram, we can figure out
                    that the 13th observation falls in the third interval (3.5–4.5 minutes). The
                    only option with such a number is 3.9 minutes.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="bold">median</em> is the middle
                    value. There are 25 observations (odd number) and therefore the median is the
                    13th ranked observation. Only 8 observations fall above 4.5, so 4.6 is too high
                    to be the median.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="bold">median</em> is the middle
                    value. There are 25 observations (odd number) and therefore the median is the
                    13th ranked observation. Only 5 observations fall above 5.5, so this is too high
                    to be the median.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>




    <multiple_choice id="q3_compu_median" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Here are the number of hours that 9 students spend on the computer on a typical day:
                </p><p> 1 6 7 6 8 11 6 12 15</p>
            <p>Which of the following represents the median number of hours spent on the computer?
            </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">6.0 </choice>
            <choice value="B">7.0 </choice>
            <choice value="C">7.5 </choice>
            <choice value="D">8.0 </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This value represents the <em style="italic">mode</em>, or the
                    most frequently occurring number. The median is the middle value in an ordered
                    data set.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. To locate the median you first need to list the values in order
                    and then locate the middle value. In this set of values, 7 is the middle most
                    number (1, 6, 6, 6, <em style="bold">7</em>, 8, 11, 12, 15).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is an odd number of values so it is not be necessary to
                    take the average of the two middle numbers.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is the middle most number in the data set. However, it
                    appears you forgot to first list the values in order before identifying the
                    middle most value.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>



</pool>
