<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="label_boxplot_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_label_boxplot" select="single">
        <body><p>Based on the results of a nationwide study, the number of contacts programmed into
                cell phones are summarized on the following boxplot:</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/u2_m2_pool_boxplot2.png" />
            <p>Choose the correct label for the point on the boxplot represented by the question
                mark:</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Minimum </choice>
            <choice value="B">Q1 </choice>
            <choice value="C">Median </choice>
            <choice value="D">Q3 </choice>
            <choice value="E">Maximum </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The minimum is the smallest observation, which is represented
                    on the far left by the end of the whisker, located at 25. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The first quartile (Q1) is the median of the bottom half of
                    the data, and is represented on the boxplot by the left side of the box, located
                    at 50. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The median is the middle value of all the observations, and is
                    represented on the boxplot by the line in the center of the box, located at 75.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The third quartile (Q3) is the median of the top half of the
                    data, and is represented on the boxplot by the right side of the box, located at
                    125. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The maximum is the largest observation, which is represented
                    on the far right by the end of the whisker, located at 200.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <fill_in_the_blank id="q2_label_boxplot">

        <body><p>The cost of taking your pet aboard the air flight with you in the continental US
                varies according to the airlines. The five number summary for prices based on a
                sample of major US airlines was: </p>
            <p>Min = 60, Q1 = 100, Median = 110, Q3 = 125, Max = 150 </p>
            <p>If we were to build the box plot for this data, the box would stretch between which
                two values? </p>
            <p>What would be the lowest value: <input_ref input="A" /> and highest
                value: <input_ref input="B" /></p>
        </body>

        <input id="A" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="one">60</choice>
            <choice value="two">100</choice>
            <choice value="three">110</choice>
            <choice value="four">125</choice>
            <choice value="five">150</choice>

        </input>
        <input id="B" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="one">60</choice>
            <choice value="two">100</choice>
            <choice value="three">110</choice>
            <choice value="four">125</choice>
            <choice value="five">150</choice>
        </input>


        <part>
            <response input="A" name="60" match="one" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The minimum is 60, which is not the lowest value (left side,
                    bottom of the box) in a boxplot. The minimum is represented on the far left (or
                    bottom) by the end of the whisker.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" name="100" match="two" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The lowest value (left side, bottom of the box) in a boxplot is
                    the first quartile, which in this data set is 100. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" name="110" match="three" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The lowest value (left side, bottom of the box) in a boxplot
                    is not the median, but rather the value representing the 25th percentile of the
                    distribution. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" name="125" match="four" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The lowest value (left side, bottom of the box) in a boxplot
                    is not the third quartile. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="A" name="150" match="five" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The lowest value (left side, bottom of the box) in a boxplot
                    is not the maximum, but rather the value representing the 25th percentile of the
                    distribution. </feedback>
            </response>

        </part>
        <part>
            <response input="B" name="60" match="one" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The minimum is 60, which is not the highest value (right side,
                    top of the box) in a boxplot. The minimum is represented on the far left (or
                    bottom) by the end of the whisker.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="B" name="100" match="two" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The highest value (right side side, top of the box) in a
                    boxplot is not the first quartile. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="B" name="110" match="three" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The highest value (right side side, top of the box) in a
                    boxplot is not the median, but rather the value representing the 75th percentile
                    of the distribution. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="B" name="125" match="four" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The highest value (right side side, top of the box) in a boxplot
                    is the third quartile, which is this data set is 125.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response input="B" name="150" match="five" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The highest value (right side side, top of the box) in a
                    boxplot is not the maximum, but rather the value representing the 75th
                    percentile of the distribution. The maximum is represented on the far right (or
                    top) by the end of the whisker. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>




    </fill_in_the_blank>

</pool>
