<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="mean_vs_median_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_mean_vs_median" select="single">
            <body>
                <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                    trauma (accidents and homicides) that were observed in a certain
                    hospital during a week. </p>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif" />
                <p>For the data described by the above histogram, which of the following is
                    a correct statement about the median?</p>
            </body>
            <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                <choice value="A">The median will be bigger than the mean. </choice>
                <choice value="B">The median will be smaller than the mean. </choice>
                <choice value="C">The median and the mean will be about the
                    same. </choice>
                <choice value="D">The median and the range will be about the
                    same. </choice>
            </input>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Notice this distribution is skewed to the right
                        (the tail is towardthe right), and we also see a suspected outlier
                        on the right side. Remember that both of these shape features will
                        tend to “pull” the <em style="italic">mean</em> more than they would pull the
                        median.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. The mean is more sensitive than the median to the
                        “tail” of a distribution, and also to outliers. We see that this
                        distribution is skewed to the right (the tail is towards the right)
                        and we also see a suspected outlier on the right side. Both of these
                        shape features will tend to “pull” the mean toward the tail more
                        than they would pull the median, meaning that the median will be
                        smaller than the mean.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that we would expect the mean and the median
                        to be nearly the same only if the distribution was nearly symmetric.
                        But notice this distribution is skewed to the right (the tail is
                        towards the right) and we also see a suspected outlier on the right
                        side. Remember that both of these shape features will tend to “pull”
                        the mean more than they would pull the median.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="italic">range</em> is the length from
                        lowest value to highest value. So, for this distribution, the range
                        is approximately 80. But remember that the <em>median</em> is the
                        middle value. Half the people must be older than the median, so the
                        median will be much less than 80, because all but one of the people
                        were younger than 80.</feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q2_mean_vs_median" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>The histogram below displays the distribution of 50 ages at death due to
                trauma (accidents and homicides) that were observed in a certain
                hospital during a week. </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment1q2.gif" />
            <p>Assume that the largest observation in this dataset is 90. If this
                observation were wrongly recorded as 900, then what would happen to the
                mean and median?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Neither the mean nor the median would change.</choice>
            <choice value="B">Both the mean and the median would change. </choice>
            <choice value="C">The mean would stay the same, but the median
                would change. </choice>
            <choice value="D">The mean would decrease, but the median would not
                change. </choice>
            <choice value="E">The mean would increase, but the median would not
                change. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the median would not change, because
                    pulling 90 to 900 would not change the 25th or the 26th value in the
                    data. But remember that the <em style="italic">mean</em> tends to be “pulled” by an
                    outlier. So moving the largest value, 90, farther to the right, to
                    900, would tend to pull the mean to the right, making it
                    larger.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the mean would change, because mean
                    tends to be “pulled” by outliers. But remember that the
                    <em style="italic">median</em> is the middle value. Moving 90 to 900 would not
                    change the 25th or the 26th value in the data, so the median would
                    be the same.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="italic">mean</em> tends to be
                    “pulled” by an outlier. So moving the largest value, 90, farther to
                    the right, to 900, would tend to pull the mean to the right. So
                    the mean would change. But the <em style="italic">median</em> is the middle
                    value. Pulling 90 to 900 would not change the 25th or the 26th value
                    in the data, so the median would be the same.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is true that the median would not change, because
                    moving 90 to 900 would not change the 25th or the 26th value in the
                    data. But remember that the <em style="italic">mean</em> tends to be “pulled” by an
                    outlier. Moving the largest value, 90, farther to the right, to 900,
                    would tend to pull the mean to the right, making it increase, not
                    decrease.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The mean will increase, because the mean tends to be
                    “pulled” by an outlier. So moving the largest value, 90, farther to
                    the right, to 900, would tend to pull the mean to the right. The
                    <em style="italic">median</em> would not be affected, because moving 90 to 900
                    would not change the 25th or the 26th value in the data. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    
    <multiple_choice id="q3_mean_vs_median" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png" />
            <p>For the data described by the above histogram, which of the following is
                a correct statement about the median?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">The median will be smaller than the mean. </choice>
            <choice value="B">The median will be larger than the mean. </choice>
            <choice value="C">The median and the mean will be about the
                same. </choice>
            <choice value="D">The median and the range will be about the
                same. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. When the distribution is skewed right, the mean is
                    “pulled up” by the large observations in the “tail” of the
                    distribution. The median, on the other hand, is only determined by
                    the order of the observations, and is not affected by their
                    magnitude. Therefore, in this case, the median is smaller than the mean.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. When the distribution is skewed right, the mean is
                    “pulled up” by the large observations in the “tail” of the
                    distribution. The median, on the other hand, is only determined by
                    the order of the observations, and is not affected by their
                    magnitude.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. When the distribution is skewed right, the mean is
                    “pulled up” by the large observations in the “tail” of the
                    distribution. The median, on the other hand, is only determined by
                    the order of the observations, and is not affected by their
                    magnitude.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the <em style="italic">range</em> is the length from
                    lowest value to highest value. So, for this distribution, the range
                    is approximately 7. But remember that the <em style="italic">median</em> is the
                    middle value. Half of the times must be greater than the median, so
                    the median will be much less than 7, because all but two of the
                    times were less than 7.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    
    <multiple_choice id="q4_mean_vs_median" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>This histogram shows the times, in minutes, required for 25 rats in an
                animal behavior experiment to successfully navigate a maze.</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image500.png" />
            <p>Assume that the largest observation in this dataset is 8.6 minutes. If
                this observation were wrongly recorded as 86, then what would happen to
                the mean and median?</p></body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"><!--Both the mean and the median will not
                            change. -->Neither the mean nor the median would change.</choice>
            <choice value="B">Both the mean and the median would change. </choice>
            <choice value="C">The mean would stay the same, but the median
                would change. </choice>
            <choice value="D">The mean would decrease, but the median would not
                change. </choice>
            <choice value="E">The mean would increase, but the median would not
                change. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                    observations, whereas the median is determined by their order. While
                    the median would stay the same, changing the largest observation from
                    8.6 to 86 would have an impact on the mean.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                    observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                    Therefore, changing the largest observation from 8.6 to 86 would have
                    an impact on the mean. However, the median would stay the
                    same.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you confused the impact of an outlier on
                    the mean and median. The mean is affected by the actual values of
                    the observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                    Therefore, changing the largest observation from 8.6 to 86 would have
                    an impact on the mean, while the median would stay the
                    same.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                    observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                    While the median would stay the same, changing the largest
                    observation from 8.6 to 86 would have an impact on the mean. But
                    remember that the mean tends to be “pulled” by an outlier. Moving
                    the largest value, 8.6, farther to the right, to 86, would tend to
                    pull the mean to the right, making it increase, not
                    decrease.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="10">
                <feedback>
                    <p>Correct. The mean is affected by the actual values of the
                        observations, whereas the median is determined by their order.
                        Therefore, changing the largest observation from 8.6 to 86 would
                        have an impact on the mean, while the median would stay the same.
                        So moving the largest value, 8.6, farther to the right, to 86,
                        would tend to pull the mean to the right. The median would not
                        be affected, because moving 8.6 to 86 would not change the 13th
                        value in the data.</p>
                    <p>Actually, we can figure out the <em style="italic">exact</em>
                        impact that the change will have on the mean: By changing 8.6 to
                        86, the sum of all the observations is increased by 86 - 8.6 =
                        77.4, and therefore the mean of the 25 observations is increased
                        by 77.4/25 = 3.1 minutes.</p>
                </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

</pool>
