<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m2_homeostatic_maintenance_01">
    <head>
        <title>Homeostasis of Ions</title>
        <objref idref="_u3_predict_OBJ"/>
    </head>

    <body>


        <p>Body functions such as regulation of the heartbeat, contraction of muscles, activation of
            enzymes, and cellular communication require tightly regulated calcium levels. Normally,
            we get a lot of calcium from our diet. The small intestine absorbs calcium from digested
            food.</p>

        <!--<image src="../webcontent/feedback_ions_calcium.gif" style="block"></image>-->

        <p>The endocrine system is the control center for regulating blood calcium homeostasis. The
            parathyroid and thyroid glands contain receptors that respond to levels of calcium in
            the blood. In this feedback system, blood calcium level is the variable, because it
            changes in response to the environment. Changes in blood calcium level have the
            following effects:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>When blood calcium is low, the parathyroid gland secretes <extra>
                    <anchor><term>parathyroid hormone</term></anchor>
                    <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/parathyroid_hormone.mp3"
                        type="audio/mp3"/>
                </extra>. This hormone causes effector organs (the kidneys and bones) to respond. The kidneys prevent calcium from being excreted in the
                urine. Osteoclasts in bones breakdown bone tissue and release calcium. When  blood  calcium levels are high, less parathyroid hormone is released. Parathyroid hormone is the main controller of blood plasma calcium levels in adults.
            <image src="../../webcontent/calcium.jpg" width="600" alt="feedback loop of blood calcium levels increasing as a result of a lack of sufficient calcium in the body."></image>
            </li>

            <li>Children have a second hormone that contributes to calcium regulation, called <extra>
                    <anchor><term>calcitonin</term></anchor>
                    <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/calcitonin.mp3"
                        type="audio/mp3"/>
            </extra>. It is released from the thyroid gland when blood calcium levels are high. Calcitonin prevents bone breakdown and causes the kidneys to reabsorb less calcium from the filtrate,
                allowing excess calcium to be removed from the body in urine.</li>
        </ul>
        <wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_calcium" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

        <p>Calcium imbalance in the blood can lead to disease or even death.
                <term>Hypocalcemia</term> refers to low blood calcium levels. Signs of hypocalcemia
            include muscle spasms and heart malfunctions. <term>Hypercalcemia</term> occurs when blood
            calcium levels are higher than normal. Hypercalcemia can also cause heart malfunction as
            well as muscle weakness and kidney stones.</p>

        <wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_calcium3" purpose="didigetthis"/>


    </body>

</workbook_page>
