<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m2_homeostatic_maintenance_03">
    <head>
        <title>Control of Cell Number</title>
        <objref idref="_u3_predict_OBJ"/>
    </head>

    <body>

        <p>Although homeostasis is often carried out by a negative feedback loop with an
            identifiable receptor, control center and effectors, it more broadly means maintaining
            variables in a range suitable for optimal function. This includes the regulation of cell
            number in our tissues so that we don’t have too few or too many. It may be hard to
            identify specific components of a feedback loop, but it is clear that there are at least
            negative feedback cycles that help maintain cell numbers. This negative feedback is
            known to occur through cell-to-cell communications of neighboring cells and an ability
            to sense the levels of nutrients and matrix in the area they are growing in. Normally
            cells will stop dividing when there is an appropriate number of cells in a tissue or
            space. If a neighboring cell is lost or if there is an inadequate number of cells, cells
            may be stimulated to divide. Cells with too many neighbors trigger an internal response
            to die in a regulated programmed way called apoptosis. When cells sense they have no
            neighbors, signals in the nucleus cause division of the cell. </p>

        <!-- <image src="../webcontent/feedback_cell_01.gif"></image>-->

        <wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_cell" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

        <wb:inline idref="_u3_m2_cell2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>

</workbook_page>
