<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="classify_receptors_DIGT1"><title>Tutor</title><question id="q1"><body>Which of the following classifications for receptors is correctly matched?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">proprioceptor – baroreceptor – Meisner corpuscle – light touch</choice><choice value="b">interoceptor – stretch receptor – nerve endings – cervical stretch during birthing</choice><choice value="c">proprioceptor - photoreceptor – specialized receptor cell – light reaching retina</choice><choice value="d">proprioceptor – nociceptor – muscle spindle – stretch</choice><choice value="e">exteroceptor – nocieceptor – free nerve ending – heart attack (feels like arm and upper chest is hurting) </choice></multiple_choice><part id="i12f851acdd1c419984346ca147d4522f"><skillref idref="classify_receptors_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While Meisner corpuscle is an encapsulated mechanoreceptor for touch, it is not a baroreceptor that detects stretch caused by fluid pressure.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This receptor sets up the example positive feedback mechanism we studied in the homeostasis module. It stimulates the release of the hormone oxytocin to increase the strength of uterine contractions.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The sensing cells for vision are exteroceptors that are not necessary for proper proprioception, although in some cases they can help overcome equilibrium problems. For example, it can be helpful to stare at a far horizon if you feel seasick while boating.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While there may be nociceptors associated with skeletal muscles, they would generate a sensation of pain. They do not contribute to perception of your own body position.</feedback></response><response match="e" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While the brain interprets the sensation as coming from the outer part of the body, the receptor itself is located in the heart cardiac muscle and would be an interoceptor.</feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
