<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="compare_pain_fibers_LBD1"><title>Tutor</title><question id="q1"><body>Silent nociceptors will only respond to mechanical stimulation if they have been sensitized by inflammation of the surrounding tissue. What has happened physiologically to these receptors, making them more responsive as a result of the various chemicals released during the inflammation response?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">the membrane potential of the receptor is now closer to its threshold potential </choice><choice value="b">the nociceptor changes the type of stimulus it can detect </choice><choice value="c">the nociceptor only becomes metabolically active during </choice><choice value="d">the free nerve ending grows new dendrites as a result of inflammation</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i721d07fd8f004e0c94d2c347866c6016"><skillref idref="compare_pain_fibers_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The same strength stimulus that previously would not create a change in membrane voltage large enough to reach threshold now does; such that pain stimuli are perceived much more easily by these.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Each receptor is specific for the type of stimulus it detects and can’t change as a result of inflammation.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The nociceptor is metabolically active all the time but doesn’t send a signal until the stimulus creates a depolarization large enough to reach threshold.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While neurons can grow new dendrites, this is mainly in the central nervous system, not unipolar sensory neurons in response to inflammation.</feedback></response><hint>Think back to the physiological processes that must occur in order for an action potential to be propagated. </hint></part></question></assessment>
