<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="compare_axons_DIGT1"><title>Tutor</title><page id="page_0"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="compare_axons_DIGT1_0"><body><p id="aa4e85394ff024c1982e60de9be42ac98">Compare the location of gray and white matter in a slice through the spinal cord and through the cerebellum (note: cerebrum would be similar to cerebellum). The outside portion is called the cortex and the inner portion is called the medulla. Based on this observation, which of the following statements is correct? </p><image id="d508340a0b804cfdb8490eba81eaffdf" src="../webcontent/Nerv_92.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="qsub_0" labels="false"><choice value="A">in the brain and spinal cord, oligodendrocytes are found in the medulla</choice><choice value="B">in the brain and spinal cord, oligodendrocytes are found in the cortex</choice><choice value="C">in the brain, nerve signals will propagate faster in the cortex</choice><choice value="D">in the spinal cord, nerve signals will propagate slower in the cortex</choice><choice value="E">in the brain, nerve impulses will be faster in the medulla and in the spinal cord they will be faster in the cortex</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="compare_axons_whvsgr_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae262866de61f44378bc55f45b52775c5">Incorrect. Oligodendrocytes would be found in the white matter and the medulla of both is not composed of white matter.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab30733f3ac2c4716811b4c6a12bfe277">Incorrect. Oligodendrocytes would be found in the white matter and the cortex of both is not composed of white matter.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="adcd44c0504444a28b7f0abed2c8d88d2">Incorrect. The brain cortex is gray matter but nerve impulses propagate faster in white matter.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aee3b89b6e5e3481782f163b623ead698">Incorrect. The spinal cord cortex is white matter where nerve impulses propagate faster in gray matter.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab7f3c6afbf214eee8259f157a598c715">Correct. The brain’s cortex and spinal cord medulla contains gray matter with neuron cell bodies, axon terminals and glial cells while the myelinated axons are found in the white matter and propagate nerve impulses quicker.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
