<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LBD2"><title>tutor</title><page id="page_0"><question id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_LBD2_0"><body>Postganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system receive input from all of the following sources except</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">preganglionic neurons in the lateral horn of all levels of the spinal cord</choice><choice value="B">preganglionic neurons that synapse in the sympathetic chain</choice><choice value="C">preganglionic neurons that originate in the lumbar level of the spinal cord</choice><choice value="D">preganglionic neurons that pass through the sympathetic chain without synapsing</choice><choice value="E">all of the above are correct, no exceptions</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic nervous system do not receive input from preganglionic neurons at cervical and sacral levels of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true for a source of input to postganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true for a source of input to postganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This statement is true for a source of input to postganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There is only one exception among the answer options.</feedback></response><hint>Preganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system do not originate from cervical and sacral levels of the spinal cord.</hint><hint>Preganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system project to two distinct sets of postganglionic neurons.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
