<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT1"><title>tutor</title><page id="page_0"><question id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT1_0"><body><p>Preganglionic axons traveling to postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic chain ganglia originate from neurons in the brainstem.</p></body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Preganglionic neurons (and their axons) originate in the thoracolumbar levels of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Preganglionic neurons (and their axons) originate in the thoracolumbar levels of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><hint>Recall the reason the sympathetic nervous system is referred to as the thoracolumbar system.</hint></part></question><question id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT1_1"><body><p>The sympathetic nervous system is referred to as the thoracolumbar system because its postganglionic neurons lie in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at thoracic and lumbar levels.</p></body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Postganglionic neurons are located outside of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The sympathetic nervous system is referred to as the thoracolumbar system because its preganglionic—not postganglionic--neurons lie in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at thoracic and lumbar levels..</feedback></response><hint>Postganglionic neurons are located outside of the spinal cord.</hint><hint>Preganglionic neurons send axons to postsynaptic neurons in the sympathetic chain.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
