<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT3"><title>tutor</title><page id="page_0"><content><p>For each statement below, decide if it is true for the sympathetic nervous system, parasympathetic nervous system, both, or neither.</p></content><question id="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_DIGT3_0"><body>Preganglionic neurons originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The sympathetic nervous system is not the only part of the autonomic nervous system with preganglionic neurons that originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The parasympathetic nervous system is not the only part of the autonomic nervous system with preganglionic neurons that originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Preganglionic neurons originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord for both the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the subdivisions of the autonomic nervous system—sympathetic or parasympathetic nervous systems—have preganglionic neurons that originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><hint>Preganglionic neurons originate within the central nervous system.</hint></part></question><question id="question_1"><body>Preganglionic neurons reside in the cerebral cortex</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. All sources of preganglionic neurons in the sympathetic nervous system are in the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sources of preganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous system are in the brainstem or at sacral levels of spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sources of autonomic nervous system preganglionic neurons do not arise above the level of the brainstem in the brain.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. No sources of preganglionic neurons are present above brainstem level in the brain.</feedback></response><hint>Neural sources of input to the autonomic nervous system are at automatic, subconscious levels of brain.</hint><hint>The highest central nervous system level for sources of input to the autonomic nervous system is at brainstem level.</hint></part></question><question id="question_2"><body>Postganglionic neurons lie within the lateral horn of spinal cord levels T1-L2</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_2" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_2"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic nervous nervous system originate in the chain or in the collateral (prevertebral) ganglia.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Postganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous system originate at or near their target organs.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Postganglionic neurons originate outside of the central nervous system.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Postganglionic neurons are part of the peripheral nervous system. They would not reside in the lateral horn of the spinal cord, which is part of the central nervous system.</feedback></response><hint>All postganglionic neurons have their cell bodies within ganglia in the peripheral nervous system.</hint><hint>The lateral horn of the spinal cord is part of the central nervous system.</hint></part></question><question id="question_3"><body>Collateral (prevertebral) ganglia contain postganglionic neurons</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_3" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_3"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Collateral (prevertebral) ganglia contain sympathetic postganglionic neurons.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Parasympathetic nervous system does not have prevertebral ganglia.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Parasympathetic nervous system does not have prevertebral ganglia.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the divisions of the autonomic nervous system—sympathetic or parasympathetic—contains collater (prevertebral) ganglia.</feedback></response><hint>Prevertebral ganglia lie in front of (anterior to) the vertebral column and are counterparts to the sympathetic chain ganglia.</hint></part></question><question id="question_4"><body>Preganglionic neurons lie in the midbrain, pons, and medulla</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_4" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_4"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Preganglion neurons in the sympathetic nervous system originate from thoracic and lumbar levels of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Preganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous system are in the brainstem and in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at sacral levels.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Preganglion neurons in the sympathetic nervous system originate from thoracic and lumbar levels of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the autonomic nervous system divisions—sympathetic or parasympathetic—have preganglionic neurons that originate in the brainstem.</feedback></response><hint>Preganglionic neurons originating in the cranium give parasympathetic nervous system the name craniosacral division of the autonomic nervous system.</hint></part></question><question id="question_5"><body>Postganglionic neurons originate at or within target organs</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_5" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_5"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic nervous system lie either in sympathetic chain ganglia or in collateral (prevertebral) ganglia.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Postganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous originate at or near the target organs.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Postganglionic neurons in the sympathetic nervous system have long axons.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the divisions of the autonomic nervous system—sympathetic or parasympathetic—have postganglionics that originates at or within target organs.</feedback></response><hint>Preganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous system have long axons.</hint></part></question><question id="question_6"><body>Postganglionic neurons are arranged as a chain along side the spinal vertebral column</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_6" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_6"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. At the upper thoracic levels, postganglionic neurons of the sympathetic nervous system are arranged vertically alongside the vertebral column.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Parasympathetic postganglionic neurons are not arranged in chains; rather, they originate at or near their target organs.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Parasympathetic postganglionic neurons are not arranged in chains; rather, they originate at or near their target organs.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the divisions of the autonomic nervous system—sympathethic or parasympathetic—has its postganglionic neurons arranged as chains.</feedback></response><hint>Sympathetic chain ganglia are sometimes referred to as paravertebral ganglia.</hint></part></question><question id="question_7"><body>Preganglionic neurons originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord levels S1-S2</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_7" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">sympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="B">parasympathetic nervous system</choice><choice value="C">both</choice><choice value="D">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_7"><skillref idref="contrast_anatomy_parasympathetic_sympathetic_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sympathetic preganglionic neurons originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at levels T1-L2.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Preganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous system originate in the brainstem and at the sacral levels of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Sympathetic preganglionic neurons originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at levels T1-L2.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the divisions of the autonomic nervous system—sympathetic or parasympathetic—has preganglionic neurons that originate in the lateral horn of the spinal cord at sacral levels.</feedback></response><hint>Only one of the divisions of the autonomic nervous system—sympathetic or parasympathetic—has preganglionic neurons that originate in the sacral region of the spinal cord.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
