<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="define_receptive_field_LBD1"><title>Tutor</title><page id="d4bd18e41e3b4b758c2149d64cb8ce62"><title>Page 1</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="ba1b9bbf843e427fa694392378912da4">If two touch receptors are stimulated at the same time, you may detect two different stimuli or only one. In order for the central nervous system to distinguish two separate stimuli, there typically has to be a non-stimulated receptor in-between the two being stimulated or their receptive fields of the two stimulated receptors don’t overlap at all.</p><p id="cdd1eb9d4cd940b0a19e68eb80ea86f2">The fingertips are a region of the body with very close two-point discrimination. What statement would best describe the receptor density and the size of receptive fields in the fingertips?</p></body><multiple_choice id="e9628bd0adf34640877152821aba32c3" labels="false" select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="a">very widely spaced receptors with large receptive fields</choice><choice value="b">very densely packed receptors with large receptive fields</choice><choice value="c">very widely spaced receptors with small receptive fields</choice><choice value="d">very densely packed receptors with small receptive fields</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i3339df8f41cf4142983d15267384efa7"><skillref idref="define_receptive_field_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac415c3eb596a4ee29154df7eeded0621">Incorrect. If they are far apart it would take a large distance between two points to stimulate both and large receptive field makes it difficult to distinguish where in that whole area the stimulus is located.</p></feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback><p id="ada0c6fe0e4734b61a984fd293f5f5995">Incorrect. If they are closer it would be easier to stimulate two at same time with small distance between two points, but their receptive fields would overlap making it difficult for the nervous system to distinguish specifically where the stimulus is occurring.</p></feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback><p id="aff10814e88e143029888b7f25c7f04b0">Incorrect. If they are widely spaced it would take a wide distance between the two points to distinguish both at same time, but the small receptive field means the location of the stimulus would be better resolved spatially by the nervous system.</p></feedback></response><response match="d" score="10"><feedback><p id="ab29d39fe334a4ea794b049e414041164">Correct. If receptors are close together it is more likely to stimulate two different ones with a non-stimulated one in-between, and with small receptive field the nervous system can more accurately resolve the spatial location of each stimulus.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="ab4b36b4746eb43c6926e78a04e9f1896">Being able to spatially discriminate means receptors are close enough to be stimulated at same time, but there is no “confusion” from overlapping receptor fields.</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
