<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="define_epsp_lbd"><title>define_epsp_LO</title><page id="page_0"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="define_epsp_lbd_0"><body><p id="abcace289c3b34054b7aeb7ade0bac7a3">What happens to a postsynaptic cell membrane if chloride channels open as a result of neurotransmitter binding?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="qsub_0" labels="false"><choice value="A">IPSP (inhibitory postsynaptic potential) is achieved</choice><choice value="B">EPSP (excitatory postsynaptic potential) occurs</choice><choice value="C">The cell membrane depolarizes</choice><choice value="D">The cell membrane repolarizes</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="define_epsp_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa411722c39dc4602bd6fc28c64100107">Correct. Chloride ions will diffuse into the cell and since they are negatively charged it will hyperpolarize the membrane causing an IPSP.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae3008497655846ea948f86c3f12a8cfc">Incorrect. EPSP will occur when positive ions, such as sodium, moves into the cell making it less negative.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aed2f1872248a4606a116d86f5343edfa">Incorrect. Depolarizing is the result of an EPSP when positive ions, such as sodium, moves into the cell making it less negative.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad8cbba292a1a401c8dba7483b969c587">Incorrect. Although the change in charge (more negative on inside of membrane) is the same, repolarization is the phase of returning to resting membrane after a depolarization not the result of a neurotransmitter binding to postsynaptic membrane.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="af0f2607234964ef5b899a37d15b17918">Negatively charged chloride ions are more concentrated outside the cell membrane and will follow their concentration gradient to diffuse across an open membrane channel.</p></hint></part></question><question id="define_epsp_lbd_1"><body><p id="ac1ca2fdb700548c6a66b49a2d9de6753">What type of summation achieves an action potential in a neuron resulting from simultaneous input of multiple other neurons?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="qsub_1" labels="false"><choice value="A">spatial summation</choice><choice value="B">multiple summation</choice><choice value="C">terminal summation</choice><choice value="D">temporal summation</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="explain_synapse_potential_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac25aa962b6bf4e7f8de883edb9d3f0c3">Correct. the input from Multiple neurons at different locations on the postsynaptic neuron with receptors can add up to cause an action potential.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aed8dac3ce6cb4db6a0b453799628c914">Incorrect. Even though this involves multiple stimulating neurons, this is not a physiological type of summation.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="af3964043a6ce451582b757007183b445">Incorrect. Even though this is happening between the axon terminal and its target, this is not a physiological type of summation.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac3f22bfac83d4f7a8f40a17f38c5b12a">Incorrect. Here the “adding” is being done over time at a single synapse, rather than from multiple neurons at one time.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="aaf67d1bd00d94be2b477a4fb105f68c1">One type of summation depends upon the location or “spacing” of several stimulating neurons at multiple synapses and the other depends on the “timing” of stimulation at a single synapse.</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
