<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="define_dermatome_DIGT1"><title>Tutor</title><page id="page_0"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="define_dermatome_DIGT1_0"><body><p id="aef3e27778ae3485fbe38f312f4204b7f">Shingles is a painful condition, often with skin rash, caused by the Varicella-zoster virus; the same virus that causes chicken pox. During the initial infection, some of the viruses moves into the dorsal roots of one or more spinal nerves and becomes dormant Later in life, the virus can reactivate, although the reason for this is not completely understood. The virus then travels back along one of the spinal nerves to the skin. It is most frequently seen extending from the back around to the front of the chest or upper abdomen on one side of the body. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Looking at the dermatomes, which spinal cord region would be involved in this kind of symptom?</p></body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" labels="false" select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">cervical</choice><choice value="B">thoracic</choice><choice value="C">lumbar</choice><choice value="D">sacral</choice><choice value="E">coccygeal</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="define_dermatome_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa0fa9b55a53e441a88eb7589c0d17a44">Incorrect. The dermatomes associated with cervical spinal nerves are on the back of head, neck, shoulder and upper arms.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aebc8fcdfdcf04788aff5ad6ba1d7745f">Correct. The dermatomes associated with thoracic spinal nerves are on the majority of the axial trunk.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab8e4f32a40c74e6a81d6c4729036592f">Incorrect. The dermatomes associated with lumbar spinal nerves are on a small portion of the lower back and around front side of leg.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aadee274d0cf84abeaa64b1890b49e7c4">Incorrect. The dermatomes associated with sacral spinal nerves are on the back of the leg and small region in groin.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab1bc8dd42dec4762ac0f1879c14dea67">Incorrect. The dermatomes associated with coccygeal spinal nerves are limited to small region in lower back.</p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
