<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="define_receptive_field_DIGT1"><title>Tutor</title><content><p>The difference in receptor distribution, receptive field and rate of adaptation for the four touch receptors will produce different sensations, depending on the stimuli. Both tactile corpuscles and tactile discs have small receptive fields. Both lamellar and bulbous corpuscles have large receptive fields. Remember that tactile and lamellar corpuscles are rapidly adapting receptors, such that they stop sending impulses with continued stimulation, but sending impulse quickly when new stimulus detected; while tactile discs and bulbous corpuscles are slowly adapting receptors continuing to send impulse for longer time with continuation of same stimulation. </p></content><question id="q1"><body>Which two receptors would be best at discriminating small differences in touch, such as detecting textures or shapes of objects?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="a">tactile and lamellar corpuscles </choice><choice value="b">lamellar and bulbous corpuscles</choice><choice value="c">tactile disc and tactile corpuscle </choice><choice value="d">tactile disc and bulbous corpuscles </choice></multiple_choice><part id="bf337bcbb73c47eaa3115d07a1a58458"><skillref idref="define_receptive_field_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Lamellar corpuscles would not be good at spatial discrimination because of their large receptive field.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because they each have large receptive fields, neither of these corpuscles would be good at spatial discrimination of sensations.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both of these have a small receptive fields which allows them to detect small differences in texture.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Bolbous corpuscles have large receptive fields so that are not goodat spatial discrimination.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which two receptors would be best at detecting changes in pressure or surface vibration over a large area?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="a">tactile and lamellar corpuscles</choice><choice value="b">lamellar and bulbous corpuscles</choice><choice value="c">tactile disc and tactile corpuscle</choice><choice value="d">tactile discs and bulbous corpuscles</choice></multiple_choice><part id="bd3f6cb550bf4899b5c791b46935bd6f"><skillref idref="define_receptive_field_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Tactile corpuscle are not good at detecting stimuli over a large area because of their small receptive field.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both of these have a large receptive fields so they will be able to detect stretch or pressure over a broad area.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because of their small receptive fields, these receptors are not good at detecting stimuli over a large area.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because the tactile disc has a small receptive field, it is not good at detecting stimuli over a large area.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Which two would be best at detecting rapid changes in touch caused by moving or dynamic stimuli?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="a">tactile and lamellar corpuscles</choice><choice value="b">lamellar and bulbous corpuscles</choice><choice value="c">tactile disc and tactile corpuscle</choice><choice value="d">tactile discs and bulbous corpuscles</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i6a3f6e2dac9a42f8be58a47d43276994"><skillref idref="define_receptive_field_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both of these are fast adapting receptors that will stop responding to continued stimulation, but will start responding again to changes in stimuli.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because bulbous corpuscles adapt slowly they are not good at detecting rapidly changing stimuli. </feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because tactile discs slowly adapt, they are not good at detecting rapidly changing stimuli.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because both of these slowly adapt, neither is good at detecting rapidly changing stimuli.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q4"><body>Which two would be best at detecting static or slow pressure changes, often related to proprioception?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="a">tactile and lamellar corpuscles</choice><choice value="b">lamellar and bulbous corpuscles</choice><choice value="c">tactile disc and tactile corpuscle</choice><choice value="d">tactile discs and bulbous corpuscles</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i8ad14381e6f84fc0b0d3c3b64a34cf03"><skillref idref="define_receptive_field_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because each of these receptors rapidly adapt, they will stop sending nerve impulses during static or slowly changing conditions. </feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because lamellar corpuscle rapidly adapt, they will stop sending nerve impulses during static or slowly changing conditions.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Because tactile corpuscles rapidly adapt, they will stop sending nerve impulses during static or slowly changing conditions.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Both of these are slowly adapting receptors and will continue to send sensory impulse during static conditions.</feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
