<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_pattern_innervation_LBD1"><title>tutor</title><question id="q1"><body><p>Axons of parasympathetic preganglionic neurons travel from the brainstem or from the lateral horn of sacral levels of the spinal cord to postganglionic neurons <input_ref input="q1_input1" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="q1_input1"><choice value="a">near or in target organs</choice><choice value="b">near the spinal vertebral column</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_parasymp_innervation_SKILL" /><response input="q1_input1" match="a" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Parasympathetic preganglionic neurons have long axons that project to the postganglionic neurons located locally near or within the target organ, gland, or tissue.</feedback></response><response input="q1_input1" match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Axons of preganglionic neurons in the parasympathetic nervous system travel relatively long distances to their target organs and tissues.</feedback></response><hint>Sympathetic preganglionic neurons have relatively short axons.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p>Axons of sympathetic preganglionic neurons travel to postganglionic neurons <input_ref input="q2_input1" /></p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="q2_input1"><choice value="a">near or in target organs</choice><choice value="b">near the spinal vertebral column</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="describe_sympath_innervation_SKILL" /><response input="q2_input1" match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Axons of preganglionic neurons in the sympathetic nervous system travel relatively short distances to their corresponding postganglionic neurons.</feedback></response><response input="q2_input1" match="b" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Sympathetic preganglionic neurons have relatively short axons that project to the postganglionic neurons located in sympathetic chain ganglia or collateral (prevertebral) ganglia located at some distance from the target organ, gland, or tissue.</feedback></response><hint>Sympathetic preganglionic neurons have relatively short axons.</hint></part></question></assessment>
