<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_neuron_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>Which part of the neuron has plasma membrane proteins that will initiate an action potential a long distance away toward its target, if the signal reaches a strong enough level called the threshold?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">axon</choice><choice value="B">cell body (soma)</choice><choice value="C">dendrite</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="describe_axon_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The axon hillock will initiate an action potential that travels away from cell body if threshold is reached.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This connects to and sends the electrical signals to this area.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is sending electrical signals to the cell body.</feedback></response><hint>This is a funnel-shaped part of the cell where one part of the neuron connects to another part.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body><p>Which part of the neuron has plasma membrane proteins that convert stimuli to electrical potential?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">axon</choice><choice value="B">cell body (soma)</choice><choice value="C">dendrite</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q2_p1"><skillref idref="describe_dendrite_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This sends electrical stimuli away from cell body.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This connects to and receives the electrical signals from this area.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This acts as the receptor for the cell, responding to some chemical or other stimuli and sending resulting electrical signal toward cell body.</feedback></response><hint>It is the part with increased surface area to allow better reception of this chemical message.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body><p>Which part of the neuron converts electrical potential to chemical stimuli for other neurons or target effector?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">axon</choice><choice value="B">cell body (soma)</choice><choice value="C">dendrite</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q3_p1"><skillref idref="describe_axon_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. At the axon synaptic terminal vesicles will release a chemical messenger across synapse in response to action potential reaching the axon terminal.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would not be at the “end” of the sequence along one neuron.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be at the “beginning” of the sequence along one neuron.</feedback></response><hint>This would happen at the “end” of the neuron that communicates with another neuron or its target across a space.</hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body><p>Which part of the neuron has most of the typical cellular organelles and the nucleus?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">axon</choice><choice value="B">cell body (soma)</choice><choice value="C">dendrite</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q4_p1"><skillref idref="describe_soma_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While sometimes very long, this part is relatively thin and specialized for propagating the action potential away from this part of the cell.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Even though it can receive input directly from other neurons, the cell body functions for cell metabolism and integration of signals for propagation if threshold is reached.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While this part can have a lot of surface area, this part is specialized for propagating the electrical signal toward this part of the cell.</feedback></response><hint>All parts have cytoplasm and some organelles, and material can move around within the cytoplasm, but one area has the nucleus and carries out majority of cellular metabolism.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
