<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="describe_brain_lbd"><title>describe_brain_lbd</title><page id="page_0"><question id="describe_brain_lbd_0"><body>In addition to meninges, fluid-filled spaces help protect the brain nervous tissue. The subarachnoid space would be found between which two meninges?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">dura mater and pia mater</choice><choice value="B">dura mater and arachnoid mater</choice><choice value="C">arachnoid and pia mater</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="describe_brain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There is another layer between these two.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be a subdural space.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The pia mater is internal, directly against the nervous tissue without a space and subarachnoid means it is below the arachnoid mater.</feedback></response><hint>Think of the order of meninges from outer to inner and review the meaning of “sub-“ as a prefix.</hint></part></question><question id="describe_brain_lbd_1"><body>Which of the following gray or white matter brain structures is correctly paired with its description?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">stellate cells: connect different parts within the same hemisphere</choice><choice value="B">projection tracts: receive sensory input and process information locally</choice><choice value="C">commissural tracts: connects right and left hemisphere</choice><choice value="D">association tracts: cells with unmyelinated connections within part of the CNS</choice><choice value="E">neocortex: tracts extending from higher to lower regions of the brain</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="describe_brain_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Gray matter stellate cells would be in gray matter and white matter tracts would connect different parts in the brain.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. White matter projection tracts would connect different parts in the brain and neurons in gray matter would have to receive and process information.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The large white matter corpus callosum is the main connection between two cerebral hemispheres, but there are also others.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Association tracts would be white matter within a hemisphere while gray matter pyramidal cells would extend to different parts of CNS.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The brain cortex would be gray matter with cells while white matter projection tracts would extend from higher to lower regions of the brain.</feedback></response><hint>The gray matter will include neuron cell bodies with synapses to other cells while the white matter appears white because it is made up of mainly myelinated neuron axons connecting different parts within the brain or between brain and spinal cord.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
