<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="explain_neurotransmitters_excite_lbd"><title>explain_neurotransmitters</title><page id="page_0"><question id="explain_neurotransmitters_excite_lbd_0"><body>How can a specific neurotransmitter, such as norepinephrine, excite one type of cell in the body causing increased metabolic activity, but inhibit another cell elsewhere in the body at the same time?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">by changing its chemical properties after it is released</choice><choice value="B">by binding to some effector cells but not others</choice><choice value="C">by binding only to excitatory receptors</choice><choice value="D">by binding only to inhibitory receptors</choice><choice value="E">by binding to receptors that cause different effect in cell</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="explain_neurotransmitters_excite_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The neurotransmitter may be degraded and reabsorbed, but doesn’t change its properties before binding to a receptor.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The neurotransmitter will bind to any cell near the release site that has the receptor for that neurotransmitter.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The neurotransmitter will bind to any cell near the release site that has the receptor for that neurotransmitter.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The neurotransmitter will bind to any cell near the release site that has the receptor for that neurotransmitter.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="10"><feedback>Correct. As with the muscarinic and nicotinic cholinergic receptors, there are different alpha and beta adrenergic receptors for norepinephrine on different effector cells and they can have either excitatory or inhibitory effects at the effector cell.</feedback></response><hint>The neurotransmitter can affect many different effector cells throughout the body, not just other neurons.</hint></part></question><question id="explain_neurotransmitters_excite_lbd_1"><body>What is the main physiological difference between fast and slow receptor response to a particular neurotransmitter?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">whether the receptor is on the cell membrane or inside the cell</choice><choice value="B">whether or not the cell has a receptor</choice><choice value="C">whether or not the receptor opens an ion channel or leads to a second messenger cascade</choice><choice value="D">whether or not there is a lot of neurotransmitter</choice><choice value="E">whether or not the post-synaptic cell is a neuron or other effector cell </choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="explain_neurotransmitters_fast_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some hormones may have receptors inside cells, but neurotransmitter receptors are all on the surface of the cell.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If a cell doesn’t have a receptor for that specific neurotransmitter, it will not be able to respond at all.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The ion channel will be quick change in membrane potential while the second messenger will cause a chemical reaction that eventually leads to membrane potential change.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The amount of neurotransmitter will not change the speed of post-synaptic cell response.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The neurotransmitter binding its receptor will influence a neuron or other effector cell in similar way.</feedback></response><hint>The neurotransmitter does not vary, so the process controlling speed or reaction must involve the post-synaptic cell.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
