<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="explain_adaptation_LBD1"><title>Tutor</title><question id="q1"><body>Which of the following is <em>not</em> an example of the physiological phenomena of adaptation?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="a">after putting on a shirt in the morning, you aren’t aware of the fabric against your skin most of the rest of the day </choice><choice value="b">after you have been in a room with scented candles burning for a while, you don’t smell the scent as strongly any more. But if the candles started a fire so that other things were burning, you would quickly detect that new smell </choice><choice value="c">when skin is being burned it hurts, but if the burn goes deep it stops hurting </choice><choice value="d">as you eat a spicy meal, the flavor may be intense initially and gets less noticeable as you eat more</choice></multiple_choice><part id="e4b069b430b84c2ca10c7027e1edde03"><skillref idref="explain_adaptation_SKILL" /><response match="a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an example of touch receptors adapting, sending fewer signals as long as the pressure of the fabric remains relatively constant.</feedback></response><response match="b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an example of olfactory receptor adaptation and only a change in odor will initiate more signals.</feedback></response><response match="c" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Nociceptors typically do not adapt; the reason a deep burn may stop hurting is because the receptors themselves have been damaged and can no longer send any signal.</feedback></response><response match="d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Taste receptors adapt rapidly, sending fewer signals with continued stimulation by a particular taste.</feedback></response><hint>Special sense receptors will also adapt similarly to some of these somatosensory receptors.</hint></part></question></assessment>
