<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="eye_muscles_DIGT1"><title>Tutor</title><page id="page_0"><content><p>The name of cranial nerve III is useful in remembering its function. All but two of the extraocular eye muscles are innervated by the oculomotor cranial nerve. Rather than trying to just memorize the other two specific ones, apply what you have learned earlier in Anatomy and Physiology.</p></content><question id="eye_muscles_DIGT1_0"><body>Cranial nerve IV innervates the muscle with a tendon that passes through a pulley-like structure superior and medial to the eye, allowing the oblique directional movement. What other previously studied skeletal structure had a pulley-like structure with the same name?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">radius</choice><choice value="B">scapula</choice><choice value="C">humerus</choice><choice value="D">ilium</choice><choice value="E">femur</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="eye_muscles_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This bone did not have a feature called the trochlea.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This bone did not have a feature called the trochlea.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The trochlea of the humerus articulated with the trochlear notch of the ulna to form the hinge elbow joint; remembering the trochlea is superior and medial will help associate the superior oblique with the trochlear cranial nerve.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This bone did not have a feature called the trochlea.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This bone did not have a feature called the trochlea.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="eye_muscles_DIGT1_1"><body>Cranial nerve VI innervates a muscle that moves the eye in the lateral direction, but both eyes cannot move in this direction at the same time. What directional term applies to this movement?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">rotate</choice><choice value="B">abduct</choice><choice value="C">depress</choice><choice value="D">adduct</choice><choice value="E">elevate</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="eye_muscles_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The two oblique muscles can move in direction other than up/down, right/left, but it isn’t rotating around the axis of the eye.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Remembering abducting the eye means moving away from midline will help associate the lateral rectus with the abducens cranial nerve.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be similar to looking down with the inferior rectus muscle.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be similar to moving toward the midline, or in this case crossing your eyes with the medial rectus and inferior oblique.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be similar to looking up with the superior rectus muscle.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
