<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<!--Created by OLI Author v3.0-->
<assessment id="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LBD3">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page id="page_0">
        <question id="identify_neurotransitters_preg_LBD3_0">
            <!--LO:identify_neurotransitters_preg_LO-->
            <body>The effects of the sympathetic nervous system are often more generalized and widespread than the effects of the parasympathetic nervous system (which tend to be more specific and localized).  How does the anatomy of the  sympathetic nervous system provide for more widespread effects?</body>
            <short_answer id="qsub_0"/>
            <part id="qpart_0">
                <response input="qsub_0" match="*" score="10"/>
                <hint>The farther a postganglionic fiber travels to the target, the more it can branch and diverge.</hint>
                <hint>The adrenal medulla is a modified sympathetic ganglion.  How does it exert its effects?</hint>
                <explanation>The sympathetic postganglionic fibers travel a long distance to their targets.  This allows the fibers to branch so that multiple target organs can be innervated by a single fiber.  In the parasympathetic nervous system, the ganglia occur near or within the target so there is very little divergence and a single fiber stimulates a single target.  Also, the adrenal medulla releases catecholamines (epinephrine and norepinephrine) to the bloodstream where they can travel throughout the body and exert an effect on any target that has a receptor.   The parasympathetic nervous system does not have a mechanism to release its neurotransmitter, acetylcholine, into the bloodstream.</explanation>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>