<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="name_exclusive_effectors_LBD1"><title>tutor</title><page id="page_0"><question id="name_exclusive_effectors_LBD1_0"><body>While most vasculature constricts with sympathetic input, vessels of the heart dilate. Why is this?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Blood vessels of the heart are made of a different type of tissue than other vasculature.</choice><choice value="B">Different neurotransmitters are released on the vessels of the heart than onto other blood vessels of the body.</choice><choice value="C">With the exception of blood vessels in the heart, other blood vessels are less pliable.</choice><choice value="D">Receptors for epinephrine/norepinephrine are different for vessels of the heart than for other vessels of the body.</choice><choice value="E">The epinephrine and norepinephrine released onto heart have different chemical structures than the epinephrine/norepinephrine released onto vasculature of other parts of the body.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="name_exclusive_effectors_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. All vascular tissue has the same constituents.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The neurotransmitter released onto vasculature of the heart by postganglionic sympathetic nervous system neurons is the same as the neurotransmitter released onto other blood vessels in the body by postganglionic sympathetic nervous system neurons.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood vessels do experience a degree of sympathetic tone due to exposure to an ongoing supply of neurotransmitter released by the sympathetic nervous system. The sympathetic tone situation is, however, different from the reason for the opposite responsiveness of heart and skeletal muscles and other blood vessels in the body to neurotransmitter release from the sympathetic nervous system neurons. The tone or pliability of blood vessels is not the reason for the opposite responsiveness of the vasculature in the heart.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The dominant adrenergic receptor subtype on blood vessels of the heart is the beta subtype. When beta-type adrenergic receptors are stimulated by norepinephrine/epinephrine, they dilate.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. All postganglionic neurons release norepinephrine and epinephrine that have known chemical structures and the chemical structure is the same as for norepinephrine and for epinephrine released at all synapses in the body.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what causes constriction and dilation.</hint><hint>Think about the effects of chemical transmission.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
