<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="spinal_tracts_lbd"><title>spinal_tracts_lbd</title><page id="page_0"><question id="spinal_tracts_lbd_0"><body><p>Which of the following is <em>not</em> correct about descending tracts of the spinal columns?</p></body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">carry motor signals</choice><choice value="B">are made of gray matter</choice><choice value="C">signals go to muscles</choice><choice value="D">signals go to glands</choice><choice value="E">signals move inferiorly</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="spinal_tracts_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is correct about the various descending tracts in the spinal columns; ascending tracts carry sensory signals.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. All tracts are white matter in the columns or funiculi of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is correct about descending tracts in the spinal column; they can go to skeletal, smooth or cardiac muscle.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is correct about descending tracts in the spinal column; ascending carry input from receptors to brain.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is correct about descending tracts coming from the brain; ascending tracts carry signals superiorly to brain.</feedback></response><hint>The ascending and descending tracts have different functions although found together in the anterior, posterior and lateral white columns.</hint></part></question><question id="spinal_tracts_lbd_1"><body><p>Which of the following would be a descending spinal tract?</p></body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">spinothalmic</choice><choice value="B">reticulospinal</choice><choice value="C">spinoreticular</choice><choice value="D">cuneate</choice><choice value="E">gracile</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="spinal_tracts_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is ascending carrying impulses to the thalamus of the brain.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This originates in the reticular region of the brain.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is ascending carrying impulses to the reticular region of the brain.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is sensory so ascending and ends in a gray matter area of the medulla oblongata.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is sensory so ascending, and ends in a gray matter area of the medulla oblongata.</feedback></response><hint>The name of the many of the tracts combines the origin and location, so the first part of a descending tract name would be part of the brain while the second part of an ascending tract would be a part of the brain. For other sensory tracts, the name describes its shape (e.g. cuneate means wedge and gracile means slender).</hint></part></question><question id="spinal_tracts_lbd_2"><body><p>The posterior root ganglion contains what?</p></body><multiple_choice id="qsub_2" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">first order sensory neurons</choice><choice value="B">second order sensory neurons</choice><choice value="C">upper motor neurons</choice><choice value="D">lower motor neurons</choice><choice value="E">sympathetic motor neurons</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_2"><skillref idref="spinal_structures_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. These unipolar neurons send sensory impulses from peripheral receptors to interneurons of the posterior horn.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These neuron cell bodies are located in the posterior horn of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These neuron cell bodies originate in the cerebrum or brainstem.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These neuron cell bodies are located in the anterior horn of the spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These cell bodies are located either in the lateral horn of the spinal cord or sympathetic ganglia.</feedback></response><hint>Ganglia contain neuron cell bodies outside the central nervous system.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
