<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="spinal_gross_digt"><title>spinal_gross_digt</title><page id="page_0"><question id="spinal_gross_digt_0"><body>Which of the following descriptions of the spinal cord gross anatomy is correct?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">It has enlargements in the cervical, thoracic and lumbar vertebrae regions.</choice><choice value="B">Its cauda equina includes spinal roots for lumbar, sacral and coccygeal nerves.</choice><choice value="C">Its medullary cone extends from the middle of the thoracic vertebrae.</choice><choice value="D">It passes from the formen magnum through the intervertebral foramen.</choice><choice value="E">It ends at the level of the fused vertebrae forming the sacrum.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="spinal_gross_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Thoracic spinal nerves arise individually, not from an enlargement.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Although they arise from spinal cord superior to conus medullaris, the roots extend within the vertebral foramen as the cauda equina.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The end of the spinal cord is more inferior, near the L1 vertebrae.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The spinal cord from the brain passes through the vertebral foramen of vertebrae; spinal nerves pass between two vertebrae to the periphery.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. It ends at the conus medullaris at the level near L1 vertebrae.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="question_1"><body>Which of the following descriptions of the spinal nerve gross anatomy is correct?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_1" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Spinal nerves arise from spinal cord and exit just inferior to associated vertebra.</choice><choice value="B">The first spinal nerve leaves between foramen magnum and atlas.</choice><choice value="C">Sacral spinal nerves originate at the cauda equina.</choice><choice value="D">Most spinal nerves leave the spinal cord through the vertebral foramen.</choice><choice value="E">The 12 pairs of spinal nerves are part of the central nervous system.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="spinal_gross_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is true for the thoracic nerves, but most of the cervical spinal nerves exit superior to the associated vertebrae because C1 exits between skull and first vertebrae, while lower spinal nerves exit inferior to the conus medullaris end of spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The foramen magnum is the opening in occipital bone for spinal cord and first cervical vertebrae is the atlas.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. All spinal nerves originate from the spinal cord, which ends at the conus medullaris; cauda equina is the spinal roots extension.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Most leave through the intervertebral foramen formed by a superior and inferior vertebrae, not the vertebral foramen formed by body, pedicles and spine of vertebrae that protects spinal cord.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There are 31 pairs of spinal nerves; both those 31 pairs and 12 pairs of cranial nerves are part of the peripheral nervous system.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
