<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="spinal_gross_lbd"><title>spinal_gross_lbd</title><page id="page_0"><question id="spinal_gross_lbd_0"><body>A portion of the pia mater, called the filum terminale, extends from the conus medullaris to the region of the sacrum and coccyx. This extension of the meninges supports what part of the central nervous system?</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">the spinal cord gray matter in the lumbar region</choice><choice value="B">the spinal cord white matter in the lumbar and sacral regions</choice><choice value="C">the spinal nerve roots and trunks in the vertebral foramen</choice><choice value="D">the lumbar spinal nerves passing through the intervertebral foramen</choice><choice value="E">the spinal nerve roots at the lumbar enlargement</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="spinal_gross_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would only be found superior to the conus medullaris because the spinal cord itself ends at L1 and is deep to the spinal cord white matter.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would only be found superior to the conus medullaris because the spinal cord itself ends at L1.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This supports the cauda equinus inferior to the conus medullaris within the vertebral column.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pia mater is contained within the vertebral foramen of vertebrae, not peripherally with through intervertebral foramen between vertebrae.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The lumbar enlargement is found at the level of the inferior thoracic vertebrae, still superior to the conus medullaris.</feedback></response><hint>The conus medullaris is the terminus of the spinal cord near vertebrae L1.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
