<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="synapse_cells_lbd"><title>synapse_cells_lbd</title><page id="page_0"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="synapse_cells_lbd_0"><body><p id="abdbaf4958e5042abb5a884333ba3bf30">Let’s examine a neural pathway that involved three (3) neurons in sequence: one propagates an action potential from threshold stimulus of receptor to spinal cord; second propagates action potential superiorly to brain stem; and third propagates action potential from brain stem to part of cerebral cortex involved in perceiving the stimulus. Which of the following is correct classification of these neurons?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="qsub_0" labels="false"><choice value="A">all three are presynaptic</choice><choice value="B">first is presynaptic, other two are postsynaptic</choice><choice value="C">first and second are presynaptic, third is postsynaptic</choice><choice value="D">first and second are presynaptic, second and third are postsynaptic</choice><choice value="E">all three are postsynaptic</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="synapse_cells_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae098bfc58ee7422fae079f251a6800b3">Incorrect. The last in sequence would not be presynaptic unless you followed it to yet another neuron beyond this example.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="acbadb0c5f9d5428eb3153d71c62e4a6e">Incorrect. This is correct but not complete because one neuron can be classified as both in this pathway.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="accced3003ef6480e9efdfc4286313c8b">Incorrect. This is correct but not complete because one neuron can be classified as both in this pathway.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="aed6b147feab34503b8a70b1ae31efb5c">Correct. The second is postsynaptic to the first, but then becomes presynaptic to the third neuron in this sequence.</p></feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa979dda2ad0d42d89b9a7f44ad3898b4">Incorrect. The first neuron would not be postsynaptic if it directly detected stimulus or was associated with a specialized non-neuron receptor.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="aa9c34d8a3988430599b7ae9e1bae1554">Even though the pathway will continue, likely involving many more neurons, for this example only consider the signal transmission from receptor to higher brain perception and classify these three neurons in this specific sequence.</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
