<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Lactose Permease" movieroot="">
    <step stepURL="swfs/introduction.swf" menustep=" Introduction ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The Escherichia coli lactose permease is an example of secondary active transport (Campbell, p. 210). This enzyme is similar in structure to others in the major facilitator superfamily (MFS) of transporters.  More than 1000 examples of MFS transporters have been identified in the genomes of bacteria, plants, and animals.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mec.swf" menustep="Lactose Permease Mechanism: ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Lactose permease (lacY gene product) is a b-galactoside-H+ symporter.  The high H+ concentration in the E. coli periplasm is used to drive the transport of lactose into the cell against its concentration gradient.  The proton gradient is generated by the oxidation of substrates via the proton pumping of the electron transport chain.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/a1.swf" menustep="       Lac Permease structure  ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The enzyme, in its substrate-free form is shown in cross-section with the periplasm at the top of the diagram.  The cavity between the N- and C- terminal domains contain the substrate and H+ binding sites.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/a2.swf" menustep="       Proton Binds  ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Proton binding to a glutamic acid sidechain in the C- terminal domain (-COO-) is the first step.  The carboxyl group of this Glu residue is in a hydrophobic environment making this protonation energetically favorable (pKa ~ 7.0). &lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/a3.swf" menustep="       Lactose Binds ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Substrate binding is the second step. The sugar binds primarily to residues in the N- terminal domain at the bottom of the cavity, roughly halfway between the bilayer boundaries.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/b1.swf" menustep="       Structural Change ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Substrate binding also triggers a major conformation change: The periplasmic opening closes and the cavity appears on the cytoplasmic side, i.e. the opening switches to the other side, but the protein, itself, does not "flip" across the membrane&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/b2.swf" menustep="       Lactose Dissociates ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The disaccharide substrate dissociates into the cytoplasm where it will be hydrolyzed (by b-galactosidase) and used for energy production or other metabolic purposes.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/b3.swf" menustep="       Proton Dissociates  ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The H+ dissociates after the substrate.  This too is a spontaneous reaction because the conformation change has also made the environment of the Glu side chain  more polar, lowering its pKa.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/c1.swf" menustep="       Return to Start ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;In the absence of substrate and H+ in the active site, the permease is more stable in its original state.  Hence, the reverse of the major conformation change returns the protein to its starting conformation for another cycle of lactose-H+ symport.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
</TUTORIAL>