<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u7_m1_Integ_system_01">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <objref idref="integument_function"/>

    </head>

    <body>
        <p>Every time you look in the mirror, you get a glimpse of one of the body’s most essential
            and dynamic systems: the integumentary system. The integumentary system is made up of
            the skin and its accessory structures, and it is responsible for much more than simply
            lending you your outward appearance. In the adult human body, the skin makes up about 16
            percent of the body weight and covers an area of 1.5 to 2 square meters. In fact, the
            skin and its accessory structures make up the largest organ system in human anatomy.
            While we do not typically think of the skin as an organ, it is made up of tissues that
            come together as a single structure to perform unique and critical functions. This unit
            will introduce you to the structures and functions of the integumentary system, and will
            describe diseases, disorders, and injuries that can affect the integumentary system.</p>

        <section>
            <title>Major Functions of the Integumentary System</title>
            <body>
                <p>The skin and its accessory structures perform a variety of essential functions,
                    such as protecting the body from environmental elements and the invasion of
                    microorganisms, acting as sensory mechanisms, and modulating body temperature.
                    Skin also has other functions, including maintaining electrolyte balance,
                    synthesizing vitamin D, storing lipids and fats for energy, and excreting
                    toxins. </p>

                <p>The skin protects the rest of the body from the basic elements of nature like
                    wind, water, and radiation from the sun. It acts as a protective barrier against
                    water loss due to the presence of keratin in cells and oils secreted to the
                    surface, which make it naturally water resistant. It also is the first line of
                    defense against mechanical abrasion and irritation caused by contact with
                    parasites or harmful chemicals. Sweat excreted from sweat glands deters microbes
                    from thriving on the skin surface by generating
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121114T170825-0500" comment="Please verify that spelling is correct without the &quot;i&quot; that I deleted."?>dermcidin<?oxy_comment_end?>,
                    which has antibiotic properties. Sweat also helps with thermoregulation by
                    cooling the body. </p>
                <wb:inline idref="_u7_m1_integument_examp_inline01" purpose="didigetthis"/>

            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Common Dysfunctions of the Integumentary System</title>
            <body>
                <p>
                    <em>Skin cancer</em> – Cancers are most common in epithelial tissues because of
                    several issues: they may contain stem cells which have high mitotic rates,  and
                    are most vulnerable to DNA damage during mitosis. Also, epidermal epithelial
                    cells are exposed to UV radiation and other environmental factors since they
                    interface with the environment. The stratum basale, one epithelial layer found
                    in the skin, can be the source of skin cancers such as basal cell carcinomas. </p>

                <p>
                    <em>Burns</em> – The skin acts as a barrier to the environment. Thermal,
                    chemical and radiation burn traumas that destroy the skin tissue often lead to
                    infections because of the loss of the skin's barrier function.</p>

                <p>
                    <em>Bedsores</em> – Also called
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121114T175147-0500" comment="spelling with &quot;u&quot; seems more common online. OK?"?>decubitus<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    ulcers, these sores develop when regions of the skin start dying because
                    constant pressure limits blood flow to that region of the skin. </p>

                <p><em>Psoriasis and acne</em> – There are many skin conditions that are caused by a
                    dysfunction of normal integumentary processes. The overproduction of skin cells
                    results in psoriasis, and acne is caused by an infected or clogged sebaceous
                    gland.</p>

                <p><em>Calluses and scars</em> – Like many systems of the body, the integumentary
                    system is able to adapt to its external environment. Calluses are thickened skin
                    that accumulates in areas of continued mechanical abrasion. Scars are caused by
                    excess fibrous tissue being deposited when repairs are made to cuts in the skin. </p>

                <p>These conditions and more will be covered as you learn about normal function of
                    the integumentary system.</p>

                <wb:inline idref="integument_diseases_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

            </body>
        </section>



    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
