<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u7_m1_Integ_system_02">
    <head>
        <title>Common Dysfunctions of the Integumentary System</title>
        <objref idref="integument_diseases"/>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            <em>Skin cancer</em> – Cancers are most common in epithelial tissues because of several
            issues: stem cells in stratum basale have high mitotic rates like all epithelia; cells
            are most vulnerable to DNA damage during mitosis. Also, epidermal epithelial cells are
            exposed to UV radiation and other environmental factors since they interface with the
            environment. </p>

        <p>
            <em>Burns</em> – The skin acts as a barrier to the environment. Thermal, chemical and
            radiation burn traumas that destroy the skin tissue often lead to infections because of
            the loss of barrier function.</p>

        <p>
            <em>Bedsores</em> – Also called decubitis ulcers, these sores develop when regions of
            the skin start dying because constant pressure limits blood flow to that region of the
            skin. </p>

        <p><em>Psoriasis and acne</em> – There are many skin conditions which are caused by a
            dysfunction of normal integumentary processes. The overproduction of skin cells
            resulting in psoriasis and acne is caused by an infected or clogged sebaceous gland. </p>

        <p><em>Calluses and scars</em> – Like many systems of the body, the integumentary system is
            able to adapt to its external environment; calluses are thickened skin which accumulates
            in areas of continued mechanical abrasion; scars are caused by excess fibrous tissue
            being deposited when repairs are made to cuts in the skin </p>

        <p>We will cover these conditions and more as we discuss normal function of the
            integumentary system.</p>



    </body>

</workbook_page>
