<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="integintro_3">
	<head>
		<title>The Integumentary System and Homeostasis</title>
		<objref idref="_u7_homeo_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Let’s check out the integumentary system in action in the following case study.</p>
		<p>You and your friend, Tori, are baking cookies. It’s the end of the semester and you both
			have been craving chocolate chip goodness. While the cookies are in the oven, you and
			Tori decide to study your anatomy and physiology. You are currently studying the
			integumentary system. The timer goes off and Tori jumps up, very excited, grabs a dish
			towel and pulls the cookie sheet out of the over. “OW!” Tori yells – as she drops the
			cookie sheet onto the table. “I just burned my hand on the cookie sheet”.</p>
		<p>You reply, “Quick, rinse it under cold water, I think that is supposed to stop the
			burn.”</p>
		<p>“It really hurts!” Tori exclaims while running her hand under the cool water from the
			faucet.</p>
		<p>“Let me see your hand” you tell Tori.</p>
		<p>When she shows you, you notice a couple blisters beginning to form on her fingers and
			palm. “I think you burned through your epidermis layer and maybe to the dermis. Don’t
			blisters mean you have a second degree burn?” you ask her.</p>
		<p>“What does that mean?” Tori asks. “Should I go to that prompt care place?”</p>
		<p>“Let’s look it up, I think if you keep it clean you will be ok. There are several layers
			of cells in the epidermis, aren’t there?” you ask. “Our textbook says if the skin
			blisters it is a sign of a second degree burn. These burns don’t typically damage the
			lower layer, the dermis.”</p>
		<p>“It’s a good thing it didn’t burn through the dermis, then I would be more prone to other
			infections, wouldn’t I? Didn’t we read about the skin protecting us from microbes around
			us?” Tori asks?</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u7_homeo_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
	<!--	<p>LBD: Tori mentions that the skin protects us from microbes, how do you think it
			accomplishes this?</p>
		<p>Hint: The skin is a very complex organ that is critical for protection and for
			survival.</p>
		<p>a. The skin is a covering that keeps things out of our body.</p>
		<p>incorrect – This is true, but there additional methods the skin uses to protect us.</p>
		<p>b. The skin secretes chemicals such as sweat and oils that form an antiseptic layer.</p>
		<p>incorrect – True, but there are other ways the skin protects besides the chemical
			layer</p>
		<p>c. The skin protects us from dehydration and drying out.</p>
		<p>correct – True, but there are more ways the skin protects</p>
		<p>d. All of the above are ways the skin protects us.</p>
		<p>Correct: Good job, as you can see, the skin has several methods of protecting the
			body.</p>-->
		<p>The integumentary system is vital for our body’s homeostasis. As we saw with Tori, the
			skin is an important barrier for protection. If the skin is damaged from a burn, or
			torn, it opens up an entry point for microbes to enter our body. This is why we always
			wear protective gloves when handling body fluids. The gloves protect us in case there
			are any openings in our skin. It’s better to be extra cautious about this. Our epidermis
			is multi-layered to make it better suited for protection. If Tori’s burn had penetrated
			deeper it also would have increased fluid loss and dehydration. The skin functions as a
			cover to keep interstitial fluids inside rather than seeping out. Every day we lose a
			small amount of water through our skin and our lungs from breathing. This water loss is
			termed insensible perspiration and is accelerated when in dry air. Our cells in the
			epidermis produce a protein known as keratin that helps to decrease water loss from our
			skin. If skin becomes dry, it cracks and creates an opening in our defenses. When you
			think of maintaining homeostasis, protection is probably one of the first processes you
			think of and the skin is vital for this.</p>
		<p>The integumentary system is also crucial for body temperature regulation. When we are too
			warm, blood vessels going to the skin open up (vasodilate) and more blood flows to the
			surface of the skin to release heat to cool the body. Our skin turns pink or red when
			this happens. If body temperature continues to rise, our sweat glands become active and
			we sweat to cool off (this is termed sensible perspiration). When we are cold, the blood
			vessels shrink (vasoconstrict) to decrease blood flow, and consequently heat loss, from
			our skin. Our skin might turn blue from the decrease in blood flow. We also have a layer
			of body hair covering our body which insulates and helps us retain heat. It’s a good
			idea to wear a hat when in cold weather to reduce heat loss from our head!</p>
		<p>Another function of the skin, isn’t commonly known. The skin produces vitamin D in
			response to sunlight or UV radiation. Vitamin D is a very important vitamin, it’s
			crucial for calcium absorption from our food, and has recently been shown to have
			anti-cancer properties. If our vitamin D levels fall, this could impact our skeletal
			system by decreasing the absorption of calcium, and consequently the amount that gets to
			our bones.</p>
		<p>Our skin is also tied into our nervous system. One of our main senses – touch is
			dependent on numerous receptors located in our skin. We can feel and process information
			regarding pressure, temperature, light touch, and pain through our skin. If Tori didn’t
			feel pain when she touched the hot cookie sheet, she wouldn’t have dropped it to reduce
			the damage from the heat.</p>
		<p>Clearly, the integumentary system is more involved in our functioning than a clear skin
		and gorgeous hair!</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u7_homeo_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<!--<p>LBD: Now that you’ve read a little more about the integumentary system and Tori, what do
			you think are the main concerns from a burn?</p>
		<p>Hint: think about the functions of the skin as outlined above.</p>
		<p>a. The skin might not be repaired and the area will be a weak spot for infection.</p>
		<p>incorrect – the epidermis layer of the skin (top layer), heals fairly quickly.</p>
		<p>b. The loss of sense of touch and areas vital for the formation of vitamin D from a
			burn.</p>
		<p>incorrect – Not in Tori’s case. Her epidermis will completely heal. There is a large
			surface area of skin on the body for vitamin D production.</p>
		<p>c. In severe burns the body is more susceptible to invasion from microbes and might
			dehydrate faster from fluid loss.</p>
		<p>correct – Yes, good job. The skin covers to protect us from invasion but also keeps
			fluids inside our body.</p>-->
	</body>
</workbook_page>
