<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="integintro_5">
	<head>
		<title>The Components of the Integumentary System </title>
		<objref idref="_u7_components_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The integumentary system is composed not only of the skin, but also nails, glands, and hair.
			The most numerous component of the integumentary system is the integument or skin. The
			skin contains the superficial epidermis, which consists of epithelial tissue, and the
			deeper dermis which is formed from dense irregular connective tissue. The epidermis
			contains nerve endings for pain, which is why Tori felt the pain of the burn. The
			epidermis is avascular, which means it doesn’t have blood capillaries. Nutrients get to
			the epidermis from the vascular dermal layer. Only those cells closest to the dermis are
			able to receive the nutrients and these cells have rapid mitotic rates. The cells in the
			epidermis migrate to the surface, and then are shed daily. They are constantly being
			replaced by the cells deeper. The dermis contains the blood vessels, sweat and oil
			glands. The dermis also has receptors for touch. Below the dermis is the hypodermis
			layer. This is the fatty layer that anchors the skin to your body. The hypodermis is
			technically not part of the integumentary system.</p>
		<p>The skin also contains sweat and oil (sebaceous) glands. Sweat glands release sensible
			perspiration to cool us when we overheat. Sweat is mostly water but also contains
			electrolytes and a waste product known as urea. Urea is one of the main components of
			urine too! Sebaceous glands produce oil, otherwise known as sebum. Sebum and sweat form
			a chemical barrier on our skin to decrease bacterial growth on our skin.</p>
		<p>Hair and nails are additional structures associated with the integumentary system. Body
			hair takes up space to compete with pathogens for room on our skin. Body hair also
			insulates us. Did you know that there are approximately 100,000 hairs on your head and
			30,000 in a man’s beard? Fingernails and toenails provide leverage and protection when
			we grab and manipulate objects.</p>
		<p>The epidermis contains the pigment melanin, which protects our cells from UV radiation.
			Melanin is also responsible for our hair, skin and eye color. Keratin was previously
			mentioned and is important for decreasing water loss from our skin. Many skin lotions
			contain keratin to prevent dry skin. Another important protein is collagen. Collagen
			provides strength to our skin. Collagen has a white appearance and often when the skin
			heals extra collagen is placed at the site. Sometimes this results in a white scar.</p>
		<p>When you study the integumentary system, you will learn about the chemical and cellular
			components which work together to maintain the integrity of the system. As consumers, we
			spend a lot of money on products meant to make our skin and hair look better, younger,
			and healthier. As you read through this topic, think about whether those products really
			can make a difference or if they are just the result of well-played marketing
			campaigns!</p>
		<wb:inline idref="_u7_components_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
	<!--	<p>LBD:</p>
		<p>T or F The dermis layer is the most superficial layer of the skin.</p>
		<p>Hint: The name of the layer gives information regarding its location.</p>
		<p>T: incorrect, no the dermis is not the superficial (top) layer of the skin.</p>
		<p>F: correct, the epidermis is the most superficial layer of the skin.</p>
		<p>Which of the following is not part of the integumentary system?</p>
		<p>Hint – This question is a little tricky, but only one structure below is not technically
			part of the integumentary system.</p>
		<p>a. dermis</p>
		<p>incorrect: The dermis is one of the main structures of the skin. It contains the blood
			vessels which provide nutrients to the cells of the epidermis.</p>
		<p>b. hair</p>
		<p>incorrect: hairs are located all over our body and are structures in the integumentary
			system.</p>
		<p>c. sebaceous glands</p>
		<p>incorrect: sebaceous glands produce sebum or oil which helps to lubricate hair and form a
			chemical barrier on our epidermis</p>
		<p>d. hypodermis</p>
		<p>correct: the hypodermis is below the dermis and not considered part of the integumentary
			system</p>
		<p>Which of the following functions to prevent water loss from the skin?</p>
		<p>HINT: This protein is a main ingredient in body lotions.</p>
		<p>a. collagen: Incorrect: Collagen is a structurally important component of the skin and
			maintains the integrity of the skin.</p>
		<p>b. keratin correct – keratin is made and released from cells of the epidermis and forms a
			barrier to decrease water loss from the skin.</p>
		<p>c. melanin: incorrect – melanin is an important pigment that protects the cells from UV
			radiation.</p>
		<p>d. vitamin D: incorrect – vitamin D is made in the skin but functions for calcium
			absorption and protects us from various cancers.</p>-->
	</body>
</workbook_page>
