<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="integ_unit_review"><head><title>Integumentary System Unit Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="be615dfcb4724e4384cb92d427899c7a">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="b623cd2c4ce54ead90f4d53248af01ad"><li><p id="af1f0ac33a5dd4820aa9cd9a3db9ff5f4">Describe the general functions of the integumentary system.</p></li><li><p id="ad55c5064951446119ad6d972c7d343e2">Describe the main function of each layer of the integumentary system.</p></li><li><p id="ea3bf060cc0f466994f27a29cbaae92d">Describe in order from simplest to most complex the major levels of organization of the integumentary system.</p></li><li><p id="b8e835883de04b759d5a182d577c25c2">Describe how the molecular assembly of keratins provides strength to integumentary tissues.</p></li><li><p id="ab2b68eed53684b88bb0ecc41719895e9">Describe the function of melanin and discuss the consequences of reduced melanin.</p></li><li><p id="aa92b09ea35fd40b5b2954b3a7bdb7e76">Describe the function of vitamin D and the production of vitamin D, and discuss the consequences of reduced vitamin D.</p></li><li><p id="bc553d7416e94e7b86be7a6684e82935">Identify the cells of the epidermis based on their location and anatomic structure (stem cells of the stratum basale, keratinocytes, melanocytes, Langerhans cells, Merkel cells).</p></li><li><p id="bdba39ce4af64e58bc7f29eadd3449ed">Describe the complementary functioning of the cells of the epidermis.</p></li><li><p id="abbd629d772d946ac919627333fbaf3ea">Describe the differences between the three categories of skin cancer.</p></li><li><p id="aa4a3519efe214557bf650d76bd3baf43">Identify the pertinent cells of the epidermis, dermis and hypodermis.</p></li><li><p id="af5dfd2dd11da45ff9a1eaf805cb14b16">Identify the tissue type making up the epidermis.</p></li><li><p id="ab6e3de120fe44a7b8fb89c5ba92866d3">Explain how wrinkles and stretch marks are related to the collagen and elastin fibers in the dermis.</p></li><li><p id="bacbae81421543ebb2dae790b2282ce5">Describe the role of melanocytes in producing skin pigmentation and also protecting mitotic cells in the stratum basale from UV damage.</p></li><li><p id="ab3c54374324844e9a1cc8a18015b9309">Describe the functions of melanocytes.</p></li><li><p id="ae021126f6879452abd13b07260afe1fe">Describe sunscreen and UVA and UVB radiation.</p></li><li><p id="af66856c6d3c94638ad03ed64558e352d">Identify and describe the layers of the epidermis, indicating which are found in thin skin and which are found in thick skin.</p></li><li><p id="c150bc3ac5cd4a94aeaacbbc1a225493">Explain why the histology of the epidermis is well-suited for its functions.</p></li><li><p id="ad03f2b463bd64196aef5859cfe87a1f8">Describe the functions of the epidermis.</p></li><li><p id="acc71c15eec2046cd91c6de3b3c8c245c">Describe the two different layers of the dermis.</p></li><li><p id="c6fe34ea92a043faa6c1eeb3db05dc28">Explain why the histology of the dermis is well-suited for its functions.</p></li><li><p id="aaca4b737f5fe4c8da928c3b83c2f0e03">Identify and describe the subcutaneous tissue, including the tissue types making up subcutaneous tissue.</p></li><li><p id="e77e98f05cf84930abc9f7f8565d34bc">Explain why the histology of the subcutaneous layer is well-suited for its functions.</p></li><li><p id="b36bfc55ff404541a8fe8d77da7b2f02">Describe how the distribution of adipose tissue differs based on gender,age, diet and exercise.</p></li><li><p id="affc18bdcb2994106973651d64bed3480">Describe the general structure and function of accessory structures of the integumentary system.</p></li><li><p id="e04b07ba27714da8a2f9b746af2ec39d">Describe the structure of hair and of a hair follicle.</p></li><li><p id="aad1f27f02a0e46adb4a451df4e186b25">Describe four functions of hair.</p></li><li><p id="afc1aacd27b6b4dbc8a76eafbe49ba81f">Describe the four stages of hair growth.</p></li><li><p id="ad6f52738b98140b5825108881209e1ea">Explain common causes of hair loss.</p></li><li><p id="aaf0917deb12844928619b8c2c691ea6b">Describe the structure and function of the nail.</p></li><li><p id="a01f041a5b8749a5b2a249bc335b1428">Contrast the structure and function of eccrine glands, apocrine glands and sebaceous glands</p></li><li><p id="ae5bc65afd1c34860a86983f9d396b164">Describe the cells involved in repairing damaged skin.</p></li><li><p id="ac1d45d99ecbc4780a110cb232099c9ee">Compare homeostasis of cell number and mitotic rate in the epidermis with pathological conditions including psoriasis and skin cancer.</p></li><li><p id="c0bfe66550db429aab0adb8fff548a58">Describe the effect of scarring on the regeneration of accessory structures.</p></li><li><p id="dcedd2f049b5457180af2747cc97e192">Predict issues related to loss of skin in burn victims for first-, second- and third-degree burns.</p></li><li><p id="adfcf8cd0726c43459cdd09c21eb2e0fd">Explain changes in the integumentary system that occur because of puberty and advanced age.</p></li><li><p id="b9612de6c607438cbbbfaafec9389361">Compare thermoregulation by the integumentary system as it pertains to subcutaneous fat, hair, sweat and blood flow.</p></li><li><p id="adf2cd6881d884b2d9b956672de7dfa31">Describe different sensory receptors located in the integumentary system.</p></li><li><p id="adb74b574e1b344fbb5027d0b76775896">Describe how a medical professional can use changes in the appearance of the skin to predict certain medical conditions.</p></li></ul><activity idref="u7_endofunitquiz" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="integumentary_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
