<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u7_m3_review"><head><title>Integumentary Homeostasis Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="a044377fd785443c8c8e52782c1a80e9">Keratin is a group of fibrous proteins that give hair, nails, and skin their tough, water-resistant properties. Melanin is a class of photopigment (&quot;photo,&quot; meaning &quot;light,&quot; and &quot;pigment,&quot; meaning &quot;colored material&quot;) with a molecular structure that allows it to absorb UV (ultraviolet) radiation from the sun. The epidermal layer of human skin synthesizes the precursor to vitamin D when exposed to UV radiation, which is s essential for general immunity against bacterial, viral and fungal infections.</p><p id="aff7331a00b04984927ea138f2880d4e">Cancer in general is initiated because of DNA damage that accumulates in a particular cell over time. Exposure to UV rays from the sun can ultimately lead to mutations in the genomes of various skin cells. Accumulation of genetic mutations over a period of time, in addition to other possible causes, can trigger cells to grow out of control. Basal cell carcinoma is caused by mutations that lead to lack of control over the growth of stem cells located in the stratum basale. It is the most common form of all cancers that occur in the United States.</p><p id="f86ebe7c86ca42d3adfecf1cbd34796d">The epidermis (or epithelial layer) is made up of four or five distinct layers (strata), depending on the region of the body. From deep to superficial, they are named the stratum basale, stratum spinosum, stratum granulosum, stratum lucidum, and stratum corneum. The thickness of thick skin is a function of the four upper layers of the epidermis.</p><p id="f6b0cd35465b4ce1957efec1cd290826">Accessory structures of the skin include hair, nails, sweat glands, and sebaceous glands. Although these structures appear to be part of the dermis, they are actually derived from the epidermis. trands of hair originate from the base of the downward extension of living epithelial cells into the dermis that is called the hair follicle. Hair serves a variety of functions. For example, hair on the head protects it from the sun and from heat loss; and hair in the nose and ears and around the eyes (eyelashes) defends the body by trapping dust particles that may contain allergens and microbes.</p><activity idref="_u7_homeostasis_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
