<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u9_m2_review"><head><title>Cardiovascular Structures and Functions Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="eb5f4dc32bc24ec0bacf73526256972d">The heart pumps continuously to provide tissues and organs with needed oxygen and remove cellular waste materials. The heart’s ability to generate its own beat is an intrinsic quality. Inside the superior wall of the right atrium a group of specialized cells called the sinoatrial (SA) node spontaneously depolarize, creating a signal that passes to the atria and the ventricles, causing their contraction.Because of this intrinsic quality, the heart is said to have automaticity, meaning it is able to self-generate a beat. </p><p id="a59e85c889744a7caa446f5f120b6f76">The electrocardiogram, also called an ECG or EKG, measures the electrical activity associated with the heart.The resultant waveform consists of P, QRS, and T waves. These deflection waves are indicative of the depolarization electrical activity just before the contraction of the atria (P wave), the depolarization electrical activity stimulating ventricular contraction (QRS complex), and repolarization of ventricles prior to relaxation (T wave). ECG tracings can provide information about the anatomy and placement of the heart in the chest cavity. It provides information about the size of the chambers and the rhythm of contraction. Importantly, ECGs are used to detect changes that have occurred in heart function.The cardiac cycle can be divided into two distinct phases, diastole and systole. During diastole, the muscles are relaxed and the chambers fill passively with blood. Systole is when the heart muscles contract. Atrial systole helps fill the ventricles while ventricular systole is responsible for pushing the blood into the pulmonary artery and aorta.</p><p id="cd2bc267e34d48b090c82200cc71a7b5">Cardiac output is one measure of the heart&apos;s efficiency. It is the amount of blood pumped per minute. Heart rate fluctuations are one way for the body to adjust the cardiac output so that it can appropriately meet the demands of the body. Cardiac output is the product of heart rate (beats per minute) and stroke volume (volume of pumped blood per beat). If the cardiac output is a function of heart rate times the stroke volume, then as the heart rate increases, so does the cardiac output. At least this is true up to a point. At very high heart rates the heart may not have time to fill appropriately during diastole, which can actually decrease cardiac output. </p><p id="a77493243bfd43f699391e4205104684">Blood pressure (BP) refers to the force per unit area that blood exerts on a vessel wall. It is measured in millimeters of mercury (mmHg). The highest arterial pressure achieved during systole is called the systolic blood pressure. The lowest arterial pressure reached during diastole is the diastolic blood pressure. The pressure of blood steadily decreases as blood travels farther and farther away from the left ventricle.Resistance refers to the factors that oppose the flow of blood. Resistance is caused by friction as blood moves through a vessel. The resistance to blood flow as it moves from the aorta to the vena cavae is known as total peripheral (i.e., systemic) resistance. </p><p id="d53fa054c5184193ac2db8804e7d5896">The ultimate goal of the cardiovascular and respiratory systems is to deliver oxygen-rich and nutrient-rich blood to the capillary networks. Although the amount of blood within the capillaries at any given time is only about 5 percent of the total volume, it is the most important blood in the body. It is at the level of the capillaries that capillary exchange occurs. The thin and porous construction of capillary walls provides an avenue for substances such as oxygen and glucose to move out of the blood plasma and into the interstitial fluids surrounding the tissue cells. The reverse process, uptake of substances such as carbon dioxide and wastes from the interstitial fluids into the plasma, occurs simultaneously.</p><activity idref="_u9_cardio_structure_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
