<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_5c">
    <head>
        <title>Organic Components of Bone</title>
       <!-- <objref idref="skeletal_levels"/>-->
        <objref idref="skeletal_levels_mols_b"/>
    </head>
    <body>  
        
        <p>You can think of the hydroxyapatite in bones as being similar to concrete. The
            chemical structure of hydroxyapatite gives it a high mechanical strength under
            compression (squeezing force), but little strength under tension (pulling force). If our
            bones were made only of hydroxyapatite, they would be very fragile, like concrete. They
            would break easily under tension. The organic components of bone help to give it
            additional strength and flexibility. </p>
        <p>Collagen, a ropelike, fibrous protein, is the major organic component of bone.
            Like rope, collagen has significant mechanical strength under tension. Therefore,
            collagen provides tensile strength to the bones. The spiral arrangement of collagen in
            combination with its ECM (extracellular matrix) components, such as water and
            specialized proteins, also makes bone more elastic and less brittle, so that it can
            absorb shock more easily.</p>
        <p>Bone matrix is a network of collagen fibers and hydroxyapatite. It is strong
            under both tension and compression. Furthermore, the collagen contributes to its
            ability to absorb sudden forces without breaking.</p>
        
        <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_sf_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        
        <p>Collagens are a class of fibrous proteins found in bone, cartilage, and other
            connective tissues. The primary structure of collagen has repeats of glycine-proline-X,
            where X can be any other amino acid. This repeated arrangement gives collagen a unique
            helical secondary structure. The
            terti<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111215T164005-0500" comment="There&apos;s already a lot of &quot;terms&quot; here, so I&apos;ve added these parentheticals -- do you think they&apos;re superfluous? I don&apos;t want to treat the students like they&apos;re idiots, but at the same time, I don&apos;t want to lose anyone just because of fancy words for three and four, ... and some students are international, which could make the meaning of these words less obvious (or in some cases more obvious, depending on where the students are from)."?>ary
            structure of collagen is a triple helix fibril, which further twists into a quaternary
            str<?oxy_comment_end?>ucture of a collagen fiber. The resulting "twisted, twisted,
            twist" is similar to the higher-ordered structures in rope.</p>
            <p>Type I collagen is the primary form of collagen found in bone. The collagen fibers in
            bone are approximately 300 nanometers long, and are arranged in a staggered pattern.
            During bone formation, the collagen fiber matrix is deposited first. Proteoglycans are a
            second class of organic components found in bone.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111215T164822-0500" comment="Lots of big words here -- should this be eplained more simply/toned down?"?>Proteoglycans
            are macromolecules composed of proteins with negatively charged glycosylated
            modifications. <?oxy_comment_end?>There are a number of proteoglycans, which are
            classified by the type of side chains on the core protein. The side chains on the
            proteoglycans are linear carbohydrates. As with cartilage, the presence of the
            negatively charged proteoglycans contributes to the resilience of the tissue and
            retention of water within the matrix. Proteoglycans also bind and release molecules for
            cell signaling.</p>
        <wb:inline idref="skeletal_levels_mols_b_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
      
    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
