<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_7d">
    <head>
        <title>Fractures</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_levels_fractures"/>
    </head>

            <body>

                        <p>The microscale structure of a bone gives it significant strength and rigidity,
                            but extreme forces can cause bones to break, or <term>fracture</term>.
                            The table below describes the most common types of fractures.</p>
                        <table>
                            <title>Common Types of Fractures</title>
                            <tr>
                                <th>Type of fracture</th>
                                <th>Description</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Simple fracture</em> (also called a closed
                        fracture)</td>
                                
                                <td>A fracture in which a bone breaks completely, but the broken
                    ends do not penetrate the skin</td>
                                
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Compound fracture</em> (also called an <em
                        style="bold">open fracture</em>)</td>
                                <td>A fracture in which the ends of the broken bone break through
                    the skin</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Comminuted</em>
                    <em style="bold">fracture</em></td>
                                <td>A fracture in which the bone is shattered or broken into several
                    pieces</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Greenstick</em>
                    <em style="bold">fracture</em></td>
                                <td>A fracture that occurs in children when one side of a bone
                    breaks, and the other side bends</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Impacted</em>
                    <em style="bold">fracture</em></td>
                                <td>A fracture in which one end of the fractured bone is forced into
                    the interior of the other end</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td><em style="bold">Stress fracture</em></td>
                                <td>A set of tiny fractures or fissures in a bone caused by repeated
                    stress on the bone</td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>
                        <p>A bone fracture affects the bone on several levels of organization. A fracture
                            involves a physical break in the mineral structure of the bone. Fractures
                            typically cause blood vessels in the bone to rupture, reducing the blood flow to
                            the bone tissue. As a result, some of the cells in the surrounding bone die.
                            These dead cells and the related cellular debris are removed by immune cells and
                            osteoclasts. Over time, various cell types—fibroblasts, chondroblasts, and
                            osteoblasts—work together to repair the mineralized bone tissue.</p>
                        <p>Fractures weaken bone, making it less able to perform its functions of
            support and protection, although once healed, the site of the fracture is stronger than
            the remaining bone. A fracture may cause a change in the shape of the bone. If that
            happens, then the way the bone responds to a contracted muscle may change. As a result,
            fractures can prevent bones from moving correctly when muscles pull on them.</p>
                        <p>There are pain receptors and nerves in the bone. The pain experienced when a
                            fractured bone moves is one way the body reacts to help itself heal. Bones heal
                            more quickly and thoroughly if they are kept immobilized (which is why the
                            typical treatment for a broken bone is to put it in a cast or other restraint).
                            Because we instinctively avoid actions that cause pain, the pain that occurs
                            when a broken bone is moved causes us to minimize the movement of that bone.
                            This, in turn, helps keep the bone stable while it heals. </p>
                        <p>Severe fractures, such as compound fractures or comminuted fractures, can cause
                            long-term or permanent disruptions to the body's homeostasis. Because a compound
                            fracture breaks through the skin, bacteria and other pathogens can enter the
                            body after a compound fracture. Those pathogens can enter the bone, blood,
                            muscles, or other tissues or organs, causing severe infection. Severe fractures
                            are also less likely to heal correctly without medical (typically surgical)
                            intervention. Improperly healed fractures can cause changes in the bone's
                            reaction to force, leading to changes in body motion (such as a limp).</p>
                        <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_fracture_inline" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                
                
    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
