<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_5d">
    <head>
        <title>Organic and Inorganic Combination</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_levels_mols_b"/>
        <objref idref="skeletal_levels_mols"/>
    </head>
    <body>  
                <p><?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111215T165606-0500" comment="This portion of this paragraph is repeated in file skeletal _5b"?>Mineralization
            of the bone matrix occurs when calcium, phosphate, and water from the extracellular
            fluids combine to form insoluble hydroxyapatite. The hydroxyapatite incorporates into
            the small pores within collagen fibrils and crystallizes into long, thin, nanosized
            plates within the collagen network. The incorporation of hydroxyapatite within the
            collagen fibers contributes to the overall compressive strength of bone.
            <?oxy_comment_end?>Within the bone matrix, the minerals, water, collagens, and
            proteoglycans function together to provide strength in tension and compression.
            Additionally, this unique environment binds and releases chemicals into the
            extracellular fluids for use throughout the body.</p>
                <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_scurvy_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
                <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_io_inline" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <example>
                    <title/>
                    <p><em style="bold">Osteogenesis imperfecta</em> (from <em style="italic">osteo</em><em
                    style="italic">-</em>, meaning bone, and <em style="italic">genesis</em>,
                meaning production or beginning) is a congenital (genetic) disorder that affects the
                structure and strength of bones. The condition is primarily caused by genetic
                mutations that affect the structure and/or quantity of type I collagen produced by
                the body. Remember that collagen is an important component of the extracellular
                matrix of bone tissue. In people with osteogenesis imperfecta, the lack of collagen
                (or presence of defective collagen) prevents the extracellular matrix from forming
                correctly. The mineral structure of the bone is weakened, and as a result, the bones
                are unusually brittle.</p>
                    <p>The bones of people with osteogenesis imperfecta break extremely easily,
                sometimes with only small amounts of pressure. The bones' brittleness reduces their
                ability to support and protect the body. They also typically take longer to heal and
                may be more prone to infection.</p>
                    <p>Bones become stronger and thicker when they are exposed to regular stress.
                        Conversely, bones that do not experience regular stress may lose extracellular
                        matrix and become less dense. In a person with osteogenesis imperfecta, bones
                        that break often (and therefore spend a lot of time immobilized in casts or
                        restraints) are exposed to much less stress. As a result, they may lose even
                        more extracellular matrix and become even more brittle.</p>
                </example>
                
                
                
                <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_osteo_inline" purpose="didigetthis"/>
      
    </body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
