<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="skeletal_5"><head><title>Molecules and Macromolecules</title><objref idref="skeletal_levels_mols" /><objref idref="skeletal_levels_mols_b" /></head><body><p id="fb6ec666ad854a9dad2909ab2e5f12a8">The major components of bone tissue at the molecular scale are minerals, water, collagen, and other proteins. At the next level of organization, small crystals of hydroxyapatite made of calcium and phosphate are embedded within collagen fibers to produce a composite (blended) material with high compressive and tensile strength.</p><p id="ee2f9fa8ddf7464db55f9ce297a11018">The skeletal system protects and supports vital organs, allows our body to move, stores important minerals, and produces blood cells. There are several chemical elements and molecules required to maintain the many functions of the skeletal system. The chemical properties of these components support bone structure and function. On a chemical level, bone is divided into inorganic and organic (carbon-containing) components.</p><p id="aabd00e3d8834d6c9fc6b575cc2fcb7c">The primary inorganic components of bone are:</p><ul id="e221f86f7cc8474fa650642f437961ce"><li><p id="aab003ebd97744438d68c86f244555b9"><em style="bold">calcium</em>, which is required for many functions throughout the body;</p></li><li><p id="b778dcd56b004d45b9c2570fa1c95664"><em style="bold">phosphorus</em> (in the form of phosphate ions), which is a component of buffer systems and energy-rich molecules; and</p></li><li><p id="f4f2cdd565ad45619fc211d6084e6425"><em style="bold">water</em>, which contributes to the compressive resistance of bone and contributes to the fluid matrix of bone.</p></li></ul><p id="e01c6055b5024d74a7163def2d930b23">The primary organic components of bone are:</p><ul id="df8c8ee8638f445896102d9e9f16e5ff"><li><p id="dedcec809fe34e63b9e2e6707f0555c1"><term>collagen</term>, the major structural protein (type I in bone and type II in cartilage); and</p></li><li><p id="c8ad032c84ca4f028891487dbe8dcca6"><term>proteoglycans</term>, which are negatively charged glycosylated proteins (glycosylated means having carbohydrate sugar groups modifying the protein).</p></li></ul><p id="aa80d81bb4da45e285cc48c3bb9ff054">Bone is approximately 60 to 70 percent inorganic mineral and 10 percent water by weight. The remaining 20 to 30 percent of bone is organic matrix (osteoid), such as collagen and proteoglycans. Your body contains 1 to 2 kilograms of calcium and nearly 600 grams of phosphorous. Nearly 99 percent of the calcium and 86 percent of the phosphorous is stored in your bones.</p></body></workbook_page>
