<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_5b">
    <head>
        <title>Inorganic Components of Bone</title>
        <!-- <objref idref="skeletal_levels"/>-->
        <objref idref="skeletal_levels_mols"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>Calcium ions (Ca<sup>2+</sup>) are stored in bone tissue, but can be released into the
            bloodstream when blood levels fall below optimal. Blood calcium is important for muscle
            contractions, nerve impulses, and blood clotting.</p>
        <p>In bone, phosphorous (P) is found in the form of phosphate ions
            (H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>). Outside of bone, phosphorous plays roles in energy
            storage (such as in ATP), and is required for the formation of DNA and RNA. Therefore,
            it is required for cellular growth, maintenance, and tissue repair. </p>
        <p>When combined with hydrogen, phosphorous forms dihydrogen phosphate ions
                (H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>). Dihydrogen phosphate acts as a buffer to maintain a
            constant pH balance by acting as either a hydrogen ion donor (acid) or a hydrogen ion
            acceptor (base). In all cells, a constant pH must be maintained to carry out cell
            functions. </p>
        <p>As mentioned in previous sections, hydroxyapatite is an inorganic calcium phosphate
            mineral that is a primary component of bone. Crystal hydroxyapatite has the chemical
            formula: Ca<sub>10</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>6</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>. </p>
        <p>During bone formation, the collagen fiber matrix is formed. Next, mineralization of the
            matrix occurs when calcium, phosphate, and water from the extracellular fluids combine
            to form insoluble hydroxyapatite. The hydroxyapatite incorporates into the small pores
            within collagen fibrils and crystallizes into long, thin, nanosized plates within the
            collagen network. The incorporation of hydroxyapatite within the collagen fibers
            contributes to the overall compressive strength of bone. Because the crystals are
            nanosized, they have a large surface area. The large surface area of the crystals makes
            it easy to release ions into the extracellular fluids when blood levels decrease.</p>
        <p>Sometimes bones contain fluoride. Fluoride is similar to the hydroxyl ion in charge and
            size. When fluoride replaces the hydroxyl ion in hydroxyapatite crystals, it forms
            fluoroapatite. Fluoroapatite is a more compact and less soluble crystal than
            hydroxyapatite. Therefore, ion exchange at the crystal surface is slower. The primary
            role of fluoride in bone is to strengthen bone mineral.</p>
        <p>Water is an important molecular component of bone matrix. Water is initially present in
            the spaces within the collagen matrix of the unmineralized bone extracellular matrix
            (osteoid). As crystals fill in the spaces between collagen fibrils, the bone is
            mineralized and the water is displaced. The water that remains in bone after this
            process is complete forms hydrogen bonds with polar, hydrophilic components of collagen.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111215T161638-0500" comment="Wow! That&apos;s a lot of 25-cent words in a row. (And there are quite a few earlier in this paragraph, as well.) If this concept is key to overall understanding, or if it will be &quot;on the test,&quot; I recommend that this paragraph, and particularly this sentence, be explained in friendlier language. "?>Water
            also assists with the compressive resistance of bone due to osmotic interactions caused
            by negatively charged proteoglycans.<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
        <p>In addition to calcium, phosphorous, water, and fluoride, the inorganic parts of bone
            also contain sodium, potassium, carbonate, and magnesium. Although these molecules do
            not form their own crystals, they are bound to hydroxyapatite crystals within bone
            mineral.</p>
        <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_calcium_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="skeletal_levels_mols_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>



    </body>
</workbook_page>
