<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd"><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="skeletal_6">
    <head>
        <title>Extracellular Matrix in Bone</title>
        <objref idref="skeletal_levels_cell"/>
    </head>

    <body>

                <p>You have already learned about the hydroxyapatite and collagen combination, which
            is responsible for giving bones their rigidity. The skeletal system is an excellent
            example of a system that is primarily composed of extracellular matrix. Generally, cells
            of the body function within a matrix to hold them together. In the case of bone, the
            extracellular matrix (ECM) is composed of crystals of hydroxyapatite and long collagen
            proteins. The hydroxyapatite and collagen work together to give bone its unique
            properties of strength, compressive resistance, and flexibility.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Cells in Bone</title>
            <body>
                <p>The previous section described the importance of the bone matrix components
                    calcium and hydroxyapatite in maintaining bone rigidity. However, bone
                    remodeling is equally important to maintaining bone health. Throughout your
                    lifetime, your bones are constantly remodeled and repaired. There are three main
                    cell types in bone, which maintain bone balance and strength:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li><extra>
                            <anchor><term>osteoclasts</term></anchor>
                            <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/osteoclasts.mp3"
                                type="audio/mp3"/>
                        </extra>, which break down and reabsorb bone;</li>
                    <li><extra>
                            <anchor><term>osteoblasts</term></anchor>
                            <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/osteoblasts.mp3"
                                type="audio/mp3"/>
                        </extra>, which deposit and build new bone; and</li>
                    <li><extra>
                            <anchor><term>osteocytes</term></anchor>
                            <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/osteocytes.mp3"
                                type="audio/mp3"/>
                        </extra>, which are mature bone cells that act as sensors for repair.</li>
                </ul>
                <p>Think of the bones of your body as a rapidly expanding city. When the old
                    buildings get outdated, they are either remodeled to make enhancements or
                    knocked down to make room for the new ones. As soon as a building is knocked
                    down, a new one is erected in its place. The construction crew recycles the old
                    building materials. Many city planners constantly monitor the building progress
                    and talk with one another about which sections of the city will get the
                    available resources.</p>
                <p>Osteoclasts secrete an acid that dissolves the inorganic components of bone:
                    calcium and phosphate. Osteoclasts also contain enzymes that digest the organic
                    components of the bone matrix, such as the proteins and proteoglycans. Bone
                    resorption (osteolysis) is complete when small cavities remain on the bone
                    surface. Osteoclast activity is important for creating the medullary cavities of
                    diaphyses, which house bone marrow. (Remember that the diaphysis is the main
                    shaft of a long bone.) Osteoclasts are important for removing calcium from bones
                    if the blood calcium levels fall, such as when a diet is deficient in calcium.
                    Remember calcium is critical for life and if levels fall, it could be fatal if
                    it wasn't taken from the bones. </p>
                <p>Osteoblasts build bone and fill in the cavities created by osteoclasts.
                    Osteoblast cells secrete osteoid (the organic portion of the bone matrix) around
                    them, and then mineralize the matrix to generate rigid bone tissue. Bone
                    mineralization occurs through osteoblast secretion of an enzyme called alkaline
                    phosphatase. Alkaline phosphatase cleaves phosphate groups to provide the
                    necessary phosphate for building hydroxyapatite. Osteoblasts are stimulated when
                    blood calcium levels increase. The excess calcium is deposited into the bones
                    for storage.</p>
              
                <p>After bone mineralization, osteoblasts trapped within the matrix differentiate
                    into osteocytes. Osteocytes have long processes
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20111216T101954-0500" comment="addition OK?"?>(outgrowths
                    or protrusions) fo<?oxy_comment_end?>r connection to other osteocytes within the
                    bone. This arrangement allows osteocytes to act as mechanical sensors.
                    Osteocytes sense mechanical strain within bone and regulate the activity of
                    osteoblasts or osteoclasts, depending on needs for calcium and phosphate. To
                    maintain bone strength, bone resorption and bone deposition must be in constant
                    balance with each other.</p>
                
                <wb:inline idref="_u5_levels_city_inline" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
                <wb:inline idref="skeletal_levels_cell_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            </body>
        </section>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
