<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u5_m2_review"><head><title>Skeletal Levels of Organization Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="ee7598ed8d2b44b6a274002939e76ddc">The major components of bone tissue at the molecular scale are minerals, water, collagen, and other proteins. At the next level of organization, small crystals of hydroxyapatite made of calcium and phosphate are embedded within collagen fibers to produce a composite (blended) material with high compressive and tensile strength. The primary inorganic components of bone are calcium, phosphorus and water. The primary organic components of bone are collagen and proteoglycans. During bone formation, the collagen fiber matrix is deposited first.</p><p id="fe87299c139d4b4bad3dd92e126f4df5">While the bone matrix components calcium and hydroxyapatite are important in maintaining bone rigidity, bone remodeling is equally important to maintaining bone health. There are three main cell types in bone, which maintain bone balance and strength:</p><ul id="e98be709eca740668db53e330cd6d7c4"><li><p id="aa91a4d9290714b2384a8cec416c90e28">osteoclasts, which break down and reabsorb bone</p></li><li><p id="aea065df483f0425f97f33f40e5fc41e8">osteoblasts, which deposit and build new bone</p></li><li><p id="afcbfb43074b54d69a68eddda3935620e">osteocytes, which are mature bone cells that act as sensors for repair</p></li></ul><p id="e9c3a3d69eb54a8abfaa5f782eb210fc">Bones form in two ways. A process known as intramembranous ossification forms bones that develop from layers of connective tissue. Flat bones such as those found in the skull develop through this process. Endochondral ossification (from the word roots endo-, meaning &quot;within,&quot; and chondral, meaning &quot;cartilage&quot;) is bone formation from a hyaline cartilage blueprint or template, which determines the future bone shape.</p><p id="c4c2c2012ce147ccb16d4edac015af3c">After bone formation, bone resorption and bone deposition occur continually in a process called bone remodeling to allow for skeletal response to mechanical use, nutritional status and as part of the bone repair and healing process. In the absence of malnutrition or disease, this process maintains homeostasis of both total bone mass and inorganic substances such as calcium and phosphate.</p><activity idref="_u5_skeletal_levels_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
