<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_pancreas_tt_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>Look at the two feedback loops, above, regulating blood glucose associated with the pancreas. Which type of homeostasis feedback is involved in these two examples?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">positive</choice><choice value="B">negative</choice></multiple_choice><part id="a72236e02e754979a9dd61c1a2b3d83c"><skillref idref="endo_pancreas_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The initiation event and result would have to be the same because this would cause more of the same stimulus.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The result is opposite, which stops the initial stimulus and release of the hormone.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Which cells of the pancreas are involved in this plasma glucose homeostasis?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">acini and beta</choice><choice value="B">alpha and beta</choice><choice value="C">beta and delta</choice><choice value="D">alpha and F (PP) cells</choice></multiple_choice><part id="df6ce61c27aa4af7a2037d8f25487345"><skillref idref="endo_pancreas_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Acini cells are the exocrine cells producing enzymes and bicarbonate ions.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Alpha produces glucagon and beta produces insulin.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Delta cells secrete the paracrine somatostatin.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. F or PP cells secrete the paracrine pancreatic polypeptide.</feedback></response><hint>These are NOT the exocrine cells around the ducts.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Most body cells have receptors for insulin; they have even recently been discovered on brain cells. But glucagon target cells are more specific, being involved in the metabolic processes that produce glucose for release back into the blood. Which of the following would you predict would be effector cells for glucagon?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">adipocytes and erythrocytes</choice><choice value="B">hepatocytes and neurons</choice><choice value="C">skeletal muscle fibers and epithelial cells</choice><choice value="D">hepatocytes and adipocytes</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i800416a9de7a4d0b9120d070ee396d7d"><skillref idref="endo_pancreas_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Erythrocytes without a nucleus and limited metabolism would not be involved in this metabolic response to increase blood glucose even though found in blood.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Neurons depend upon constant supply of glucose and would not be involved in the release to blood.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. These would take up glucose and muscle even stores glycogen, but would not be involved in the release to blood.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The main target is liver, but even adipose cells can indirectly be involved in glucose conservation by providing alternative fuel to body cells.</feedback></response><hint>These cells would have to accomplish the effects depicted in the feedback loop.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
