<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_parathyroid_tt_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Explain the difference between the three major effectors in these feedback loops: kidney reabsorption, bone resorption, and intestine absorption.</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="i6fe80e0373e9499ca2f87f051918d49a"><skillref idref="endo_parathyroid_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>Reabsorption refers to absorbing something that has been filtered; the kidneys are moving calcium from the filtered plasma back into the blood to conserve calcium, or it is lost from the body in urine. Resorption refers to remodeling by lysis; the osteoclasts are dissolving the calcium phosphate (hydroxyapatite) bone matrix to release minerals into the blood, thereby remodeling the bone structure. Absorption refers to bringing into the body from outside, so calcium is absorbed from food into the intestinal cells and then into blood for transport through body.</explanation></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Explain the physiological mechanism that connects kidney stone formation to hyperparathyroidism.</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="e5890faf95794503aca967a9246ef57e"><skillref idref="endo_parathyroid_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>Under the influence of increased PTH, the kidney tubule cells would not reabsorb calcium ions, so the level of blood would return to homeostatic levels, but a side-effect is increased calcium in the filtrate for excretion with urine. This excess calcium in the nephron tubules and kidney tubes can crystalize to form one of the common kidney stones that block tubes, damage tissue and cause pain.</explanation></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Explain the physiological mechanism that connects osteoporosis to hyperparathyroidism.</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="i52cfbcb3068647ba935e0d2eeb1ed1c9"><skillref idref="endo_parathyroid_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>Under the influence of increased PTH, the osteoclasts become more active and no longer balanced with osteoblast bone deposition for normal homeostatic bone remodeling. The level of calcium in blood is maintained homeostatically for normal function of nerves and muscle, but the bone matrix has lost calcium and can become thin and brittle.</explanation></part></question><question id="q4"><body>What hormone(s) are produced by the parathyroid glands?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">ATCH</choice><choice value="B">ADH</choice><choice value="C">LH</choice><choice value="D">PTH</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i82212f4f86e24380b0c47b19a34332cb"><skillref idref="endo_parathyroid_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Adrenocorticotropic hormone is secreted by the anterior pituitary.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Antidiuretic hormone is released by the posterior pituitary.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Luteinizing hormone is secreted by the anterior pituitary.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Parathyroid hormone (PTH) is secreted by the parathyroid gland.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
