<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_3.dtd">
<!--Created by OLI Author v2.0-->
<assessment id="endo_parathyroid_tt_lbd">
    <title>tutor</title>
    <page>
        <question id="q1">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>
                
                <p>Which type of homeostasis feedback is involved in these two examples?</p></body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">positive</choice>
                <choice value="B">negative</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The initiation event and result would have to be the same
                        because this would cause more of the same stimulus.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. The result is opposite, which stops the initial stimulus and
                        release of the hormone.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>Compare the initiation event and the result from stimulating the different
                    target organs. Notice the two examples have opposite initiation events and
                    effects, but each brings the level back within homeostatic range.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="q2">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>Which cells of the thyroid gland are involved in this plasma calcium ion
                homeostasis?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">parathyroid cells</choice>
                <choice value="B">parafollicular cells</choice>
                <choice value="C">interstitial cells</choice>
                <choice value="D">paracrine cells</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Be careful not to confuse these cells of a different gland
                        because it also includes the prefix “para”.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. These C cells are located between the follicles of the
                        thyroid gland.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. These cells are in-between the tubules where sperm formation
                        occurs in testes.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. These cells secrete a hormone-like chemical that only affects
                        near cells.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>These are <em>not</em> the epithelial cells forming the follicle around the colloid for
                    T3 &amp; T4 production inside the thyroid gland.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="q3">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>Which cells of the parathyroid gland are involved in this plasma calcium ion
                homeostasis?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">C cells</choice>
                <choice value="B">beta cells</choice>
                <choice value="C">chief cells</choice>
                <choice value="D">oxyphil cells</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. These are located between the follicles of the thyroid gland
                        and produce calcitonin.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. These are located in the pancreas and produce
                        insulin.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. These cells produce PTH in response to falling plasma calcium
                        levels.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The function of these cells in the parathyroid gland is not
                        fully understood, but they don’t produce PTH.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>This is the “primary” but not only type of cell found in this endocrine
                    gland.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="q4">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>Which of the following cells would <em>not</em> have receptors for calcitonin and
                PTH?</body>
            <multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single">
                <choice value="A">kidney cells of the nephron tubule</choice>
                <choice value="B">stomach cells</choice>
                <choice value="C">osteoclasts of bone</choice>
                <choice value="D">intestine cells</choice>
            </multiple_choice>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Calcitonin-receptor complex inhibits these cells from
                        reabsorbing calcium from the filtrate so it is excreted in urine, while
                        PTH-receptor complex stimulates these cells to reabsorb calcium increasing
                        blood calcium levels.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. Neither hormone has any effect on the gastric digestion,
                        although food is one source of calcium in the blood.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Calcitonin-receptor complex prevents them from dissolving the
                        bone matrix, while PTH-receptor complex stimulates matrix resportion
                        releasing calcium into blood.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Calcitonin-receptor complex inhibits calcium absorption, while
                        PTH-receptor complex works with vitamin D to increase calcium absorption
                        from food into blood.</feedback>
                </response>
                <hint>The hormones will only cause the resulting metabolic change in cells with
                    specific receptor for that hormone. The cell will have receptors for both
                    hormones, so the opposite responses will be determined by which hormone is being
                    secreted and binding to the receptor at that time.</hint>
            </part>
        </question>
        <question id="q5">
            <!--LO:-->
            <body>While the indirect effect of both calcitonin and PTH on osteoblasts is still being
                studied, what would be the expected effect of each hormone?</body>
            <short_answer id="A"/>
            <part>
                <response input="A" match="*" score="10"/>
                <hint>Similar to the effect on osteoclasts, their effects would be opposite, one
                    stimulating and other inhibiting; but the end result of the specific hormone
                    would stay the same.</hint>
                <explanation>Calcitonin would stimulate osteoblast activity to deposit more bone
                    matrix, removing it from the blood. PTH would inhibit osteoblasts so they don’t
                    remove the blood calcium being conserved by the kidney and absorbed by the
                    intestine.</explanation>
            </part>
        </question>
    </page>
</assessment>
