<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_LOO_stimuli_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>No matter which homeostatic feedback loop is diagrammed, they all include a stimulus that changes to initiate and provide feedback to the control center. Click the correct types of stimuli involved in the feedback homeostatic regulation of hormone production for each characteristic or situation below (check all that apply):</p><p>Involves some kind of chemical stimulating the release of hormone into blood:</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">humoral</choice><choice value="B">tropic hormonal</choice><choice value="C">neural</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i0a13ce2f7d454e5d90c37962e306512b"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_stim_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Typically the chemical is a solute or ion in body fluids that stimulates a chemoreceptor, often located in the endocrine gland to stimulate hormone production.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hormone is the chemical messenger binding to its specific target cell receptor in another endocrine gland, stimulating it to produce another different hormone.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The neurotransmitter doesn’t travel far but still binds to its specific receptor to stimulate the release of a hormone into the blood.</feedback></response><hint>All three types of stimuli will affect some kind of receptor.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Would stimulate the quickest release of endocrine hormone.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">humoral</choice><choice value="B">tropic hormonal</choice><choice value="C">neural</choice></multiple_choice><part id="cf7d6205b06048feb8ccfb7ab5310164"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_stim_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The changing solute or ion would need to circulate to contact the sensor.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The hormone needs to circulate in the blood to reach the other endocrine gland.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The neuron releases its neurotransmitter directly at the gland it is stimulating.</feedback></response><hint>All three types of stimuli will affect some kind of receptor.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>Would be the slowest to stimulate the release of endocrine hormone.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">humoral</choice><choice value="B">tropic hormonal</choice><choice value="C">neural</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i162f5e2bb3894cbcabd32843f0b57b92"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_stim_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. While it would take a while, the gland can respond as soon as the change has been detected.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Something has to first stimulate the endocrine gland producing the tropic hormone that, in turn, stimulates the target endocrine gland to produce its hormone.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The endocrine gland would be stimulated quickly by nervous stimulation.</feedback></response><hint>All three types of stimuli will affect some kind of receptor.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q4"><body>Homeostatic mechanisms stimulated by changes in body fluid composition (humoral) often involve more than one hormone in a negative feedback loop. Why would this be typical? For example: insulin decreases blood glucose while glucagon increases blood glucose; parathyroid hormone increases blood calcium levels while calcitonin from thyroid decreases blood calcium in children.</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="i10e5198c97fb4b79860f4b568ed7d94a"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_stim_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>Stimulating opposite responses to maintain body fluid homeostasis will need to involve different target cells and metabolic responses. Because each hormone has a specific receptor and specific effect on its target cells, it will take different hormones to maintain this humoral component within homeostatic range. As it increases, it would stimulate release of one hormone but not the other; as it decreases, it would stimulate release of the other hormone.</explanation></part></question></page></assessment>
