<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_intracellular_recep_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Which of the following is correctly matched?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Steroid hormones bind to a nuclear receptor. Thyroid hormones bind to a cytoplasmic receptor.</choice><choice value="B">Steroid hormones bind to a cytoplasmic receptor. Thyroid hormones bins to a nuclear receptor.</choice><choice value="C">Steroid hormones bind to an intracellular receptor. Thyroid hormones bind to a plasma membrane receptor.</choice><choice value="D">Steroid hormones bind to a plasma membrane receptor. Thyroid hormones bind to an intracellular receptor.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i011f15feb0e746f294f6fe8c241ac286"><skillref idref="endo_intracellular_recep_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Steroid hormones bind to a receptor in the cytoplasm and the resulting complex stimulates the DNA; thyroid hormones bind to intracellular but not cytoplasmic receptors.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Steroid hormones bind to a cytoplasmic receptor forming a complex that then stimulates transcription and thyroid hormones bind to nuclear receptors that inhibit transcription until hormone binds.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Steroid hormones do bind to an intracellular receptor in the cytoplasm, but so do thyroid hormones.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Both of these hormones bind to some kind of intracellular receptors.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="q2"><body>Peptide hormones must bind to a plasma membrane hormone receptor because:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">They are small</choice><choice value="B">They are too big</choice><choice value="C">They are polar</choice><choice value="D">They are nonpolar</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i9988814fc7d24828b3b0b2cefb8db8f0"><skillref idref="endo_intracellular_recep_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some peptide hormones may be small but it is not their size that keeps them from passing through the membrane.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some peptide hormones may be large but it is not their size that keeps them from passing through the membrane.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. They are polar meaning they will not be able to pass through the nonpolar portion of the plasma membrane.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. They are polar meaning they will not be able to pass through the nonpolar portion of the plasma membrane.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
