<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_LOO_hormones_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Using this diagram to illustrate the child birth example, which letter on this positive feedback loop image would represent the release of the hormone oxytocin? <image src="../webcontent/birth_rate_diagram.png" /></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">A</choice><choice value="B">B</choice><choice value="C">C</choice><choice value="D">D</choice><choice value="E">E</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i179978834a6a4cd69b1c83fe5c5ff296"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_loops_SKILL" /><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The initial mechanical stimulus from the baby would this part.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be stretch of the cervix, whether initial event or continued because of positive feedback effect.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The receptors use nerve action potentials to communicate with the control center.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The hormone is released by the control center and travels in the blood to the cervix effector to stimulate more smooth muscle contraction.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would be continued stretch of the cervix because of the positive feedback effect</feedback></response><hint>The hormone is the chemical message that is being released in response to the stimulus; other communication would be neural between sensor and control center.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>In this diagram for oxytocin, what type of receptor would be involved in this positive feedback loop?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">photoreceptor</choice><choice value="B">chemoreceptor</choice><choice value="C">mechanoreceptor</choice><choice value="D">thermoreceptor</choice></multiple_choice><part id="dbf94a6df56c49d69f3d86ebc6ef82e3"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_loops_SKILL" /><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The only photoreceptors in humans are located in the retina of the eye.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The receptor is not responding to the hormone chemical; instead the stretching is stimulating the release of a chemical that causes a change in the effector.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The mechanoreceptors detect the push of the fetus against the cervix and uterine walls as labor is initiated.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Thermoreceptors are not involved in this feedback loop although they are involved in body temperature homeostasis through a different loop.</feedback></response><hint>The receptors are located in the cervix and uterus.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>In this diagram for oxytocin, what would be the control center?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">pancreas</choice><choice value="B">cervix</choice><choice value="C">mammary gland</choice><choice value="D">pituitary</choice></multiple_choice><part id="d12dea4e3ede40f5b70c18b1a3aba367"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_loops_SKILL" /><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pancreas releases both exocrine secretions and endocrine hormones, but not oxytocin.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the location of the receptor.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This responds to oxytocin for lactation as another target effector for a different positive feedback loop (review homeostasis unit).</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. As you will learn later, it is specifically the combined hypothalamus and posterior pituitary, also known as the neurohypophysis.</feedback></response><hint>This control center is releasing the hormone oxytocin when stimulated by the input from receptor.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q4"><body>The cervical and uterine tissue become more sensitive to oxytocin during late pregnancy in response to increased levels of estrogen in the mother’s blood. What is changing to make this tissue more sensitive to oxytocin and enhance this positive feedback?</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="b30fff0b68b044999901235ae6cbf2fb"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_loops_SKILL" /><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>The steroid estrogen hormone is stimulating the transcription of protein receptors for oxytocin that are inserted into the smooth muscle cell membrane. Oxytocin binds to its receptor to stimulate stronger and longer contractions for birth.</explanation></part></question><question id="q5"><body>A positive feedback loop is unstable and would result in a runaway situation if something did not terminate the continued increased stimulus. In the example of child birth, why does the feedback loop stop eventually?</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="i7084a0868a4c4bf494d153481a1ca7ab"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_loops_SKILL" /><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>After the baby is born, the stretch receptors are no longer stimulated and the release of oxytocin decreases.</explanation></part></question><question id="q6"><body>The contractions will continue for minutes to an hour after the baby is born. This helps expel the placenta, also known as the afterbirth. Why would the contractions continue for this time period even though the baby has been born?</body><short_answer id="A" /><part id="i7d5a0c380f094c3585982172700d7681"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_loops_SKILL" /><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>Hormones produced before the end of stretch receptors being stimulated are still circulating in the blood and will continue to stimulate the uterine smooth muscle with receptors for oxytocin until the hormone is bound or degraded slowly. Unlike the nervous system which initiates and ends stimulation quickly, the endocrine system is not only slower to initiate, but also slower to end its effect.</explanation></part></question></page></assessment>
