<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_LOO_location_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>What would happen to a body cell that doesn’t have a specific receptor for a specific hormone that is released and circulating in the blood?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The cell would increase its physiological response to that hormone</choice><choice value="B">The cell would decrease its physiological response to that hormone</choice><choice value="C">The cell would not respond to the hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part id="e63377c2922d4617b0611dea6bc96c2b"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_recep_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Without a receptor there would be no mechanism to influence the cell’s metabolism.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Without a receptor there would be no mechanism to influence the cell’s metabolism.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. A cell will only respond if it has a receptor for a specific hormone, regardless of the amount circulating and coming into contact with that cell.</feedback></response><hint>These receptors bind to hormones in a mechanism similar to the way enzymes work. Only the receptor-hormone complex can initiate the effect in a target cell.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>What would happen to a body cell if a specific hormone receptor was completely blocked by another chemical, such as a drug?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The cell would increase its physiological response to that hormone</choice><choice value="B">The cell would die</choice><choice value="C">The cell would not respond to the hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i3c49710f1bf3446aa0b5bebc6a4c17b9"><skillref idref="endo_hormone_recep_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Some drugs can enhance hormone effect, but by activating the receptor.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. If the receptors were blocked completely, it is as if the cell did not have any receptors for that hormone.</feedback></response><hint>A non-hormone chemical can sometimes bind to the receptor but not stimulate the same response.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
