<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="endo_LOO_regulation_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>This diagram illustrates the negative feedback mechanism involving three hormones. <image src="../webcontent/negative_feedback_diagram.png" /> Which letter on this negative feedback loop image would represent the release of the hormone that is the “opposite change” restoring homeostasis?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A">A</choice><choice value="B">B</choice><choice value="C">C</choice><choice value="D">D</choice><choice value="E">E</choice></multiple_choice><part id="q1_p1"><skillref idref="endo_hormones_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The thyroid releasing hormone has an effect on the anterior pituitary but is not itself the hormone being monitored and controlled homeostatically.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The thyroid stimulating hormone has an effect on the thyroid gland but is not itself the hormone being monitored and contolled homeostatically.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The two thyroid hormones (T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub>) are increasing as a direct opposite change from the stimulus that was a decrease in their plasma concentration.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The resulting increased level of the thyroid hormones back into homeostatic range provides the negative feedback to stop the loop to prevent too much being produced.</feedback></response><response match="E" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The indirect effect would stimulate the additional production of thyroid hormone even if the thyroid hormone level was within homeostatic range, facilitating a response temporarily not controlled by the negative feedback loop.</feedback></response><hint>The gland producing the hormone being monitored would be the final “effector” in this loop.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>In this negative feedback loop, there are two “control centers” receiving feedback from the change initiated by the effector. One is neural and one is endocrine. A similar control relationship between these two exists for several tropic hormones that control other endocrine glands. Based on this, which endocrine gland is sometimes called the “master gland”?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">thyroid gland</choice><choice value="B">anterior pituitary gland</choice><choice value="C">posterior pituitary gland</choice><choice value="D">hypothalamus</choice></multiple_choice><part><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the final “effector” increasing the production of the hormone in response to its detected decrease in the blood plasma.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. This endocrine gland produces a variety of hormones under the control of the hypothalamus, many of which then control other endocrine glands.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This part of the pituitary only stores and releases hormones produced in the hypothalamus, such as oxytocin involved in a positive feedback loop.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is the “master” of the “master gland” by releasing both stimulating and inhibiting hormones to control the gland’s production of several tropic hormones.</feedback></response><hint>In this scenario, the hypothalamus would be the “master” of the “master gland”.</hint></part></question><question id="q7"><body>Look at letter “E” on the feedback diagram. What would be the advantage of input from other parts of the brain continuing to stimulate the hypothalamus, and thus more thyroid hormone production even if the blood level has returned within normal homeostatic range?</body><short_answer id="A" /><part><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><hint>Most body cells have receptors for thyroid hormone and it stimulates increased metabolism. A by-product of cell metabolism is heat. People with an underactive thyroid gland are at higher risk for hypothermia.</hint><explanation>Temporarily increased levels of thyroid releasing and stimulating hormone would result in elevated thyroid hormone levels above the homeostatic range. This would allow the body to generate metabolic heat in an emergency situation, improving cold-tolerance along with other homeostatic body temperature regulating mechanisms. This response is most noticeable in young children.</explanation></part></question></page><page><question id="q3"><body>Elevated levels of cortisol, also known as the “stress hormone”, can inhibit the production of thyroid stimulating hormone from the anterior pituitary. What would be the effect on the production of thyroid hormone by the thyroid gland?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">increased production of thyroid hormone</choice><choice value="B">decreased production of thyroid hormone</choice><choice value="C">stable production of thyroid hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This would result from an increase in TSH, not its inhibition.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Even as thyroid plasma levels fell, the hypothalamus would not be able to stimulate thyroid without the production of the tropic TSH hormone by the anterior pituitary.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The absence of TSH would definitely affect the thyroid gland’s hormone production.</feedback></response><hint>Chronic stress is often related to symptoms of hypothyroidism.</hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body>The autoimmune Grave’s disease results in antibodies in the blood that bind to thyroid stimulating hormone receptors, mimicking their metabolic effect on the target cell. What would be the effect on the production of thyroid hormone by the thyroid gland?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">increased production of thyroid hormone</choice><choice value="B">decreased production of thyroid hormone</choice><choice value="C">stable production of thyroid hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Even though the negative feedback reduces the production of releasing and stimulating hormones, the antibodies would continue to stimulate thyroid hormone production.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The receptors would be stimulated by not only the hormone but also this antibody, negating the negative feedback control to maintain homeostasis.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The antibody is chemically behaving as TSH and would definitely affect the thyroid gland’s hormone production.</feedback></response><hint>Grave’s disease often causes symptoms of hyperthyroidism.</hint></part></question><question id="q5"><body>A different autoimmune Hashimoto’s thyroiditis disease results in destruction of thyroid cells by lymphocytes. What would be the effect on the production of thyroid hormone by the thyroid gland?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">increased production of thyroid hormone</choice><choice value="B">decreased production of thyroid hormone</choice><choice value="C">stable production of thyroid hormone</choice></multiple_choice><part><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The remaining cells that have not been destroyed by the autoimmune response would not be able to produce more hormone.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The reduction in hormone producing cells would reduce the gland’s ability to produce sufficient hormone even with sufficient TRH and TSH production.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Destruction of the endocrine cells would definitely affect the thyroid gland’s ability to produce hormones.</feedback></response><hint>A person with Hashimoto’s thyroiditis exhibits symptoms of hypothyroidism.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="q6"><body>What would be the advantage of having the negative feedback from the increased thyroid hormones to both the hypothalamus and the anterior pituitary?</body><short_answer id="A" /><part><response input="A" match="*" score="10" /><hint>Consider what would happen if only the hypothalamus received feedback. Think about one of the major differences between neural and endocrine control.</hint><explanation>By providing feedback to “stop” the continued release of both hypothalamus releasing hormone and anterior pituitary stimulating hormone, the thyroid will more quickly stop releasing more hormone. Without this, it would take much longer for the hypothalamus to stop stimulating the anterior pituitary and then the anterior pituitary to stop stimulating the thyroid and the level of circulating thyroid hormone would fluctuate more and potentially increase above the homeostatic range. This situation, however, also makes it hard to artificially mimic the homeostatic maintenance of blood thyroid hormone levels with drug replacements. It often takes weeks or months of adjusting drug doses to treat hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism with drugs.</explanation></part></question></page></assessment>
