<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m1_intro_00">
   <head>
      <title>Major Functions of the Cardiovascular System</title>
      <objref idref="describe_major_functions_cardio_OBJ"/>
      <objref idref="identify_major_diseases_cardio_OBJ"/>
   </head>
   <body>
      <!--<p><em style="highlight">[NOTE: link to introduction of systems for this unit]</em></p>-->
            <p>All metabolic processes in the body require nutrients and oxygen and
               produce waste products. Nutrients are absorbed through the digestive
               system and oxygen is acquired through the respiratory system. The
               cardiovascular system is responsible for moving material through the
               body. The heart pumps blood throughout the blood vessels.</p>
      <section>
         <title>Common Dysfunctions of the Cardiovascular System</title>
         <body>
            <p>In this unit, we will discuss many different cardiovascular
               disorders.</p>
            <p><em style="bold">Blood Disorders</em></p>
            <p>The variety of disorders that affects blood highlights how physiology can
               be impacted by genetics, environmental changes, pathogens or a
               combination of all of these factors. For example, digestive diseases or
               prolonged poor nutrition can lead to a loss of blood protein called
               hypoalbuminemia. There are numerous genetic conditions in blood which
               cause coagulation (blood clots) inside the body, which can be exacerbated
               by poor diet and lack of exercise. Also, there are numerous genetic
               anemias (insufficient number of red blood cells) including thalassemia
               that are found in regions of the word prone to malaria infection. Malaria
               is an example of a pathogenic infection of blood cells.</p>
            <p><em style="bold">Vascular Disorders</em></p>
            <p>Vascular disorders including hypertension (high blood pressure) are
               primarily a function of lifestyle including diet, exercise and stress.
               Recent studies have shown that genetics also plays a role in the presence
               and progression of these disorders.</p>
            <p><em style="bold">Disorders of the Heart</em></p>
            <p>Your heart will beat billions of times in your life, on average once per
               second; an electrical impulse will cause a mechanical contraction. If the
               heart conduction system or mechanical system falters, it can lead to
               devastating changes in heart physiology and whole body physiology. Even
               if the heart weakens over time it can have damaging effects since the
               heart never gets a chance to rest.</p>
         </body>
      </section>
   </body>
</workbook_page>
