<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_02">
    <head>
        <title>Hormonal Regulation of the Fluid Balance</title>
        <objref idref="endo_fluid_balance"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Maintaining a proper water balance in the body is important to avoid dehydration or
            excess water. The water concentration of the body is monitored by
                <term>osmoreceptors</term> in the hypothalamus, which detect the concentration of
            electrolytes in the blood. The concentration of electrolytes in the blood rises when
            there is water loss due to excessive perspiration, inadequate water intake, or low blood
            volume due to blood loss. An increase in blood electrolyte levels results in a neural
            signal being sent from the osmoreceptors to the hypothalamus. The hypothalamus produces
                <term>antidiuretic hormone (ADH)</term>, which is transported to, and released from,
            the posterior pituitary. It is also known as vasopressin. The target cells for ADH are
            the distal tubule cells in the kidneys, which are stimulated to absorb more water from
            urine, resulting in an increase in the water level of blood and making urine which is
            more concentrated.</p>
        <p>Chronic underproduction of ADH results in <term>diabetes insipidus</term>. If the
            posterior pituitary does not release enough ADH, water cannot be retained by the kidneys
            and is eliminated in the urine. This causes increased thirst, but water taken in is lost
            again, and water must be continually consumed. If the condition is not severe,
            dehydration may not occur, but severe cases can lead to electrolyte imbalances due to
            dehydration.</p>
        <p>Another hormone responsible for maintaining electrolyte concentrations in extracellular
            fluids is <term>aldosterone</term>, a steroid hormone that is produced by the adrenal
            cortex. In contrast to ADH, which promotes the reabsorption of water to maintain proper
            water balance, aldosterone maintains proper water balance by enhancing Na<sup>+</sup>
            reabsorption from extracellular fluids. Because it affects the concentrations of
            minerals, Na<sup>+</sup>, aldosterone is referred to as a mineralocorticoid. Aldosterone
            release is stimulated by a decrease in blood sodium levels, blood volume, or blood
            pressure, or an increase in blood potassium levels. Aldosterone targets the renal
            tubules of the kidneys, where it causes the reabsorption of Na<sup>+</sup> from urine
            and the secretion of K<sup>+</sup> into the urine. It also prevents the loss of
                Na<sup>+</sup> from sweat, saliva, and gastric juice. The reabsorption of
                Na<sup>+</sup> also results in the osmotic reabsorption of water, which alters blood
            volume and blood pressure.</p>
        <p>Aldosterone production can be stimulated by low blood pressure, which triggers a sequence
            of chemical releases. When blood pressure drops, cells in the juxtaglomerular apparatus
            of the kidney detect this and release <term>renin</term>. Renin circulates in the blood
            and reacts with a protein produced by the liver called angiotensinogen. When
            angiotensinogen is cleaved by renin, it produces angiotensin I, which is then converted
            into angiotensin II. Angiotensin II impacts water and Na<sup>+</sup> reabsorption and
            causes the release of aldosterone by the adrenal cortex with a similar effect;
            ultimately these increase blood pressure. Angiotensin II also causes an increase in ADH
            and increased thirst, which both help to increase fluids and raise blood pressure.</p>
        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_fluid_tt_digt"/>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_fluid_balance_digt"/>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
