<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_04">
    <head>
        <title>Hormonal Regulation of Metabolism</title>
        <objref idref="endo_metabolism"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Blood glucose levels vary widely over the course of a day as periods of food consumption
            alternate with periods of fasting. Insulin and glucagon are the two hormones that are
            primarily responsible for maintaining homeostasis of blood glucose levels. Additional
            regulation is mediated by the thyroid hormones.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Regulation of Blood Glucose Levels by Insulin and Glucagon</title>
            <body>
                <!--    <objref idref="endo_glycogen"/>-->
                <p>Cells of the body require nutrients in order to function, and they obtain these
                    nutrients through feeding. In order to manage nutrient intake, storing excess
                    and utilizing stores when necessary, the body uses hormones to modulate
                    energy metabolism. <term>Insulin</term> is produced by the beta cells of the
                    pancreas, which are stimulated to release insulin as blood glucose levels rise,
                    for example, after a meal is consumed. Insulin lowers blood glucose levels by
                    enhancing glucose uptake by most body target cells, which utilize glucose for
                    ATP production; muscle cells are a good example. It also stimulates the liver to
                    convert glucose to glycogen, which is then stored by cells for later use.
                    Increased glucose uptake occurs through an insulin-mediated increase in the
                    number of glucose transporter proteins in cell membranes, which remove glucose
                    from circulation by facilitated diffusion. As insulin binds to its target cell,
                    it triggers the cell to incorporate transport proteins into its membrane. This
                    allows glucose to enter the cell, where it can be used as an energy source.
                    However, this does not always occur in all body cells, as some cells in the
                    kidneys and brain have been shown to regularly access glucose without the use of
                    insulin. Insulin also stimulates the conversion of glucose to fat in adipocytes
                    and the synthesis of proteins. The actions of insulin which cause blood glucose
                    concentrations to fall, called a hypoglycemic effect, inhibit further insulin
                    release from beta cells through a negative feedback loop.</p>
                <p>Decreased insulin production or reduced sensitivity of cells to insulin can lead
                    to a condition called <term>diabetes mellitus</term>. This prevents glucose from
                    being absorbed by cells, causing high levels of glucose in the blood, or
                        <term>hyperglycemia</term>. High blood glucose levels make it difficult for
                    the kidneys to reabsorb all the filtered glucose, resulting in glucose being
                    lost in urine. High glucose levels also result in less water being reabsorbed by
                    the kidneys because the water is retained in the urine to osmotically balance
                    the high levels of excess glucose. This causes increased urination, which may
                    result in dehydration. Over time, high blood glucose levels can cause nerve
                    damage to the eyes and peripheral body tissues, as well as damage to the kidneys
                    and cardiovascular system. On the other hand, over-secretion of insulin can lead
                    to low blood glucose levels, or <term>hypoglycemia</term>. This causes
                    insufficient glucose availability to cells, often leading to muscle weakness,
                    and can sometimes cause unconsciousness or death if left untreated.</p>
                <p>When blood glucose levels decline below normal levels, for example, between meals
                    or when glucose is utilized rapidly during exercise, the hormone
                        <term>glucagon</term> is released from the alpha cells of the pancreas.
                    Glucagon raises blood glucose levels, called a hyperglycemic effect, by
                    stimulating the breakdown of glycogen to glucose in skeletal muscle cells and
                    liver cells in a process called <term>glycogenolysis</term>
                    (glycogen-splitting). Glucose can then be utilized as energy by muscle cells and
                    released into circulation by the liver cells. Glucagon also stimulates
                    absorption of amino acids from the blood by the liver, which then converts them
                    to glucose. This process of glucose synthesis is called
                        <term>gluconeogenesis</term> (new glucose formation). Glucagon also
                    stimulates adipose cells to release fatty acids into the blood. Collectively,
                    these glucagon-mediated actions result in an increase in blood glucose levels to
                    normal homeostatic levels. Rising blood glucose levels inhibit further glucagon
                    release by the pancreas. In this way, insulin and glucagon work together to
                    maintain glucose homeostasis.</p>

            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Regulation of Blood Glucose Levels by Thyroid Hormones</title>
            <body>
                <p>The basal metabolic rate, which is the amount of calories required by the body at
                    rest, is determined by two hormones produced by the thyroid gland:
                        <term>thyroxine</term>, also know as tetraiodothyronine or T<sub>4</sub>,
                    and <term>triiodothyronine</term>, also know as T<sub>3</sub>. Dietary iodine is
                    needed to synthesize these hormones. These hormones affect nearly every cell in
                    the body except for the adult brain, uterus, testes, and spleen. They cross the
                    plasma membrane of target cells and bind to receptors on the mitochondria,
                    resulting in increased ATP production. In the nucleus, T<sub>3</sub> and
                        T<sub>4</sub> activate genes involved in energy production and glucose
                    oxidation. This results in increased rates of metabolism and body heat
                    production, which is known as the hormone’s calorigenic effect.</p>
                <p>Disorders can arise from both the underproduction and overproduction of thyroid
                    hormones. <term>Hypothyroidism</term>, under activity of the thyroid hormones,
                    can cause a low metabolic rate, leading to weight gain, sensitivity to cold, and
                    reduced mental activity, among other symptoms. In children, hypothyroidism can
                    cause cretinism, which causes mental retardation and growth defects.
                        <term>Hyperthyroidism</term>, the over-activity of thyroid hormones, can
                    lead to an increased metabolic rate, causing weight loss, excess heat
                    production, sweating, and an increased heart rate. Graves’ disease is one such
                    hyperthyroid condition. In the absence of iodine, thyroid hormones are not
                    produced, colloid storage increases, and thyroid enlargement
                        (<term>goiter</term>) occurs.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <composite_activity purpose="didigetthis">
            <wb:inline idref="endo_glycogen_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <wb:inline idref="endo_metabolism_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <wb:inline idref="endo_metabolism_tt_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        </composite_activity>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
