<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_03">
    <head>
        <title>Hormonal Regulation of the Reproductive System</title>
        <objref idref="endo_repro"/>
        <objref idref="endo_repro_male"/>
        <objref idref="endo_repro_female"/>
        <objref idref="endo_milk"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Regulation of the reproductive system is a process that requires the action of hormones
            from the pituitary gland, the adrenal cortex, and the gonads. During puberty in both
            males and females, the hypothalamus produces <term>gonadotropin-releasing hormone
                (GnRH)</term>, which stimulates the release of <term>follicle-stimulating hormone
                (FSH)</term> and <term>luteinizing hormone (LH)</term> from the anterior pituitary.
            These hormones regulate the gonads (testes in males and ovaries in females) and
            therefore are called <term>gonadotropins</term>. In both males and females, FSH
            stimulates gamete production, and LH stimulates production of hormones by the gonads. An
            increase in gonad hormone levels inhibits GnRH production through a negative feedback
            loop.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Regulation of the Male Reproductive System</title>
            <body>
              
                <p>In males, FSH and LH regulates the maturation of sperm cells. FSH stimulates the
                    support cells in the testes called Sertoli (sustentacular) cells. These cells nourish and
                    regulate the maturation of the sperm and produce androgen binding protein (ABP).
                    ABP keeps the level of testosterone high within the testes, relative to the
                    plasma levels. FSH production is inhibited by the hormone <term>inhibin</term>,
                    which is also released by the Sertoli cells in the testes. LH stimulates
                    production of the sex hormones (<term>androgens</term>) by the interstitial or
                    Leydig cells of the testes and therefore is also called interstitial
                    cell-stimulating hormone (ICSH).</p>
                <p> The most important androgen in males is <term>testosterone</term>. Testosterone
                    promotes the production and maturation of sperm and determines secondary sex
                    characteristics. The adrenal cortex of both males and females also produces
                    small amounts of testosterone, although the role of this additional hormone
                    production in males is not well understood.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Regulation of the Female Reproductive System</title>
            <body>
                
                <p>In females, FSH stimulates development of support cells around the egg, which
                    develop into structures called follicles. LH regulates the development and
                    release of the egg from the follicle. Follicle cells initially produce the
                    hormone <term>estrogen</term> that has effects on the hypothalamus and anterior
                    pituitary, as well as the uterus. LH stimulates the egg to mature within the growing follicle. As
                    estrogen levels rise, it triggers the anterior pituitary to release a surge of
                    LH that stimulates ovulation. The follicle cells remaining in the ovary become
                    the corpus luteum and now produce both estrogen and progesterone as well as
                    inhibin, all of which inhibit the anterior pituitary.</p>
                <p>Estrogen and <term>progesterone</term> are steroid hormones that prepare the body
                    for pregnancy. Estrogen produces secondary sex characteristics in females, while
                    both estrogen and progesterone together regulate the uterine menstrual cycle.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Regulation of the Female Reproductive System and Childbirth</title>
            <body>
              
                <p>In addition to producing FSH and LH, the anterior pituitary also produces the
                    hormone <term>prolactin (PRL)</term>. In females, prolactin stimulates the production of milk
                    by the mammary glands following childbirth. Prolactin levels are regulated by
                    the hypothalamic hormones <term>prolactin-releasing hormone (PRH)</term> and
                    <term>prolactin-inhibiting hormone (PIH)</term>, the latter of which is now known to be
                    dopamine. Usually prolactin production is inhibited, but PRH, estrogen and infant
                    suckling stimulation remove the inhibition. Males can produce small amounts of
                    prolactin and its role in other aspects of reproduction and immunity are not
                    well understood but are being investigated in humans.</p>
                <p>The posterior pituitary releases the hormone <term>oxytocin</term>, which stimulates
                    contractions during childbirth. The uterine smooth muscles are not very
                    sensitive to oxytocin until late in pregnancy when the number of oxytocin
                    receptors in the uterus peaks. Stretching of tissues in the uterus and vagina
                    stimulates oxytocin release in childbirth. Contractions increase in intensity as
                    blood levels of oxytocin rise until the birth is complete. Oxytocin also
                    stimulates the contraction of myoepithelial cells around the milk-producing
                    cells of the mammary glands. As these cells contract, milk is forced from the
                    secretory alveoli into milk ducts and is ejected from the breasts in a milk
                    let-down reflex. Oxytocin release is stimulated by the suckling of an infant,
                    which triggers the synthesis of oxytocin in the hypothalamus and its release
                    into circulation at the posterior pituitary.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
       
        <wb:inline idref="endo_repro_female_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
      <!--  <wb:inline idref="endo_repro_female_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
        <composite_activity purpose="didigetthis"><wb:inline idref="endo_repro_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_repro_male_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            <wb:inline idref="endo_milk_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/></composite_activity>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
