<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_08">
    <head>
        <title>Hormonal Regulation of Stress</title>
        <objref idref="endo_stress"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>When a threat or danger is perceived, the body responds by releasing hormones that will
            ready it for the fight-or-flight response. The effects of this response are familiar to
            anyone who has been in a stressful situation: increased heart rate, dry mouth,
            butterflies in your stomach and sweating. This is what we call a short-term stress. When
            one is under stress for more than several hours (or chronically), it translates into
            long term stress.</p>
        <p> The sympathetic nervous system regulates the stress response via the hypothalamus.
            Stressful stimuli cause the hypothalamus to signal the adrenal medulla via nerve
            impulses, which mediates short-term stress responses, and to the adrenal cortex, via the
            hormone adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), which mediates long-term stress
            response.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Short-Term Stress Response</title>
            <body>
                <p>Upon stimulation, the adrenal medulla releases the hormones
                        <term>epinephrine</term> (also known as adrenaline) and
                        <term>norepinephrine</term> (also known as noradrenaline), collectively
                    referred to as the catecholamines. The release of these hormones into the blood
                    provides the body with a burst of energy that is needed to respond to a
                    stressful situation. Epinephrine and norepinephrine increase blood glucose
                    levels by stimulating the liver and skeletal muscles to break down glycogen and
                    by stimulating glucose release by liver cells. These hormones also increase
                    oxygen availability to cells by increasing the heart rate and dilating the
                    bronchioles. In addition, they increase the blood supply to essential organs
                    such as the heart, brain, and skeletal muscles by stimulating specific blood
                    vessels to relax or by constricting other vessels to divert blood away from
                    nonessential organs such as the skin, digestive system, and kidneys. </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Long-Term Stress Response</title>
            <body>
                <p> In a long-term stress response, the hypothalamus triggers the release of ACTH
                    from the anterior pituitary. The adrenal cortex is stimulated by ACTH to release
                    steroid hormones called <term>corticosteroids</term>. The two main
                    corticosteroids are <term>glucocorticoids</term>, such as <term>cortisol</term>,
                    and <term>mineralocorticoids</term>, such as aldosterone. The glucocorticoids
                    primarily affect glucose metabolism by stimulating glucose synthesis. They also
                    stimulate the redistribution of fat stored in adipose tissue for use in meeting
                    long-term energy requirements. Glucocorticoids also have anti-inflammatory
                    properties through inhibition of the immune system. For example, cortisone is
                    used as an anti-inflammatory medication; however, it cannot be used long term as
                    it increases susceptibility to disease due to its immune-suppressing effects as
                    well as changes to blood pressure and constant heart stimulation.</p>
                <p> Mineralocorticoids function to regulate ion and water balance of the body. The
                    hormone aldosterone stimulates the reabsorption of water and sodium ions in the
                    kidney, which results in increased blood pressure and volume.</p>
                <p> Hypersecretion of glucocorticoids, unrelated to a normal stress response, can be
                    caused by a condition known as <term>Cushing’s disease</term>. This can cause
                    the accumulation of adipose tissue in the face and neck and excessive glucose in
                    the blood. Hyposecretion of the corticosteroids, independent of the normal
                    stress response, is often the result of <term>Addison’s disease</term>, which
                    may result in low blood sugar levels and low electrolyte levels.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_stress_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_stress_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
