<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_07">
    <head>
        <title>Hormonal Regulation of Growth</title>
        <objref idref="endo_growth"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Hormonal regulation is required for the growth and replication of most cells in the body.
                <term>Growth hormone (GH)</term> produced by the anterior pituitary accelerates the
            rate of protein synthesis, particularly in skeletal muscle and bones. Growth hormone has
            direct and indirect mechanisms of action. One direct action is the stimulation of fat
            breakdown (lipolysis) and release into the blood by adipocytes. This results in a switch
            by most tissues from utilizing glucose as an energy source to utilizing fatty acids.
            This process is called a <term>glucose-sparing effect</term>. Another direct action
            occurs in the liver, where GH stimulates glycogen breakdown, and subsequent release of
            glucose into the blood. Blood glucose levels increase as most tissues are metabolizing
            fatty acids instead of glucose. The GH-mediated increase in blood glucose levels is
            called a <term>diabetogenic effect</term> because it is similar to the high blood
            glucose levels seen in diabetes mellitus.</p>
        <p> The indirect mechanism of GH action is mediated by somatomedins or <term>insulin-like
                growth factors (IGFs)</term>, which are a family of growth-promoting proteins
            produced by the liver. IGFs stimulate the uptake of amino acids from the blood, allowing
            the formation of new proteins, particularly in skeletal muscle cells, cartilage cells,
            and other target cells. GH levels are regulated by two hormones produced by the
            hypothalamus. GH release is stimulated by <term>growth hormone-releasing hormone
                (GHRH)</term> and is inhibited by growth hormone-inhibiting hormone (GHIH), also
            called somatostatin. Both of these are produced by the hypothalamus and delivered to the
            anterior pituitary by the hypophyseal portal vein.</p>
        <p> Over-secretion of growth hormone can lead to <term>gigantism</term> in children, causing
            excessive growth. In adults, excessive GH can lead to <term>acromegaly</term>, a
            condition in which bones still capable of growth in the face, hands, and feet enlarge.
            Under-production of GH in adults does not appear to cause any abnormalities, but in
            children it can result in <term>pituitary dwarfism</term>, in which growth is
            proportionally reduced.</p>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_growth_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_growth_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
