<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_05">
    <head>
        <title>Hormonal Control of Blood Calcium Levels</title>
        <objref idref="endo_calcium"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>Regulation of blood calcium concentration is important for proper muscle contractions and
            release of neurotransmitters. Calcium also affects voltage-gated plasma membrane ion
            channels, affecting nerve impulses and other cell physiology. If plasma calcium levels
            are too high, membrane permeability to sodium decreases and membranes become less
            responsive. If plasma calcium levels are too low, membrane permeability to sodium
            increases and convulsions or muscle spasms can result.</p>
        <p>Blood calcium levels are regulated by <term>parathyroid hormone (PTH)</term>, which is
            produced by the parathyroid glands. PTH is released in response to low blood
                Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels. PTH increases Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels by targeting the
            skeleton, the kidneys, and the intestine. In the skeleton, PTH stimulates osteoclasts,
            causing bone to be broken down and releasing Ca<sup>2+</sup> from bone into the blood.
            PTH also inhibits osteoblasts, reducing Ca<sup>2+</sup> deposition in bone. In the
            kidneys and intestines, PTH stimulates the reabsorption of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. While PTH
            acts directly on the kidneys to increase Ca<sup>2+</sup> reabsorption, its effects on
            the intestine are indirect. PTH triggers the formation of calcitriol, an active form of
            vitamin D, which acts on the intestines to increase absorption of dietary calcium. PTH
            release is inhibited by rising blood calcium levels.</p>
        <example>
            <p> Hyperparathyroidism results from an overproduction of parathyroid hormone. This
                results in excessive calcium being removed from bones and being introduced into
                blood circulation. This causes structural weakness of the bones, which can lead to
                deformation and breakage, and nervous system impairment due to high blood calcium
                levels. Hypoparathyroidism, the underproduction of PTH, results in extremely low
                levels of blood calcium, which causes impaired muscle function and may result in
                tetany—severe sustained muscle contraction.</p>
        </example>
        <p> The hormone <term>calcitonin</term> is produced by the parafollicular or C cells of the
            thyroid and has the opposite effect on blood calcium levels as PTH. Calcitonin decreases
            blood calcium levels by inhibiting osteoclasts, stimulating osteoblasts, and stimulating
            calcium excretion by the kidneys. This results in calcium being added to the bones to
            promote structural integrity. Calcitonin appears to play a major plasma calcium
            homeostasis role only in children, and in pregnant women to reduce maternal bone loss.
            Its role in adults is not well understood and it may be more important in regulating
            bone remodeling than blood plasma homeostasis.</p>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_calcium_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <section purpose="didigetthis">
            <title/>
            <body>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_calcium_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
                <wb:inline idref="endo_diseases_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
