<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u10_m2_homeostasis_09">
    <head>
        <title>Disruption and Dysfunction of Homeostasis</title>
        <objref idref="endo_disrupt"/>
    </head>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Tumors</title>
            <body>
                <p>Endocrine glands tightly regulate hormone synthesis and release to maintain
                    homeostasis in the body. Although they are rare, tumors in endocrine glands do
                    occur, disrupting normal hormone synthesis. These cancers, called neuroendocrine
                    tumors or NETs, affect cells of the endocrine and nervous system that control
                    hormone synthesis.</p>
                <p>Tumors of endocrine glands can produce symptoms that are similar to those caused
                    by hypersecretion of hormones in endocrine disorders. For example, tumors of the
                    adrenal glands that result in the excess production of steroid hormones produce
                    symptoms of Cushing’s disease, which includes the accumulation of adipose tissue
                    in the face and neck and excessive glucose in the blood.</p>
                <p>Tumors of the pancreas that affect beta cells are called insulinomas, and those
                    that affect alpha cells are called glucagonomas. Beta cell tumors result in the
                    production of excess amounts of the hormone insulin, which results in
                    hypoglycemia. Alpha cell tumors result in the production of excess amounts of
                    the hormone glucagon, which results in hyperglycemia and symptoms similar to
                    those seen in diabetes.</p>
                <p>Tumors of the pituitary gland fall into two groups: secreting and non-secreting
                    tumors. Secreting tumors cause the secretion of excess amounts of pituitary
                    hormones. Symptoms of secreting pituitary tumors are related to the function of
                    the hormone that is affected. For example, growth hormone-producing tumors can
                    lead to gigantism and acromegaly.</p>
                <p>Medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) is a cancer of the parafollicular cells of the
                    thyroid gland. The parafollicular cells produce the hormone calcitonin, which
                    plays a role in calcium regulation and bone formation. Unlike in other cancers,
                    the increased levels of calcitonin produced by MTC in adults are not harmful.
                    Increased blood calcitonin levels are used to diagnose MTC.</p>
                <p>Many secretory NETs can be tentatively diagnosed by measuring blood hormone
                    levels to identify hormones that are present in excess. Treatment of these
                    tumors can include surgery to remove the tumor or affected endocrine gland and
                    chemotherapy.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Osteoporosis</title>
            <body>
                <p>Osteoporosis is a disease of the skeletal system characterized by a decrease in
                    bone density and deterioration of bone tissue. The mechanism of disease onset is
                    an imbalance between bone formation and bone resorption, with bone resorption
                    occurring at a greater rate than bone formation. Hormone levels play a vital
                    role in maintaining a balance in bone turnover. Osteoporosis affects primarily
                    the elderly and is three times more common in women than in men. This may be
                    related to lower peak bone mass in women and to hormonal changes that occur
                    during menopause. Low estrogen levels increase the rate of bone turnover, which
                    alters the balance between bone formation and bone resorption. The decrease in
                    estrogen that occurs during menopause appears to be the primary cause of
                    osteoporosis in women over 50 years of age.</p>
                <p>The elderly also have decreased levels of the hormone calcitriol, which is the
                    active form of vitamin D<sub>3</sub>. Vitamin D helps maintain calcium balance
                    in the skeleton by stimulating calcium absorption in the intestines and by
                    maintaining calcium and phosphate levels for bone formation. Vitamin D also
                    helps to maintain homeostatic levels of parathyroid hormone (PTH). Decreased
                    vitamin D levels are associated with increased PTH levels, which result in
                    increased bone turnover and bone loss.</p>
                <p>Decreased dietary intake of calcium in the elderly is also associated with
                    osteoporosis. In addition to the decreased availability of calcium for bone
                    formation, low blood calcium levels stimulate the parathyroid glands to
                    synthesize more PTH. PTH stimulates the release of calcium from bones to maintain
                    blood calcium levels, resulting in increased bone loss.</p>
                <p>Osteoporosis can be prevented by maintaining a lifestyle that includes exercise
                    and proper nutrition. It can be treated using the hormone calcitonin, which is
                    normally produced by the parafollicular cells of the thyroid gland. Calcitonin
                    functions to lower blood calcium levels and promotes bone formation. Calcium and
                    vitamin D supplements have also been shown to reduce the incidence of
                    osteoporosis.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <wb:inline idref="endo_disrupt_tt_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
