<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m1_homeostasis_examp_inline01"><title>Homeostasis and Disease</title><page><question id="_u1_reflection_on_own_body"><body><p>Diabetes Mellitus is a set of metabolic diseases wherein the body either does not produce enough of the hormone insulin or cells do not respond to the insulin that is produced. This results in high levels of sugar (glucose) in the blood. Diabetes Mellitus results from an inability to properly control the homeostasis of what?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true"><choice value="bl_pressure">blood pressure</choice><choice value="bl_glucose">blood glucose levels</choice><choice value="bl_flow">blood flow</choice><choice value="insulin">insulin levels</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u1_reflection_on_own_body_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_Explain_vital_SKILL" /><response match="bl_pressure" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although blood pressure is a homeostatically controlled variable, it is not the problem in diabetes.</feedback></response><response match="bl_glucose" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The body tries to keep blood glucose levels between 90 and 100 mg/dl (milligrams per deciliter), but in untreated diabetes it can be much higher than this.</feedback></response><response match="bl_flow" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Blood contains the sugar, but flow is not the culprit in this condition.</feedback></response><response match="insulin" score="0"><feedback>Not quite. The amount of insulin itself is not necessarily the problem. Sometimes there is enough insulin, but the body is unable to use it properly. Insulin levels usually control the blood glucose levels, but it is blood glucose levels being out of the homeostatic range that causes problems in untreated diabetes. </feedback></response><hint>Homeostasis is the ability to maintain a relatively constant internal environment.</hint><hint>Think about which factor is fluctuating and not being controlled by the body.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
