<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m1_vital_function_inline-Combined"><title>Thinking About Body Function</title><page><title>Exchange with the Environment</title><content><p>How does the body exchange with the environment? Indicate whether or not the functions below help the body exchange with the environment.</p></content><question id="_u01_m01_vital02_1"><body>Breathing</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital02_1_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_exchange_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Breathing allows us to bring in oxygen and expel waste (carbon dioxide).</feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although you cannot see an exchange taking place, breathing allows us to bring in oxygen and expel waste (carbon dioxide). </feedback></response><hint>Exchange with the environment involves everything that goes in and out of the body.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital02_3"><body>Heart Beating</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital02_3_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_exchange_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the heart beat drives the transport of materials that are exchanged with the respiratory and digestive systems into or out of the blood, this body function does not directly participate in the exchange. </feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Although the heart beat drives the transport of materials that are exchanged with the respiratory and digestive systems into or out of the blood, this body function does not directly participate in the exchange. </feedback></response><hint>Exchange with the environment involves material going in or out of the body, not the transport of those items within the body.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital02_4"><body>Defecation</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital02_4_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_exchange_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Exchanging with the environment includes getting rid of waste. Defecation removes solid, undigested waste from the digestive system. </feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Exchanging with the environment includes getting rid of waste. Build-up of toxins or undigested material can cause physiological problems. </feedback></response><hint>Exchange with the environment involves everything that goes in and out of the body.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital02_2"><body>Eating and drinking</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital02_2_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_exchange_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Both eating and drinking bring materials into the body.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Both eating and drinking bring materials into the body. </feedback></response><hint>Exchange with the environment involves everything that goes in and out of the body.</hint></part></question></page><page><title>Transport throughout the Body</title><content><p>What has to move or flow through the body? Indicate which materials are transported throughout the body.</p></content><question id="_u01_m01_vital03_1"><body>Water</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital03_1_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_transport_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Water is used as a solvent to carry materials through the body.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Water is used as a solvent to carry materials through the body.</feedback></response><hint>Blood flows through the body. What is the primary fluid component of blood?</hint><hint>What materials do you observe that ‘flow’?</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital03_2"><body>Nutrients</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital03_2_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_transport_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Nutrients are needed to support a variety of functions throughout the body.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Nutrients are needed to support a variety of functions throughout the body.</feedback></response><hint>Materials that are needed throughout the body but come in at one location are transported through the body.</hint><hint>Do nutrients travel throughout the body for proper function?</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital03_4"><body>Muscles</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital03_4_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_transport_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Muscles are usually considered stationary in the body.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback>Correct. While muscles shorten and lengthen, muscles do not flow and are not transported through the body.</feedback></response><hint>Do muscles flow throughout the body?</hint><hint>Muscles change shape when they help generate force but do not themselves move around within the body.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital03_5"><body>Oxygen</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital03_5_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_transport_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Oxygen is carried through the body by red blood cells to help metabolize materials inside the body’s tissues. </feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oxygen is carried through the body by red blood cells to help metabolize materials inside the body’s tissues. </feedback></response><hint>Body processes need food and oxygen, which we get from the environment. These processes also produce waste.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital03_3"><body>Waste products</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital03_3_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_transport_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The body produces wastes, which need to be transported to centers of processing and excretion. </feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The body produces wastes, which need to be transported to centers of processing and excretion. </feedback></response><hint>Wastes are produced throughout the body and need to travel to places of processing before they can be excreted to the environment.</hint></part></question></page><page><title>Structure, Support, Movement, Protection</title><content><p>What structure(s) is/are directly responsible for helping you stand up straight? Indicate whether the items below help do this as part of the vital functions of providing structure, support and protection.</p></content><question id="_u01_m01_vital04_1"><body>Lungs</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital04_1_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_structure_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although lungs bring in oxygen needed throughout the body, it is not directly responsible for you standing up straight.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Although lungs bring in oxygen needed throughout the body, it is not directly responsible for you standing up straight.</feedback></response><hint>Think of the parts of your body needed to lift something.</hint><hint>Lungs helps exchange gasses in the body.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital04_2"><body>Bones</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital04_2_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_structure_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Bones provide the structure needed to stand up straight.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Bones provide the structure needed to stand up straight.</feedback></response><hint>Think of the parts of your body needed to lift something.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital04_3"><body>Stomach and intestines</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital04_3_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_structure_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the digestive system brings in nutrients needed by the body, it is not directly responsible for you standing up straight.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Although the digestive system brings in nutrients needed by the body, it is not directly responsible for you standing up straight.</feedback></response><hint>The digestive system brings nutrients into the body and gets rid of wastes.</hint></part></question><question id="_u01_m01_vital04_4"><body>Muscles</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="false"><choice value="yes">yes</choice><choice value="no">no</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital04_4_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_structure_SKILL" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Muscles provide the force needed to maintain straight posture.</feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Muscles provide the force needed to maintain straight posture.</feedback></response><hint>Think of the parts of your body needed to lift something.</hint></part></question></page><page><title>Control and Regulation</title><question id="_u01_m01_vital05_1"><body>What is the most important regulator and coordinator of multiple functions in the body?</body><multiple_choice id="ans" shuffle="true"><choice value="heart">heart</choice><choice value="bones">bones</choice><choice value="eyes">eyes</choice><choice value="stomach">stomach</choice><choice value="brain">brain</choice></multiple_choice><part id="_u01_m01_vital05_1_p1"><skillref idref="_u1_identify_vital_control_SKILL" /><response match="heart" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The heart is important for transporting nutrients needed in a variety of processes but does not regulate multiple functions within the body. The nervous and endocrine systems help regulate the cardiovascular system function.</feedback></response><response match="bones" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Bones do participate in homeostasis, but do not regulate multiple body functions. </feedback></response><response match="eyes" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Eyes help us interact with the environment but do not regulate multiple body functions; we must process this sensory information both consciously (by making decisions) and unconsciously (with automated processes) to affect other systems.</feedback></response><response match="stomach" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The stomach has an important part in the regulation of the digestive system but does not regulate multiple functions within the body.</feedback></response><response match="brain" score="1"><feedback>Correct. We use the brain to process information and control bodily functions both consciously (by making decisions) and unconsciously (with automated processes).</feedback></response><hint>We either consciously or unconsciously control most of our body functions with this organ.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
