<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_control_lbd_inline"><title>Heart Rate and Blood Pressure Activity</title><page><question id="_u03_m01_feedback_control_lbd"><body><p>First, predict how changes in both heart rate and blood vessel diameter will affect blood pressure. As the heart rate increases, we would expect the blood pressure to <input_ref input="i1" /> and as the heart rate decreases, we would expect the blood pressure to <input_ref input="i2" />. As the blood vessels in the body constrict (decrease in diameter), we would expect the blood pressure to <input_ref input="i3" /> and as the blood vessels in the body dilate (increase in diameter), we would expect the blood pressure to <input_ref input="i4" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i1" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1a">increase</choice><choice value="v1b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i2" shuffle="false"><choice value="v2a">increase</choice><choice value="v2b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i3" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">increase</choice><choice value="v3b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i4" shuffle="false"><choice value="v4a">increase</choice><choice value="v4b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i043102c433414964bab4b756f7fe5ce0"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i1" match="v1a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. An increase in heart rate would cause blood pressure to go up.</feedback></response><response input="i1" match="v1b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in heart rate would cause blood pressure to go up.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the effect of pumping more blood through the body in the same amount of time.</hint></part><part id="i37da05897880473cbdbd8dfbfb7010cd"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i2" match="v2a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A decrease in heart rate would cause blood pressure to go down.</feedback></response><response input="i2" match="v2b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. A decrease in heart rate would cause blood pressure to go down.</feedback></response><hint>Think about effect of pumping less blood through the body in the same amount of time.</hint></part><part id="i13bb799e5d274190a7592038f954f7e3"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i3" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If the same amount of blood has to travel through smaller-diameter vessels, there will be more resistance, and therefore more pressure.</feedback></response><response input="i3" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the same amount of blood has to travel through smaller-diameter vessels, there will be more resistance, and therefore more pressure.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the effect that decreasing the diameter of a tube would have on the fluid flowing through it.</hint></part><part id="c7979ac8d17e400fa0cc396a39447037"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i4" match="v4a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The dilation of the blood vessels would decrease the blood pressure.</feedback></response><response input="i4" match="v4b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The dilation of the blood vessels would decrease the blood pressure.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the effect that increasing the diameter of a tube would have on the fluid flowing through it.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="_u03_m01_feedback_control_lbd_2"><body><p>Blood pressure is the <input_ref input="i5" /> of this homeostatic feedback loop. It is monitored by baroreceptors in certain blood vessels. A change in blood pressure causes baroreceptors to send impulses to the brainstem. This compares input to the set point and functions as the <input_ref input="i6" /> of the homeostatic feedback loop. An increase in blood pressure causes the brainstem to send signals on a set of neurons going to the heart, where they release a chemical called acetylcholine. To counteract this increase in blood pressure, acetylcholine causes the heart rate to <input_ref input="i7" />, bringing the blood pressure back down. Conversely, if blood pressure drops below the set point, the cardiovascular center sends signals on neurons going to the heart to release norepinephrine, also known as noradrenaline adrenaline (similar to the adrenaline or epinephrine from adrenal gland). Norepinephrine has the opposite effect of acetylcholine, causing the heart rate to <input_ref input="i8" />, bringing the blood pressure back up.</p><p>At the same time, a drop in blood pressure will stimulate the brainstem to direct the release of norepinephrine to some blood vessels, which causes them to constrict, causing the blood pressure to <input_ref input="i9" />. A return to the normal rate of norepinephrine release allows the blood vessels to return to normal diameter and blood pressure usually returns back to normal.</p><p>Another negative feedback loop regulates blood pressure by using the kidneys to regulate fluid levels in the body. If the kidneys excrete more fluid from the body, it causes the total volume of body fluids such as blood to decrease. As the blood volume falls, blood pressure would <input_ref input="i10" />. If the kidneys were stimulated to conserve more fluid in the body, that could cause the volume of blood to increase, and blood pressure could <input_ref input="i11" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="i5" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1a">variable</choice><choice value="v1b">receptor</choice><choice value="v1c">control center</choice><choice value="v1d">effector</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i6" shuffle="false"><choice value="v1a">variable</choice><choice value="v1b">receptor</choice><choice value="v1c">control center</choice><choice value="v1d">effector</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i7" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">increase</choice><choice value="v3b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i8" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">increases</choice><choice value="v3b">decreases</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i9" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">increase</choice><choice value="v3b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i10" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">increase</choice><choice value="v3b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="i11" shuffle="false"><choice value="v3a">increase</choice><choice value="v3b">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="i7ba6d9dc3b7043c3b9f7e2a436123375"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i5" match="v1a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Blood pressure is the variable being monitored and controlled.</feedback></response><response input="i5" match="v1b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Receptors would detect changes in the blood pressure.</feedback></response><response input="i5" match="v1c" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The control center would determine what changes need to be made for proper adjustment of blood pressure.</feedback></response><response input="i5" match="v1d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Effectors would execute the necessary changes to adjust blood pressure.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what is being controlled or adjusted in this feedback loop example.</hint></part><part id="a2c0d7c1f3f34cbd94f6bb8f366806a7"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i6" match="v1a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The variable is the thing that is being monitored and controlled.</feedback></response><response input="i6" match="v1b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Receptors would detect changes in the blood pressure.</feedback></response><response input="i6" match="v1c" score="1"><feedback>Correct. The brainstem determines what changes need to be made for proper adjustment of blood pressure.</feedback></response><response input="i6" match="v1d" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Effectors would execute the necessary changes to adjust the blood pressure.</feedback></response><hint>Think about what is determining the changes that are needed in this feedback loop example.</hint></part><part id="e31450110a9b41598b5a51577bc074e8"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i7" match="v3a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect, if the heart rate were to increase, the blood pressure would continue to increase in a positive feedback loop.</feedback></response><response input="i7" match="v3b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If the heart rate decreases, the blood pressure will also decrease.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the effect of heart rate on blood pressure.</hint></part><part id="i8d1ce614d24041c3a9565747cda6db92"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i8" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If the heart rate increases, the blood pressure will also increase.</feedback></response><response input="i8" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect, if the heart rate were to decrease, the blood pressure would continue to decrease in a positive feedback loop.</feedback></response><hint>Think about effect of heart rate on blood pressure.</hint></part><part id="d0f9575316864f81a3aafcb5b5deb970"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i9" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If blood vessels constrict, the blood pressure will rise.</feedback></response><response input="i9" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If blood vessels constrict, diameter decreases and will cause an opposite change in the blood pressure.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the opposite effect of blood vessel diameter on blood pressure.</hint></part><part id="a4a49ccc2b07460a961149d5ecdc9bb5"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i10" match="v3a" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If blood volume falls, the blood pressure also falls, unless something else compensates for that drop.</feedback></response><response input="i10" match="v3b" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If blood volume falls, the blood pressure also falls, unless something else compensates for that drop.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the effect that changing the total volume (amount) of blood flowing through the heart and blood vessels would have on blood pressure.</hint></part><part id="i9bcb5e384f0d4435ab53867a470fdd61"><skillref idref="_u3_describe_negative_SKILL" /><response input="i11" match="v3a" score="1"><feedback>Correct. If the blood volume increases, the blood pressure also increases, unless something else compensates for that increase.</feedback></response><response input="i11" match="v3b" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the blood volume increases, the blood pressure also increases, unless something else compensates for that increase.</feedback></response><hint>Think about the effect that changing the volume of blood flowing through the heart and blood vessels would have on blood pressure.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
