<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_define_digt"><title>Define Homeo</title><page id="page_0"><question id="_u3_define_digt_0"><body>Homeostasis allows us to:</body><multiple_choice id="qsub_0" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Jump over a piece of broken glass when we see it.</choice><choice value="B">Hit a baseball when it is pitched to us.</choice><choice value="C">Increase our blood pressure when we are stressed.</choice><choice value="D">Maintain our blood sodium levels after eating a bag of salty pretzels.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an example of a conscious response to an environmental cue. Although this reaction might prevent our body from having to take steps to regulate the internal state (if we allowed a cut to happen), it is not an example of homeostasis by itself.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This is an example of a learned motor response (reflex), which does not have to do with regulating our internal environment.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Regulating blood pressure near a constant value is an example of how the body homeostasis occurs. But when blood pressure increases away from the target value, this is not an example of homeostasis, but an example of a process that disrupts homeostasis.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Regulating blood sodium levels is critical to the function of cells within the body. Therefore, there are body systems that regulate this value, even when challenged by a high amount of salt in the diet.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="_u3_define_digt2_0"><body><p>Describe how each of the following levels of organization contribute to homeostasis of cellular ATP levels during exercise.</p><p>Cellular:</p></body><short_answer id="qsub_0" /><part id="qpart_0"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response input="qsub_0" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>Although there are many correct answers, one example would be that chemical reactions that regulate the amount of ATP within the cell. Certain enzymes in the enzymatic pathway for making ATP will be inhibited when ATP levels are high (called feedback inhibition), while these same enzymes will not be inhibited when ATP is low. Exercise stimulates a use in ATP and a de-inhibition of these enzymes in order to maintain ATP levels within the cell.</explanation></part></question><question id="_u3_define_digt2_1"><body>Organ (in this case a whole muscle):</body><short_answer id="qsub_1" /><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response input="qsub_1" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>One way that a whole muscle can maintain ATP levels during exercise is to affect the amount of blood flow to the organ. Local tissues/organs are important regulators of flow to themselves, releasing chemicals that constrict or dilate the blood vessels that feed the organs. In the case of exercise, blood flow to muscles can increase significantly, providing the oxygen and glucose necessary for ATP production. </explanation></part></question><question id="_u3_define_digt2_2"><body>Organ Systems:</body><short_answer id="qsub_1" /><part id="qpart_1"><skillref idref="_u3_define_homeostasis_SKILL" /><response input="qsub_1" match="*" score="10" /><explanation>In order to maintain ATP levels in the muscles during exercise, the muscles need to obtain an increased level of blood flow. The muscles themselves contribute by dilating the blood vessels that feed them, but this must be matched by an increase in cardiac output from the heart. Therefore the heart increased cardiac output, often from a resting state near 5 liters/min to a value near 15 L/min.</explanation></part></question></page></assessment>
