<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="NervousSystemIntroduction_2">
	<head>
		<title>The Components of the Nervous System </title>
		<objref idref="describe_nervous_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		
		<p>Imagine that you decide to bake a cake for your Anatomy and Physiology professor’s
			birthday. You find a recipe, locate the ingredients and then one by one, measure and add
			each to the mixing bowl. You stir the mixture and before you know it, the cake is in the
			oven and you can return to your homework. You start to salivate as a yummy chocolate
			aroma wafts through the room. The timer goes off, but unfortunately, when removing the
			pan from the oven you burn your hand through a hole in the hot pad. Rather than dropping
			the cake, you make a split second decision to hold on, enduring the pain so that you can
			set the cake pan down safely even though the consequences of a burnt hand will be with
			you for a few days. All aspects of baking a cake from your decision to bake a cake, to
			reading the recipe, measuring and mixing ingredients, smelling a delicious chocolate
			aroma and automatically starting to salivate in case you decide to sneak a piece of
			cake, and withdrawing your hand to prevent a burn are functions of the nervous system.
			Although quite different behaviors, they all include the general functions of the
			nervous system listed below:</p>
		<ol>
			<li><em style="italic">The nervous system detects changes in our internal and external environment (stimuli) 
				using specific neurons or specialized cells communicating with neurons called </em><term>sensory receptors</term>. <p>Sensory receptors can detect a variety
			of different external and internal stimuli such as: skin temperature, light (for
			vision), sound, chemicals in food (taste) and air (smells), pressure, pain, blood pH,
			core body temperature, bladder distension as well as many other stimuli.</p></li>
			<li><em style="italic">Sensory receptors transform stimuli into <term>electric signals</term> that
				our nervous system can understand. </em><p>The nervous system cannot directly interpret
				stimuli like light, heat or sound. The information has to be transformed into an
				electrical signal for the nervous system to receive and process the information.</p></li>
			<li><em style="italic">Sensory <term>neurons</term> transmit the electrical signals from the periphery
				to the <term>central nervous system</term> (brain and spinal cord). </em><p>This information travels
				from the <term>sensory receptor</term> (the site of transformation) along neural processes called
				<term>axons</term> towards the central nervous system (<term>CNS</term>).</p></li>
			<li><em style="italic">The central nervous system (brain and spinal cord) processes
				incoming sensory information to generate “appropriate” responses and also to give us
				the perception of the stimulus. </em><p>The signal can be compared to a normal value
				(set point) or related to past experiences to determine if the stimulus requires a
				response. Processing of the signal is called <term>integration</term>. In order to perceive a
				stimulus, the sensory information must be transmitted to specific areas of the
				brain.</p></li>
			<li><em style="italic">The central nervous system sends commands (electrical signals
				passed along neurons) out to the target tissues to produce the response. </em><p>The
				target tissues of the nervous system are muscles and glands.</p></li></ol>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_nervous_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				
	</body>
</workbook_page>
