<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment 2.3//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_2_3.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_assessment_2_3.css"?>
<assessment id="_u4_m3_checkpoint1" max_attempts="3" recommended_attempts="1">
    <title>Random Variables Checkpoint 1</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you
            are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window
            will ask "This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?",
            click "OK" if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p>
        <p>If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost.
            After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to
            be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p>
    </introduction>
    <!--<content available="instructor_only">
        <p><em>Instructors: you can download the solution set for this checkpoint by clicking on the
                following link:</em>
            <link href="../webcontent/_u4_m3_checkpoint1.pdf">Solution Set</link>.</p>
    </content>-->
    <section id="assess_06_accidents">
        <content>
            <p>The random variable X, representing the number of accidents in a certain intersection
                in a week, has the following probability distribution: </p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <td> x </td>
                    <td> 0 </td>
                    <td> 1 </td>
                    <td> 2 </td>
                    <td> 3 </td>
                    <td> 4 </td>
                    <td> 5 </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td> P(X=x) </td>
                    <td> 0.20 </td>
                    <td> 0.30 </td>
                    <td> 0.20 </td>
                    <td> 0.15 </td>
                    <td> 0.10 </td>
                    <td> 0.05 </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </content>
        <multiple_choice id="prob3-1" select="single">
            <body>
                <p>The random variable X, representing the number of accidents in a certain
                    intersection in a week, has the following probability distribution: </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <td> x </td>
                        <td> 0 </td>
                        <td> 1 </td>
                        <td> 2 </td>
                        <td> 3 </td>
                        <td> 4 </td>
                        <td> 5 </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td> P(X=x) </td>
                        <td> 0.20 </td>
                        <td> 0.30 </td>
                        <td> 0.20 </td>
                        <td> 0.15 </td>
                        <td> 0.10 </td>
                        <td> 0.05 </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                <p>What is the probability that in a given week there will be at most 3
                    accidents?</p>
            </body>
            <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 0.70 </choice>
                <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 0.85 </choice>
                <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 0.35 </choice>
                <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 0.15 </choice>
                <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; 1.00 </choice>
            </input>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have found the probability that in a
                        given week there will be less than 3 accidents. Recall that you want to find
                        the probability that in a given week there will be at most 3 accidents. In
                        other words, what is the probability that in a given week there will be less
                        than 4 accidents?</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. P(X &#8804; 3) = 0.20 + 0.30 + 0.20 + 0.15 = 0.85 or P(X &#8804;
                        3) = 1 - P(X &#8804; 4) = 1 - (0.10 + 0.05) = 1 - 0.15 = 0.85 </feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have found the probability that in a
                        given week there will be either 2 or 3 accidents. Recall that you want to
                        find the probability that in a given week there will be at most 3 accidents.
                        As a result, you must take into account the probability that in a given week
                        there will be no accidents, 1 accident, 2 accidents, and 3
                        accidents.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have found the probability of the
                        complementary event, that in a given week there will be more than 3
                        accidents. Recall that you want to find the probability that in a given week
                        there will be at most 3 accidents.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that if an event has probability 1 of occurring,
                        then it must contain all outcomes in the sample space that have non-zero
                        probability of occurring. Notice that the probability that in a given week
                        there are more than 3 accidents is non-zero. This means that the probability
                        that in a given week there are at most 3 accidents must not be equal to
                        1.</feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
        </multiple_choice>
        <multiple_choice id="prob3-2" select="single">
            <body>
                <p>The random variable X, representing the number of accidents in a certain
                    intersection in a week, has the following probability distribution: </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <td> x </td>
                        <td> 0 </td>
                        <td> 1 </td>
                        <td> 2 </td>
                        <td> 3 </td>
                        <td> 4 </td>
                        <td> 5 </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td> P(X=x) </td>
                        <td> 0.20 </td>
                        <td> 0.30 </td>
                        <td> 0.20 </td>
                        <td> 0.15 </td>
                        <td> 0.10 </td>
                        <td> 0.05 </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                <p>By the third day of a particular week, 2 accidents have already occurred in the
                    intersection. What is the probability that there will be less than a total of 4
                    accidents during that week?</p>
            </body>
            <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 1.00 </choice>
                <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 0.90 </choice>
                <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 0.85 </choice>
                <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 0.70 </choice>
                <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; 0.50 </choice>
            </input>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The fact that 2 accidents have occurred over the course of
                        the first 3 days in a week does not imply that these are the only accidents
                        that will occur in the intersection for that entire week. However, this
                        information does imply that there must be at least 2 accidents over the
                        course of that week, because 2 accidents have already occurred.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have found: given that 2 accidents have
                        already occurred, the probability that less than 5 accidents will occur in
                        that week. Recall that you want to find: given that 2 accidents have already
                        occurred, the probability that less than 4 accidents will occur in the
                        entire week.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have found the probability that in a
                        given week there are at most 3 accidents. Recall that you are given the fact
                        that two accidents have occurred in the first 3 days and you want to find
                        the probability that there are less than 4 accidents in the week. You should
                        be conditioning in some way on the fact that 2 accidents have already
                        occurred during the week.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. We are given that 2 accidents have already happened. In other
                        words, we are given X ≥ 2 and we need to find how likely X is to be less than
                        4. <image style="block" src="../webcontent/6_formula1.gif"/>
                    </feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have found the probability that in a
                        given week there are at least 2 accidents. Recall that you want to find,
                        given that 2 accidents have already occurred, the probability that less than
                        4 accidents will occur in the entire week.</feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
        </multiple_choice>
        <multiple_choice id="prob3-3" select="single">
            <body>
                <p>The random variable X, representing the number of accidents in a certain
                    intersection in a week, has the following probability distribution: </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <td> x </td>
                        <td> 0 </td>
                        <td> 1 </td>
                        <td> 2 </td>
                        <td> 3 </td>
                        <td> 4 </td>
                        <td> 5 </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td> P(X=x) </td>
                        <td> 0.20 </td>
                        <td> 0.30 </td>
                        <td> 0.20 </td>
                        <td> 0.15 </td>
                        <td> 0.10 </td>
                        <td> 0.05 </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                <p>On average, how many accidents are there in the intersection in a week?</p>
            </body>
            <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
                <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; 5.3 </choice>
                <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; 2.5 </choice>
                <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; 1.8 </choice>
                <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; 0.30 </choice>
                <choice value="E"> &#160;&#160; 0.1667 </choice>
            </input>
            <part>
                <response match="A" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. Notice that the maximum number of accidents allowed in a
                        week in this distribution is 5. This implies that the average number of
                        accidents in a week must be at most 5.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="B" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. It seems that you have weighted each of the possible
                        numbers of accidents in a week equally. Remember that the average, or mean,
                        of a distribution is a weighted sum of the possible outcomes, in which each
                        weight is equal to the probability of that outcome occurring.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="C" score="10">
                    <feedback>Correct. We need to find the mean of X, μx. μx = (0 * 0.20) + (1 *
                        0.30) + (2 * 0.20) + (3 * 0.15) + (4 * 0.10) + (5 * 0.05) = 1.8.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="D" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The average of a distribution is generally not the same as
                        the most likely outcome of that distribution. Remember that the average, or
                        mean, of a distribution is a weighted sum of the possible outcomes, where
                        each weight is equal to the probability of that outcome
                        occurring.</feedback>
                </response>
                <response match="E" score="0">
                    <feedback>Incorrect. The average of a distribution is generally not the same as
                        1/|S|, where S is the sample space and |S| represents the number of outcomes
                        in the sample space. Remember that the average, or mean, of a distribution
                        is a weighted sum of the possible outcomes where each weight is equal to the
                        probability of that outcome occurring.</feedback>
                </response>
            </part>
        </multiple_choice>
    </section>
    <multiple_choice id="prob3-4" select="single">
        <body>
            <p> The following three histograms represent the probability distributions of the three
                random variables X, Y, and Z. </p>
            <p>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment6q4image1.gif"/>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment6q4image2.gif"/>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment6q4image3.gif"/>
            </p>
            <p> Which of the three random variables has the largest standard deviation? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A"> &#160;&#160; X </choice>
            <choice value="B"> &#160;&#160; Y </choice>
            <choice value="C"> &#160;&#160; Z </choice>
            <choice value="D"> &#160;&#160; All three random variables have the same standard
                deviation. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. All of these variables take on the same values (1 - 5), but the
                    one with the largest standard deviation will take on values further from the
                    mean much more often than values closer to the mean. There is another random
                    variable other than X that has more values further from the mean.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. All of these variables take on the same values (1 - 5), but the
                    one with the largest standard deviation will take on values further from the
                    mean much more often than values closer to the mean. Most of the values for Y
                    are close to the mean so this random variable would have the smallest standard
                    deviation.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. All three random variables take the values 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and it
                    is pretty easy to see (by symmetry) that the mean of all three random variables
                    is 3. The random variables are different, though, with respect to how likely
                    they are to have values that are “far” from the mean. We see that out of the
                    three random variables, random variable Z is the most likely to have values 1
                    and 5 (which are the furthest from the mean), and therefore Z has the largest
                    standard deviation. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although the random variables take on the same values, they do
                    not have equal standard deviations. For example, random variable X will have a
                    larger standard deviation than random variable Y because it takes on values 2
                    and 4 more often.<!-- Consider the remaining options. (C) is the right answer.-->
                </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</assessment>
