<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_fast_slow_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body><p>The structure of different muscle fiber types allows them to perform specific functions. Extrapolate from the description what function these structures would lend themselves to.</p><p>These fibers contain a lot of mitochondria so that they can:</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">produce ATP anaerobically.</choice><choice value="B">produce ATP aerobically.</choice><choice value="C">produce ATP using glycolysis.</choice><choice value="D">produce ATP using fermentation.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i904d0a434e9c4d918da862a94dccd9be"><skillref idref="_u5_fast_slow_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Anaerobic respiration occurs in the cytoplasm and produces less energy than is possible with the mitochondria.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The more mitochondria you have the more oxygen you can use to combine with glucose to make energy.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. glycolysis occurs in the cytoplasm and produces less energy than is possible with the mitochondria.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fermentation occurs in the cytoplasm and produces less energy than is possible with the mitochondria.</feedback></response><hint>Mitochondria are the location of a specific type of respiration that produces the most ATP.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>These fibers have a relatively small diameters so they:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">can produce less tension but contract for a longer period of time.</choice><choice value="B">can produce more tension and contract for longer period of time.</choice><choice value="C">can produce more tension and contract for a shorter period of time.</choice><choice value="D">can produce less tension but contract for a shorter period of time.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="caa8e123a5ba4796a367ae642f80f0ce"><skillref idref="_u5_fast_slow_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Smaller diameter decreases the tension and increases how long it takes the muscle to fatigue.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The smaller diameter decreases the amount of tension.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The smaller diameter decreases the amount of tension and increases how long it takes the muscle to fatigue.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The smaller diameter increases how long it takes the muscle to fatigue.</feedback></response><hint>These fibers are slow twitch fibers.</hint></part></question><question id="q3"><body>These fibers have a large blood supply and myoglobin in them so they can:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Have enough carbon dioxide to enable anaerobic metabolism.</choice><choice value="B">Have enough oxygen to enable anaerobic metabolism.</choice><choice value="C">Have enough carbon dioxide to enable aerobic metabolism.</choice><choice value="D">Have enough oxygen to enable aerobic metabolism.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i2295f638a6404c5aab39bf3a32ff6184"><skillref idref="_u5_fast_slow_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Carbon dioxide can be produces by anaerbic respiration but is not required for it.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. anaerobic metabolism occurs in the absence of oxygen.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Oxygen is required from aerobic metabolism, not carbon dioxide.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Myoglobin contains oxygen which can be used for aerobic respiration.</feedback></response><hint>Anaerobic metabolism does not require oxygen.</hint></part></question><question id="q4"><body>If we combine the functions of all these structures together we get a fiber that can create a lot of energy aerobically and sustain low tension contractions for a long period of time. This type of fiber is a:</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Slow oxidative</choice><choice value="B">Fast oxidative</choice><choice value="C">Fast glycolytic</choice><choice value="D">Slow glycolytic</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i15cfadf6a6124139ad28fe39b0c16094"><skillref idref="_u5_fast_slow_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Slow oxidative fibers have all of these characteristics.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fast oxidative have some of these characteristics but have intermediate fatigue resistance.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Fast glycolytic produce high amounts of tension for short amounts of time.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. There is not a fiber that has this name.</feedback></response><hint>Think of which process requires more oxidation.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
