<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_org_tissue_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The specialized structures found in muscle cells allow the cells to perform their functions more efficiently. Which of the following correctly describes the role of parts of a triad?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The T tubules create an action potential. The terminal cisternae store magnesium.</choice><choice value="B">The T tubules are part of the endoplasmic reticulum a make proteins. The terminal cisternae are part of the endoplasmic reticulum that store calcium.</choice><choice value="C">The T tubules store calcium. The terminal cisternae allow action potential to travel into the muscle cells.</choice><choice value="D">The T tubules allow the action potential to travel into the muscle cells. The terminal cisternae store calcium.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i5e06f5d75514475ca7c70ebe059df8cc"><skillref idref="_u5_org_tissue_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The terminal cisternae store calcium, not the T tubules that are extensions of the sarcolemma.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The T tubules are part of the sarcolemma, not the endoplasmic reticulum.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The terminal cisternae store calcium, not the T tubules that are extensions of the sarcolemma.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The T tubules are extensions of the sarcolemma that extend into the cell to transmit the signal, and the cisternae are part of the sarcoplasmic reticulum.</feedback></response><hint>Transverse tubules are part of the sarcolemma.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
