<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_distribution_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>The amount of each type of muscle fiber that a person has is in part determined by their genetic make-up. This genetic make up differs from person to person. For example you would expect someone who is really good at sprinting to have a high percentage of what type of fiber?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">SO</choice><choice value="B">FG</choice><choice value="C">FO</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i7c8e516a388047aca360e7a1200cee88"><skillref idref="_u5_distribution_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. You would expect to find SO fibers in a long distance runner because they provide less explosive energy but take longer to fatigue.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. You would expect to find FG fibers because they provide short bursts of high tension contractions good for sprinting.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. FO fibers have characteristics that are in between the other types of fibers and do not supply the same burst of high tension as FG fibers would.</feedback></response><hint>This fiber must produce a lot of tension fast.</hint></part></question><question id="q2"><body>If this person wanted to increase the efficiency of their FG fibers what type of exercises would they want to do?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Anaerobic</choice><choice value="B">Aerobic</choice></multiple_choice><part id="bfa638a416714e1eb18afe5f7159ec4d"><skillref idref="_u5_distribution_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Anaerobic because FG fibers need a fast source of energy and do not have time for aerobic respiration to happen.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Aerobic excises will increase the SO fibers.</feedback></response><hint>FG fibers do not require as much oxygen as SO fibers.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
