<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u5_twtich_lbd"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>A skeletal muscle fiber has a resting membrane potential that must be depolarized before an impulse can begin and cause a muscle twitch. This means there is a threshold stimulus that must be reached for the fiber to contract. Use this information to pick the most accurate statement from below.</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The “All or Nothing” Theory of muscle contraction states: If the muscle fiber reaches the threshold stimulus of +30mV then the muscle fiber will be in summation and can enter tetanus.</choice><choice value="B">The “All or Nothing” Theory of muscle contraction states: If the threshold stimulus of + 30mV is not reached no part of the fiber will contract; once the threshold stimulus of+30mV is reached the whole muscle fiber will contract.</choice><choice value="C">The “All or Nothing” Theory of muscle contraction states: None of the muscle will contract until the threshold stimulus of +30mV is reached. Once it is reached the muscle fiber will enter tetanus.</choice><choice value="D">The “All or Nothing” Theory of muscle contraction states: Once one muscle fiber reaches the threshold stimulus of 30mV the entire muscle will automatically contract.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i02b0aea8964144bb83fdda09ba97a0cf"><skillref idref="_u5_twitch_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In order to reach tetanus the muscle has to be stimulated multiple times and maintain a sustained contraction.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Once the threshold is reached the entire fiber will contract.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In order to reach tetanus the muscle has to be stimulated multiple times and maintain a sustained contraction.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A muscle (organ) consists of multiple muscle fibers that each need to be stimulated.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
