<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_levels_org_quiz" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="6"><title>Respiratory Levels of Organization</title><introduction><p id="b11d7bea7ab44e22973df51f6609a64f">You may save your work at any time by clicking on <em style="bold">Save</em>. When you are finished working, click on <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, a pop up window will ask &quot;This will submit your answers and finish this assignment. Are you sure?&quot;, click &quot;OK&quot; if you are ready to submit your answers for final grading. </p><p id="c9d6d6bd52d0452f83872d1c91a05083">If you close this window without having saved or submitted, your changes will be lost. After pressing <em style="bold">Submit and Finish</em>, please wait for your answers to be scored. <em style="bold">Do NOT</em> click on it more than once.</p></introduction><page id="b55a9220628c458c85e5d6e65d47b488"><multiple_choice id="gas_exchange_lung" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae638b6d2ea394c97ab67570ddf40a663">Gas exchange at the respiratory membrane is known as:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f6cc9d053312461e870668f5ee3c1fa5" labels="false"><choice value="A">Ventilation</choice><choice value="B">External respiration</choice><choice value="C">Internal respiration</choice><choice value="D">Cellular respiration</choice></input><part id="gas_exchange_lung_p1"><skillref idref="differentiate_between_internal_external_respiration" /><skillref idref="define_external_respiration" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="afb8184ef04364f7b93e91f1da8aaf1d9">Incorrect. Ventilation is the movement of air into and out of our lungs.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="aa8919efe2ca24f45898cb8d7a2ee871a">Correct. External respiration is the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide at the respiratory membrane.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae086ed9254db4977b559bfee4040e8de">Incorrect. Internal respiration is the exchange of gas between the tissues and the blood.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa9118b2bc678458f92c1c64aa09571ad">Incorrect. Cellular respiration is a process used to convert nutrients to energy.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="oxygen_nutrients" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="addfd5d473b4b4a25aee83f17bf769ce9">In order to convert nutrients to energy the human body requires:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a68d04cfd3314076b8aafb76e06c453c" labels="false"><choice value="A">Carbon dioxide</choice><choice value="B">Carbon monoxide</choice><choice value="C">Water</choice><choice value="D">Oxygen</choice></input><part id="oxygen_nutrients_p1"><skillref idref="explain_necessity_oxygen" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="acf894d02727f4407962ca48e87f986ba">Incorrect. Carbon dioxide is released as a waste product while energy is being produced.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="addfceddb8e1d425b9e77798800453b03">Incorrect. Carbon monoxide is a poison that can inhibit oxygen transport in the blood.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae2dd005ecedd4688bedbc1cb1ddaadaa">Incorrect. Water will be produced as part of the energy releasing process.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac79fa2f59e3e4397a2988b187c9fe49c">Correct. Oxygen is required to obtain energy from nutrients such as glucose.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="henrys_law" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae6ce8305a28945bb90097f5ad68ea236">When a bottle of pop is opened you will hear the characteristic hissing that signifies the escaping of carbon dioxide from the liquid into the atmosphere. Which gas law explains why this occurs?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a66b88917b264ecc88f52bd78e2c3f46" labels="false"><choice value="A">Boyle’s Law</choice><choice value="B">Gay-Lussac’s Law</choice><choice value="C">Henry’s Law</choice><choice value="D">Charles’s Law</choice></input><part id="henrys_law_p1"><skillref idref="apply_boyles_law" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aadc7d7a9e9f4190aab54aa0e336474f">Incorrect. Boyle studied the relationship between the pressure and volume of a gas. He came up with the relationship P<sub>1</sub>V<sub>1</sub>= P<sub>2</sub>V<sub>2</sub></p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="acc397de0431d470aa7043c9afaf27f18">Incorrect. Gay Lussac studied how the volumes of gases interacted in chemical reactions and came up with his law of combining volumes.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ae1adc2a5d4054f52b34744b6dc4e262a">Correct. Henry’s law states that the solubility of a gas is proportional to the partial pressure of the gas above the liquid. As the can of pop is opened the partial pressure of the atmosphere is lower and some of the dissolved carbon dioxide comes out of the solution.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="aad16ad8464bf4e78b4ee4f5601d7adb8">Incorrect. Charles’ law is based on the observations he made about the relationship between the temperature of gas and the volume of a gas. His law states that the volume of a gas is directly proportional to its temperature.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="henrys_law_1" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac0463777176b4f75a099bd76eb4c37f3">If a person is visiting Denver, CO (the mile high city) Why may they need to increase the rate of ventilation until they adapt?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="e8da3133051f4c61807b99e56875fc6c" labels="false"><choice value="A">The concentration of oxygen is higher at higher altitudes which means it will be harder to move the oxygen into our plasma.</choice><choice value="B">The concentration of oxygen is lower at higher altitudes which means it will be harder to move the oxygen into our plasma.</choice><choice value="C">The partial pressure of oxygen is higher at higher altitudes which means it will be harder to move the oxygen into our plasma.</choice><choice value="D">The partial pressure of oxygen is lower at higher altitudes which means it will be harder to move the oxygen into our plasma.</choice></input><part id="henrys_law_1_p1"><skillref idref="explain_pulmonary_ventilation" /><skillref idref="apply_boyles_law" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aea5c666bb386416293ae92f90bd1ef99">Incorrect. The concentration of oxygen in Earth’s atmosphere is 21% and this is constant and does not change with altitude.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="afcca3a7a4c2040fd9e1a343419d2a79f">Incorrect. The concentration of oxygen in Earth’s atmosphere is 21% and this is constant and does not change with altitude.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aef36608eed694aab9269c442b4edf5f0">Incorrect. According to Henry’s law, if the partial pressure of oxygen increased it would be easier to dissolve the oxygen in solution, not harder.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="af19e75c022d54d909e5f90217e86a405">Correct. According to Henry’s law, if the partial pressure of oxygen decreases it will be harder to dissolve the oxygen in solution. This means our body will have to compensate by increasing our rate of respiration.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="mechanisms_gas_exchange" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae7305b815bac4bcab3baf9cd06aa741e">During external respiration,the partial pressure of oxygen is higher in the pulmonary arteries is higher than in alveoli.</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="a1cc3b3e56694beca2bf556a92477a57" labels="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></input><part id="mechanisms_gas_exchange_p1"><skillref idref="define_external_respiration" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac7065244d2114a3fb7693354e5dc0eca">Incorrect. Oxygen will move from an area of high partial pressure to an area of lower partial pressure. So if the partial pressure was higher in the pulmonary arteries oxygen would would move from the blood to the alveoli.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac5034a042a5e45f5a49686d2bc5c9931">Correct. Oxygen will move from the higher partial pressure of the alveoli and into the the capillaries that branched off of of the pulmonary arteries. This will allow blood to be transported around the body.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="external_respiration" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="afacd5e2dfc23492a831a36fc7ff1dd4f">Which of the following accurately describe external respiration?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f99c93834a464307bbf10746b864c927" labels="false"><choice value="A">The partial pressure of oxygen is lower in the pulmonary capillaries because the oxygen from the blood has been used by the body tissues so oxygen will diffuse from the alveoli into the capillaries.</choice><choice value="B">The partial pressure of carbon dioxide is lower in the pulmonary capillaries because the body has created carbon dioxide a waste product so it will diffuse into the alveoli.</choice><choice value="C">The partial pressure of carbon dioxide is higher in the tissues because cells constantly producing it as a waste product so it will diffuse into the capillaries.</choice><choice value="D">The partial pressure of oxygen is lower in the tissues because cells are constantly using it to make energy so oxygen will diffuse from the capillaries into the body tissue.</choice></input><part id="external_respiration_p1"><skillref idref="define_external_respiration" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac1282563b8c84131980eb1e90bfb8b0c">Correct. In external respiration there is an exchange of oxygen from the alveoli into the capillaries and of carbon dioxide into the alveoli from the capillaries.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="af982ba91ff1a45e1b9b82a5b8dac6c10">Incorrect. The partial of carbon dioxide is higher in the pulmonary capillaries because the cells of the body have created it as a waste product of metabolism. This carbon dioxide will diffuse into the alveoli.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac2025dc3a3b243f79ce8ab40e4db6b84">Incorrect. This is a correct description of internal respiration which is the exchange of gasses between the tissues and the blood capillaries.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="addc8d3bc0c3f4da2ab49914ce470d80a">Incorrect. This is a correct description of internal respiration which is the exchange of gasses between the tissues and the blood capillaries.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="mucins" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af511e087fc9c4a1a8d60e3a56e087e23">Which component of mucus allows it to maintain local level of hydration?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f95b8752463d44209fa7366c7071ce5b" labels="false"><choice value="A">Immunoglobulins</choice><choice value="B">Salt</choice><choice value="C">Mucins</choice><choice value="D">Hemoglobin</choice></input><part id="mucins_p1"><skillref idref="relate_structure_function_mucus" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad5c97364ff914f7dab81044111fe8d0b">Incorrect. Immunoglobulins function in the role of protecting the body from pathogens.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aad9db5e63652490d8100a3a7b51bfd72">Incorrect. Salts play different roles in water balance but are not the primary component of mucus that allows for local hydration.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="abcef1fd257754a42ae81b6917aaa667d">Correct. Mucins are high molecular weight proteins with glycosylations that attract large amounts of water.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="abffdd47442ad4d7ea7e90f282d93dc44">Incorrect. Hemoglobin is a protein found in red blood cells that carries oxygen</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="lack_of_surfactant" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="acd6a0b2eda694e4393b94e3382bb23a1">A baby born prematurely may lack surfactant which can result in:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a8a5388829494b13a9db3d2b614cf406" labels="false"><choice value="A">A lack of hydration in the respiratory system.</choice><choice value="B">Increased amount of respiratory infections because of a lack of immunoglobulin.</choice><choice value="C">The alveoli may end up collapsing during exhalation.</choice><choice value="D">A decrease in the red blood cells ability to transport oxygen.</choice></input><part id="lack_of_surfactant_p1"><skillref idref="describe_function_surfacant" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad6bfb0991d2a4a8fb6663d7ecb44af74">Incorrect. A baby lacking mucus will cause a lack of hydration not surfactant.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab940bdba3e9648e2891840c62f1a31c8">Incorrect. Immunoglobulins can be found in the mucus and in the blood, it is not a functiof surfactant.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad28e53b436db4dae862e657a7f4c9b59">Correct. The function of surfactant is to disrupt the surface tension of the alveoli and prevent them from collapsing.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab700ba72b31a4afc84a498e263c8110d">Incorrect. Hemoglobin is the macromolecule found in red blood cells that carries oxygen not surfactant.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="parts_hemoglobin" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="aa9eb82fffc9a4863bf3bae4de1176856">Which part of hemoglobin is not properly matched with its description?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="ad527ac280834c448359cb70afdbf44d" labels="false"><choice value="A">Globin is the protein portion of the hemoglobin that provides structure.</choice><choice value="B">Heme is the planar ring portion of hemoglobin that provides stability.</choice><choice value="C">Iron is the metal portion of hemoglobin that binds to oxygen.</choice><choice value="D">All of the parts of the hemoglobin molecule are correctly matched.</choice></input><part id="parts_hemoglobin_p1"><skillref idref="identify_parts_hemoglobin" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac6a521050b7543a8aaac0225f9a5a5ca">Incorrect. Although the globin part is the protein portion of the hemoglobin it is not the only correctly described portion.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="aac59d996a86e4d658a772d6367526067">Incorrect. Although heme is the planar ring portion of the hemoglobin, it is not the only correctly described portion.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ae22bbf4466a144d8aaece5bcdae99b08">Incorrect. Although the iron is the metal portion of the hemoglobin it is not the only correctly described portion.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaf83281e91164c7ea6eecd20c8203b34">Correct. All three parts of a hemoglobin molecule are correctly matched with their descriptions.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="transport_oxygen_blood" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="af4168ea2ddf649d4979b4f8be3c4ffb5">Oxygen is transport in the blood by:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d3b78b8b9b8d449e860fcac8ba9d89a9" labels="false"><choice value="A">Myoglobin, hemoglobin, white blood cells</choice><choice value="B">Myoglobin, hemoglobin, dissolved in the plasma</choice><choice value="C">Hemoglobin, red blood cells, white blood cells</choice><choice value="D">Hemoglobin,red blood cells, dissolved in the plasma</choice></input><part id="transport_oxygen_blood_p1"><skillref idref="describe_functions_hemoglobin" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="add2821a50484427e8aa69d57a36c3328">Incorrect. Myoglobin stores oxygen in the muscle cells. Oxygen is carried by hemoglobin but that is a protein which is located in red blood cells not white blood cells. White blood cells participate in the immune response and do not transport oxygen.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="add9a08ef6d4147fc856b48dc5c54fa72">Incorrect. Myoglobin stores oxygen in the muscle cells. Hemoglobin is a protein found in red blood cells that transports the majority of oxygen to body tissues. Some oxygen is dissolved and transported in the blood plasma.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad2a1fbc9936141bf8249dc9d917b5f2a">Incorrect. Even though, hemoglobin is a protein found in red blood cells that transports the majority of oxygen to body tissues. White blood cells participate in the immune response and do not transport oxygen.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac1499b577dea407e9c14e747d0413028">Correct. Red blood cells contain high concentrations of hemoglobin which is the protein that transports oxygen to the body’s tissues. Also, Even though oxygen is not very soluble in our blood plasma, a small amount of oxygen is transported in the blood plasma.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="heme" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ac60b1fed8ba541e3b994a950a62eea0d">If one heme group dissociates with oxygen it is easier for the other three heme groups in the hemoglobin molecules to dissociate with their oxygen.</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="df44546024f040b383b87d63a8784158" labels="false"><choice value="A">True</choice><choice value="B">False</choice></input><part id="heme_p1"><skillref idref="identify_parts_hemoglobin" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback><p id="afe664fa1cce449c6824bd18fc9649296">Correct. The affinity of oxygen to bind to a heme group changes based on whether oxygen is bound to other heme groups in the molecule.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="adc8803e7dec243b1b09a069588d8f3ca">Incorrect. The affinity of oxygen to bind to a heme group based on whether oxygen is bound to other heme groups in the same molecules. It helps to facilitate loading and unloading of oxygen.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><fill_in_the_blank id="lactic_acid" grading="automatic"><body><p id="d615739025d543f0b84131e6d724419c">As lactic acid builds up in the blood it will <input_ref input="A" /> the pH of the blood and <input_ref input="B" /> the association of oxygen with hemoglobin.</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="A"><choice value="one">raise</choice><choice value="two">lower</choice></input><input shuffle="false" id="B"><choice value="one">raise</choice><choice value="two">lower</choice></input><part id="p1"><skillref idref="predict_shift_oxygen-hemoglobin_dissociation" /><response match="one" score="0" name="raise" input="A"><feedback><p id="aa0c1f658631741c19d05dfa090ed6baf">Incorrect. pH and hydrogen ion concentration have an inverse relationship. Lactic acid will cause an increase in the hydrogen ion concentration because it is an acid, which will lower the pH. </p></feedback></response><response match="two" score="10" name="lower" input="A"><feedback><p id="ae4c57d9fd59e42228e8f7b19f4c43c47">Correct. pH and hydrogen ion concentration have an inverse relationship. As the blood becomes more acidic because of the lactic acid the pH will lower. </p></feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="predict_shift_oxygen-hemoglobin_dissociation" /><response match="one" score="0" name="raise" input="B"><feedback><p id="af0bf5c5d19ce45e08234e329936eb1c3">Incorrect. As the pH of the blood drops it signals to the body that there is a need for more oxygen. If the affinity between oxygen and hemoglobin was to increase, the oxygen would not be able to diffuse into the cells as readily for use.</p></feedback></response><response match="two" score="10" name="lower" input="B"><feedback><p id="adf365017fb1942dc8af26d1df213cf02">Correct. As the pH of the blood falls it signals to the body that there is a need for more oxygen. This will result in a lower affinity between oxygen and hemoglobin so oxygen can diffuse into the body cells for use. </p></feedback></response></part></fill_in_the_blank><multiple_choice id="carbon_dioxide_transport" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ae1a011b5c2624f7cbabcb2a130bc1a28">Which is the most common form mechanism of carbon dioxide transport?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d4f5e631000047569a97ac4f8a65a96e" labels="false"><choice value="A">Carbaminohemoglobin</choice><choice value="B">Carbon dioxide</choice><choice value="C">Bicarbonate</choice><choice value="D">Carbonic anhydrase</choice></input><part id="carbon_dioxide_transport_p1"><skillref idref="describe_carbon_dioxide_transport" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac59341c66379457aa24f52f719e9d508">Incorrect. Only about 20-23% of carbon dioxide is carried on the hemoglobin as carbaminohemoglobin.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ad170cdc1b22d4b7bb5872f735deff8b5">Incorrect. The major component of blood is water and carbon dioxide will undergo a chemical reaction with the water.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ad29c93451df84d7db2fa14e313aa9191">Correct. About 70% of carbon dioxide is transported in our blood as bicarbonate.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab2edcd2fa09a47caabe7a56ebeb96367">Incorrect. Carbonic anhydrase is an enzyme that catalyzes the reaction of water and carbon dioxide.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="type_1_alveolar_cells" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="abbe5085ba35b4215aca4587bc15aed01">Which of the following cell types is not matched properly with its function?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ea852709697c4188b7acb82cedb58a03" labels="false"><choice value="A">Ciliated cells- sweep mucus towards the pharynx.</choice><choice value="B">Goblet cells- secrete mucus.</choice><choice value="C">Basal cells- reproduce to regenerate and maintain epithelial layer.</choice><choice value="D">Type I alveolar cells- Secrete surfactant.</choice></input><part id="type_1_alveolar_cells_p1"><skillref idref="describe_locations_epithelial_tissue" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa7e3b420716a416594bdb6cfc95e00db">Incorrect. The ciliated cells have cilia on their apical surface that move mucus towards the pharynx to be swallowed.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac4bfe2bc36f044ee9eb32baf2d302fb0">Incorrect. Goblet cells secrete mucus to help trap microorganisms in the respiratory system.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac0f5395925354a659bdec018d3ab5f32">Incorrect. Basal cells are stem cells that continually reproduce to renew the epithelial cell layer of the respiratory tract.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback><p id="af9ec8deb0bd94fa996b7859079b94f7d">Correct. Type I alveolar cells are squamous cells that allow for easy diffusion of gases. Type II alveolar cells secrete surfactant.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="bronchial_ciliated_cells" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="acd787b25e98a459d882177a67cdbf987">Ciliated cells of the bronchial tree function to:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f2e2179fc5f846bdab4d9629bd8a318e" labels="false"><choice value="A">Receive and send sensory signals</choice><choice value="B">Secrete mucus</choice><choice value="C">Sweep mucus towards the pharynx</choice><choice value="D">Increase the surface area for diffusion</choice></input><part id="bronchial_ciliated_cells_p1"><skillref idref="describe_functions_epithelial_cells_airways" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa01b14d604ac448ca1d69bf8c1348ef4">Incorrect. The ciliated cells of the bronchial tree have the mechanical function of beating.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback><p id="ac3e3fb3fead3427b88b80cc567de542c">Incorrect. The goblet cells secrete the mucus, the ciliated cells move the mucus.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac902b7298eea49c98e0a47eadabf9abe">Correct. The cilia beat to create the mucociliary escalator that moves mucus and the microorganisms trapped in it towards the pharynx.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="ab28973f9460644dd88d934fe3edd969f">Incorrect. The diffusion of gas occurs through the squamous cells of the terminal bronchioles and alveoli.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>
