<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<TUTORIAL thisTitle="Biological Membranes" movieroot="">
<step stepURL="swfs/proteins_mobility.swf" menustep="Biological Membranes">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Biological membranes are dynamic structures composed of a diverse set of phospholipid molecules and proteins. In the case of eukaryotic organisms, they also contain the steroid cholesterol.
The phospholipid component of the biological membrane is responsible for the key property of membranes, they act as an impermeable barrier towards most molecules. Molecules can only cross the membrane with the aid of proteins within the membrane.  
Therefore, membranes define the boundary of  cells as well intra-cellular organelles. &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
<step stepURL="swfs/molecules.swf"  menustep="Phospholypid Structure">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;Phospholipids contain only two fatty acids attached to a glycerol head. The phosphate group along with the glycerol group make the head of the phospholipid hydrophilic, whereas the fatty acid tail is hydrophobic. Thus phospholipids are amphipathic: a molecule with a polar end and a hydrophobic end. When phospholipids are in an aqueous solution they will self assemble into micelles or bilayers, structures that exclude water molecules from the hydrophobic tails while keeping the hydrophilic head in contact with the aqueous solution.    &lt;/html&gt;</text>
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/micelle-liposome.swf"  menustep="Micelle Formation">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;When fatty acids or phospholipids are added to water they self-assemble into aggregates such that the charged or polar heads groups make contact with the water and the hydrophobic hydrocarbon tails are restricted to water-free areas. In the case of fatty acids and other detergent like molecules, they will orient at an air-water interface such that the non-polar tails project into the air. In addition, some fatty acids will enter the water and spontaneously form single shelled structures called micelles.
        &lt;br&gt;When you are ready to continue click the  "&lt;b&gt;Forward&lt;/b&gt;" button.
        When fatty acids or phospholipids are added to water they self-assemble into aggregates such that the charged
        or polar heads groups make contact with the water and the hydrophobic hydrocarbon tails are restricted to water-free areas. In the case of fatty acids and other detergent like molecules, they will orient at an airater interface such that the non-polar tails project into the air. In addition, some fatty acids will enter the water and spontaneously form single shelled structures called micelles.
        &lt;br&gt;When you are ready to continue click the  "&lt;b&gt;Forward&lt;/b&gt;" button.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="../../simulator06/simulator.swf?mypath=../../webcontent/simulator06/&Myfile=XMLS/BilayerPermeability.xml" menustep="Bilayer Permeability" >
    <text>&lt;html&gt; This diagram shows a lipid bilayer that is formed from two layers of phospholipids molecules. 
        The polar head-groups of the phospholipids are oriented towards of the aqueous solvent while the long non-polar hydrocarbon, or acil, chains are sequestered in the interior of the membrane. 
        Note that:
        i) The membrane is flexible and dynamic.
        ii) Water molecules, which are polar but uncharged, rarely cross the membrane. 
        iii) Ions, such as Na+, never cross the membrane. 
        &lt;/html&gt;
    </text>  
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/bilayer.swf"  menustep="Membrane Bilayer">
    <text>&lt;html&gt; The cell membrane must be a dynamic structure if the cell is to grow and respond to environmental changes. To keep the membrane fluid at physiological temperatures the cell alters the composition of the phospholipids. The right ratio of saturated to unsaturated fatty acids keeps the membrane fluid at any temperature conducive to life. The fluidity of the membrane is demonstrated in the following animation. The lipids in the membrane are in random bulk flow moving about 22 micrometers per second. Phospholipids freely move in the same layer of the membrane and rarely flip to the other layer. Flipping of phospholipids from one layer to the other rarely occurs because flipping requires the hydrophilic head to pass through the hydrophobic region of the bilayer.&lt;/html&gt;
    </text> 
</step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/carrier.swf" textURL="text_carrier.swf" menustep="Carrier Proteins">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;There are three main types of proteins that shuttle molecules across the membrane:
        &lt;b&gt;Uniport:&lt;/b&gt; transport a single molecule across the membrane.
        &lt;b&gt;Symport:&lt;/b&gt; transport two different molecules in the same direction.
        &lt;b&gt;Antiport:&lt;/b&gt; transport two different molecules in opposite directions.&lt;/html&gt;</text>
    </step> 
    <step stepURL="swfs/glut10.swf" menustep="Uniport - Glucose transporter">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;Glucose is an essential substrate for the metabolism of most cells. Because glucose is a polar molecule, its transport through biological membranes requires specific transporter proteins. Down here the structure of the glut1 transporter from different views.&lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="../../simulator06/simulator.swf?mypath=../../webcontent/simulator06/&Myfile=XMLS/TransportChannel_small.xml" menustep="&nbsp;    Begin Simulation" xscale=".5" yscale=".5">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The Glucose molecules in this example are too large to freely pass through the membrane.  This Glucose Transporter allows them through the specific channel through the protein. &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step> 
<step stepURL="swfs/ADP-ATP.swf" menustep="Antiport - ADP/ATP translocase">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The mitochondrial ADP/ATP translocase (AAT) catalyses the exchange, across the inner membrane of the organelle, of cytosolic ADP for ATP, produced in the matrix by ATP-synthase. The AAT undergoes substantial conformational changes during transport. Down here different models of the AAT  structure from different views.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mitochondria-intro.swf" menustep="    ADP-ATP exchange">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; Proteins of the mitochondrial carrier family are embedded in this membrane, and each member of the family achieves the selective transport of a specific metabolite. Among these, the ADP/ATP carrier transports ADP into the mitochondrial matrix and exports ATP toward the cytosol after its synthesis. &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mitochondria.swf" menustep="    mitrochondria">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The ADP/ATP carrier is embedded in the inner membrane of the mitochondria where it transports ATP from the matrix to the inner membrane space while simultaneously transporting ADP from the inner membrane space to the matrix. Thus the protein is providing an exchange function.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mitochondria-phase1.swf" menustep="    phase 1">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; The dimer structure of the ADP/ATP carrier presents the structure of the molecule that accepts ADP into the closed cup conformation of the protein while the dimer pair in the open conformation binds ATP. Following binding each member of the dimer pair undergoes a conformational change that the releases the bound molecule on the opposite side of the membrane.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mitochondria-phase2.swf" menustep="    phase 2">
        <text>&lt;html&gt; Having completed the first exchange reaction, the opposite member of the dimer pair is ready to undertake the transfer reaction. Again the cup structure binds the ADP while the open structure binds ATP. Conformational change then releases the ADP to the matrix and ATP to the inner membrane space.  &lt;/html&gt; </text>
    </step>
   <step stepURL="swfs/introduction.swf" menustep="Symport - Lactose Permease">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The Escherichia coli lactose permease is an example of secondary active transport (Campbell, p. 210). This enzyme is similar in structure to others in the major facilitator superfamily (MFS) of transporters.  More than 1000 examples of MFS transporters have been identified in the genomes of bacteria, plants, and animals.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/mec.swf" menustep="    Lactose Permease Mechanism: ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Lactose permease (lacY gene product) is a b-galactoside-H+ symporter.  The high H+ concentration in the E. coli periplasm is used to drive the transport of lactose into the cell against its concentration gradient.  The proton gradient is generated by the oxidation of substrates via the proton pumping of the electron transport chain.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/a1.swf" menustep="    Lac Permease structure  ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The enzyme, in its substrate-free form is shown in cross-section with the periplasm at the top of the diagram.  The cavity between the N- and C- terminal domains contain the substrate and H+ binding sites.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/a2.swf" menustep="    Proton Binds  ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Proton binding to a glutamic acid side chain in the C- terminal domain (-COO-) is the first step.  The carboxyl group of this Glut residue is in a hydrophobic environment making this protonation energetically favorable (pKa ~ 7.0). &lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/a3.swf" menustep="    Lactose Binds ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Substrate binding is the second step. The sugar binds primarily to residues in the N- terminal domain at the bottom of the cavity, roughly halfway between the bilayer boundaries.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/b1.swf" menustep="    Structural Change ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;Substrate binding also triggers a major conformation change: The periplasmic opening closes and the cavity appears on the cytoplasmic side, i.e. the opening switches to the other side, but the protein, itself, does not "flip" across the membrane&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/b2.swf" menustep="    Lactose Dissociates ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The di saccharine substrate dissociates into the cytoplasm where it will be hydrolyzed (by b-galactosidase) and used for energy production or other metabolic purposes.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/b3.swf" menustep="    Proton Dissociates  ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;The H+ dissociates after the substrate.  This too is a spontaneous reaction because the conformation change has also made the environment of the Glut side chain  more polar, lowering its pKa.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/c1.swf" menustep="    Return to Start ">
<text>&lt;html&gt;In the absence of substrate and H+ in the active site, the permease is more stable in its original state.  Hence, the reverse of the major conformation change returns the protein to its starting conformation for another cycle of lactose-H+ symport.&lt;/red&gt;
            &lt;/html&gt;
        </text>
    </step>
   <step stepURL="swfs/sodium-potassium.swf"  menustep="An Active antiport transporter">
    <text>&lt;html&gt;This is an example of an antiport transporter than uses the energy of ATP to transport 3 Na+ ions outside of the cell in exchange for the influx of 2 K+ ions into the cell. The main features of the cycle are:
   1) Binding of 3 Na+ ions
   2) Phosphorylation of a carboxylic group by ATP, causing an allosteric change in the enzyme, allowing the Na+ to cross.
   3) Two K+ bind to the external face of the transporter.
   4) Dephosophorylation of the enzyme causes another allosteric change, bringing the K+ into the cell&lt;/html&gt;</text>
    </step>
    <step stepURL="swfs/sodium-potassium_title.swf" menustep="    ATP ">
        <text>&lt;html&gt;The energy that cells use is chemical bond energy, the shared electrons that holds atoms together in molecules. Cell movements require energy and chemical reactions are the font of energy in every living cell. Most cell processes use the same energy source: adenosine tri phosphate ATP. The ATP contains three phosphate groups. The bond between the second and third phosphate groups can be broken to release a small amount of energy. &lt;/html&gt;</text>
    </step>

</step>
</TUTORIAL>