<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m3_Integ_Homeo_03"><head><title>Changes in the Integumentary System</title><objref idref="integument_endocrine_regulation" /></head><body><section id="de0452f107844508bf6556816b93a9a2"><title>Puberty</title><body><p id="b48daa6ce15846acbb75c0ca629b08aa">During puberty, the changes in the endocrine system produce hormones that regulate aspects of the integumentary system. Sebaceous glands, apocrine sweat glands and hair growth become active or more active.</p></body></section><section id="db00d34b312249238244543d73fc1655"><title>Advanced Aging</title><body><p id="ac7afda6897c492a82818a1f40417d08">All organ systems in the body, including the integumentary system, undergo subtle changes over time that add up as a person ages. Reductionsin metabolic activity and cell division, lowered blood circulation, and decreased hormonal levels are some of the basic changes that occur in the human body as it ages.</p><p id="b41fcb24582e422e8c7f5f4607da28b3">The epidermis is made up of several layers of cells that are shed and replaced by basal stem cell division. With aging, these cells divide less reliably and aging skin becomes thinner. The dermis, which is responsible for the elasticity and resilience of the skin, also weakens since elastin fibers become cross-linked and don’t stretch. Repair of wounds occurs more slowly as a person ages. The hypodermis, which stores fats in its adipose tissue, loses its structure due to the reduction and redistribution of fat, which in turn is affected by hormonal levels. The accessory structures also have lowered activity, generating thinner hair and nails, and reduced amounts of sebum and sweat. Reduced sweating ability causes the elderly to be unable to tolerate extreme heat. Other cells in the skin, such as melanocytes and dendritic cells, also become less active, leading to a paler appearance and lowered immunity. Wrinkling of skin occurs mainly due to the breakdown of collagen and elastin, the weakening of muscles under the skin, and the inability of the skin to retain adequate moisture.</p><p id="e5165657bf964357b249730e8d5be78a">Many anti-aging products line the shelves of stores today. These products (mainly composed of tretinoin, or Retin-A) try to introduce more structure into the skin, first by rehydrating the skin with moisturizers, and then by triggering mitotic activity of the underlying cells to encourage tissue formation and regeneration. Some products contain epidermal growth factor, which induces collagen synthesis, the end-product of wound healing, to give the skin a healthier look.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="integument_endocrine_regulation" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
