<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u7_m3_Integ_Homeo_05">
	<head>
		<title>The Sense of Touch</title>
		<objref idref="skin_sensory_nerves"/>
		<objref idref="med_changes"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The fact that you can feel an ant crawling on your skin, causing you to flick it off
			before it bites, is due to the fact that the sensory receptors in the skin (especially
			the hair root plexus associated with the hair in the follicles) can sense changes in the
			environment. This occurs via sensory receptors that convert physical or chemical stimuli
			into electrical signals that are sent to the central nervous system (CNS; brain and
			spinal cord). The CNS then processes this sensory input and generates a voluntary
			response to the ant. The skin acts as a <term>sense organ</term> because the dermis and
			hypodermis contain <term>sensory receptors</term> that extend into the epidermis. These
			receptors, such as Merkel discs, are more concentrated at the fingertips and lips, which
			are most sensitive to touch. Examples of other sensory receptors present in the skin are
				<term>tactile
				(<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T181244-0500" comment="correction OK?"?>Meissner's<?oxy_comment_end?>)
				corpuscles</term> and <term>lamellated (Pacinian) corpuscles</term> that respond to
			pressure and vibration, respectively, and free nerve endings that are sensitive to
			temperature (hot or cold) and pain.</p>

		<section>
			<title>Skin Conditions and General Health</title>
			<body>
				<p>There are a variety of conditions that can change the appearance of the skin. In
					vitiligo, the melanocytes in certain areas lose the ability to produce melanin,
					possibly due to an autoimmune reaction, leading to loss of pigmentation in
					patches. Liver disease or liver cancer can cause an accumulation of bile and the
					yellow pigment bilirubin, leading to the skin appearing yellow or jaundiced
					("jaune" is French for "yellow"). Tumors of the pituitary gland can result in
					the secretion of large amounts of
					<?oxy_comment_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T181836-0500" comment="change OK?"?>corticotropin<?oxy_comment_end?>-releasing
					hormone (CRH), which can stimulate excessive levels of melanocyte-stimulating
					hormone (MSH) and adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH). In Addison’s disease
					excessive CRH stimulates production of adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) and
					MSH. In these diseases, the skin takes on a deep bronze color.</p>
				<p>The oxygen content of blood in the dermal vascular system is reflected in skin
					hue. Healthy individuals who have adequate supplies of the red-colored
					oxygen-bound hemoglobin usually have a pink hue to their cheeks and lips.
					Indeed, hemoglobin and the vasculature of the skin also contributes to skin
					color in people with fairer skin. A sudden drop in oxygenation of the skin can
					initially cause the skin to turn ashen (or white). If there is a prolonged
					reduction in oxygen levels, it makes the skin appear blue (cyanosis), which
					happens when a person has a limited oxygen supply to the body. The blue color is
					most obvious in areas where blood capillaries are close to the surface, like the
					lips and nail beds. Blue lips is a sign of hypoxia and hypothermia, which lead
					to drastically reduced peripheral circulation, or of any other condition that
					prevents adequate oxygenation of the blood, which can occur in a variety of lung
					diseases. At the other extreme, elevated blood levels of carbon monoxide can
					cause the lips and oral mucosa to appear bright cherry red because the carbon
					monoxide molecule binds to hemoglobin tighter than oxygen, giving the hemoglobin
					in the red blood cells the bright red color. Carbon monoxide poisoning is fatal,
					and prompt treatment with pure oxygen is indicated.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>

			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="skin_sensory_nerves" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="med_changes_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
