<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u7_m3_Integ_Homeo_01"><head><title>Integumentary Homeostasis</title><objref idref="skin_hair_renewal" /><objref idref="compare_homeostasis" /><objref idref="describe_scarring" /></head><body><p id="ada19a67455440c0875393ee27a4a5c3">In earlier sections,you learned about the amazing regenerative capacity of skin: Basal cells divide and differentiate to form keratinocytes, which move superficially to the surface and change their structure along the way. There are some cases where this regenerative property can cause problems, and some traumas where regeneration is put to the test.</p><example id="edca112f96cd44df912edf0eecf3dd3d"><title>Psoriasis</title><p id="de3c1d376cc843e99c7bf70a560f05a1">Psoriasis is an autoimmune disorder where too many skin cells are produced. Skin rapidly accumulates and looks silvery-white in appearance. Plaques from plaque psoriasis frequently occur on the skin of the elbows and knees, but can affect any area, including the scalp, palms of hands and soles of feet, and genitals. The disorder is a chronic recurring condition that varies in severity from minor localized patches to complete body coverage.</p></example><section id="bca9f107e8ce4171a36550c536f85e02"><title>Wound Repair and Scarring</title><body><p id="ba5976da7a2b4ae5ab54a177c98104f6">The first step to repairing damaged skin is the formation of a blood clot that scabs over with time. Many different types of cells are involved in wound repair, especially if the surface area that needs repair is extensive. Before the basal stem cells of stratum basale can re-create the epidermis, fibroblasts and mesenchymal cells mobilize and divide rapidly to repair the damaged tissue, forming a loose, highly vascular tissue called granulation tissue. This increased vascular network helps deliver the oxygen and nutrients necessary for further repair. Immune cells, like macrophages, roam the area and engulf any foreign matter, reducing the chance of infection while also clearing away any tissue debris.</p><p id="fe8f858bd2bf4bf0b267837ddcc529c5"><term>Scars</term> occur when there is repair of skin damage, but the healing process prevents regeneration of the original skin structure. Almost every cut or wound, with the exception of ones that only scratch the surface (epidermal wounds), leads to some degree of scar formation. As the tissue tries to repair itself to the original state, fibroblasts often generate a greater density of collagen fibers than were in the original tissue, which is what results in scar formation. This dense, fibrous structure (connective tissue) has few cells and does not allow for the regeneration of accessory structures (epithelial tissue) like hair follicles, sweat glands, or sebaceous glands.</p><p id="cc7b0bf8fa454a79b077d6231ac2291e">Sometimes, scarring does not stop when the wound is healed. This results in the formation of a raised or hypertrophic scar called a <term>keloid</term>. In contrast, scars that result from acne and chickenpox have a sunken appearance and are called atrophic scars.</p><p id="a860fd2d56f04aa2b7006ccfe4db65ce">Scarring of skin after wound healing is a natural process and does not need to be treated further. Application of oil and lotions may reduce the formation of scar tissue by keeping the skin soft and pliable as it heals, allowing the separate edges to be pulled together. However, modern cosmetic procedures like dermabrasion, laser treatments, and filler injections have been invented as remedies for severe scarring. All of these procedures try to reorganize the structure of the epidermis and underlying collagen in the connective tissue to make it look more natural.</p></body></section><section id="d60174e571464256895502c8b4acd1c8" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="skin_hair_renewal" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="describe_scarring" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
