<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u7_m3_Integ_Homeo_02">
	<head>
		<title>Burns</title>
		<objref idref="predict_skin_issues"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p><term>Burns</term> are wounds that result when the skin is exposed to intense heat, radiation,
			electrical current, or caustic chemicals. Burns cause skin cells to die, disrupting the
			epithelial barrier that normally prevents fluid loss. Depending on the severity of the
			burn, dehydration, electrolyte imbalance, and renal and circulatory
			failure<?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170447-0500" content=","?>
			may follow. Burn patients are treated with intravenous fluids to offset the dehydration,
			as well as intravenous nutrients that enable the body to repair tissues and replenish
			lost proteins. Another serious threat to a burn patient is the high possibility of
			infection. Burned skin is extremely susceptible to bacteria and other pathogens, as the
			loss of body covering provides a direct pathway for the entry of microorganisms.</p>
		<p>Burns are classified by the degree of their severity. In <term>first-degree burns</term>, only
			the epidermis is damaged. Although painful, these burns typically heal on their own
			within a few days. A typical sunburn is a first-degree burn. <term>Second-degree
				burns</term> destroy both the epidermis and the dermis. They result in painful
			blistering of the skin. It is important for individuals with second-degree burns to keep
			the area clean and sterile in order to prevent infection. If this is done, the burns
			heal on their own within several weeks.</p>
		<p><term>Third-degree burns</term> are more serious and penetrate the full thickness of the skin,
			including the subcutaneous (hypodermis) layer. The skin may appear white, red, or black.
				<term>Fourth-degree burns</term> are the most severe, affecting the underlying
			muscle and bone as well.
			Third<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170631-0500"?>-<?oxy_insert_end?>
			and
			fourth<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170633-0500"?>-<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170634-0500" content=" "?>degree
			burns are usually not as painful because the nerve endings themselves are damaged.
			However, a
			third<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170649-0500"?>- or
			<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170648-0500" content="/"?>fourth<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170654-0500"?>-<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170654-0500" content=" "?>degree
			burn results in rapid water loss and infection due to the exposure of the underlying
			tissue, and requires emergency trauma care. Full-thickness burns cannot be repaired
			locally because the local repair machinery itself is
			damaged<?oxy_insert_start author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170825-0500"?>.
			Full-thickness
			burns<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="michellemyers" timestamp="20121126T170839-0500" content=" and"?>
			require excision of the affected tissue (amputation in severe cases), followed by
			grafting of skin from an unaffected part of the body, or from skin grown in tissue
			culture for grafting purposes.</p>
		<!--<p>skin_damage_DIGI</p>-->

	</body>
</workbook_page>
<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>
