<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="casei1">
    <head>
        <title>Case C→Q (1 of 2) </title>
        <objref idref="compare_quantitative_distributions"/>
    </head>
<body>
   
        <section>
            <title>Case C→Q: Categorical Explanatory Variable and Quantitative Response
                Variable</title>
            <body>
                <p>Recall the role-type classification table for framing our discussion about the
                    relationship between two variables:</p>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/casei1.gif" alt="It is possible
for any type of explanatory variable to be paired with any type of response variable.
The possible pairings are:
Categorical Explanatory → Categorical Response (C→C),
Categorical Explanatory → Quantitative Response (C→Q),
Quantitative Explanatory → Categorical Response (Q→C), and
Quantitative Explanatory → Quantitative Response (Q→Q). In this section we will be working on C→Q"/>
                <p>We are now ready to start with Case C→Q, exploring the relationship between two
                    variables where the explanatory variable is categorical, and the response
                    variable is quantitative. As you'll discover, exploring relationships of this
                    type is something we've already discussed in this course, but we didn't frame
                    the discussion this way.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <example>
            <title>Hot Dogs</title>
            <p>
                <em>Background:</em> People who are concerned about their health may prefer hot dogs
                that are low in calories. A study was conducted by a concerned health group in which
                54 major hot dog brands were examined, and their calorie contents recorded. In
                addition, each brand was classified by type: beef, poultry, and meat (mostly pork
                and beef, but up to 15% poultry meat). The purpose of the study was to examine
                whether the <em>number of calories</em> a hot dog has is related to (or affected by)
                its <em>type</em>. (Reference: Moore, David S., and George P. McCabe (1989). <em
                    style="italic">Introduction to the Practice of Statistics</em>. Original source:
                    <em style="italic">Consumer Reports</em>, June 1986, pp. 366-367.)</p>
            <p>Answering this question requires us to examine the relationship between the
                categorical variable, Type and the quantitative variable Calories. Because the
                question of interest is whether the type of hot dog affects calorie content, </p>
            <ul>
                <li>the <em>explanatory</em> variable is <em>Type</em>, and</li>
                <li>the <em>response</em> variable is <em>Calories</em>.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Here is what the raw data look like: </p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/casei2.gif" alt="A table of the data. There are
three columns, &quot;Brand&quot;, &quot;Type&quot;, and &quot;Calories&quot;. &quot;Type&quot; is the
Explanatory variable, and &quot;Calories&quot; is the Response variable. Some example data:
    Brand 1, Beef, 186;
    Brand 2, Poultry, 129;
    Brand 3, Beef, 181;
    Brand 4, Meat, 183;
    ... (abbreviated) ...
    Brand 54, Poultry, 144"/>
            <p>The raw data are a list of types and calorie contents, and are not very useful in
                that form. To explore how the number of calories is related to the type of hot dog,
                we need an informative visual display of the data that will compare the three types
                of hot dogs with respect to their calorie content. </p>
            <p>The visual display that we'll use is <em>side-by-side boxplots</em> (which we've seen
                before). The side-by-side boxplots will allow us to <em>compare the
                    distribution</em> of calorie counts within each category of the explanatory
                variable, hot dog type:</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/casei3.gif" alt="Three box plots. The vertical axis
is labeled &quot;Calories&quot;. There are three box plots, one each for Beef, Other Meat, and Poultry.
The box plot characteristics are summarized in the table below."/>
            <p>As before, we supplement the side-by-side boxplots with the descriptive statistics of
                the calorie content (response) for each type of hot dog separately (i.e., for each
                level of the explanatory variable separately):</p>
            <table title="Descriptive Statistics: Calories by Type">
                <tr>
                    <th>Statistic</th>
                    <th>Beef</th>
                    <th>Meat</th>
                    <th>Poultry</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>min</th>
                    <td>111</td>
                    <td>107</td>
                    <td>86</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Q1</th>
                    <td>139.5</td>
                    <td>138.5</td>
                    <td>100.5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Median</th>
                    <td>152.5</td>
                    <td>153</td>
                    <td>113</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Q3</th>
                    <td>179.75</td>
                    <td>180.5</td>
                    <td>142.5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Max</th>
                    <td>190</td>
                    <td>195</td>
                    <td>152</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <!--   RS 07/28/10 - replaced by table above
        <alternatives group="statistics.package"><default><pref:value preference="statistics.package"/></default>
<alternative value="excel">                 <title>Excel 2007 Instructions</title>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/casei4excel.gif"/>
</alternative>
<alternative value="minitab">                 <title>Minitab Instructions</title>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/casei4.gif"/>
</alternative>
<alternative value="r">                 <title>R Instructions</title>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/casei4r.gif"/>
</alternative>
</alternatives>-->
            <p>Let's summarize the results we got and interpret them in the context of the question
                we posed:</p>
            <p>By examining the three side-by-side boxplots and the numerical summaries, we see at
                once that poultry hot dogs, as a group, contain fewer calories than those made of
                beef or meat. The median number of calories in poultry hot dogs (113) is less than
                the median (and even the first quartile) of either of the other two distributions
                (medians 152.5 and 153). The spread of the three distributions is about the same, if
                IQR is considered (all slightly above 40), but the (full) ranges vary slightly more
                (beef: 80, meat:88, poultry: 66). The general recommendation to the health-conscious
                consumer is to eat poultry hot dogs. It should be noted, though, that since each of
                the three types of hot dogs shows quite a large spread among brands, simply buying a
                poultry hot dog does not guarantee a low-calorie food.</p>
        </example>
        <p>What we learn from this example is that when exploring the relationship between a
            categorical explanatory variable and a quantitative response (Case C→Q), we essentially
                <em>compare the distributions of the quantitative response for each category of the
                explanatory variable</em> using side-by-side boxplots supplemented by descriptive
            statistics. Recall that we have actually done this before when we talked about the
            boxplot and argued that boxplots are most useful when presented <activity_link
                idref="boxplot3" target="self">side by side</activity_link> for comparing
            distributions of two or more groups. This is exactly what we are doing here!</p>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
