<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="causation4">
    <head>
        <title>Causation and Lurking Variables (4 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="recognize_association_causation"/>
        <objref idref="explain_simpsons_paradox"/>

    </head>
    <body>
       
        <p>So far, we have: </p>
        <ul>
            <li>discussed what lurking variables are,</li>
            <li>demonstrated different ways in which the lurking variables can interact with the two
                studied variables, and</li>
            <li>understood that the existence of a possible lurking variable is the main reason why
                we say that association does not imply causation.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>As you recall, a lurking variable, by definition, is a variable that was not included in
            the study, but could have a substantial effect on our understanding of the relationship
            between the two studied variables.</p>
        <p>What if we <em style="italic">did</em> include a lurking variable in our study? What kind
            of effect could that have on our understanding of the relationship? These are the
            questions we are going to discuss next.</p>
        <p>Let's start with an example:</p>
        <example>
            <title>Hospital Death Rates</title>
            <p>
                <em>Background:</em> A government study collected data on the death rates in nearly
                6,000 hospitals in the United States. These results were then challenged by
                researchers, who said that the federal analyses failed to take into account the
                variation among hospitals in the severity of patients' illnesses when they were
                hospitalized. As a result, said the researchers, some hospitals were treated
                unfairly in the findings, which named hospitals with higher-than-expected death
                rates. What the researchers meant is that when the federal government explored the
                relationship between the two variables&#8212;hospital and death rate&#8212;<em>it
                    also should have included in the study (or taken into account) the lurking
                    variable&#8212;severity of illness.</em>
            </p>
            <p>We will use a simplified version of this study to illustrate the researchers' claim,
                and see what the possible effect could be of including a lurking variable in a
                study. (Reference: Moore and McCabe (2003). <em style="italic">Introduction to the
                    Practice of Statistics</em>.)</p>
            <p>Consider the following two-way table, which summarizes the data about the status of
                patients who were admitted to two hospitals in a certain city (Hospital A and
                Hospital B). Note that since the purpose of the study is to examine whether there is
                a "hospital effect" on patients' status, "Hospital is the explanatory variable, and
                "Patient's Status" is the response variable. <image style="block"
                    src="../webcontent/causation6.gif" alt="A two-way table. The columns are the
categories within the variable &quot;Patient's Status&quot;. These categories are &quot;Died&quot;
and &quot;Survived.&quot; In addition, there is a &quot;Total&quot; column. The rows are categories
for the variable &quot;Hospital&quot;. These categories are &quot;Hospital A&quot; and &quot;Hospital
B&quot;. Like usual there is also a &quot;Total&quot; Row. Here is the data in &quot;Row,Column: Value
&quot; format:
    Hospital A, Died: 63;
    Hospital A, Survived: 2037;
    Hospital A, Total: 2100;
    Hospital B, Died: 16;
    Hospital B, Survived: 784;
    Hospital B, Total: 800;
    Total, Died: 79;
    Total, Survived: 2821;
    Total, Total: 2900;"/>
            </p>
            <p>When we supplement the two-way table with the conditional percents within each
                hospital: <image style="block" src="../webcontent/causation7.gif" alt="A
two-way table with the same rows and columns as the previous two-way table, except the Total
row has been removed. Here is the data in the same format:
    Hospital A, Died: 3%;
    Hospital A, Survived: 97%;
    Hospital A, Total: 100%;
    Hospital B, Died: 2%;
    Hospital B, Survived: 98%;
    Hospital B, Total: 100%;"/>
            </p>
            <p>we find that Hospital A has a higher death rate (3%) than Hospital B (2%). Should we
                jump to the conclusion that a sick patient admitted to Hospital A is 50% more likely
                to die than if he/she were admitted to Hospital B? <em>Not so fast ...</em>
            </p>
            <p>Maybe Hospital A gets most of the severe cases, and that explains why it has a higher
                death rate. In order to explore this, we need to <em>include (or account for) the
                    lurking variable "severity of illness" in our analysis.</em> To do this, we go
                back to the two-way table and split it up to look separately at patents who are
                severely ill, and patients who are not. <image style="block"
                    src="../webcontent/causation10.gif" alt="The original two-way table has been
split into two two-way tables, one for &quot;Patients severely ill&quot; and one for &quot;Patients
not severely ill.&quot; Once again, here are the columns, for the variable &quot;Patient's
Status&quot;: &quot;Died&quot;, &quot;Survived&quot;, &quot;Total&quot;. The rows, for the variable
&quot;Hospital&quot;: &quot;Hospital A&quot;, &quot;Hospital B&quot;, &quot; Total&quot;. Data will
be given in &quot;Row,Column: Value&quot; format.

    Table for &quot;Patients severely ill:&quot;
    Hospital A, Died: 57;
    Hospital A, Survived: 1443;
    Hospital A, Total: 1500;
    Hospital B, Died: 8;
    Hospital B, Survived: 192;
    Hospital B, Total: 200;
    Total, Died: 65;
    Total, Survived: 1635;
    Total, Total: 1700;
                
    Table for &quot;Patients not severely ill:&quot;
    Hospital A, Died: 6;
    Hospital A, Survived: 594;
    Hospital A, Total: 600;
    Hospital B, Died: 8;
    Hospital B, Survived: 592;
    Hospital B, Total: 600;
    Total, Died: 14;
    Total, Survived: 1186;
    Total, Total: 1200;"/>
            </p>
            <p>As we can see, Hospital A <em>did</em> admit many more severely ill patients than
                Hospital B (1,500 vs. 200). In fact, from the way the totals were split, we see that
                in Hospital A, severely ill patients were a much higher proportion of the
                patients&#8212;1,500 out of a total of 2,100 patients. In contrast, only 200 out of
                800 patients at Hospital B were severely ill. To better see the effect of including
                the lurking variable, we need to supplement each of the two new two-way tables with
                its conditional percentages: <image style="block"
                    src="../webcontent/causation11.gif" alt="Two
two-way tables with the same rows and columns as the previous two-way table, except the Total
row has been removed. Here is the data in the same format:
    Table for &quot;Patients severely ill:&quot;
    Hospital A, Died: 3.8%;
    Hospital A, Survived: 96.2%;
    Hospital A, Total: 100%;
    Hospital B, Died: 4.0%;
    Hospital B, Survived: 96.0%;
    Hospital B, Total: 100%;
    
    Table for &quot;Patients not severely ill:&quot;
    Hospital A, Died: 1.0%;
    Hospital A, Survived: 99.0%;
    Hospital A, Total: 100%;
    Hospital B, Died: 1.3%;
    Hospital B, Survived: 98.7%;
    Hospital B, Total: 100%;"/>
            </p>
            <p>Note that despite our earlier finding that overall Hospital A has a higher death rate
                (3% vs. 2%), when we take into account the lurking variable, we find that actually
                it is Hospital B that has the higher death rate both among the severely ill patients
                (4% vs. 3.8%) and among the not severely ill patients (1.3% vs. 1%). <em>Thus, we
                    see that adding a lurking variable can change the direction of an
                    association.</em>
            </p>
            <p>Whenever including a lurking variable causes us to rethink the direction of an
                association, this is called <em>Simpson's paradox.</em>
            </p>
            <p>The possibility that a lurking variable can have such a dramatic effect is another
                reason we must adhere to the principle: </p>
        </example>
        <theorem type="principle">
            <statement>
                <p>Association <em>does not</em> imply causation!</p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>
       
    </body>
</workbook_page>
