<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="causation5">
    <head>
        <title>Causation and Lurking Variables (5 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="recognize_association_causation"/>
        <objref idref="explain_simpsons_paradox"/>
    </head>
    <body>
       
        <p>It is <em style="italic">not</em> always the case that including a lurking variable makes
            us rethink the direction of the association. In the next example we will see how
            including a lurking variable just helps us gain a deeper understanding of the observed
            relationship. </p>
        <example>
            <title>College Entrance Exams</title>
            <p>As discussed earlier, in the United States, the SAT is a widely used college entrance
                examination, required by the most prestigious schools. In some states, a different
                college entrance examination is prevalent, the ACT. </p>
          
            <youtube src="Nnj1YlqzkX4"></youtube>
          <!--  <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="500" height="340"
                purpose="walkthrough">
                <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/causation5_movie.swf</param>
                <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
                <param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
            </flash> --> 
            <p>To see a static version of this movie, <activity_link idref="causation5altflash"
                    target="new">click here</activity_link>.</p>
        </example>
        <p>The last two examples showed us that including a lurking variable in our exploration may</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Lead us to rethink the direction of an association (as in the Hospital/Death Rate
                example).</li>
            <li>Help us to gain a deeper understanding of the relationship between variables (as in
                the SAT/ACT example). </li>
        </ul>
  
    
        <activity idref="causation5lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        
        <wb:inline idref="interpret_two_var_tutor" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <section>
            <title>Let's Summarize</title>
            <body>
                <ul>
                    <li>A <em>lurking variable</em> is a variable that was not included in your
                        analysis, but that could substantially change your interpretation of the
                        data if it were included. </li>
                    <li>Because of the possibility of lurking variables, we adhere to the principle
                        that <em>association does not imply causation</em>. </li>
                    <li>Including a lurking variable in our exploration may<ul>
                            <li>Help us to gain a deeper understanding of the relationship between
                                variables.</li>
                            <li>Lead us to rethink the direction of an association. </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Whenever including a lurking variable causes us to rethink the direction of
                        an association, this is an instance of <em>Simpson's paradox</em>. </li>
                </ul>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
