<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="causation3">
    <head>
        <title>Causation and Lurking Variables (3 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="recognize_association_causation"/>
    </head>
<body>
   
        <p>The next example will illustrate another way in which a lurking variable might interfere
            and prevent us from reaching any causal conclusions.</p>
        <example>
            <title>SAT Test</title>
            <p>For U.S. colleges and universities, a standard entrance examination is the SAT test.
                The side-by-side boxplots below provide evidence of a relationship between the
                student's country of origin (the United States or another country) and the student's
                SAT Math score.</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/causation4.gif" alt="A side-by-side boxplot.
The vertical axis is labeled &quot;SAT Math Score&quot;, and it ranges from 450 to 800. The
horizontal axis is labeled &quot;Country&quot; and has two categories, &quot;Other&quot; and
&quot;US&quot;."/>
            <p>The distribution of international students' scores is higher than that of U.S.
                students. The international students' median score (about 700) exceeds the third
                quartile of U.S. students' scores. Can we conclude that the country of origin is the
                    <em>cause</em> of the difference in SAT Math scores, and that students in the
                United States are weaker at math than students in other countries?</p>
            <p>No, not necessarily. While it <em style="italic">might</em> be true that U.S.
                students differ in math ability from other students&#8212;i.e. due to differences in
                educational systems&#8212;we can't conclude that a student's country of origin is
                the cause of the disparity. One important <em>lurking variable</em> that might
                explain the observed relationship is the educational level of the two populations
                taking the SAT Math test. In the United States, the SAT is a standard test, and
                therefore a broad cross-section of all U.S. students (in terms of educational level)
                take this test. Among all international students, on the other hand, only those who
                plan on coming to the U.S. to study, which is usually a more selected subgroup, take
                the test. </p>
            <p>The following figure will help you visualize this explanation:</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/causation5.gif" alt="A flowchart. We have two
causes, one of which is &quot;Education level of SAT Takers&quot;. This is a &quot;Lurking variable
&quot; The other cause is &quot;Nationality (X)&quot;. Both of these might be causes of &quot;
SAT-Math score (Y)&quot;. We have observed an association between &quot;Nationality (X)&quot; and
&quot;SAT-Math Score (Y)&quot;. Notice that between these two variables is also a suspected
cause relationship."/>
            <p>Here, the explanatory variable (X) <em>may</em> have a causal relationship with the
                response variable (Y), but the lurking variable might be a contributing factor as
                well, which makes it very hard to isolate the effect of the explanatory variable and
                prove that it has a causal link with the response variable. In this case, we say
                that the lurking variable is <em>confounded</em> with the explanatory variable,
                since their effects on the response variable cannot be distinguished from each
                other.</p>
        </example>
        <p>Note that in each of the above two examples, the lurking variable interacts differently
            with the variables studied. In example 1, the lurking variable has an effect on both the
            explanatory and the response variables, creating the illusion that there is a causal
            link between them. In example two, the lurking variable is confounded with the
            explanatory variable, making it hard to assess the isolated effect of the explanatory
            variable on the response variable.</p>
        <p>The distinction between these two types of interactions is not as important as the fact
            that in either case, the observed association can be at least partially explained by the
            lurking variable. The most important message from these two examples is therefore:
                <em>An observed association between two variables is not enough evidence that there
                is a </em>
        </p>
        <p>
            <em>causal relationship between them.</em>
        </p>
        <p>In other words ... </p>
        <theorem type="principle">
            <statement>
                <p>Association <em>does not</em> imply causation!</p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>
    <wb:inline idref="lurking_variable_tutor" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    <wb:inline idref="lurking_variable_tutor_2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
   
    
        <activity idref="causation3lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
