<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="linear4">
 <head>
  <title>Linear Relationships (4 of 8)</title>


  <objref idref="interpret_correlation_coefficient"/>


 </head>
 <body>

  <section>
   <title>Properties of r</title>
   <body>
    <p>We now discuss and illustrate several important properties of the correlation coefficient as
     a numerical measure of the strength of a linear relationship. </p>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <p>The correlation does not change when the units of measurement of either one of the
       variables change. In other words, if we change the units of measurement of the explanatory
       variable and/or the response variable, the change has <em style="italic">no effect on the
        correlation (r)</em>.</p>
      <p>To illustrate, following are two versions of the scatterplot of the relationship between
       sign legibility distance and driver's age: </p>
      <image style="block" src="../webcontent/linear5.gif"
       alt="Two scatterplots showing the
data for Driver Age vs. Sign Legibility. The first scatterplot's vertical axis is labeled
&quot;Sign Legibility Distance (feet)&quot; and the axis ranges from a little less than 300
to 600 feet. The horizontal axis is labeled &quot;Driver Age (years)&quot; and it
ranges from 15 to 85. The second scatterplot has the same horizontal axis but the
vertical axis is labeled &quot;Sign Legibility Distance (meters)&quot; and it ranges
from 80 to 180."/>
      <p>The top scatterplot displays the original data where the maximum distances is measured in
        <em style="italic">feet</em>. The bottom scatterplot displays the same relationship but with
       maximum distances changed to <em style="italic">meters</em>. Notice that the Y-values have
       changed, but the correlations are the same. This example illustrates haw changing the units
       of measurement of the response variable has no effect on r, but as we indicated above, the
       same is true for changing the units of the explanatory variable, or of both variables. </p>
      <p>This might be a good place to comment that the correlation (r) is <em style="italic"
        >unitless</em>. It is just a number. </p>
     </li>
     <li>
      <p>The correlation measures only the <em style="italic">strength</em> of a linear relationship
       between two variables. It <em>ignores</em> any other type of relationship, no matter how
       strong it is. For example, consider the relationship between the average fuel usage of
       driving a fixed distance in a car, and the speed at which the car drives: </p>
      <image style="block" src="../webcontent/linear6.gif"
       alt="A scatterplot in which the vertical axis
 is labeled &quot;Fuel Used (liter/100km)&quot; and the horizontal axis is labeled &quot;Speed
 (km/h).&quot; The amount of fuel used rapidly decreases from speed=0 to about speed=60, where
 fuel used reaches its minimum value, then fuel used slowly increases linearly as speed increases."/>
      <p>Our data describe a fairly simple curvilinear relationship: the amount of fuel consumed
       decreases rapidly to a minimum for a car driving 60 kilometers per hour, and then increases
       gradually for speeds exceeding 60 kilometers per hour. The relationship is very strong, as
       the observations seem to perfectly fit the curve. </p>
      <p>Although the relationship is strong, the correlation r = -0.172 indicates a weak <em
        style="italic">linear</em> relationship. This makes sense considering that the data fails to
       adhere closely to a linear form: </p>
      <image style="block" src="../webcontent/linear7.gif"
       alt="The same scatterplot, except a blue line
 with arrow has been draw over the plot, in the direction of a negative relationship. The data plotted
 does not align at all with this arrow."/>
      <p>The correlation is useless for assessing the strength of any type of relationship that is
       not linear (including relationships that are curvilinear, such as the one in our example).
       Beware, then, of interpreting the fact that r is close to 0 as an indicator of a weak
       relationship rather than a weak <em style="italic">linear</em> relationship. This example
       also illustrates how important it is to <em style="italic">always look at the data in the
        scatterplot</em> because, as in our example, there might be a strong nonlinear relationship
       that r does not indicate.</p>
      <p>Since the correlation was nearly zero when the form of the relationship was not linear, we
       might ask if the correlation can be used to determine whether or not a relationship is
       linear.</p>
     </li>
     <li>
      <p>The correlation by itself is <em style="italic">not</em> sufficient to determine whether a
       relationship is linear. To see this, let's consider the study that examined the effect of
       monetary incentives on the return rate of questionnaires. Below is the scatterplot relating
       the percentage of participants who completed a survey to the monetary incentive that
       researchers promised to participants, in which we find a <em style="italic">trong curvilinear
        relationship</em>:</p>
      <image style="block" src="../webcontent/linear8.gif"
       alt="A scatterplot in which the vertical
axis shows &quot;Percentage Returned&quot; and the horizontal axis shows &quot;Incentive (dollars).
&quot; The data plotted shows a strong curvilinear relationship which roughly approximates a square
root function."/>
      <p>The relationship is curvilinear, yet the correlation r = 0.876 is quite close to 1.</p>
      <p>In the last two examples, we have seen two very strong curvilinear relationships, one with
       a correlation close to 0 and one with a correlation close to 1. Therefore, the correlation
       alone does not indicate whether a relationship is linear. The important principle here is: </p>
      <p>
       <em style="italic">Always look at the data!</em>
      </p>
     </li>
     <li>
      <p>The correlation is heavily influenced by outliers. As you will learn in the next two
       activities, the way in which the outlier influences the correlation depends on whether the
       outlier is consistent with the pattern of the linear relationship. </p>
      <p>Using the applet below, we explore how an outlier affects the correlation. </p>
      <iframe
       src="../../../webcontent/html_activities/linear_relationships_scatterplot/linear_relationships_scatterplot.html"
       height="700" width="750"/>
      <!--   <applet archive="../../webcontent/correlationregression.jar" code="CorrelationRegression.class" width="500" height="400" logging="true"/>-->
      <p>To see how an outlier affects the correlation, do the following: </p>
      <ol>
       <li>
        <p>Fill the scatterplot with a hypothetical positive linear relationship between X and Y (by
         clicking on the graph about a dozen times starting at lower left and going up diagonally to
         the top right). Pay attention to the correlation coefficient calculated at the top right of
         the applet. (Clicking on the garbage can will let you start over.) </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>Once you are satisfied with your hypothetical data, create an outlier by clicking on one
         of the data points in the upper right of the graph, and dragging it down along the right
         side of the graph. Again, pay attention to what happens to the value of the correlation.
        </p>
       </li>
      </ol>
     </li>
    </ol>
    <p>Hopefully, you've noticed the correlation decreasing when you created this kind of outlier,
     which <em style="italic">is not consistent</em> with the pattern of the relationship. </p>
    <p>The next activity will show you how an outlier that <em style="italic">is consistent</em>
     with the direction of the linear relationship actually strengthens it. </p>
    <activity idref="linear4lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
   </body>
  </section>
 </body>
</workbook_page>
