<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="linear5">
    <head>
        <title>Linear Relationships (5 of 8)</title>

        <objref idref="use_least_squares_regression"/>


    </head>
    <body>

        <section>
            <title>Linear Regression: Summarizing the Pattern of the Data with a Line</title>
            <body>
                <p>So far we've used the scatterplot to describe the relationship between two
                    quantitative variables, and in the special case of a linear relationship, we
                    have supplemented the scatterplot with the correlation (r). The correlation,
                    however, doesn't fully characterize the linear relationship between two
                    quantitative variables&#8212;it only measures the strength and direction. We
                    often want to describe more precisely how one variable changes with the other
                    (by "more precisely," we mean more than just the direction), or
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101101T130043-0400" comment="use italic instead of bold for emphasis"?><em>predict
                    </em><?oxy_comment_end?> the value of the response variable for a given value of
                    the explanatory variable. In order to be able to do that, we need to summarize
                    the linear relationship with a line that best fits the linear pattern of the
                    data. In the remainder of this section, we will introduce a way to find such a
                    line, learn how to interpret it, and use it (cautiously) to make
                    predictions.</p>
                <p>Again, let's start with a motivating example: </p>
                <p>Earlier, we examined the linear relationship between the age of a driver and the
                    maximum distance at which a highway sign was legible, using both a scatterplot
                    and the correlation coefficient. Suppose a government agency wanted to predict
                    the maximum distance at which the sign would be legible for 60-year-old drivers,
                    and thus make sure that the sign could be used safely and effectively.</p>
                <p>How would we make this prediction?</p>
                <youtube src="8hf3dMf59cI"></youtube>
              <!--    <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="500" height="340"
                    purpose="walkthrough">
                    <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/linear5_movie.swf</param>
                    <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
                    <param name="LoggingLibraryPath"
                        >../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
                </flash>-->
                <p>To see a static version of this movie, <activity_link idref="linear5altflash"
                        target="new">click here</activity_link>
                </p>
                <p>How and why did we pick this particular line (the one shown in red in the above
                    walkthrough) to describe the dependence of the maximum distance at which a sign
                    is legible upon the age of a driver? What line exactly did we choose? We will
                    return to this example once we can answer that question with a bit more
                    precision.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
