<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="relationships_intro2">
<head>
<title>The Role-Type Classification (2 of 2)</title>
    <objref idref="classify_role_type"/>
</head>
<body>
   
<p>If we further classify each of the two relevant variables according to <em>type</em> (categorical
            or quantitative), we get the following four possibilities for <em>role-type
                classification</em>:</p>
<ol>
            <li>Categorical explanatory and quantitative response </li>
            <li>Categorical explanatory and categorical response </li>
            <li>Quantitative explanatory and quantitative response </li>
            <li>Quantitative explanatory and categorical response </li>
        </ol>
<p>This role-type classification can be summarized and easily visualized in the following table
            (note that the explanatory variable is always listed first):</p>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/relationships_overview1.gif" alt="It is possible
for any type of explanatory variable to be paired with any type of response variable.
The possible pairings are:
Categorical Explanatory → Categorical Response (C→C),
Categorical Explanatory → Quantitative Response (C→Q),
Quantitative Explanatory → Categorical Response (Q→C), and
Quantitative Explanatory → Quantitative Response (Q→Q)"/>
<p>This role-type classification serves as the infrastructure for this entire section.
In each of the four cases, different statistical tools (displays and numerical measures) should be used to explore the relationship between the two variables. This suggests the following important principle:</p>
<theorem type="principle">
<statement><p>When confronted with a research question that involves exploring the relationship between two
                    variables, the first and most crucial step is to determine which of the four cases
                    represents the data structure of the problem. In other words, the first step
                    should be classifying the two relevant variables according to their role and
                    type, and only then can we determine what statistical tools should be used to
                    analyze them.</p></statement>
</theorem>
<p>Now let's go back to our eight examples and determine which of the four cases represents the data
            structure of each:</p>
<example>
<title>1</title>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<em>Gender</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable, and it is <em>categorical</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<em>Test score</em> is the <em>response</em> variable, and it is <em>quantitative</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Therefore, this is an example of <em>case
                            C→Q</em>.</td>
</tr>
</table>
</example>
<example>
<title>3</title>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<em>Light Type</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable, and it is <em>categorical</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<em>Nearsightedness</em> is the <em>response</em> variable, and it is <em>categorical</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Therefore, this is an example of <em>case
                            C→C</em>.</td>
</tr>
</table>
</example>
<example>
<title>5</title>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<em>SAT Score</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable, and it is <em>quantitative</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<em>GPA of Freshman Year</em> is the <em>response</em> variable, and it is <em>quantitative</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Therefore, this is an example of <em>case
                            Q→Q</em>.</td>
</tr>
</table>
</example>
<example>
<title>7</title>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<em>Time</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable, and it is <em>quantitative</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<em>Driving Test Outcome</em> is the <em>response</em> variable, and it is <em>categorical</em>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Therefore, this is an example of <em>case
                            Q→C</em>.</td>
</tr>
</table>
</example>
<p>Now you complete the rest (click
   <xref idref="overviewexamples" page="relationships_intro1">here</xref> to open a separate
   window with the eight examples).</p>
    <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_roletype2_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/><!--<flash src="../../webcontent/flash/role_type2q1.swf" width="505" height="540" purpose="learnbydoing">
<param name="problem_name">role_type2q1</param>
</flash>-->
    <section purpose="didigetthis"><title>Did I Get This?</title><body>
        <p>In each of the following three problems, you are presented with a brief description of a
            study involving two variables. Based on the role-type classification of the two
            variables, you are asked to determine which of the four cases represents the
            data structure of the problem.</p>
        <p>For your convenience, here again is the role-type classification table:</p>
        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/relationships_overview1.gif" alt="
            Categorical Explanatory → Categorical Response (C→C),
            Categorical Explanatory → Quantitative Response (C→Q),
            Quantitative Explanatory → Categorical Response (Q→C),
            Quantitative Explanatory → Quantitative Response (Q→Q)"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_roletype2_tutor2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_roletype2_tutor3" purpose="didigetthis"/>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_roletype2_tutor4" purpose="didigetthis"/></body></section>
    <!--<activity idref="relationships_introselfassess" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
<p>The remainder of this section on exploring relationships is guided by this role-type
            classification. In the next three parts, we elaborate on cases
            C→Q,
            C→C,
            and
            Q→Q.
            More specifically, we will learn the appropriate statistical tools (visual display and
            numerical summaries) that will allow us to explore the relationship between the two
            variables in each of the cases. Case
            Q→C
            is
                <em style="italic">not</em>
            discussed in this course and is typically covered in more advanced courses. The
            section concludes with a discussion on causal relationships. </p>
<p>

</p>

</body>
</workbook_page>
