<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
 xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
 id="relationships_intro1">
 <head>
  <title>The Role-Type Classification (1 of 2)</title>
  <objref idref="classify_role_type"/>
 </head>
 <body>
 
  <p>While it is fundamentally important to know how to describe the distribution of a single
   variable, most studies pose research questions that involve exploring the relationship
    between <em style="italic">two</em> variables using the collected data.</p>
  <p>Here are a few examples of such research questions with the two variables highlighted:</p>
  <section id="overviewexamples">
   <title>Examples</title>
   <body>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <p>Is there a relationship between <em>gender</em> and <em>test scores</em> on a particular
       standardized test?</p>
      <p>Other ways of phrasing the same research question include the following:</p>
      <ul>
       <li>Is performance on the test related to gender?</li>
       <li>Is there a gender effect on test scores?</li>
       <li>Are there differences in test scores between males and females?</li>
      </ul>
     </li>
     <li>How is the <em>number of calories</em> in a hot dog related to (or affected by) the
       <em>type of hot dog</em> (beef, meat or poultry)? In other words, are there differences in
      the number of calories among the three types of hot dogs? </li>
     <li>Is there a relationship between the <em>type of light</em> a baby sleeps with (no light,
      night-light, lamp) and whether or not the child develops <em>nearsightedness</em>? </li>
     <li>Are the <em>smoking habits</em> of a person (yes, no) related to the person's
       <em>gender</em>? </li>
     <li>How well can we predict a student's freshman year <em>GPA</em> from his/her <em>SAT
       score</em>? </li>
     <li>What is the relationship between driver's <em>age</em> and sign legibility
       <em>distance</em> (the maximum distance at which the driver can read a sign)? </li>
     <li>Is there a relationship between the <em>time</em> a person has practiced driving while
      having a learner's permit and <em>whether or not this person passed the driving test</em>? </li>
     <li>Can you predict a person's <em>favorite type of music</em> (classical, rock, jazz) on the basis of
      his/her <em>IQ level</em>? </li>
    </ol>
   </body>
  </section>


  <p>In most studies involving two variables, each of the variables has a role. We distinguish
   between: </p>
  <ul>

   <li>The <em>explanatory</em> variable (also commonly referred to as the <em style="bold"
     >independent variable</em>)&#8212;the variable that claims to explain, predict, or affect the
    response; and </li>
   <li>The <em>response</em> variable (also commonly referred to as the <em style="bold">dependent
     variable</em>)&#8212;the outcome of the study.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Typically, the explanatory (or independent) variable is denoted by <em>X</em>, while
    the response (or dependent) variable is denoted by <em>Y</em>. </p>
  <section>
   <title>Explanatory and Response Variables<!--Comment--></title>
   <body>
    <p>In this course, we use the terms <em style="italic">explanatory</em> and <em style="italic">response</em> variables
     instead of <em style="italic">independent</em> and <em style="italic">dependent</em> variables.</p>
   </body>

  </section>
  <p>Now, let's go back to some of the examples and classify the two relevant variables according to
   their roles in the study.</p>
  <example>
   <title>1</title>
   <p>We want to explore whether the outcome of the study&#8212;the score on a test&#8212;is
    affected by the test-taker's gender.</p>
   <table>
    <tr>
     <td>Therefore:</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>Gender</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>Test score</em> is the <em>response</em> variable
     </td>
    </tr>
   </table>
  </example>
  <example>
   <title>3</title>
   <p>In this study, we explore whether the nearsightedness of a person can be explained by the type
    of light that person slept with as a baby. </p>
   <table>
    <tr>
     <td>Therefore:</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>Light type</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>Nearsightedness</em> is the <em>response</em> variable
     </td>
    </tr>
   </table>
  </example>
  <example>
   <title>5</title>
   <p>Here we are examining whether a student's SAT score is a good predictor for the student's GPA
    freshman year. </p>
   <table>
    <tr>
     <td>Therefore:</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>SAT score</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>GPA of freshman year</em> is the <em>response</em> variable</td>
    </tr>
   </table>
  </example>
  <example>
   <title>7</title>
   <p>Here we are examining whether a person's outcome on the driving test (pass/fail) can be
    explained by the length of time this person has practiced driving prior to the test.</p>
   <table>
    <tr>
     <td>Therefore:</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>Time</em> is the <em>explanatory</em> variable</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>
      <em>Driving test outcome</em> is the <em>response</em> variable</td>
    </tr>
   </table>
  </example>
  <!--<p>Now, using the same reasoning, you classify the two variables in the other examples (click
    <activity_link idref="overviewexamples" target="new">here</activity_link> to open a separate
   window with the eight examples above)</p>-->
  <p>Now, using the same reasoning, the following exercise will help you to classify the two
   variables in the other examples (click <xref idref="overviewexamples" page="relationships_intro1"
    >here</xref> to open a separate window with the eight examples above).</p>

  <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_roletype1_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
  <!--<flash src="../../webcontent/flash/role_type1q1.swf" width="505" height="350"
   purpose="learnbydoing">
   <param name="problem_name">role_type1q1</param>
  </flash>-->
  <activity idref="relationships_overviewwonder" purpose="manystudentswonder"/>
 </body>
</workbook_page>
