<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="scatterplot5">
    <head>
        <title>Scatterplot (5 of 5)</title>



        <objref idref="graph_quantitative_variables"/>





    </head>
    <body>

        <section>
            <title>A Labeled Scatterplot</title>
            <body>
                
                <p>In certain circumstances, it may be reasonable to indicate different subgroups or
                    categories within the data on the scatterplot, by labeling each subgroup
                    differently. The result is called a <em>labeled scatterplot</em>, and can
                    provide further insight about the relationship we are exploring. here is an
                    example. </p>
                <example>
                    <title>Hot Dogs</title>
                    <p>Recall the hot dog example from case C→Q, in which 54 major hot dog brands
                        were examined. In this study, both the <em>calorie content</em> and the
                            <em>sodium level</em> of each brand was recorded, as well as the
                            <em>type</em> of hot dog: beef, poultry, and meat (mostly pork and beef,
                        but up to 15% poultry meat). In this example, we will explore the
                        relationship between the sodium level and calorie content of hot dogs, and
                        we will label the three different types of hot dogs to create a labeled
                        scatterplot. </p>
                    <youtube src="teS5d2s8PS8"></youtube>  
               
                  <!--    <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="500"
                        height="360" purpose="walkthrough">
                        <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/scatterplot_movie.swf</param>
                        <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
                        <param name="LoggingLibraryPath"
                            >../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
                    </flash>-->
                    <p>To see a static version of this walkthrough, <activity_link
                            idref="scatterplot5altflash" target="new">click
                        here</activity_link>.</p>
                </example>
                <activity idref="scatterplot5lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Let's Summarize</title>
            <body>
                <ul>
                    <li>The relationship between two quantitative variables is visually displayed
                        using the <em>scatterplot</em>, where each point represents an individual.
                        We always plot the explanatory variable on the horizontal X axis, and the
                        response variable on the vertical Y axis. </li>
                    <li>When we explore a relationship using the scatterplot, we should describe the
                            <em>overall pattern</em> of the relationship and any <em>deviations</em>
                        from that pattern. To describe the overall pattern consider the
                            <em>direction</em>, <em>form</em> and <em>strength</em> of the
                        relationship. Assessing the strength just by looking at the scatterplot can
                        be problematic; using a numerical measure to determine strength will be
                        discussed later in this course. </li>
                    <li>Adding labels to the scatterplot that indicate different groups or
                        categories within the data might help us get more insight about the
                        relationship we are exploring. </li>
                </ul>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Checkpoint</title>
            <body>
                <p>This checkpoint will test your understanding of the material you have learned
                    thus far in this module.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <activity idref="_u2_m2_checkpoint1_pool" purpose="checkpoint"/>
            </body>
        </section>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
