<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="scatterplot1">
<head>
<title>Scatterplot (1 of 5)</title>

    <objref idref="graph_quantitative_variables"/>







</head>
<body>
    
<p>In the previous two cases we had a categorical explanatory variable, and therefore exploring the
                                                relationship between the two variables was done by
                                                comparing the distribution of the response variable
                                                for each category of the explanatory variable:</p>
<ul>
<li>In case C→Q we compared distributions of the quantitative response.</li>
<li>In case C→C we compared distributions of the categorical response.</li>
</ul>
<p>Case Q→Q is different in the sense that both variables (in particular the explanatory variable) are quantitative, and therefore, as you'll discover, this case will require a different kind of treatment and tools. Let's start with an example:</p>
<example>
<title>Highway Signs</title>
<p>A Pennsylvania research firm conducted a study in which 30 drivers (of ages 18 to 82 years old)
                                                  were sampled, and for each one, the maximum
                                                  distance (in feet) at which he/she could read a
                                                  newly designed sign was determined. The goal of
                                                  this study was to explore the relationship between
                                                  a driver's <em>age</em> and the <em>maximum
                                                  distance</em> at which signs were legible, and
                                                  then use the study's findings to improve safety
                                                  for older drivers. (Reference: Utts and Heckard,
                                                  <em style="italic">Mind on Statistics</em> (2002).
                                                  Originally source: Data collected by Last
                                                  Resource, Inc, Bellfonte, PA.)</p>
<p>Since the purpose of this study is to explore the effect of age on maximum legibility distance,
</p>
<ul>
<li>the <em>explanatory</em> variable is <em>Age</em>, and</li>
<li>the <em>response</em> variable is <em>Distance</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here is what the raw data look like:


<image style="block" src="../webcontent/scatterplot2.gif"  alt="A table of the data. There are
three columns, &quot;Driver&quot;, &quot;Age&quot;, and &quot;Distance&quot;. &quot;Age&quot; is the
Explanatory variable, and &quot;Distance&quot; is the Response variable.
Some example data:
Driver 1, 18, 510;
Driver 2, 32, 410;
Driver 3, 55, 420;
Driver 4, 23, 510;
... (abbreviated) ...
Driver 30, 82, 360;"/>
</p>
<p>Note that the data structure is such that for each individual (in this case driver 1....driver
                                                  30) we have a pair of values (in this case
                                                  representing the driver's age and distance). We
                                                  can therefore think about these data as 30 pairs
                                                  of values: (18, 510), (32, 410),
                                                  (55, 420), ... , (82, 360).</p>
<p>The first step in exploring the relationship between driver age and sign legibility distance is to create an appropriate and informative graphical display.  
The appropriate graphical display for examining the relationship between two quantitative variables is the <em>scatterplot</em>. 
Here is how a scatterplot is constructed for our example:</p>
<p>To create a scatterplot, each pair of values is plotted, so that the value of the explanatory
                                                  variable (X) is plotted on the horizontal axis,
                                                  and the value of the response variable (Y) is
                                                  plotted on the vertical axis. In other words, each
                                                  individual (driver, in our example) appears on the
                                                  scatterplot as a single point whose X-coordinate
                                                  is the value of the explanatory variable for that
                                                  individual, and whose Y-coordinate is the value of
                                                  the response variable. Here is an illustration:
                                                  <image style="block"
                                                  src="../webcontent/scatterplot3.gif" alt="A
scatterplot. The Y-Axis is labeled &quot;Sign Legibility Distance (feet)&quot;, and the X-axis is labeled
&quot;Driver Age (years)&quot; Already plotted is Driver 1's data point. It is located at x=18,y=510. Also,
Driver 2's data point has been ploted, at x=32,y=410."/> And here is
                                                  the completed scatterplot: <image style="block"
                                                  src="../webcontent/scatterplot4.gif" alt="The completed
scatterplot. There are 30 data points, shown as black dots scattered about."/>
                                                </p>
</example>
<section>
<title>Comment</title>
<body>
<p>It is important to mention again that when creating a scatterplot, the explanatory variable
                                                  should always be plotted on the horizontal X-axis,
                                                  and the response variable should be plotted on the
                                                  vertical Y-axis.
                                                  <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T132310-0400" comment="Consider rethinking this sentence. Isn&apos;t it true that by the time you get to the graphical display phase of your study, you should already have chosen which variable was explanatory? That choice must remain consistent throughout the study, so you cannot really just choose at random which way to plot the data -- you must follow your previous decision. Or. if THIS is thefirst &quot;decision time, when you must choose which is explanatory and which is response, perhaps that should be mentioned here, and it should be pointed out again that the choice you make at this point must remain consistent throughout the study."?>If
                                                  in a specific example we do not have a clear
                                                  distinction between explanatory and response
                                                  variables, each of the variables can be plotted on
                                                  either axis.<?oxy_comment_end?>
                                                  </p>
</body>
</section>
</body>
</workbook_page>
