<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
    id="scatterplot4">
    <head>
        <title>Scatterplot (4 of 5)</title>
        <objref idref="graph_quantitative_variables"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>We will now look at two more examples:</p>
        <example>
            <title>Average Gestation Period</title>
            <p>The average gestation period, or time of pregnancy, of an animal is closely related
                to its longevity (the length of its lifespan.) Data on the average gestation period
                and longevity (in captivity) of 40 different species of animals have been examined,
                with the purpose of examining how the gestation period of an animal is related to
                (or can be predicted from) its longevity. (Source: Rossman and Chance. (2001).
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T140037-0400" comment="Is this a book? if so, place in talics, and include publisher and place of publication"?>Workshop
                statistics: Discovery with data and Minitab<?oxy_comment_end?>. Original source:
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T135916-0400" comment="italic"?>The
                1993 world almanac and book of facts<?oxy_comment_end?>).</p>
            <p>Here is the scatterplot of the data.</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/scatterplot17.gif"
                alt="A scatterplot in which the vertical axis
is labeled &quot;Gestation (days)&quot; and it ranges from 0 to 700 days. The horizontal axis is labeled
&quot;Longevity (years)&quot; and it ranges from 0 to 40 years."/>
            <p>What can we learn about the relationship from the scatterplot? The direction of the
                relationship is <em>positive</em>, which means that animals with longer life spans
                tend to have longer times of pregnancy (this makes intuitive sense). An arrow drawn
                over the scatterplot below illustrates this:</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/scatterplot18.gif"
                alt="The same scatterplot with a line and arrow
drawn from the lower left to the upper right corners of the plot. Every point of data is confined to x&le;26
and y&le;500, but there is one point at roughly x=40 and y=650 which is an outlier. There are also two red
vertical lines at x=5 and x=12 which will be explained."/>
            <p>The form of the relationship is again essentially <em>linear</em>. There appears to
                be <em>one outlier</em>, indicating an animal with an exceptionally long longevity
                and gestation period. (This animal happens to be the elephant.) Note that while this
                outlier definitely deviates from the rest of the data in term of its magnitude, it
                    <em><?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T140309-0400" comment="use italics for emphasis, rather than bold"?>does<?oxy_comment_end?></em>
                follow the direction of the data.</p>
            <p>
                <em>Comment:</em> Another feature of the scatterplot that is worth observing is how
                the variation in gestation increases as longevity increases. This fact is
                illustrated by the two red vertical lines at the bottom left part of the graph. Note
                that the gestation periods for animals who live 5 years range from about 30 days up
                to about 120 days. On the other hand, the gestation period of animals who live 12
                years varies much more, and ranges from about 60 days up to more than400 days.</p>
        </example>
        <example>
            <title>Fuel Usage</title>
            <p>As a third example, consider the relationship between the average amount of fuel used
                (in liters) to drive a fixed distance in a car (100 kilometers), and the speed at
                which the car is driven (in kilometers per hour). (Source: Moore and McCabe, (2003).
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T140807-0400" comment="make italic"?>Introduction
                to the practice of statistics<?oxy_comment_end?>. Original source: T.N. Lam. (1985).
                "Estimating fuel consumption for engine size," Journal of Transportation
                Engineering, vol. 111)</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/scatterplot19.gif"
                alt="A scatterplot of fuel usage in
relation to speed. The vertical axis is labeled &quot;Fuel Used (liters/100km)&quot; and the 
Horizontal axis is labeled &quot;Speed (km/h)&quot;"/>
            <p>The data describe a relationship that decreases and then increases&#8212;the amount
                of fuel consumed decreases rapidly to a minimum for a car driving 60 kilometers per
                hour, and then increases gradually for speeds exceeding 60 kilometers per hour. This
                suggests that the speed at which a car economizes on fuel the most is about 60 km/h.
                This forms a curvilinear relationship that seems to be very strong, as the
                observations seem to perfectly fit the curve. Finally, there do not appear to be any
                outliers.</p>
        </example>
        <wb:inline idref="u1_m2_scatterplot4_tutor1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
        <!--<flash src="../../../webcontent/flash/didigetthis_scatterplot4q1.swf" width="505" height="600">
<param name="problem_name">didigetthis_scatterplot4q1</param>-->
        <!--<activity idref="scatterplot4selfassess" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
        <section>
            <title>Comment</title>
            <body>
                <p>The example in the last activity provides a great opportunity for interpretation
                    of the form of the relationship in context. Recall that the example examined how
                    the percentage of participants who completed a survey is affected by the
                    monetary incentive that researchers promised to participants. Here again is the
                    scatterplot that displays the relationship:</p>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/scatterplot25.gif"
                    alt="A scatterplot. The vertical axis is labeled
&quot;Percentage Returned&quot; and the Horizontal Axis is labeled &quot;Incentive (dollars)&quot; The shown
data closely follows a curved line which grows more quickly at lower values of dollars."/>
                <p>The positive relationship definitely makes sense in context, but what is the
                    interpretation of the curvilinear form in the context of the problem? How can we
                    explain (in context) the fact that the relationship seems at first to be
                    increasing very rapidly, but then slows down? The following graph will help
                    us:</p>
                <image style="block" src="../webcontent/scatterplot26.gif"
                    alt="The same scatterplot, except that
some boxes have been drawn. The first box encompasses the area of the plot from x=0,y=0 to x=0,y=16.
x=0,y=16 is the location of the first data point, showing that when the incentive is $0, the return
rate is 16%. The next box encompasses the are from x=0,y=0 to x=10,y=43. This shows that when the
incentive is $10, the return rate is 43%. The next box is the area between x=0,y=0 and x=30,y=54.
The last box is from x=0,y=0 to x=40,y=57."/>
                <p>Note that when the monetary incentive increases from $0 to $10, the percentage of
                    returned surveys increases sharply&#8212;an increase of 27% (from 16% to 43%).
                    However, the same increase of $10 from $30 to $40 doesn't result in the same
                    dramatic increase in the percentage of returned surveys&#8212;it results in an
                    increase of only 3% (from 54% to 57%). The form displays the phenomenon of
                    "diminishing returns"&#8212;a return rate that after a certain point fails to
                    increase proportionately to additional outlays of investment. $10 is worth more
                    to people relative to $0 than it is relative to $30.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
