<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u4_m02_probability_trees1">
    <head>
        <title>Probability Trees (1 of 3)</title>
        <objref idref="use_probability_trees"/>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p>So far, when two categorical variables are involved, we have displayed counts or
            probabilities for various events with two-way tables and with Venn diagrams. Another
            display tool, called a <em>probability tree</em>, is particularly useful for showing
            probabilities when the events occur in stages and conditional probabilities are
            involved.</p>
        <example>

            <p>A sales representative tells his friend that the probability of landing a major
                contract by the end of the week, resulting in a large commission, is .4. If the
                commission comes through, the probability that he will indulge in a weekend vacation
                in Bermuda is .9. Even if the commission doesn't come through, he may still go to
                Bermuda, but only with probability .3.</p>
            <p>First, let's identify the given probabilities for events involving <em>C</em> (the
                commission comes through) and <em>V</em> (the sales rep takes a Bermuda
                vacation):</p>
            <p>P(C) = .4 [and so P(not C) = .6],</p>
            <p>P(V | C) = .9 [and so P(not V | C) = .1], and</p>
            <p>P(V | not C) = .3 [and so P(not V | not C) = .7.]</p>
            <p>There are two stages in the problem. First, the sales rep will either get the
                commission or not.</p>
            <p>Second, based on what happened in the first stage, the sales rep will either take the
                Bermuda vacation or not.</p>
            <p>We follow exactly the same reasoning when we build the probability tree.</p>
        </example>

        <youtube src="PVQszIj-X_A"></youtube>
        <!--    <flash src="../../../webcontent/OLICamtasiaController.swf" width="402" height="326"
            purpose="walkthrough">
            <param name="movieURL">../../webcontent/flash/_u4_voiceover5.swf</param>
            <param name="movieFPS">5</param>
            <param name="LoggingLibraryPath">../../../webcontent/OLILoggingLibrary.swf</param>
        </flash>-->
        <p>There are two important things to note here:</p>
        <p>1. The probabilities in the <em>first branch-off are non-conditional probabilities</em>
            P(C) = .4, P(not C) = .6. However, the probabilities that appear in the <em>second
                branch-off are conditional probabilities. </em>The top two branches assume that C
            occurred: P(V | C) = .9, P(not V | C) = .1. The bottom two branches assume that not C
            occurred: P(V | not C) = .3, P(not V | not C) = .7</p>
        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image009.gif"
            alt="A probability tree. The bottom of the tree
(where there is the trunk) represents the first event (in this case, getting the commission). From there,
two branches (lines) are drawn. This is the branch-off. One branch is represents getting the commission and
the other represents not getting the commission. Each of these branches lead to a point. At both
of these points is the second event (going to a vacation). Each of these points has two branches. These 
represent either going on vacation or not going on vacation. Notice that this tree has two levels of points,
one for each event. We will be naming paths through the tree  with the notation &quot;{first branch-off: 
probability of branch-off; second branch-off: probability of  branch-off; ...}&quot;. Each branch-off
represents the path we take when we need to take a branch, and  the probability for taking that branch is
provided. This probability tree demonstrates how branches map to probabilities.
    {C: .4} represents P(C);
    {not C: .6} represents P(not C);
    {C: .4; V: .9} represents P(V|C);
    {C: .4; not V: .1} represents P(not V|C);
    {not C: .6; V: .3} represents P(V|not C);
    {not C: .6; not V: .7} represents P(not V|not C);"/>
        <p>2. The second thing to note is that probabilities of branches that branch out from the
            same point always add up to one.</p>
        <image style="block" src="../webcontent/image010.gif"
            alt="A probability tree demonstrating the rule.
For the point intersecting C, we have the branches {C, .4} and {C, .6}. Note that .4 + .6 = 1.
For the point intersecting {C: .4, V: .9} and {C: .4, not V: .1}, note that the probabilities for V
and not V add up to 1 (.9 + .1 = 1). For the last point intersecting {not C: .6, V: .3} and {not C:
.6, not V: .7}, note that the probabilities for V and not V add up to 1 (.3 + .7 = 1)"/>
        <p>The following "bare" tree is missing the appropriate probabilities in each of its
            branches. Complete them.</p>
        <!--<activity idref="_u4_m2_dig6" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
        <wb:inline idref="u3_m2_trees1_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
