<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u4_m02_cond_prob_and_indep1">
<head>
<title>Conditional Probability and Independence</title>

</head>
<body>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>
<p>In the last
                    module<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101109T095828-0500"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    we established the five basic rules of probability, which include the two
                    restricted versions of the Addition Rule and Multiplication Rule: The Addition
                    Rule for <em>Disjoint</em> Events and the Multiplication Rule for
                        <em>Independent</em> Events. We have also established a General Addition
                    Rule for which the events need not be disjoint. In order to complete our set of
                    rules, we still require a General Multiplication Rule for which the events need
                    not be independent. In order to establish such a rule, however, we first need to
                    understand the important concept of <em>conditional probability.</em>
                </p>
<p>This module will be organized as follows: We'll first introduce the idea of conditional
                    probability, and use it to formalize our definition of independent events, which
                    in the first module was presented only in an intuitive way. We will then develop
                    the General Multiplication Rule, a rule that will tell us how to find P(A
                        <em>and</em> B) in cases when the events A and B are not necessarily
                    independent. We'll conclude with a discussion of probability trees, a method of
                    displaying conditional probability visually
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101109T100039-0500"?>that<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101109T100038-0500" content="which"?>
                    is very helpful in solving problems.</p>
</body>
</section>
</body>
</workbook_page>
