<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u4_m02_conditional_probability1">
<head>
<title>Conditional Probability (1 of 2)</title>
    <objref idref="explain_conditional_probability"/>
    <objref idref="find_conditional_probabilities"/>
</head>
<body>
    
    <p>In the first part of this module, we'll introduce the concept of conditional probability. The
            idea here is that the probabilities of certain events may be affected by whether or not
            other events have occurred. Let's illustrate this idea with a simple example:</p>
<example>

<p>All the students in a certain high school were surveyed, then classified according to gender and whether they had either of their ears pierced:</p>
<image style="block" src="../webcontent/image001.gif" alt="A table of the data. The column headings are
&quot;Pierced,&quot; &quot;Not Pierced,&quot; and &quot;Total.&quot; The Rows are &quot;Male,&quot;
&quot;Female,&quot; and &quot;Total.&quot; The data in the cells is given in &quot;Row, Column:
Value&quot; format:
        Male, Pierced: 36;
        Male, Not Pierced: 144;
        Male, Total: 180;
        Female, Pierced: 288;
        Female, Not Pierced: 32;
        Female, Total: 320;
        Total, Pierced: 324;
        Total, Not Pierced: 176;
        Total, Total: 500;"/>
<p>(Note that this is a two-way table of counts that was first introduced when we talked about the
                                                  relationship between two categorical variables. It
                                                  is not surprising that we are using it again in
                                                  this example, since we indeed have two categorical
                                                  variables here: <em>Gender:</em> M or F (in our
                                                  notation, "not M"), and <em>Pierced:</em> Yes or
                                                  No)</p>
<p>Suppose a student is selected at random from the school. Let <em>M</em> and <em>not M</em> denote the events of being male and female, respectively, and <em>E</em> and <em>not E</em> denote the events of having ears pierced or not, respectively.  We'll start by asking what will seem like simple questions, and we'll build our way to conditional probability:</p>
    <ol style="lower-alpha">
  <li>  <p>What is the probability that the student has one or both ears pierced?</p>

<p>Since a student is chosen at random from the group of 500 students, out of which 324 are
                                                  pierced,</p>
<p> P(E) = 324/500 = .648</p></li>
<li><p>What is the probability that the student is male?</p>
<p>Since a student is chosen at random from the group of 500 students, out of which 180 are
                                                  male,</p>
<p> P(M) = 180/500 = .36</p></li>
<li><p>What is the probability that the student is male and has ear(s) pierced? </p>
<p>Since a student is chosen at random from the group of 500 students out of which 36 are male and
                                                  have their ear(s) pierced, P(M and E) = 36/500 =
                                                  .072</p>
<p>Now something new:</p></li>
<li><p>
                                                  <em>Given</em> that the student that was chosen is
                                                  male, what is the probability that he has one or
                                                  both ears pierced?</p>
<p>At this point, new notation is required, to express the probability of a certain event given
                        that another event holds. We will write "the probability of having one or
                        both ears pierced (E) , given that a student is male (M)" as <em>P(E |
                            M).</em>
                    </p></li></ol>
<p>A word about this new notation: The event whose probability we seek (in this case E) is written
                                                  first, the vertical line stands for the word
                                                  "given" or "conditioned on," and the event that is
                                                  given (in this case M) is written after the "|"
                                                  sign.</p>
<p>We call this probability the <em>conditional probability</em> of having one or both ears pierced, given that a student is male: it assesses the probability of having pierced ears under the condition of being male. Now to solve for the probability, we observe that choosing from only the males in the school essentially alters the sample space S from all students in the school to all male students in the school. The total number of possible outcomes is no longer 500, but has changed to 180.  Out of those 180 males, 36 have ear(s) pierced, and thus:</p>
<p> P(E | M) = 36/180 = .20.</p>
</example>
</body>
</workbook_page>
