<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>

<workbook_page id="_u01_m01_metacog_mindset">
    <head>
        <title>Learning Strategies (1 of 4)</title>
        
       
    </head>
    <body>
        <p><!--OLI Statistics-->Probability and Statistics is not your typical course. Our goal is for you to work through the course
            materials online, in your own time, and in the way that is most efficient given your prior
            knowledge.</p>
 
        <p>While you will have more flexibility than you do in a traditional course, you will also
            have more responsibility for your own learning. You will need to</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Plan how to work through each unit.</li>
            <li>Determine how to use the various features of the course to help you learn.</li>
            <li>Decide when you need to seek additional support.</li>
        </ul>
        <section><title>What You Need to Know about Each Unit</title>
        <body>
        <p>Each unit in this course has features designed to support you as an independent learner,
                    including the following: </p>
        <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p><em style="bold"><term>Explanatory content:</term></em> The content is the
                            informational “meat” of every chapter. It consists of short passages of
                            text with information, examples, images, and explanations.</p>
                    </li>
                    <!--<li><em style="bold"><term>Walkthroughs:</term></em> The explanatory content is supplemented occasionally by short walkthrough movies 
                that help explain the concepts being presented.       </li>-->
                   
                    <li>
                        <p><em style="bold"><term>Learn By Doing activities:</term></em> Learn By
                            Doing activities give you the chance to practice the concept that you
                            are learning, with hints and feedback to guide you if you struggle. </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p><em style="bold"><term>Did I Get This? activities:</term></em> Did I Get
                            This? activities are your chance to do a quick self-check to assess
                            your own understanding of the material before doing a graded activity. </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p><em style="bold"><term>Many Students Wonder sidebars:</term></em> These
                            short passages provide supplementary material that you may find
                            interesting, but that is not necessary to understand the main concepts
                            presented in the course.</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p><em style="bold"><term>Checkpoints:</term></em> Taking these short
                            assessments will show your instructor how well you have understood the
                            material.</p>
                    </li>
            <li>
                <p><em style="bold"><term>Lab exercises:</term></em> Lab exercises, called
                    <em style="italic">StatTutors</em>, occur at the end of some modules. In these labs, you will
                    practice the process of a statistical investigation. You will
                    investigate a research question using real data and technology. These
                    labs provide the opportunity to integrate concepts from various
                    modules.</p>
            </li>
                </ul>
       

        </body></section>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
