<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u01_mindset_1">
	<head>
		<title>Learning Strategies (2 of 4)</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		
		
		<section>
			<title>About This Course</title>
			<body>
				<p>Many math classes are about following the rules. You learn a set of steps for
					doing a specific type of problem, and then you repeat those same steps to answer
					new problems. The result is that you can answer questions correctly by following the
					steps without ever understanding <em style="italic">why</em> you are following them. <em style="bold"
						>This course is not like that.</em>
				</p>
				
				<p>In the words of one student:</p>
				
				<ul style="none">
					<li><p><em style="italic">In my old math classes, I used to just skim a
						chapter, copy the equations down, and use the equations to solve the
						problems. It saved me time, and I could still pass. But when I tried
						that in this class, I started failing because they set up the
						problems a different way. You really have to pay attention and think
						about them to get them right. It was harder, but I think I ended up
						learning a lot more.</em></p>
						<!--<p><em style="italic">~ From a former student</em></p>--></li>
				</ul>
				<p>This course is designed to help students learn why and when specific rules are
					appropriate, not just <em style="italic">how</em> to use those rules. In order
					to succeed in this course, you need to understand the concepts of statistics so
					you can decide for yourself about the right ways to solve problems. <!--that come up.
					That means this course is both harder and more useful -->Mastering both the concepts and the methods means that this course is harder—but also more useful—than a typical math class. </p>
				<p>In the next section, you will learn about what the student quoted above and other students did to
					succeed in this course and how you can succeed too. </p>
				
			</body>
		</section>
		
		
		<!--  <section>
			<title>Check Your Understanding</title>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="mindset_1a"/>
			</body>
		</section>-->
		
		
		
		
		
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
