<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u01_mindset_3">
	<head>
		<title>Learning Strategies (4 of 4)</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		
		
		<section>
			<title>How to Succeed</title>
			<body>
				<p>So far, we have learned that</p>
				
				<ul>
					<li>This course is about getting the meaning of statistics, not just following
						steps to get an answer.</li>
					<li>Achieving this understanding is possible because our brains can get stronger and can change to learn
						new things.</li>
					
				</ul>
				<p>So how do you do it? How do you actually strengthen your
					brain and succeed in this kind of course? We asked some former students to tell
					us their advice for success. </p>
				<p>These students said it was most important to</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Do the Did I Get This? and Learn By Doing questions in the course.</li>
					<li>Ask questions.</li>
					<li>Study your mistakes.</li>
					<li>Explain the ideas to yourself in different ways until they are clear.</li>
					
				</ul>
				
				<pullout>
					<p>From a former student 1:</p>
					<p>In my old math classes, I used to just skim a chapter, copy the equations
						down, and use the equations to solve the problems. It saved me time, and I
						could still pass. But when I tried that in this class, I started failing
						because they set up the problems a different way. You really have to pay
						attention and think about them to get them right. It was harder, but I think
						I ended up learning a lot more. </p>
					<p>So you can’t just read things and expect to pass. You have to do the practice
						problems. There are these questions in the course that say “Did I Get
						This?”. And it was tempting to just skip them, but that’s how I almost
						failed. Those Did I Get This? questions were like little speed bumps that
						slowed me down and made me understand what I was reading.</p>
					
				</pullout>
				
				<pullout>
					<p>From a former student 2:</p>
					<p>One thing that helped me get a good grade was fixing my mistakes before they
						count for points. It’s like, everyone makes mistakes, but are you going to
						find them when you’re reading, or are they going to bite you on the
						homework? I want to catch them early. The questions in the module were good
						to catch and fix my mistakes before they counted for points. They aren’t
						graded, but they definitely help your grade.</p>
				</pullout>
				<pullout>
					<p>From a former student 3:</p>
					<p>This course is different than other math classes I’ve taken. You have to
						really understand the material if you want to pass. But they give you help
						to do that. The practice problems are definitely helpful, and also talking
						to the teacher is really good. The teacher’s job is to help you when you’re
						confused… so yeah, don’t be afraid to ask lots of questions! </p>
				</pullout>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Summary</title>
			<body>
				
				<p>As you have read, previous students made suggestions such as the following:<!--suggested things like: --></p>
				<ul>
					<li>Do the practice problems.</li>
					<li>Look carefully at your mistakes.</li>
					<li>Ask lots of questions. </li>
				</ul>
				
				<p>What do these practices have in common? They are all ways of challenging your brain
					to get active, think deeply, and make new connections. </p>
				<p>You might think “that sounds like more work”... and you’re right. Easy strategies
					like skimming the book might work in other classes. But this class is different.
					<em style="italic">You will need to learn new things to pass this class, and you should expect it
						to feel hard as your brain gets stronger.</em> The feeling of struggling is a normal
					part of how your brain gets stronger when it learns things. </p>
				<p>Think about it this way: <em style="italic">Strategies that feel easy, such as skipping the practice
					problems and only reading and listening, are kind of like going to the gym and
					lifting balloons instead of weights.</em> Even if you spend a lot of time doing it,
					you won't get stronger. The harder strategies are like real weights. They're a
					lot harder to lift, and it might feel like you're struggling, but they pay off.
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title/>
			<body>
				<p>We’d like your help explaining what you have just learned in your own words. We
					will use your responses to help explain these ideas to future students in this
					class. </p>
				<p>In the box below, please explain, in your own words, what you have learned about
					how to pass this class. You might talk about</p>
				<ul>
					<li>What we know on how the brain can get stronger and what that means for
						students in this class </li>
					<li>Your own ideas about how to actively engage with what you are learning
						instead of just passively reading </li>
					
				</ul>
				
				<wb:inline idref="mindset_2"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		
		
		
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
