<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
	xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"
	id="bigpicture">
	<head>
		<title>The Big Picture</title>
	</head>
	<body>
				<p>In a nutshell, what statistics is all about is <em>converting data into useful
				information</em>. Statistics is therefore a process <!--where we are:-->in which we</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Collect data, <!--collecting data, --></li>
			<li>Summarize data, and <!--summarizing data, and--></li>
			<li>Interpret data. <!--interpreting data. --></li>
		</ul>
		<p>To really understand how this process works, we need to put it in a context. We will do that by
			introducing one of the central ideas of this course&#8212;the <em>Big Picture of
				Statistics</em>. We will introduce the Big Picture by building it gradually and
			explaining each step. At the end of the introductory explanation, once you have the full
			Big Picture in front of you, we will show it again using a concrete example. </p>
		<p>The process of statistics starts when we identify what group we want to study or learn
			something about. We call this group the <em>population</em>. Note that the word
			<em style="italic">population</em> here (and in the entire course) <!--is not just used to refer-->does not refer only to people; it is
			used in the broader statistical sense<!--, where population can--> to refer not only to people,
			but also to animals, <!--things etc-->objects, and so on. For example, we might be interested in </p>
		<ul>
			<li>The opinions of the population of U.S. adults about the death penalty</li>
			<li>How the population of mice react to a certain chemical</li>
			<li>The average price of the population of all one-bedroom apartments in a certain city</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Population, then, is the entire group that is the target of our interest:</p>
		<image style="inline" src="../webcontent/population.png" alt="Pictorial representation of a population"/>
		<p>In most cases, the population is so large that, as much as we want to, there is absolutely no
			way we can study all of it (imagine trying to get the opinions of <em style="italic">all</em> U.S.
			adults about the death penalty). A more practical approach would be to examine and
			collect data only from a subgroup of the population, which we call a <em style="italic">sample</em>. We call
			this first step, which involves choosing a sample and collecting data from it,
				<em>producing data</em>.</p>
		<image style="inline" src="../webcontent/data.png" alt="Producing data is visualized as taking a subset of
 the population, and creating a new set of points."/>
		<p>It should be noted that since, for practical reasons, we need to compromise and examine only a
			sub-group of the population rather than the whole population, we should make an effort
			to choose a sample in such a way that it will represent the population well. For
			example, if we choose a sample from the population of U.S. adults, and ask their
			opinions about the death penalty, we do not want our sample to consist of only
			Republicans or only Democrats.</p>
		<p>Once the data have been collected, what we have is a long list of answers to questions, or
			numbers, and in order to explore and make sense of the data, we need to summarize that
			list in a meaningful way. This second step, which consists of summarizing the collected
			data, is called <em>exploratory data analysis</em>.</p>
		<image style="inline" src="../webcontent/eda.png" alt="Exploratory data analysis is performed on
the data which is a subset of the population."/>
		<p>Now we've obtained the sample results and summarized them, but we are not done. Remember that
			our goal is to study the population, so what we want is to be able to draw conclusions
			about the population based on the sample results. Before we can do so, we need to look
			at how the sample we're using may differ from the population as a whole, so that we can
			factor that into our analysis. To examine this difference, we use <em>probability</em>. </p>
		<p>In essence, probability is the "machinery" that allows us to draw conclusions about the
			population based on the data collected about the sample.</p>

		<image style="inline" src="../webcontent/probability.png" alt="The data and summarization of the data
created from data analysis are examined using probability, which is the first step in allowing us to
draw conclusions about the population based on the data."/>
		
		<p>Finally, we can use what we've discovered about our sample to draw conclusions about our population.  
			We call this final step in the process
				<em>inference</em>.</p>
		<image style="block" src="../webcontent/inference.png" alt="First, a set of data was created from a
subset of the population. Then, we perform exploratory data analysis on the data. With these results, we
apply probability which is our first step in drawing conclusions about the population from the data. After
we have applied probability to the data, we can draw conclusions. This is called inference, the second step
in drawing conclusions."/>
		<p>This is the <em>Big Picture of statistics</em>. </p>
		<p/>
		<example>
			<p>At the end of April 2005, a poll was conducted (by ABC News and the <em style="italic">Washington Post</em>) for the
				purpose of learning the opinions of U.S. adults about the death penalty. </p>
			<p>
				<em>1. Producing Data:</em> A (representative) sample of 1,082 U.S. adults was
				chosen, and each adult was asked whether he or she favored or opposed the death
				penalty. </p>
			<p>
				<em>2. Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA):</em> The collected data were summarized, and
				it was found that 65% of the sampled adults favor the death penalty for persons
				convicted of murder. </p>
			<p>
				<em>3 and 4. Probability and Inference:</em> Based on the sample result (of 65%
				favoring the death penalty) and our knowledge of probability, it was concluded (with
				95% confidence) that the percentage of those who favor the death penalty in the
				population is within 3% of what was obtained in the sample (i.e., between 62% and
				68%). The following figure summarizes the example: </p>
			
			<image style="inline" src="../webcontent/big_picture_example.png" alt="A visual representation 
of the poll conducted about the opinions of U.S. adults about the death penalty. The large population, which 
represents the U.S. adults, and data was produced from 1082 of these adults by asking them about the death 
penalty. In the data set, we have 1082 responses, and exploratory data analysis tells us that 65% are in
in favor of the death penalty. Using both probability and inference, we can draw the conclusion that we are
95% sure that the population percentage is within 3% of 65% (i.e., between 62% and 68%). This brings us back
to where we started, the population."/>
		</example>
		<p/>
		
		
		
		<section>
			<title>Course Structure</title>
			<body>
				<p>The structure of this entire course is based on the Big Picture. The course has 
					<!--four units, one-->one unit for each of the steps in the Big Picture. As the figure below shows, we
					start this course with EDA (even though it is second in the process of
					statistics), continue to discuss producing data, then <!--go on-->proceed to
					probability, so that at the end we’ll be able to discuss inference. The
					following figure summarizes the structure of the course. </p>
			</body>
		</section>
	
			<image style="inline" src="../webcontent/big_picture_units.png" alt="Producing data (step 1 in
the big picture) is covered in Unit 2. Exploratory data analysis (step 2) is covered in Unit 1.
Probability (step 3) is covered in Unit 3, and inference (step 4) is covered in Unit 4."/>
			<p>As you’ll see, the Big Picture is the basis upon which the entire course is built, both 
			conceptually and structurally. We will refer to it often, and having it in mind will help you
			as you go through the course.</p>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
