<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="overview">
	<head>
		<title>Course Overview</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Idea</title>
			<body>
				<p>One of the main design principles behind <em>Statistics Online</em> is that, wherever possible, content is presented to the student in many different formats:</p>
			<ul>
						<li>Text</li>
						<li>Graphical slides with audio overlay</li>
						<li>Interactive exercises</li>
						<li>Intelligent tutoring system (StatTutor)</li>
						<li>Small inline tutors ("Mini-tutors")</li>
					</ul>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Navigation</title>
			<body>
				<p>There are several ways to navigate through the course:</p>
			<ul>
						<li>Menu on the left side of page <image style="block" src="../webcontent/toc.gif"/>
					</li>
						<li>Navigation bars at the top and bottom of each page <image style="block"
							src="../webcontent/navbar.gif"/>
					</li>
					</ul>
				
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Learning Opportunities/Activities</title>
			<body>
				<p>Sprinkled throughout the course are buttons that represent additional learning opportunities or activities for the student:</p>
				<section>
					<title>Module Objectives</title>
					<body>
						<p>At any point during the course, from any page of the course, the student has access to the
							learning objectives for the current module by clicking on the objectives
							button in the top or bottom navigation bar. <image style="block"
								src="../webcontent/objectives.gif"/>
						</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Learn By Doing</title>
					<body>
						<p>Periodically, students are given opportunities to practice what they have learned. These activities typically contain instructions for performing an activity in a statistical package and then ask the student questions about the activity. Students can then compare their own answers with answers that the course author would have given.
								<image style="block" src="../webcontent/learnbydoing.gif"/>
						</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Did I Get This?</title>
					<body>
						<p>Throughout the course, there are opportunities for students to take self-assessments to gauge their understanding of the content. These self-assessments do not count towards the students' grades, and can be taken as many times as desired.
								<image style="block" src="../webcontent/didigetthis.gif"/>
						</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Many Students Wonder...</title>
					<body>
						<p>This button will launch a page that contains frequently asked questions. These questions generally address common misconceptions that students have, or clarify points that have been made in the main page.
								<image style="block" src="../webcontent/wonder.gif"/>
						</p>
					</body>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>StatTutor</title>
					<body>
						<p>StatTutor is a Web-based intelligent tutor that provides students with a data analysis
							problem, supports them as they attempt to solve it, and gives hints and
							feedback along the way. <image style="block"
								src="../webcontent/tutor.gif"/>
						</p>
					</body>
				</section>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
