<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u3_m2_glucose2"><title>Glucose Regulation</title><page><question id="glucose1"><body>What problem(s) is/are associated with glucose homeostasis dysfunction?</body><multiple_choice shuffle="false"><choice value="kidney">kidney dysfunction</choice><choice value="blind">blindness</choice><choice value="both">both</choice><choice value="neither">neither</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i64cbd3bf16ac4a979c9acf0c880ef4f6"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_list_function_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_predict_SKILL" /><response match="kidney" score="0"><feedback>This is only partly correct. Eyesight and other body functions can also be severely impacted by glucose homeostasis dysfunction.</feedback></response><response match="blind" score="0"><feedback>This is only partly correct. Kidney function and other body functions can also be severely impacted by glucose homeostasis dysfunction.</feedback></response><response match="both" score="1"><feedback>Correct. And in addition to the eyes and kidneys, there are other areas of the body that can also be severely impacted by glucose homeostasis dysfunction.</feedback></response><response match="neither"><feedback>Incorrect. There are many areas of the body which can be severely impacted by glucose homeostasis dysfunction.</feedback></response><hint>Diabetes is associated with glucose homeostasis dysfunction.</hint><hint>Unregulated diabetes can cause frequent urination and overgrowth of blood vessels into the retina of the eye.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="glucose2"><body>What system of the body is important in the regulating of molecules and macromolecules in the body as a receptor and control center?</body><multiple_choice><choice value="endocrine">endocrine system</choice><choice value="digestive">digestive system</choice><choice value="urinary">urinary system</choice><choice value="skeletal">skeletal system</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i7caebb65ab474a40a6da021e743b9a09"><skillref idref="_u3_list_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_list_function_SKILL" /><skillref idref="_u3_predict_SKILL" /><response match="endocrine" score="1"><feedback>Correct. Other things can also regulate molecules and macromolecules, including the nervous system, but many times the endocrine system serves as receptor and regulator.</feedback></response><response match="digestive"><feedback>Incorrect. Often the digestive system is involved in homeostasis feedback loops as an effector to adjust absorption, but not as a receptor and control center.</feedback></response><response match="urinary"><feedback>Incorrect. Often the urinary system is involved in homeostasis feedback loops as a way to get rid of excess molecules and macromolecules, but not usually as a receptor or control center.</feedback></response><response match="skeletal"><feedback>Incorrect. The skeletal system is involved in calcium homeostasis, but not as a receptor or control center.</feedback></response><hint>What system is involved in calcium and insulin regulation?</hint><hint>What system produces hormones?</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
