<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u5_endUnit5_review"><head><title>Muscular System Unit Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="f284ebc3f03c4232955e38038309b780">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this unit on muscle tissue and the skeletal muscular system. Could you demonstrate your knowledge of each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="ccd9c64324394069bd74cd18857ee38a"><li><p id="aca59917627384627a847a29e63084222">Describe the major functions of muscle tissue. </p></li><li><p id="ae09b7b4a0e4f44c8b801a5fa90b60865">Identify major diseases associated with the skeletal musculature and their causes. </p></li><li><p id="aceb335ebfeb5492a88e484c8b2307e3e">Describe the different structural levels of skeletal muscle organization.</p></li><li><p id="af89f0d40469146e583eac1d0d2f3c369">Describe the interaction of actin and myosin in force generation. Identify which cofactors (ions and proteins) regulate actin-myosin force generation.</p></li><li><p id="d5def36d77b847aaac26479564c11dcb">Describe how the parallel organization of a sarcomere relates to force generation function; predict what effect changes in filament overlap would have on large-scale muscle function. </p></li><li><p id="ab789248349be4019888c841292b054db">Explain how the cellular organization of fused skeletal muscle cells allows muscle tissue to contract properly.</p></li><li><p id="af45acbd701f2497cacbf621d73d84eab">Describe myoblast fusion to generate multinucleated skeletal muscle cells and tissue structure.</p></li><li><p id="ae9c3c4f1d6144976b8c36b5a4a4c00c1">Compare and contrast the structure, location in the body and function of skeletal muscle, cardiac muscle and smooth muscle.</p></li><li><p id="ae82583524dc44c0384daf277b376dfc1">Identify skeletal, cardiac and smooth muscle cells by anatomical features. </p></li><li><p id="acde7ed1ff7eb4c08a87c9b5e8f35e570">Describe how cellular anatomical features relate to force generation.</p></li><li><p id="ac246957fbaf34a108cd2a23829a7cb22">Describe the sequence of events involved in the contraction cycle of skeletal muscle. </p></li><li><p id="af25dbc24fb8b4f009c3cc352444e593d">Describe the anatomy of the neuromuscular junction.</p></li><li><p id="ad5adbeba4e6a40d0b4fd0e60592b8d92">Explain the physiology of the neuromuscular junction.</p></li><li><p id="af354144806da4ba4a21ffc933f0c177d">Explain how an electrical signal from the nervous system is communicated to muscle cells.</p></li><li><p id="ac09013e2bb4a4f0cbe130186d026c169">List the sources of energy used in muscle contraction.</p></li><li><p id="aeae417df305349dab279e4b9a473e9c5">Describe the mechanisms that muscle fibers use to generate ATP for muscle contraction.</p></li><li><p id="aed2a04e8276a4eb1ae774846557e54f4">Explain the three phases twitch undergoes as viewed on a myogram.</p></li><li><p id="aeb80cb6be9af4f208e7ee52616505d25">Explain the effects of summation and recruitment on muscle contraction.</p></li><li><p id="ae9daf8a9b6a54a608c478d03ba9b23fe">Describe the difference between tetanus and treppe.</p></li><li><p id="ae5f68c0110994cfc88bd1e012b242522">Describe the specialized structures of muscle cells.</p></li><li><p id="ad76033759db646dc8b6b2b9fbc0d634a">List the anatomical and metabolic characteristics of fast, slow, and intermediate muscle fibers. </p></li><li><p id="b785fa55deae4f74b2e8331b658490d8">Identify muscle tissue as being a mixture of SO, FG and FO cells/fibers.</p></li><li><p id="aaaa66b509aed46cf84dfd6f6cd309f99">Describe the difference in distribution of cell/fiber types in different specific body muscles.</p></li><li><p id="ae5b40c831bf04d5eaeaa9acdf3c7dabf">Define the terms muscle tone, hypotonia and hypertonia.</p></li><li><p id="af32586b23f9548e4be7cfab18fe91dfb">Describe the difference between isometric and isotonic contractions of muscle.</p></li><li><p id="ae12a5d82e889472085edd7fc5135a7f2">Describe the composition of the connective tissue layer that surrounds each cell, fascicle, muscle and group of muscles. </p></li><li><p id="ac850874a863e4654b2b3e8e4cc33fed4">Describe different fiber organization (parallel, convergent, pinnate, sphincter) and how the organization is related to functions.</p></li><li><p id="af6a7686e9e4543019cd2858a9c301f01">Define the terms: aponeuroses, tendons, bursae.</p></li><li><p id="ab72a770d9f214599a9a57b37e05ee8c4">Differentiate among the three classes of levers in terms of the relative position of fulcrum, effort and load, as well as in terms of the relative power and range of motion.</p></li><li><p id="ae19be48af73149d3aa00c450dbfb65a2">Define the terms prime mover (or agonist), antagonist, synergist and fixator and provide an example of each.</p></li><li><p id="ac58b1eb95e2f4aedb35ef44d3db40cc0">Explain how some muscles are named: Include examples of muscles named by shape, size, location, movement they produce, and direction of fibers.</p></li><li><p id="afa94074fd32a4718ad91890ec85b7569">Explain the role of the muscular system in maintaining temperature homeostasis.</p></li><li><p id="aa72abef3d4b541f5be7d6f4a977f5a65">Provide examples of factors that can affect muscle size.</p></li><li><p id="ae8cbb883aac74d25930c9569924459fd">Describe several factors that can affect the endurance of muscles.</p></li><li><p id="afc34aab194c34e16ae400a3aba4006ab">Describe how an improperly functioning skeletal muscular system would affect other systems.</p></li><li><p id="ad47f466c0dbd48ed9d8b4e3761f423a7">Describe how muscle tissue within the cardiovascular system contributes to proper function.</p></li><li><p id="ae58d36469d2244aabd35e516b61efa96">Describe how muscle tissue within the digestive system contributes to proper function.</p></li></ul><activity idref="u5_endofunitquiz" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="_u6_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
