<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u6_m2_review">
    
    <head>
        <title>Muscle Structures and Functions Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        <p>Skeletal muscles (organs) are almost never completely relaxed. Even if a muscle is not producing movement, some of the muscle fibers 
            (cells) in the organ contract to produce muscle tone. The two main types of skeletal muscle contractions are isotonic and isometric. </p>    
      
        <p>Inside each skeletal muscle, muscle fibers (a single muscle cell is called a muscle fiber; not to be confused with fibers found 
            in connective tissue) are organized into groups called fascicles, or bundles of muscle fibers (cells). Each fascicle contains
            many long muscle fibers bound by a middle layer of connective tissue called the perimysium.Inside each fascicle, each individual
            muscle fiber is encased in a connective tissue layer called the endomysium. The plasma membrane, or sarcolemma, of a skeletal 
            muscle fiber is located just under the endomysium. The sarcolemma is the site of action potential conduction, which triggers 
            muscle contraction. Within the sarcolemma is the sarcoplasm, the cytoplasm of the muscle cell.</p>
        
        <p>The mechanisms by which muscles act on bones are depicted using descriptions based on levers. A lever is a rigid structure, in this
            case a bone, that moves on a fixed point called the fulcrum, in this case an articulation. The body has only a few first-class levers.
            One is involved in head flexion (pulling the head down toward the chest) and head extension (pulling the head back up into normal position). 
            In a second-class lever, the load is located between the applied force and the fulcrum. In third-class levers the force is applied 
            between the load and the fulcrum.</p>
        
        <p>Make sure you understand gross anatomy nomenclature for muscles, and be able to distinguish between agonists and antagonists.</p>
        <!--  Quiz  --> 
        <activity idref="_u6_structures_functions_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
    </body>
    
</workbook_page>

