<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u6_m3_review"><head><title>Muscular Levels of Organization Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="efaac65294d044f88efcd6549f094d0c">Myosin is a protein that converts the chemical energy stored in the bonds of ATP into the kinetic energy of movement. Myosin is the force-generating protein in all muscle cells, and a coordinated effort among many myosin molecules pulling on actin, generates force 
 for movement. The point at which the head and tail of the molecule meet is flexible and allows the head to move back and forth. 
 This allows myosin to “walk” and pull on actin filaments. Actin filaments are made of individual globular (spherical) protein subunits
 that assemble linearly into helical (twisted) filaments. In skeletal muscle, tropomyosin and troponin regulate contraction by controlling
 the interaction between actin and myosin filaments.</p><p id="ac1e51506fb94b7daeebd0ee00401c46">Myofilaments are organized structures in muscle cells that contain the actin and myosin. The organized globular proteins of actin in muscle cells form a thin filament, and bundles of over 200 myosin proteins form a thick filament. Make sure you completely understand the anatomy
 of a sarcomere before proceeding, and be able to compare and contrast the structure, location in the body and function of the three different 
 types of muscle.</p><p id="cecda9d3a2184735981f600584473631">Skeletal muscle is contracted voluntarily. Communication occurs between a neuron and a muscle fiber through neurotransmitters. Neural excitation causes the release of neurotransmitters from the synaptic terminal into the synaptic cleft, where they can then bind to the 
 appropriate receptors on the motor end-plate.</p><activity idref="_u6_muscle_lvl_org_quiz_pool" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
