<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="compu_cond_prob_u2_m2_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_compu_cond_prob_u2_m2" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>High blood pressure is unhealthy. Here are the results of one of the studies that
                link high blood pressure to death from cardiovascular disease. The researchers
                classified a group of white males aged 35 to 64 as having low blood pressure or high
                blood pressure, then followed the subjects for 5 years. The following two-way table
                gives the results of the study:</p>
            <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment2q9.gif" />
            <p>In this example, which of the following would be appropriate to calculate?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Conditional row percentages </choice>
            <choice value="B">Conditional column percentages </choice>
            <choice value="C">The correlation coefficient r </choice>
            <choice value="D">The five-number summary of both variables </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. To explore a categorical relationship, the most appropriate
                    summary is the outcome percentages within each <em>explanatory</em> group. For
                    the table shown, think about whether the row variable (cardiovascular death) or
                    the column variable (blood pressure) would be the <em>explanatory</em>
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. To explore a categorical relationship, the most appropriate
                    summary is the outcome percentages within each <em>explanatory</em> group. In
                    this case, the column variable (blood pressure) would be the explanatory
                    variable, so the appropriate percentages are the death percentages from each
                    blood pressure group. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient is a summary value for a
                    scatterplot, not for a two-way table. To explore a categorical relationship, the
                    most appropriate summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory
                    group.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Five-number summaries are only appropriate for lists of
                    quantitative measurements. But a two-way table summarizes categorical variables,
                    not quantitative variables. To explore a categorical relationship, the most
                    appropriate summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory
                    group.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_compu_cond_prob_u2_m2" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>A 2009 study analyzed data from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health.
                Participants were followed into adulthood. Each study participant was categorized as
                to whether they were obese (BMI &gt;30) or not and whether they were dating,
                cohabiting, or married. The researchers were trying to determine the effect of
                relationship status on obesity. The table below summarizes the results.</p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <td />
                    <td align="center"><em style="bold">Dating</em></td>
                    <td align="center"><em style="bold">Cohabiting</em></td>
                    <td align="center"><em style="bold">Married</em></td>
                    <td align="center"><em style="bold">Total</em></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td align="left"><em style="bold">Obese</em></td>
                    <td align="right">81</td>
                    <td align="right">103</td>
                    <td align="right">147</td>
                    <td align="right">331</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td align="left"><em style="bold">Not obese</em></td>
                    <td align="right">359</td>
                    <td align="right">326</td>
                    <td align="right">277</td>
                    <td align="right">962</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td align="left"><em style="bold">Total</em></td>
                    <td align="right">440</td>
                    <td align="right">429</td>
                    <td align="right">424</td>
                    <td align="right">1,293</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p>In this example, which of the following would it be appropriate to calculate?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Conditional row percentages</choice>
            <choice value="B">Conditional column percentages</choice>
            <choice value="C">The correlation coefficient (r)</choice>
            <choice value="D">The five-number summary of both variables</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. To explore a categorical relationship, the most appropriate
                    summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory group. For the table
                    shown, think about whether the row variable (obesity) or the column variable
                    (relationship status) would be the explanatory variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. To explore a categorical relationship, the most appropriate
                    summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory group. In this case,
                    the column variable (relationship status) would be the explanatory variable, so
                    the appropriate percentages are the obesity percentages from each relationship
                    status group.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient is a summary value for a
                    scatterplot involving two quantitative (numerical) variables not for a two-way
                    table involving two categorical variables. To explore a categorical
                    relationship, the most appropriate summary is the outcome percentages within
                    each explanatory group.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Five-number summaries are appropriate only for lists of
                    quantitative measurements. A two-way table summarizes categorical variables, not
                    quantitative variables. To explore a categorical relationship, the most
                    appropriate summary is the outcome percentages within each explanatory
                    group.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
