<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="estimate_r_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>Suppose that the correlation r between two quantitative variables was found to be r =
            0. Which of the following is the best interpretation of this correlation value?</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">There is a strong linear relationship between the two variables. </choice>
            <choice value="B">There is no linear relationship between the two variables. </choice>
            <choice value="C">There is a strong relationship between the two variables. </choice>
            <choice value="D">There is no relationship between the two variables. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A correlation coefficient <em style="italic">far</em> from zero
                    would indicate a strong linear relationship. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The correlation coefficient indicates the strength of the
                    linearity of a scatterplot relationship, and a correlation coefficient that is
                    zero indicates no linear relationship. However, that there might still be some
                    other (non-straight-line) kind of relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A correlation coefficient <em style="italic">far</em> from zero
                    would indicate a strong linear relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Not quite right. The correlation coefficient only measures <em style="italic">linear</em> relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
   

    <multiple_choice id="q2_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>The data in the scatterplot below are an individual's weight and the time it takes
            (in seconds) on a treadmill to raise his or her pulse rate to 140 beats per minute. The
            o's correspond to females and the +'s to males. Which of the following conclusions is
            most accurate?<image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment2q8.gif" />
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">There is a positive correlation between gender and weight. </choice>
            <choice value="B">There is a negative correlation between time and weight for males and
                for females. </choice>
            <choice value="C">There is a positive correlation between time and weight for males and
                for females. </choice>
            <choice value="D">There is a negative correlation between gender and weight.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There can only be a <em style="italic">correlation</em> between
                    two quantitative variables. But notice that "gender" is categorical. Also, the
                    correlation coefficient would be positive only when the points tend to rise from
                    left to right.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. For each separate gender, we see that the points on the
                    scatterplot tend to <em style="italic">fall</em> from left to right. This
                    indicates a <em style="italic">negative</em> relationship. So the correlation
                    coefficient would be negative for males, and would also be negative for females.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient would be positive only when the
                    points tend to rise from left to right. But on the scatterplot, we see that, for
                    both males and females, the points tend to fall from left to right. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The scatterplot does show a negative correlation pattern, but
                    there can only be a <em style="italic">correlation</em> between two quantitative
                    variables. But notice that "gender" is categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q3_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>What can we say about the relationship between the correlation r and the slope b of
            the least-squares line for the same set of data? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Both r and b always have values between −1 and 1. </choice>
            <choice value="B">r is always larger than b. </choice>
            <choice value="C">r and b have the same sign (+ or −). </choice>
            <choice value="D">The slope b is always equal to the square of the correlation r. </choice>
            <choice value="E">b is always larger than r. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It’s true that the correlation r always has a value between −1
                    and 1, but there is no such restriction on slope. The slope of a line can exceed
                    1 or −1.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that the correlation r always has value between −1 and
                    1, but a regression line could have a slope larger than 1. So it’s possible for
                    b to be larger than r.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Although the correlation r isn’t the same as the slope b, the
                    thing they always have in common is their <em style="italic">sign</em>.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is no such relationship between slope and correlation.
                    Remember that the correlation r always has a value between 0 and 1, so the
                    square of the correlation will also be between −1 and 1. But there is no such
                    restriction on slope.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Remember that for points that tend to rise from left to right,
                    the correlation is close to 1 when the points are tightly clustered around the
                    regression line. But if the regression line is shallow, the slope could be close
                    to zero. So it’s possible for b to be <em style="italic">less</em> than
                    r.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q4_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>If there is no relationship (linear or otherwise) between two quantitative variables
            as observed on a scatterplot, the value of the correlation coefficient, r, is likely to
            be which of the following? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Closer to 1</choice>
            <choice value="B">Closer to −1</choice>
            <choice value="C">Closer to 0 </choice>
            <choice value="D">Either closer to −1 or 1</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Recall that a correlation close to 1 indicates a strong
                    positive relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Recall that a correlation close to −1 indicates a strong
                    negative relationship.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. A correlation value close to 0 indicates no relationship between
                    two quantitative variables.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Recall correlation close to 1 or −1 indicates reasonably strong
                    positive or negative relationships, respectively.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q5_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>Using data from 100 hospitals, a correlation of r = 0.78 is found between the size of
            a hospital (measured in number of beds) and the average length of patient stays
            (measured in days). Which of the following is true?</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">There is a pretty strong positive linear correlation between number of
                beds and length of hospital stay.</choice>
            <choice value="B">Increasing hospital size must be the cause of longer patient stays. </choice>
            <choice value="C">“Severity of illness” is a possible lurking variable that is behind
                this relationship.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient by itself isn’t enough to determine
                    whether the relationship was linear. You would need to look at the scatterplot
                    to determine if the relationship was a straight-line trend.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You can’t determine <em style="italic">causation</em> merely from the nature of a
                    display. Just because there might be an <em style="italic">association</em>, that doesn’t (by itself)
                    indicate anything about <em style="italic">causation</em>. Causation can only be determined by knowing
                    the nature of the study design.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Severity of illness is a possible lurking variable, since the
                    seriousness of a patient’s condition is will determine the length of stay. Also, since
                    larger hospitals are more likely to treat severe conditions, this would
                    explain why the patient stays are longer for large hospitals.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q6_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>The data in the scatterplot below are an individual's age (in years) and the expected
            life span (in years). The circles correspond to females and the x's to males. Which of
            the following conclusions is most accurate?<image style="block" src="../webcontent/u2_m2_checkpoint2_image1.gif" />
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">There is a positive correlation between gender and life expectancy. </choice>
            <choice value="B">There is a negative correlation between gender and life expectancy. </choice>
            <choice value="C">There is a positive correlation between age and life expectancy for
                both males and females.</choice>
            <choice value="D">There is a negative correlation between age and life expectancy for
                both males and females.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There can only be a "correlation" between two quantitative
                    variables. But notice that "gender" is categorical. Also, the correlation
                    coefficient would be positive only when the points tend to rise from left to
                    right.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The scatterplot does show a negative correlation pattern, but
                    there can only be a "correlation" between two quantitative variables. But notice
                    that "gender" is categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient would be positive only when the
                    points tend to rise from left to right. But on the scatterplot, we see that, for
                    both males and females, the points tend to fall from left to right. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. For each separate gender, we see that the points on the
                    scatterplot tend to fall from left to right. This indicates a negative
                    relationship. So the correlation coefficient would be negative for males, and
                    would also be negative for females. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

    <multiple_choice id="q7_estimate_r_pool" select="single">
        <body>Suppose the correlation between two variables (x, y) in a data set is determined to
            be r = 0.63, What must be true about the slope, b, of the least-squares line estimated
            for the same set of data? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">The slope will also be a value between −1 and 1. </choice>
            <choice value="B">The slope will have the opposite sign as the correlation. </choice>
            <choice value="C">The slope b is always equal to the square of the correlation r. </choice>
            <choice value="D">The slope will have the same sign as the correlation.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It’s true that the correlation r always has a value between −1
                    and 1. But there is no such restriction on slope. The slope of a line can exceed
                    1 or be less than −1.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A line’s slope indicates if the points rise from left to right
                    or fall from left to right, the same as correlation. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is no such relationship between slope and correlation.
                    Remember that the correlation r always has a value between −1 and 1, so the
                    square of the correlation will be between 0 and 1. But there is no such
                    restriction on slope. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The slope, b, will always have the same sign as the correlation
                    coefficient, r. Lines with positive slope tend to rise left to right, just like
                    points that are positively associated. Lines with negative slope tend to fall
                    left to right, just like points that are negatively associated.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>


</pool>
