<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="estimate_r_interp_regress_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_estimate_r_interp_regress" select="single">
        <body>A local ice cream shop kept track of the number of cans of cold soda it sold each
            day, and the temperature that day, for two months during the summer. The data are
            displayed in the scatterplot below: <image style="block" src="../webcontent/assessment2q3.gif" /> The one outlier corresponds to a day on
            which the refrigerator for the soda was broken. Which of the following is true? </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">A reasonable value of the correlation coefficient r for these data is
                1.2. </choice>
            <choice value="B">If the temperature were measured in degrees Celsius (C = 5/9*(F-32)),
                the value of r would change accordingly. </choice>
            <choice value="C">If the outlier were removed, r would increase. </choice>
            <choice value="D">If the outlier were removed, r would decrease. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient r must be between −1 and 1. It
                    cannot be larger than 1.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The correlation coefficient r is a unitless number, so it’s not
                    affected by a change of units.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The outlier makes the data less "tightly clustered" around the
                    linear trend. Removing the outlier will increase the overall tightness of the
                    points around their straight-line trend, so the correlation coefficient would be
                    closer to 1. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. For a scatterplot where the trend is generally rising, the
                        <em>more</em> linear the scatterplot is, the <em>closer to 1</em> the
                    correlation coefficient r will be. Notice that removing the outlier will
                        <em>increase</em> the overall tightness of the points around their
                    straight-line trend.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>


    <multiple_choice id="q2_estimate_r_interp_regress" select="single">
        <body>The weights (in pounds) and cholesterol levels (in mg/dL) of several individuals was
            observed. The data are shown in the scatterplot below: <image style="block" src="../webcontent/estimate_r_interp_regress_pool_b1_graphic.gif" /> The outlier on
            the graph is likely due to an error in recording the data. Which of the following
            statements is true?</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">A reasonable value of the correlation coefficient r for these data is
                1.2. </choice>
            <choice value="B">If the weight (WT) were measured in kilograms instead of pounds (1 lb
                = 0.4536 kg) the value of r would change accordingly. </choice>
            <choice value="C">If the outlier were removed, the correlation coefficient (r) would increase. 
            </choice>
            <choice value="D">If the outlier were removed, the correlation coefficient (r) would decrease. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While the graph shows a positive association, the correlation
                    coefficient must range between −1 and 1.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Correlation is unitless, meaning that changing the units of
                    either variable, x or y, won’t change its value.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The outlier lies outside the linear pattern formed by most of the
                    data. Since correlation measures how tightly the points in a graph cluster about
                    a straight line, removing the outlier, which has the largest deviation from the
                    line will increase the correlation. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The outlier lies outside the linear pattern formed by most of
                    the data. Since correlation measures how tightly the points in a graph cluster
                    about a straight line, removing the outlier, which has the largest deviation
                    from the line will increase the correlation.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

</pool>
