<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="interp_2x2_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_interp_2x2" select="single">
        <!-- LO: interp_2x2 -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the tables is the appropriate table of conditional percentages to discover
                if the region where one lives affects whether or not one has health insurance?</p>
            <image src="../../webcontent/flash/didigetthis_caseii2_02q3image1.gif" />
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Table A</choice>
            <choice value="B">Table B</choice>
            <choice value="C">Table C</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This table reports the conditional percentages for each value of
                    the explanatory variable (region) displayed in the rows: northeast, midwest,
                    south, and west.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This table reports percentages each cell contributes to the
                    whole rather than conditional percentages for each value of the explanatory
                    variable.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. We need to find the conditional percentages for each value of
                    the explanatory variable. This table displays the conditional percentages for
                    health insurance, which is not the explanatory variable.</feedback>
            </response>

        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_interp_2x2" select="single">
        <!-- LO: interp_2x2 -->
        <body>
            <p>A 2009 study analyzed data from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health.
                Participants were followed into adulthood. Each study participant was categorized as
                to whether they were obese (BMI &gt;30) or not and whether they were dating,
                cohabiting, or married. The table below summarizes the results.</p>
            <image src="../webcontent/checkpoint_pool_table1.gif" />
            <p>What percentage of those who were married were obese? (Round your answer to 1 decimal
                place.)</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">34.7% (147/424)</choice>
            <choice value="B">44.4% (147/331)</choice>
            <choice value="C">32.8% (424/1293)</choice>
            <choice value="D">25.6% (331/1293)</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The percentage of those who were married that were obese is
                    calculated as the number of married and obese participants divided by the number of
                    married participants (147/424).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It looks like you calculated the percentage of obese participants who
                    were married (147/331). The question asks for the percentage of <em style="italic">married participants who were obese.</em></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It looks like you calculated the percent of participants who were
                    married (424/1293). The question asks for the percentage of married participants <em style="italic">who were obese.</em></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It looks like you calculated the percentage of participants who were
                    obese (331/1293). The question asks for the percentage of <em style="italic">married</em> participants who
                    were obese.</feedback>
            </response>

        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

</pool>
