<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="interp_scatterplot_pool">
	<title>pool</title>
	<multiple_choice id="q1_interp_scatterplot" grading="automatic" select="single">
		<body>
			<p id="ae2174acddf604def9e2d832be3c9f9a2">A local ice cream shop kept track of the number of cans of cold soda it sold each day, and the temperature that day, for 2 months during the summer. The data are displayed in the scatterplot below:</p>
			<image id="f55f64c1d37e4967b920b0b125c7d8e7" src="../webcontent/assessment2q3.gif" alt="" style="block" vertical-align="middle">
				<caption />
				<popout enable="true" />
			</image>
			<p id="aa45babf4993c4f0aaf074cbf470a94d8">Which of the following is the best description of the relationship between X and Y as it appears in the scatterplot?</p>
		</body>
		<input shuffle="false" id="ifd1fda36ce1e493dbef4d173bae970e8" labels="false">
			<choice value="A">Positive linear relationship with outlier(s)</choice>
			<choice value="B">Positive linear relationship with no outlier(s)</choice>
			<choice value="C">Positive nonlinear relationship with outlier(s)</choice>
			<choice value="D">Negative linear relationship with no outlier(s)</choice>
			<choice value="E">Negative nonlinear relationship with outlier(s)</choice>
			<choice value="F">Negative nonlinear relationship with no outlier(s)</choice>
		</input>
		<part id="d0ca40b0c673410dbb69c6a307cef91a">
			<response match="A" score="10">
				<feedback>
					<p id="ad4c2d318b08e4236998fba3e32691627">Correct. The graph displays a positive relationship: an increase in X is associated with an increase in Y. The relationship is linear because it can be described as points scattered about a line. Finally, it has one point that deviates from the pattern of the relationship, which is considered an outlier.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="B" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="ad3d432ce28b04a99928f86f2f2945dda">Incorrect. While the relationship is positive and linear, it does have one outlier—the point on the lower right that deviates from the pattern of the relationship.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="C" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="abf32115c9ef744228d01968a7197c561">Incorrect. While you're correct that the relationship is positive and has an outlier, the relationship is linear, because it can be described as points scattered about a line.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="D" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="ac43b3e7fb2324d479b7554a6ff70d61d">Incorrect. While the relationship is linear, it is positive, because an increase in X is associated with an increase in Y. It also does have one outlier—the point on the lower right that deviates from the pattern of the relationship.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="E" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="abbab1fae5b174f0e9584d25d4fb0ff25">Incorrect. While you're correct that the relationship has an outlier, it is positive, because an increase in X is associated with an increase in Y, and it is linear, because it can be described as points scattered about a line.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="F" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="af172efb420944dbc85f787d954aa3ec2">Incorrect. The graph displays a positive relationship: an increase in X is associated with an increase in Y. The relationship is linear, because it can be described as points scattered about a line. Finally, it has one point that deviates from the pattern of the relationship, which is considered an outlier.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
		</part>
	</multiple_choice>
	<multiple_choice id="q2_interp_scatterplot" grading="automatic" select="single">
		<body>
			<p id="ac993d37eb83a4c5d95723516df8d4134">The following scatterplot shows the relationship between the amount of money spent (budget) and the amount of money earned (gross) for the 13 Hollywood movies with the highest profit.</p>
			<image id="bef7c2d020084b2e9a3c94741edb9e80" src="../webcontent/assessment2q4.gif" alt="" style="block" vertical-align="middle">
				<caption />
				<popout enable="true" />
			</image>
			<p id="adfa0cb7b2e464bd48a218ad20fd4dbf3">Which of the following best describes the relationship between X(budget) and Y(gross) as it appears in the scatterplot?</p>
		</body>
		<input shuffle="false" id="ib5e4f327c64e480d9351e6733c68c837" labels="false">
			<choice value="A">Negative linear relationship</choice>
			<choice value="B">Positive linear relationship</choice>
			<choice value="C">Positive nonlinear relationship</choice>
			<choice value="D">Negative nonlinear relationship</choice>
		</input>
		<part id="a04ae51b646646078ded630dafe54b67">
			<response match="A" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="aaab18f41dcb74f088a09654bbec82ffd">Incorrect. A negative relationship results when Y decreases as X increases. Additionally, the data do not form a straight line.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="B" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="ace9ccb51bce94334a9263fc13d73e549">Incorrect. Although you are correct that the relationship is positive, the data do not form a straight line.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="C" score="10">
				<feedback>
					<p id="abed32f3853094fc5a6767b06b8e7ebe7">Correct. The relationship is positive and nonlinear because as X increases, Y also increases and the data do not form a straight line.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
			<response match="D" score="0">
				<feedback>
					<p id="af97c6c7ea5cd4f2a82e64aa9af19f5a5">Incorrect. Although you are correct that the relationship is nonlinear, the data do not have a negative relationship because as X increases, Y also increases.</p>
				</feedback>
			</response>
		</part>
	</multiple_choice>
</pool>
