<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="recog_simpson_paradox_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_recog_simpson_paradox" select="multiple">
        <body>
            <p>A study was done on the timeliness of flights categorized as either "on time" or
                "delayed" of two major airlines: StatsAir and AirMedian. Data were collected over a
                period of time from five major cities and it was found that StatsAir does better
                overall (i.e., has a smaller percentage of flights categorized as delayed). However,
                in each of the five cities separately, AirMedian does better (i.e., has a smaller
                percentage of flights categorized as delayed in each city).</p>
            <p>Which of the following is correct? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">This is an example of Simpson's paradox.</choice>
            <choice value="B">"City" is a lurking variable in this example.</choice>
            <choice value="C">This is an example of a negative association between
                variables.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    there is at least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that "city" is a lurking variable, because
                    there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups
                    separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However, there is at least
                    one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is appropriate to call an association positive or negative
                    only when the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables
                    ("timeliness" and "city") are categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is an example of Simpson’s paradox, because there is an
                    association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups separately
                    but reverses when the groups are combined. Such reversal typically indicates a
                    lurking variable, which in this case is "city."</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However, it
                    is appropriate to call an association positive or negative only when the
                    variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("timeliness" and
                    "city") are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that "city" is a lurking variable, because
                    there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups
                    separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However, it is appropriate
                    to call an association positive or negative only when the variables are
                    quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("timeliness" and "city") are
                    categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. Such
                    reversal typically indicates a lurking variable, which in this case is "city."
                    However, it is appropriate to call an association positive or negative only when
                    the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("timeliness"
                    and "city") are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>


    <multiple_choice id="q2_recog_simpson_paradox" select="multiple">
        <body>
            <p>A study of admission rates of men and women into graduate programs for several majors
                at a certain university was conducted. The study found that overall a higher
                percentage of men were admitted than women. However, when looking at each major
                program separately it was found that the rate of admission for women was higher than
                that for men.</p>
            <p>Which of the following statements is true? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">This is an example of Simpson’s paradox.</choice>
            <choice value="B">This is an example of a negative association between
                variables.</choice>
            <choice value="C">“Type of major” may be a lurking variable in this study.</choice>
            <choice value="D">This situation is mathematically impossible.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s
                    paradox, there is at least one other correct response.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Since the variables in this example are both categorical, it is
                    not appropriate to describe the association as negative or positive.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that “type of major” is a lurking
                    variable, there is at least one other correct response.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This situation can occur mathematically. Remember that it is
                    possible to observe an association when looking at groups separately that can
                    reverse when groups are combined.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s
                    paradox, this is not an example of a negative association: since the variables
                    in this example are both categorical, it is not appropriate to describe the
                    association as negative or positive. Additionally, there is at least one other
                    correct response.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is an example of Simpson’s paradox in which an observed
                    association disappears when the additional variable “type of major” is
                    considered. Thus “type of major” is a lurking variable that may explain the
                    difference in admission rates between men and women at this
                    university.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s
                    paradox, this situation can occur mathematically. Remember that it is possible
                    to observe an association when looking at groups separately that can “reverse”
                    when groups are combined.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “type of major” is a lurking variable.
                    However, since the variables in this example are both categorical, it is not
                    appropriate to describe the association as negative or
                    positive.<!--inserted missing feedback, 10/8 ~carol--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Since the variables in this example are both categorical, it is
                    not appropriate to describe the association as negative or positive. Also, this
                    situation can occur mathematically. Remember that it is possible to observe an
                    association when looking at groups separately that can reverse when groups are
                    combined.<!--inserted MORE missing feedback, 10/8 ~carol--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “type of major” is a lurking variable.
                    However, this situation can occur mathematically. Remember that it is possible
                    to observe an association when looking at groups separately that can reverse
                    when groups are
                    combined.<!--inserted YET MORE missing feedback, 10/8 ~carol--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s
                    paradox and that “type of major” is a lurking variable, this is not an example
                    of a negative association, since the variables in this example are both
                    categorical it is not appropriate to describe the association as negative or
                    positive.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s
                    paradox, it is not appropriate to label the association as “negative” since the
                    variables are both categorical. Also, this situation can occur mathematically.
                    Remember that it is possible to observe an association when looking at groups
                    separately that can reverse when groups are combined.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s
                    paradox and that “type of major” is a lurking variable, it is not appropriate to
                    label the association as negative, since the variables are both categorical.
                    Also, this situation can occur mathematically. Remember that it is possible to
                    observe an association when looking at groups separately that can reverse when
                    groups are combined.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “type of major” is a lurking variable.
                    However, since the variables in this example are both categorical, it is not
                    appropriate to describe the association as negative or positive. Also, this
                    situation can occur mathematically. Remember that it is possible to observe an
                    association when looking at groups separately that can reverse when groups are
                    combined.<!--inserted even MORE missing feedback, 10/8 ~carol--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox
                    and that “type of major” is a lurking variable. However, since the variables in
                    this example are both categorical, it is not appropriate to describe the
                    association as negative or positive. Also, this situation can occur
                    mathematically. Remember that it is possible to observe an association when
                    looking at groups separately that can reverse when groups are
                    combined.<!--and MORE missing feedback, 10/8 ~carol--></feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. At least one answer is
                    correct.<!--and more missing feedback, 10/8 ~carol--></feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>


    <multiple_choice id="q3_recog_simpson_paradox" select="multiple">
        <body>
            <p>A study was done of all homicide convictions in the State of Florida between 1976 and
                1980 in order to examine if the application of the death sentence was racially
                biased. The data showed that a larger percentage of white suspects (11.2%) were
                sentenced to death than black suspects (8.5%). However, if the race of the victim
                was included in the analysis, the study found that for white victims, a larger
                percentage of black suspects (19.3%) were sentenced to death than white suspects
                (12.3%).</p>
            <p>Which of the following is correct? Check all that apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">“Race of the suspect” is a lurking variable in this
                situation.</choice>
            <choice value="B">“Race of the victim” is a lurking variable in this situation.</choice>
            <choice value="C">This is an example of Simpson’s paradox.</choice>
            <choice value="D">This is an example of a negative association.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. “Race of the suspect” is the <em style="italic">explanatory</em> variable in this situation, because we are investigating
                    if race of the suspect impacts whether or not the death penalty is used.
                    Additionally, there is at least one correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “race of the victim” is a lurking
                    variable, because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each
                    of several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    there is at least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    there is at least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is only appropriate to call an association positive or
                    negative when the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables
                    ("race of suspect” and "use of death penalty") are categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “race of the victim” is a lurking
                    variable, because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each
                    of several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study. Additionally, there
                    is at least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study. Additionally, there
                    is at least one other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It is only appropriate to call an association positive or
                    negative when the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables
                    ("race of suspect” and "use of death penalty") are categorical. Additionally,
                    “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study. There is at least
                    one correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. This is an example of Simpson’s paradox, because there is an
                    association that is seen a particular way for each of several groups separately
                    but reverses when the groups are combined. Such reversal typically indicates a
                    lurking variable, which in this case is "race of victim."</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “race of the victim” is a lurking
                    variable, because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each
                    of several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    it is only appropriate to call an association positive or negative when the
                    variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("race of suspect”
                    and "use of death penalty") are categorical. Additionally, there is at least one
                    other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However, it
                    is only appropriate to call an association positive or negative when the
                    variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("race of suspect”
                    and "use of death penalty") are categorical. Additionally, there is at least one
                    other correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. Such
                    reversal typically indicates a lurking variable, which in this case is "race of
                    victim." However, “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that “race of the victim” is a lurking
                    variable, because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each
                    of several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. However,
                    “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study and it is only
                    appropriate to call an association positive or negative when the variables are
                    quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("race of suspect” and "use of
                    death penalty") are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. Such
                    reversal typically indicates a lurking variable, which in this case is "race of
                    victim." However, “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study and
                    it is only appropriate to call an association positive or negative when the
                    variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("race of suspect”
                    and "use of death penalty") are categorical. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. Such
                    reversal typically indicates a lurking variable, which in this case is "race of
                    victim." However, it is only appropriate to call an association positive or
                    negative when the variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables
                    ("race of suspect” and "use of death penalty") are categorical. </feedback>
            </response>

            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an example of Simpson’s paradox,
                    because there is an association that is seen a particular way for each of
                    several groups separately but reverses when the groups are combined. Such
                    reversal typically indicates a lurking variable, which in this case is "race of
                    victim." However, “race of suspect” is the explanatory variable in the study and
                    it is only appropriate to call an association positive or negative when the
                    variables are quantitative. But in this case, both variables ("race of suspect”
                    and "use of death penalty") are categorical.</feedback>
            </response>

            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one correct answer.</feedback>
            </response>

        </part>
    </multiple_choice>

</pool>
