<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u3_m02_causation_and_experiments3_openfree">
<head>
<title>Causation and Experiments (3 of 3)</title>

    <objref idref="identify_study_design"/>
    <objref idref="explain_conclusions"/>




</head>
<body>
   
<section>
<title>Pitfalls in Experimentation</title>
<body>
<p>Some of the inherent difficulties that may be encountered in experimentation are the Hawthorne
                    effect, lack of realism,
                    non<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T175738-0400" content="-"?>compliance,
                    and treatments that are unethical, impossible, or impractical to impose.</p>
<p>We already introduced a hypothetical experiment to determine if people tend to snack more while they watch TV: Recruit participants for the study. While they are presumably waiting to be interviewed, half of the individuals sit in a waiting room with snacks available and a TV on. The other half sit in a waiting room with snacks available and no TV, just magazines. Researchers determine whether people consume more snacks in the TV setting. </p>
<p>Suppose that, in fact, the subjects who sat in the waiting room with the TV consumed more snacks
                    than those
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180051-0400"?>who<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180050-0400" content="in"?>
                    sat in the room without
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180056-0400"?>the
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>TV. Could we conclude that in their everyday lives, and in
                    their own homes, people eat more snacks when the TV is on? Not necessarily,
                    because people's behavior in this very controlled setting may be quite different
                    from their ordinary behavior. If they suspect their snacking behavior is being
                    observed, they may alter their
                    behavior<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180134-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    either consciously or subconsciously. This phenomenon, whereby people in an
                    experiment behave differently from how they would
                    normally<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180215-0400"?>
                    behave<?oxy_insert_end?>, is called the <em>Hawthorne effect</em>. Even if they
                    don't suspect they are being observed in the waiting room, the relationship
                    between TV and snacking there might not be representative of what it is in real
                    life. One of the greatest advantages of an
                    experiment<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180339-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180337-0400" content="---"?>that
                    researchers
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180349-0400" content="themselves "?>take
                    control of the explanatory
                    variable<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180345-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180343-0400" content="---"?>can
                    also be a disadvantage in that it may result in a rather unrealistic setting.
                        <em>Lack of realism</em> (also called <em>lack of ecological
                        validity<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180524-0400" content=") "?></em><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180527-0400"?>)
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>is a possible drawback
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180533-0400"?>to
                    the<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T180532-0400" content="in"?>
                    use of an experiment rather than an observational study to explore a
                    relationship. Depending on the explanatory variable of interest, it may be quite
                    easy or it may be virtually impossible to take control of the variable's values
                    and still maintain a fairly natural setting.</p>
<p>In our hypothetical smoking cessation example, both the observational study and the experiment
                    were carried out on a random sample of
                    1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181750-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>000
                    smokers with intentions to quit. In the case of the observational study, it
                    would be reasonably feasible to locate
                    1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181755-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>000
                    such people in the population at large, identify their intended method, and
                    contact them again a year later to establish whether they succeeded or not. In
                    the case of the experiment, it is not so easy to take control of the explanatory
                    variable (cessation method) merely by telling all
                    1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181759-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>000
                    subjects what method they must use.
                        <em>Non<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181803-0400" content="-"?>compliance</em>
                    (failure to submit to the assigned treatment) could enter in on such a large
                    scale as to render the results invalid. In order to ensure that the subjects in
                    each treatment group actually undergo the assigned treatment, researchers would
                    need to pay for the treatment and make it easily available. The cost of doing
                    th<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181818-0400"?>at<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181817-0400" content="is"?>
                    for a group of
                    1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181822-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>000
                    people would go beyond the budget of most researchers. Even if the drugs or
                    therapy were paid for, it is very unlikely that most of the subjects contacted
                    at random would be willing to use a method not of their own choosing, but
                    dictated by the researchers. From a practical standpoint, such a study would
                    most likely be carried out on a smaller group of volunteers, recruited via
                    flyers or some other sort of advertisement. The fact that they are volunteers
                    might make them somewhat different from the larger population of smokers with
                    intentions to quit, but it would reduce the more worrisome problem of
                    non-compliance. Volunteers may have a better overall chance of success, but if
                    researchers are primarily concerned with which method is most successful, then
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181844-0400"?>the
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>relative success of the various methods should be roughly the
                    same for the volunteer sample as it would be for the general population, as long
                    as the methods are randomly assigned. Thus, the most vital stage for
                    randomization in
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T182145-0400" comment="Is this statement universally true of every experiment? If not, &quot;an&quot; should be changed to &quot;this&quot;"?>an<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    experiment is
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181937-0400"?>during<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181926-0400" content="for"?>
                    the assignment of treatments, rather
                    than<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T181944-0400" content=" for"?>
                    the selection of subjects.</p>
<p>There are other, more serious drawbacks to experimentation, as illustrated in the following hypothetical examples:</p>
<example>

<p>Suppose researchers want to determine if the drug Ecstasy causes memory loss. One possible design would be to take a group of volunteers and randomly assign some to take Ecstasy on a regular basis, while the others are given a placebo. Test them periodically to see if the Ecstasy group experiences more memory problems than the placebo group.</p>
<p>The obvious flaw in this experiment is that it is unethical (and actually also illegal) to administer a dangerous drug like Ecstasy, even if the subjects are volunteers. The only feasible design to seek answers to this particular research question would be an observational study.</p>
</example>
<example>

<p>Suppose researchers want to determine whether females wash their hair more frequently than males. </p>
<p>It is impossible to assign some subjects to be female and others male, and so an experiment is
                        not an option here. Again, an observational study would be the
                        <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T182535-0400"?>only
                        <?oxy_insert_end?>way to proceed.</p>
</example>
<example>

<p>Suppose researchers want to determine whether being in a lower income bracket may be responsible for obesity in women, at least to some extent, because they can't afford more nutritious meals and don't have the means to participate in fitness activities.</p>
<p><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183433-0400"?>The socioeconomic status of
                        the study subject is a variable that cannot be controlled by the
                        researchers, so an experiment is impossible. (Even if the researchers could
                        somehow raise the money to provide a random sample of women with substantial
                        salaries, the effects of their eating habits during their lives before the
                        study began would still be present, and would affect the study's
                        outcome.)<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183433-0400" content="It is theoretically possible to manipulate the explanatory variable by providing substantial salaries to a random sample of women, but this would be too expensive an undertaking for any researcher."?></p>
</example>
<p>These examples should convince you that, depending on the variables of interest, researching
                    their relationship via an experiment may be too unrealistic, unethical, or
                    impractical. Observational studies are subject to
                    flaws<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183538-0400" content=" themselves"?>,
                    but often they are the only recourse. </p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Let's summarize what we've learned so far: </title>
<body>
<p>
<em>1.</em>
<em> Observational studies:</em>
</p>
<p><?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183644-0400" comment="use bullets for lists, rather than asterisks"?>*<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183741-0400"?>The
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>explanatory variable's values
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183750-0400"?>are
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>allowed to occur naturally.</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183756-0400"?>B<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183755-0400" content="b"?>ecause
                    of the possibility of lurking variables, it is difficult to establish
                    causation.</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183800-0400"?>I<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183759-0400" content="i"?>f
                    possible, control for suspected lurking variables by studying groups of similar
                    individuals separately.</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183804-0400"?>S<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183804-0400" content="s"?>ome
                    lurking variables are difficult to control for; others may not be
                    identified.</p>
<p>
<em>2. Experiments</em>
</p>
<p>* <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183820-0400"?>The
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>explanatory variable's values are controlled by researchers
                    (treatment is imposed).</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183828-0400" content="r"?><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183829-0400"?>R<?oxy_insert_end?>andomized
                    assignment to treatments automatically controls for all lurking variables.</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183838-0400" content="m"?><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183838-0400"?>M<?oxy_insert_end?>aking
                    subjects blind avoids
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183841-0400"?>the
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>placebo effect.</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183846-0400"?>M<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183846-0400" content="m"?>aking
                    researchers blind avoids conscious or
                    sub<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T183850-0400" content="-"?>conscious
                    influences on their subjective assessment of responses.</p>
<p>* <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184037-0400"?>A
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>randomized controlled double-blind experiment is generally
                    optimal for establishing causation.</p>
<p>* <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184208-0400"?>A <?oxy_insert_end?>lack
                    of realism may prevent researchers from generalizing experimental results to
                    real<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184213-0400"?>-<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184213-0400" content=" "?>life
                    situations.</p>
<p>*
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184219-0400"?>N<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184218-0400" content="n"?>on<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184217-0400" content="-"?>compliance
                    may undermine an experiment.
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184222-0400"?>A
                    <?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184223-0400" content="V"?><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184224-0400"?>v<?oxy_insert_end?>olunteer
                    sample might solve (at least partially) this problem.</p>
<p>* <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184408-0400"?>It
                    is<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184405-0400" content="some treatments are"?>
                    impossible,
                    impractical<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184238-0400" content=","?>
                    or unethical to
                    impose<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T184415-0400"?> some
                    treatments<?oxy_insert_end?>.</p>
</body>
</section>
    <!--<section>
        <title>Checkpoint</title>
        <body>
            <p>This checkpoint will test your understanding of the material you have learned thus far in this module.</p>
            <p>
                
                    
            </p>
            <activity idref="_u3_m2_checkpoint1" purpose="checkpoint"/>
        </body>
    </section>-->
    
    
</body>
</workbook_page>
