<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u3_m02_wrapup_openfree">
    <head>
        <title>Wrap-Up (Designing Studies)</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>In this module we distinguished among different types of studies and learned the details
            of each type of study design. By doing so, we also expanded our understanding of the
            issue of establishing causation that was first discussed in the previous unit of the
            course. In the Exploratory Data Analysis unit, we learned that in general, association
            does not imply causation, due to the fact that lurking variables might be responsible
            for the association we observe, which means we cannot establish that there is a causal
            relationship between our "explanatory" variable and our response variable.</p>
        <p>In this module we completed the causation puzzle by learning under what circumstances an
            observed association between variables
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101104T110501-0400" comment="use italics instead of all caps for emphasis"?>CAN<?oxy_comment_end?>
            be interpreted as causation. We saw that in observational studies, the best we can do is
            to control for what we think might be potential lurking variables, but we can never be
            sure that there aren't any others that we didn't anticipate. Therefore, we can come
            closer to establishing causation, but never
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101104T110649-0400" comment="add italics for emphasis"?>really<?oxy_comment_end?>
            establish it. </p>
        <p>The only way we can, at least in theory, eliminate the effect of (or control for)
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101104T110854-0400" comment="use italics instead of all caps for emphasis"?>ALL<?oxy_comment_end?>
            lurking variables is by conducting a randomized control experiment, in which subjects
            are randomly assigned to one of the treatment groups. Only in this case can we interpret
            an observed association as causation. Obviously, due to ethical or other practical
            reasons, not every study can be conducted as a randomized experiment. Where possible,
            however, a double-blind randomized control experiment is about the best study design we
            can use. </p>
        <p>Another very common study design is the survey. While a survey is a special kind of
            observational study, it really is treated as a separate design, since it is so common
            and is the type of study that the general public is most often exposed to (polls). It is
            important that we be aware of the fact that the wording, ordering, or type of questions
            asked in a poll could have a impact on the response. In order for a survey's results to
            be reliable, these issues should be carefully considered when the survey is
            designed.</p>
        <!--<activity idref="depression" purpose="lab"/>-->
        <activity idref="ctat2_m3_stattutor" purpose="lab"/>
     
        <section>
            <title>End of Section Questions</title>
            <body>
                <!--<p>Before you do the checkpoint activity, please evaluate your understanding of the learning
                    objectives for the Producing Data unit and use the first <em>My Response</em>
                    link below to ask any questions you might have about the material that you would
                    like the instructor to address. Your questions can be for clarification of the
                    material or further insight. Your self-evaluation and questions may also shape
                    the discussions in class.</p>
                <p>Your response will not be graded, but will be available for your instructor to
                    read. Answering these questions may also shape the discussions in class.</p>-->
                <activity idref="_u3_m02_wrapup1_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>
            </body>
        </section>
        <!--<section>
            <title>Checkpoint</title>
            <body>
                <p>This checkpoint will test your understanding of the material you have learned in this module.</p>
                <p>
                    
                        
                </p>
                <activity idref="_u3_m2_checkpoint2" purpose="checkpoint"/>
            </body>
        </section>
        <p>After you complete the checkpoint, if additional questions arise that you would like to discuss
            in class, please click on the <em>My Response</em> link below and submit the additional
            questions.</p>
        <activity idref="_u3_m02_wrapup1_feedback_post_quiz" purpose="myresponse"/>-->
        
    </body>
</workbook_page>
