<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u3_m02_causation1">
<head>
<title>Causation and Observational Studies (1 of 2)</title>


    <objref idref="explain_conclusions"/>



</head>
<body>
   
<section>
<title>Causation and Observational Studies</title>
<body>
<p>Suppose the <em>observational study</em> described
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T123244-0400"?>o<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T123244-0400" content="i"?>n
                    the previous page were carried out, and researchers determined that the
                    percentage succeeding with the combination drug/therapy method was highest,
                    while the percentage succeeding with
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140523-0400"?>neither
                    therapy nor
                    drugs<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140518-0400" content="the cold turkey method"?>
                    was lowest. In other words, suppose there is clear evidence of an association
                    between method used and success rate. Could they then conclude that the
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140604-0400"?>combination
                    <?oxy_insert_end?>drug/therapy method causes success more than
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140622-0400"?>using
                    neither therapy nor a
                    drug<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140648-0400" content="the cold turkey method"?>? </p>
<!--:WARNING: Removed paragraph enclosing image element.--><image style="block" src="../webcontent/image004.gif"
alt="A visual representation of the relationship between the Exploratory Variable and Response Variable.
The Exploratory Variable is the Method being used, and it might or might not be related to the Response
Variable, which is either Success or Failure."/>
<p>It is at precisely this point that we confront the underlying weakness of most observational
                    studies: some members of the sample have opted for certain values of the
                    explanatory variable (method of quitting), while others have opted for other
                    values. It could be that those individuals may be different in additional ways
                    that would also play a role in the response of interest. For instance, suppose
                    women are more likely to choose certain methods to quit, and suppose women in
                    general tend to quit more successfully than men. The data would make it appear
                    that the method itself were responsible for success, whereas in truth it may
                    just be that being female is the reason for success. We can express this
                    scenario in terms of the key variables involved. In addition to the explanatory
                    variable (method) and the response variable (success or failure), a third,
                        <em>lurking</em> variable (gender) is tied in (or <em>confounded</em>) with
                    the explanatory variable's values, and may itself cause the response to be
                    success or failure. The following diagram illustrates this
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141323-0400" comment="Suggest writing &quot;cause&quot; next to each question mark in graphic"?>situation.<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
<!--:WARNING: Removed paragraph enclosing image element.--><image style="block" src="../webcontent/image005.gif"
    alt="Here, the Exploratory Variable, which is the Method, may affect the Response Variable, which is
Success or Failure. We also have a Lurking Variable, which is Gender. It is confounded with the
Exploratory Variable, so it may also be affecting the Response Variable."/>
<p>Since the difficulty arises because of the lurking variable's values being tied in with those of the explanatory variable, one way to attempt to unravel the true nature of the relationship between explanatory and response variables is to separate out the effects of the lurking variable. In general, we <em>control</em> for the effects of a lurking variable by separately studying groups that are similar with respect to this variable. </p>
<p>We could control for the lurking variable
                    "<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140915-0400"?>g<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T140915-0400" content="G"?>ender"
                    by studying women and men separately. Then, if both women and men who chose one
                    method have higher success rates than those opting for another method, we would
                    be closer to producing evidence of causation.</p>
<!--:WARNING: Removed paragraph enclosing image element.--><image style="block" src="../webcontent/image006.gif"
    alt="Now, we have two separate studies. The study for Women is represented using one circle representing
the Method, connected to another circle with an arrow. The other circle represents Success or Failure.
We have the same diagram for Men, showing that Women and Men are now separated into totally different
studies."/>
<p>The diagram above demonstrates how straightforward it is to control for the lurking variable gender. </p>
<p>Notice that we did not claim that controlling for gender would allow us to make a definite claim
                    of causation, only that we would be closer to establishing a causal connection.
                    This is due to the fact that other lurking variables may also be involved, such
                    as the level of the participants' desire to quit. Specifically, those who have
                    chosen to use the drug/therapy method may already be the ones who are most
                    determined to succeed, while those who have chosen to quit
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141022-0400" content="cold turkey, "?>without
                    <?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141100-0400" content="taking the incentive to "?>invest<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141111-0400"?>ing<?oxy_insert_end?>
                    in drugs or
                    therapy<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141116-0400" content=","?>
                    may, from the outset, be less committed to quitting. The following
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141400-0400" comment="Suggest writing &quot;cause&quot; next to each question mark in graphic."?>diagram<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    illustrates this scenario.</p>
<!--:WARNING: Removed paragraph enclosing image element.--><image style="block" src="../webcontent/image007.gif"
alt="The Exploratory Variable, which is the Method, may affect the Response Variable, which is
Success or Failure. We also have a Lurking Variable, which is Desire to Quit. It is confounded
with the Exploratory Variable because those with more desire to quit may use drugs and/or therapy.
So, the Lurking Variable may also be affecting the Response Variable."/>
<p>To attempt to control for this lurking variable, we could interview the individuals at the outset in order to rate their desire to quit on a scale of 1 (weakest) to 5 (strongest), and study the relationship between method and success separately for each of the five groups. But desire to quit is obviously a very subjective thing, difficult to assign a specific number to. Realistically, we may be unable to effectively control for the lurking variable "desire to quit."</p>
<p>Furthermore, who's to say that gender and/or desire to quit are the only lurking variables
                    involved? There may be other subtle differences among individuals who choose one
                    of the four various methods that researchers fail to imagine as they attempt to
                    control for possible lurking variables. For example, smokers who opt
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141451-0400"?>to quit
                    using neither therapy nor
                    drugs<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141506-0400" content="for the cold turkey method"?>
                    may tend to be in a lower income bracket than those who opt for (and can afford)
                    drugs and/or therapy. Perhaps smokers in a lower income bracket also tend to be
                    less successful in quitting because more of their family members and co-workers
                    smoke. Thus,
                    socio<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T141527-0400" content="-"?>economic
                    status is yet another possible lurking variable in the relationship between
                    cessation method and success rate.</p>
<p>It is because of the existence of a virtually unlimited number of potential lurking variables that we can never be 100% certain of a claim of causation based on an observational study. On the other hand, observational studies are an extremely common tool used by researchers to attempt to draw conclusions about causal connections. If great care is taken to control for the most likely lurking variables (and to avoid other pitfalls which we will discuss presently), and if common sense indicates that there is good reason for one variable to cause changes in the other, then researchers may assert that an observational study provides good evidence of causation.</p>
</body>
</section>
</body>
</workbook_page>
