<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u3_m02_causation_and_experiments1">
<head>
<title>Causation and Experiments (1 of 3)</title>

    <objref idref="explain_conclusions"/>




</head>
<body>
    
<section>
<title>Causation and Experiments</title>
<body>
<p>Recall that in an experiment, it is the researchers who assign values of the explanatory variable
                    to the participants. The key to ensuring that individuals differ only with
                    respect to explanatory
                    values<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144348-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144344-0400" content="---"?>which
                    is also the key to establishing
                    causation<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144406-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144401-0400" content="---"?>lies
                    in the way this assignment is carried out.
                    <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144431-0400"?>Let's<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144430-0400" content="We"?>
                    return to the smoking cessation study as a context to explore the essential
                    ingredients of experimental design.</p>
</body>
</section>
<example>

<p>In our discussion of the distinction between observational studies and experiments, we described
                the following experiment: collect a representative sample of
                1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144449-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>000
                individuals from the population of smokers who are just now trying to quit. We
                divide the sample into 4 groups of 250 and instruct each group to use a different
                method to quit. One year later, we contact the same
                1<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144459-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>000
                individuals and determine whose attempts succeeded while using our designated
                method. </p>
<p>This was an
                experiment<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144512-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                because the researchers themselves determined the values of the explanatory variable
                of interest for the individuals studied, rather than letting them choose. </p>
</example>
<p>We will begin by using the context of this smoking cessation example to illustrate the
            specialized vocabulary of experiments. First of all, the explanatory variable, or <em>
                factor</em>, in this case is the method used to quit. The different imposed values
            of the explanatory variable, or <em>treatments</em> (common abbreviation: ttt), consist
            of the four possible quitting methods. The groups receiving different treatments are
            called <em>treatment groups</em>. The group that tries to quit
            <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144611-0400"?>without drugs or
            therapy
            <?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144606-0400" content="cold turkey "?>could
            be called the <em>control</em>
            <em>group</em><?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144634-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144629-0400" content="---"?>those
            individuals on whom no specific treatment was imposed. Ideally, the <em>subjects</em>
            (human participants in an experiment) in each treatment group differ from those in the
            other treatment groups only with respect to the treatment (quitting method). As
            mentioned in our discussion of why lurking variables prevent us from establishing
            causation in observational studies, eliminating all other differences among treatment
            groups will be the key to asserting causation via an experiment. How can this be
            accomplished?</p>
<section>
<title>Randomized Controlled Experiments</title>
<body>
<p>Your intuition may already tell you, correctly, that
                        <em>r</em><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T171408-0400" content=" "?><em>andom
                        assignment to treatments</em> is the best way to prevent treatment groups of
                    individuals from differing from each other in ways other than the treatment
                    assigned. Either computer software or tables can be utilized to accomplish the
                    random assignment. The resulting design is called a <em>randomized controlled
                        experiment,</em> because researchers control values of the explanatory
                    variable with a randomization procedure. Under random assignment, the groups
                    should not differ significantly with respect to any potential lurking variable.
                    Then, if we see a relationship between the explanatory and response variables,
                    we have evidence that it is a causal one.</p>
<!--:WARNING: Removed paragraph enclosing image element.--><image style="block" src="../webcontent/image008.gif"
alt="A visual representation of the experimental study. A large circle represents the entire
population. Through random selection we generate the sample, which is represented as a smaller
circle. The circle representing the samples is divided up evenly into 4 pieces, each piece
representing one value of the explanatory variable (method). The pieces are treatment groups
randomly assigned by researchers."/>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Comment</title>
<body>
<p>Note that in a randomized controlled experiment, a randomization procedure may be used in two
                    phases. First, a sample of subjects is collected. Ideally it would be a
                        <em>random sample</em> so that it would be perfectly representative of the
                    entire population. (<em>Comment:</em> often researchers have no choice but to
                    recruit volunteers. Using volunteers may help to offset one of the drawbacks to
                    experimentation which will be discussed later, namely the problem of
                    non<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144931-0400" content="-"?>compliance.)
                    Second, we <em>assign individuals randomly</em> to the treatment groups to
                    ensure that the only difference between them will be due to the treatment and we
                    can get evidence of causation. At this stage, randomization is vital. </p>
<p>Let's discuss some other issues related to
                    experiment<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T144955-0400"?>ation<?oxy_insert_end?>.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Inclusion of a Control Group</title>
<body>
<p>A common misconception is that an experiment must include a control group of individuals
                    receiving no
                    treatment<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T145018-0400" content=" per se"?>.
                    There may be situations where a complete lack of treatment is not an option, or
                    where including a control group is ethically questionable, or where researchers
                    explore the effects of a treatment without making a comparison. Here are a few
                    examples:</p>
<example>

<p>If doctors want to conduct an experiment to determine whether Prograf or Cyclosporin is more effective as an immunosuppressant, they could randomly assign transplant patients to take one or the other of the drugs. It would, of course, be unethical to include a control group of patients not receiving any immunosuppressants. </p>
</example>
<example>

<p>Recently, experiments have been conducted
                        <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T145255-0400"?>in
                        which<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T145253-0400" content="where"?>
                        the treatment is a highly invasive brain surgery. The only way to have a
                        legitimate control group in this case is to randomly assign half of the
                        subjects to undergo the entire surgery except for the actual treatment
                        component (inserting stem cells into the brain). This, of course, is also
                        ethically problematic (but, believe it or not,
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T145900-0400" comment="Is this stil being done, or should this be changed to past tense.

I think a source should be included for the information, and possibly a discussion of the controversy that ensued. If you don&apos;t want to go into that kind of detail, I&apos;d remove the &quot;believe it or not it&apos;s being done&quot; assertion."?>is
                        being<?oxy_comment_end?> done<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T145514-0400" content="!!!"?>)<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T145518-0400"?>.<?oxy_insert_end?>
                        <!--Read the article here, and decide whether you personally feel such an experiment is ethical.</p>
				<p>[hyperlink to Real Knife, Fake Surgery]--></p>
</example>
<example>

<p>There may even be an experiment designed with only a single treatment. For example, makers of a new hair product may ask a sample of individuals to treat their hair with that product over a period of several weeks, then assess how manageable their hair has become. Such a design is clearly flawed because of the absence of a comparison group, but it is still an experiment because use of the product has been imposed by its manufacturers, rather than chosen naturally by the individuals. A flawed experiment is nevertheless an experiment. </p>
</example>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Comment: </title>
<body>
<p>The word <em>control</em> is used in at least three different senses. In the context of
                    observational studies, we <em>control for a confounding variable</em> by
                    separating it out. Referring to an experiment as a <em>controlled experiment
                    </em>stresses that the values of the experiment's explanatory variables
                    (factors) have been assigned by researchers, as opposed to having occurred
                    naturally. In the context of experiments, the <em>control group</em> consists of
                    subjects who do not receive a
                    treatment<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T150116-0400" content=" per se"?>,
                    but who are otherwise handled identically to those who do receive the
                    treatment.</p>
<activity idref="_u3_m2_lbd1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
</body>
</section>
</body>
</workbook_page>
