<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u3_m02_causation2">
<head>
<title>Causation and Observational Studies (2 of 2)</title>


    <objref idref="explain_conclusions"/>



</head>
<body>
   
<p>Observational studies are subject to other pitfalls besides lurking variables, arising from
            various aspects of the design for evaluating the explanatory and response values. The
            next pair of examples
            illustrate<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T142942-0400"?>s<?oxy_insert_end?>
            some other difficulties that may arise.</p>
<example>

<p>Suppose researchers want to determine if people tend to snack more while they watch TV. One
                possible design that we considered was to recruit participants for an observational
                study, and give them journals to record their hourly activities the following day,
                including TV watched and
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143236-0400"?>snacks<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143234-0400" content="food"?>
                consumed. Then they could review the journals to determine if
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143252-0400"?>snack<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143251-0400" content="food"?>
                consumption was higher during TV times.</p>
<p>We identified this as a prospective observational study, carried forward in time. Studying people
                in the more natural setting of their own homes makes
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143323-0400"?>the
                study<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143322-0400" content="it"?>
                more realistic than a contrived experimental setting. Still, when people are obliged
                to record their behavior as it occurs, they may be too self-conscious to act
                naturally. They may want to avoid embarrassment and so
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143354-0400"?>they may
                <?oxy_insert_end?>cut back on their TV viewing, or their snack consumption, or the
                combination of the two.</p>
</example>
<example>

<p>Yet another possible design is to recruit participants for a retrospective observational study.
                Ask them to recall, for each hour of the previous day, whether they were watching
                TV, and what
                <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143442-0400"?>snacks<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143440-0400" content="food"?>
                they consumed each hour. Determine if food consumption was higher during the TV
                times. </p>
<p>This design has the advantage of not disturbing people's natural behavior in terms of TV viewing
                or snacking. It has the disadvantage of relying on people's memories to record those
                variables' values from the day before. But one day is a relatively short period of
                time<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143533-0400"?> to
                remember such details<?oxy_insert_end?>, and as long as people are willing to be
                honest, the results of this study could be fairly reliable. The issue of eliciting
                honest responses will be addressed in our discussion of sample surveys.</p>
</example>
<p>By now you should have an idea of how
            difficult<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143702-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143659-0400" content="---"?>or
            perhaps <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143706-0400"?>even
            <?oxy_insert_end?>impossible<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143713-0400"?>&#8212;<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143710-0400" content="---"?>it
            is to establish causation in an observational study, especially due to the problem of
            lurking variables. The key to establishing causation is to rule out the possibility of
            any lurking variable, or in other words<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143847-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
            <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143855-0400"?>to
            <?oxy_insert_end?>ensure that individuals differ <em>only with respect to
                the<?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101103T143912-0400" content="ir"?>
                values of the explanatory variable</em>. In general, this is a goal which we have a
            much better chance of accomplishing by carrying out a well-designed experiment. </p>
</body>
</workbook_page>
