<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="_u3_m02_identifying_study_design1">
<head>
<title>Identifying Study Design (1 of 2 )</title>
    <objref idref="identify_study_design"/>
</head>
<body>
   
<p>
<em/>
</p>
<section>
<title>Identifying Study Design</title>
<body>
<p>Because each type of study design has its own advantages and trouble spots, it is important to
                                                  begin by determining what type of study we are
                                                  dealing with. The following example helps to
                                                  illustrate how we can distinguish among the three
                                                  basic types of design mentioned in the
                                                  introduction&#8212;observational studies, sample
                                                  surveys, and experiments.</p>
</body>
</section>
<example>

<p>Suppose researchers want to determine whether people tend to snack more while they watch
                                                  television. In other words, the researchers would
                                                  like to explore the relationship between the
                                                  explanatory variable "TV" (a categorical variable
                                                  that takes the values "on'" and "not on") and the
                                                  response variable "snack consumption."</p>
<p>Identify each of the following designs as being an observational study, a sample survey, or an experiment.</p>
<p>
                                                  <em>1.</em> Recruit participants for a study.
                                                  While they are presumably waiting to be
                                                  interviewed, half of the individuals sit in a
                                                  waiting room with snacks available and a TV on.
                                                  The other half sit in a waiting room with snacks
                                                  available and no TV, just magazines. Researchers
                                                  determine whether people consume more snacks in
                                                  the TV setting. </p>
<p>This is an<em> experiment</em>, because the researchers take control of the explanatory variable
                                                  of interest (TV on or not) by <em>assigning
                                                  </em>each individual to either watch TV or not,
                                                  and determine the effect that has on the response
                                                  variable of interest (snack consumption).</p>
<p>
                                                  <em>2.</em> Recruit participants for a study. Give
                                                  them journals to record hour by hour their
                                                  activities the following day, including when they
                                                  watch TV and when they consume snacks. Determine
                                                  if snack consumption is higher during TV times. </p>
<p>This is an observational study, because the participants themselves determine whether or not to
                                                  watch TV. There is no attempt on the researchers'
                                                  part to interfere.</p>
<p>
                                                  <em>3.</em> Recruit participants for a study. Ask
                                                  them to recall, for each hour of the previous day,
                                                  whether they were watching TV, and what snacks
                                                  they consumed each hour. Determine whether snack
                                                  consumption was higher during the TV times.</p>
<p>This is also an observational study; again, it was the participants themselves who decided
                                                  whether or not to watch TV. Do you see the
                                                  difference between 2 and 3? See the comment
                                                  below.</p>
<p>
                                                  <em>4.</em> Poll a sample of individuals with the
                                                  following question: While watching TV, do you tend
                                                  to snack: (a) less than usual; (b) more than usual; or (c) the same amount as usual?</p>
<p>This is a sample survey, because the individuals self-assess the relationship between TV watching and snacking.</p>
</example>
<section>
<title>Comment</title>
<body>
<p>Notice that in Example 2, the values of the variables of interest (TV watching and snack
                                                  consumption) are recorded forward in time. Such
                                                  observational studies are called
                                                  <em>prospective</em>. In contrast, in Example 3,
                                                  the values of the variables of interest are
                                                  recorded backward in time. This is called a
                                                  <em>retrospective</em> observational study. We'll
                                                  discuss this distinction later in this module.</p>
</body>
</section>
<!--<activity idref="_u3_m2_dig1" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
    <wb:inline idref="u2_m2_studydesign1_tutor1" purpose="didigetthis"/>
<p>While some studies are designed to gather information about a single variable, many studies
                                                attempt to draw conclusions about the relationship
                                                between two variables. In particular, researchers
                                                often would like to produce evidence that one
                                                variable actually causes changes in the other. For
                                                example, the research question addressed in the
                                                previous example sought to establish evidence that
                                                watching TV could cause an increase in snacking.
                                                Such studies may be especially useful and
                                                interesting, but they are also especially vulnerable
                                                to flaws that could invalidate the conclusion of
                                                causation. In several of the examples in this module
                                                we will see that although evidence of an association
                                                between two variables may be quite clear, the
                                                question of whether one variable is actually causing
                                                changes in the other may be too murky to be entirely
                                                resolved. In general, with a well-designed
                                                experiment we have a better chance of establishing
                                                causation than with an observational study. However,
                                                experiments are also subject to certain pitfalls,
                                                and there are many situations in which an experiment
                                                is not an option. A well-designed observational
                                                study may still provide fairly convincing evidence
                                                of causation under the right circumstances.</p>
</body>
</workbook_page>
