<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="id_lurking_var_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_id_lurking_var" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>In the coastal United States, there is an established correlation between ice cream
                sales and shark attacks. Which of the following might we conclude from this
                data?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Eating ice cream may increase the likelihood of a shark attack. </choice>
            <choice value="B">Increases in shark attacks may increase ice cream sales. </choice>
            <choice value="C">This is an anomaly and there is no relationship between shark attacks
                and ice cream sales. </choice>
            <choice value="D">There may be a third variable that creates a link between ice cream
                sales and shark attacks.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it may be possible that there is a mechanism by which
                    sharks might be attracted to ice cream, it is not the likely choice. Since shark
                    attacks tend to happen when people swim, which is in warm weather, and ice cream
                    sales also tend to increase during warm weather, there is a likely lurking
                    variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It seems unlikely that people eat more ice cream due to
                    increased reports of shark attacks. Since shark attacks tend to happen when
                    people swim, which is in warm weather, and ice cream sales also tend to increase
                    during warm weather, there is a likely lurking variable here that confounds the
                    results. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While this data may be an anomaly, there is a more likely
                    explanation. Since shark attacks tend to happen when people swim, which is in
                    warm weather, and ice cream sales also tend to increase during warm weather,
                    there is a likely lurking variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since shark attacks tend to happen when people swim, which is in
                    warm weather, and ice cream sales also tend to increase during warm weather,
                    there is a likely lurking variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_id_lurking_var" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>Suppose a study finds a positive correlation between the number of TV sets in the
                home of high school seniors and their admission rate into college. Which of the
                following might we conclude from this data?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">The increase in home TV sets improves the likelihood of college
                admission.</choice>
            <choice value="B">Better students tend to have a TV set available. </choice>
            <choice value="C">There may be a third variable that creates a link between the number
                of TVs in the home and college admission rate. </choice>
            <choice value="D">This is an anomaly and there is no relationship between TVs in the
                home and college admission rate.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it may be possible that there is a mechanism by which
                    more TVs in the home may increase chances of college admission, it is not the
                    likely choice. Since the number of TVs in the home tend to be correlated with
                    the income and education of the parents and students from wealthier homes with
                    more educated parents tend to have a better admission rate into college there is
                    a likely lurking variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It seems unlikely that better students tend to be the ones
                    watching the most TV. Since the number of TVs in the home tend to be correlated
                    with the income and education of the parents and students from wealthier homes
                    with more educated parents tend to have a better admission rate into college
                    there is a likely lurking variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Since the number of TVs in the home tend to be correlated with
                    the income and education of the parents and students from wealthier homes with
                    more educated parents tend to have a better admission rate into college there is
                    a likely lurking variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While this data may be an anomaly, there is a more likely
                    explanation. Since the number of TVs in the home tend to be correlated with the
                    income and education of the parents and students from wealthier homes with more
                    educated parents tend to have a better admission rate into college there is a
                    likely lurking variable here that confounds the results. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
