<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="id_study_design_2_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_id_study_design_2" select="single">
        <body>
            <p><em style="bold">Research Question: </em>What is the combined effect of medication
                and diet on blood pressure in adult males?</p>
            <p>A randomized, controlled experiment investigated this question using a random sample
                of 540 adult males as subjects. At the beginning of the study, researchers measured
                the blood pressure of all the subjects. Each subject was given a month's supply of
                either Drug A, Drug B, or a placebo, then was assigned to be on either a low-fat
                diet or a low-salt diet for that month-long period. At the end of the month, the
                researchers measured the blood pressure of each subject again, and compared the two
                blood pressure readings. </p>
            <p>How many different groups are there altogether in this study? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">2 </choice>
            <choice value="B">3 </choice>
            <choice value="C">4 </choice>
            <choice value="D">5 </choice>
            <choice value="E">6 </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you identified the number of diet groups. Notice
                    that there were three different drug treatment groups (A, B, or placebo), and in
                    each of these groups, there had to be <em>two</em> different diet groups (low
                    fat or low salt).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Although there were three different drug treatment groups (A,
                    B, or placebo), notice that for each of these groups, there had to be two diet
                    groups (low fat or low salt).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Notice that there were three different drug treatment groups
                    (A, B, or placebo), and in each of these groups, there had to be two different
                    diet groups (low fat or low salt).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you summed the number of drug groups with the number
                    of diet groups. Notice that there were three different drug treatment groups (A,
                    B, or placebo), and in each of these groups, there had to be two different diet
                    groups (low fat or low salt).</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. There were three different drug treatment groups (A, B, or
                    placebo), and in each of these groups, there had to be two different diet groups
                    (low fat or low salt), for a total of 3 * 2 = 6 different combinations of drug
                    and diet in the study. So there were 6 different treatment groups that a subject
                    could get assigned to. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_id_study_design_2" select="single">
        <body>
            <p><em style="bold">Research Question: </em>What is the combined effect of fertilizer
                and watering on cherry tomato plants? </p>
            <p>Planters were built that each contained 10 cherry tomato plants. Each planter was
                identical except that it received a different treatment of water and fertilizer than
                the other planters. Treatments consisted of a combination of one of four watering
                schedules and one of three fertilizer concentrations. The plants were tended
                according to these treatments, and after 65 days, the average number and weight of the
                tomatoes per plant were measured for each treatment group. </p>
            <p>How many different groups are there altogether in this study? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">3 </choice>
            <choice value="B">4 </choice>
            <choice value="C">7 </choice>
            <choice value="D">12 </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you identified the number of fertilizer groups.
                    Notice that there were three different fertilizer treatment groups, and in each
                    of these groups, there had to be four different watering schedules.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you identified the number of watering treatment
                    groups. Notice that there were four different watering treatment groups, and in
                    each of these groups, there had to be three different fertilizer schedules.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. It appears you summed the number of fertilizer groups with the
                    number of watering groups. Notice that there were three different fertilizer
                    treatment groups, and in each of these groups, there had to be four different
                    watering schedules.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. There were three different fertilizer treatment groups, and in
                    each of these groups, there had to be four different watering schedules, for a
                    total of 3 * 4 = 12 different combinations of fertilizer and watering schedule
                    in the study. So there were 12 different treatment groups.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
