<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="id_study_design_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_id_study_design" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following is an extremely important design element to have in an
                experimental study? Check all that apply. </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">Treatments that are imposed by the experimenter</choice>
            <choice value="B">A placebo</choice>
            <choice value="C">Groups which are exactly the same size</choice>
            <choice value="D">Randomized selection of participants</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that assignment of treatment by experimenters
                    is a key aspect of experimental studies there is at least one other important
                    design element that you are missing. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While placebos may be useful (or even essential) in some
                    studies they may be unethical in others. Also, there is at least one correct
                    design element. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is nice to have groups of approximately the same size,
                    it is not important that the sizes be identical or even necessarily that close.
                    Also, there is at least one correct design element. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While random selection of participants is a very important
                    aspect of experimental design there is at least one other important design
                    element that you are missing. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that assignment of treatment by experimenters
                    is a key aspect of experimental studies, placebos are not required (and may be
                    unethical in some studies) and there is at least one other important design
                    element that you are missing. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that assignment of treatment by experimenters
                    is a key aspect of experimental studies, it is not essential that groups be of
                    identical size. Also, there is at least one other important design element that
                    you are missing. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Randomly assigning subjects to treatments administered by
                    researchers are two very important aspects to good experimental design.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Placebos are not required (and may even be unethical in some
                    studies) and it is not essential that groups be of identical size. Also, there
                    is at least one correct design element. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While random selection of participants is a very important
                    aspect of experimental design, placebos are not required (and may even be
                    unethical in some studies) and there is at least one other important design
                    element that you are missing. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While random selection of participants is a very important
                    aspect of experimental design, it is not essential that groups be of identical
                    size and there is at least one other important design element that you are
                    missing. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that assignment of treatment by experimenters
                    is a key aspect of experimental studies, placebos are not required (and may even
                    be unethical in some studies) and it is not essential that groups be of
                    identical size. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that assignment of treatment by experimenters
                    is a key aspect of experimental studies and random selection of participants is
                    a very important aspect of experimental design, placebos are not required (and
                    may even be unethical in some studies). </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that assignment of treatment by experimenters
                    is a key aspect of experimental studies and random selection of participants is
                    a very important aspect of experimental design, it is not essential that groups
                    be of identical size. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While random selection of participants is a very important
                    aspect of experimental design, placebos are not required (and may even be
                    unethical in some studies) and it is not essential that groups be of identical
                    size. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Placebos are not required (and may even be unethical in some
                    studies) and it is not essential that groups be of identical size. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There are important aspects of experimental design you are
                    missing. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_id_study_design" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>In a large lecture hall, students were handed a drawing of a woman. Students didn’t
                know that those on the left side of the center aisle received a drawing of a young
                woman while those on the right side of the aisle were given a drawing of an old
                woman. A slide was then projected with an drawing that was an ambiguous combination
                of the two handouts and students were asked a series of questions. </p>
            <p>This is an example of which of the following? </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">A blind observational study </choice>
            <choice value="B">An observational study that isn’t blind </choice>
            <choice value="C">A blind experiment </choice>
            <choice value="D">An experiment that isn’t blind </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is a case in which a treatment was administered therefore
                    it is not an observational study. As the students did not know the nature of the
                    treatment it was blind. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. This is a case in which a treatment was administered therefore
                    it is not an observational study. Additionally, as the students did not know the
                    nature of the treatment it was blind. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The drawing of the woman was the treatment and the students were
                    blind to the fact that they were getting different information. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While this is an experiment, it is one in which the students do
                    not know what treatment they are getting—or perhaps that they are receiving a
                    treatment at all—so it is blind. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q3_id_study_design" select="multiple">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>In a study to determine the relationship between self esteem and eating, subjects had
                been randomly divided into two groups. One group of subjects were individually told
                something intended to boost their self esteem while in the other group subjects were
                individually told something intended to lower their self esteem. Each subject was
                then individually led into a room alone and asked to count the number of chocolate
                chip cookies in a very large container and told they could eat as many as they liked
                while conducting their count. Researchers then counted the number of cookies eaten
                by subjects in each group. </p>
            <p> Which of the following statements is true regarding this study? Check all that
                apply. </p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">This study is an observational study. </choice>
            <choice value="B">This study is blind. </choice>
            <choice value="C">This study is an experimental study. </choice>
            <choice value="D">The treatment was the number of cookies eaten.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Subjects were administered a treatment so it is not an
                    observational study. Additionally, there is at least one true statement.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that the study is blind, there is at
                    least one other true statement. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that a treatment was administered so it
                    is an experimental study, there is at least one other true statement.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The treatment was the manipulation of subjects self-esteem, not
                    the number of cookies eaten. Additionally, there is at least one true statement.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect.While you are correct that the study is blind, subjects were
                    administered a treatment so it is not an observational study. Additionally,
                    there is at least one other true statement. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that a treatment was administered so it
                    is an experimental study, there is at least one other true statement.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Subjects were administered a treatment so it is not an
                    observational study and the treatment was the manipulation of subjects
                    self-esteem, not the number of cookies eaten. Additionally, there is at least
                    one true statement. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The study involves an administered treatment (therefore it is an
                    experiment) and subjects did not know the nature of the treatment so it is
                    blind. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that the study is blind, the treatment
                    was the manipulation of subjects self-esteem, not the number of cookies eaten.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C,D" score="5">
                <feedback> Incorrect. While you are correct that a treatment so it is an
                    experimental study, the treatment was the manipulation of subjects self-esteem,
                    not the number of cookies eaten. Additionally, there is at least one other true
                    statement. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study involves an administered
                    treatment (therefore it is an experiment) and subjects did not know the nature
                    of the treatment so it is blind. However, it is not an observational study as a
                    study cannot be both an experiment and observational. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that the study is blind, subjects were
                    administered a treatment so it is not an observational study and the treatment
                    was the manipulation of subjects self-esteem, not the number of cookies eaten.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C,D" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that this is an experimental study since
                    subjects were administered a treatment so it can’t also be an observational
                    study and the treatment was the manipulation of subjects self-esteem, not the
                    number of cookies eaten. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C,D" score="8">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study involves an administered
                    treatment (therefore it is an experiment) and subjects did not know the nature
                    of the treatment so it is blind. However, the treatment was the manipulation of
                    subjects self-esteem, not the number of cookies eaten. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C,D" score="5">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study involves an administered
                    treatment (therefore it is an experiment) and subjects did not know the nature
                    of the treatment so it is blind. However, since it is an experiment is cannot
                    also be an observational study and the treatment was the manipulation of
                    subjects self-esteem, not the number of cookies eaten. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. At least one of the options is correct. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q4_id_study_design" select="single">
        <body>In an experiment to see if aspirin reduces the chance of having a heart attack, which of
            the following would be a placebo?</body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">The place where the subjects go when they have a heart
                attack</choice>
            <choice value="B">A dummy pill that looks like aspirin but has no active
                ingredients</choice>
            <choice value="C">A procedure for deciding who gets the aspirin treatment</choice>
            <choice value="D">The sampling method</choice>
            <choice value="E">The randomization procedure</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The word <em style="italic">placebo</em> doesn’t refer to a place.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. A placebo is a nonactive treatment used in a study for proper
                    comparison. In this case, it ensures that any comparative effect in the aspirin
                    group is really due to the active ingredient rather than just due to the
                    "placebo effect." </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">placebo</em> isn’t a procedure, and it doesn’t determine who
                    gets the treatment.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">placebo</em> isn’t a sampling method.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A <em style="italic">placebo</em> isn’t a procedure, and it doesn’t cause
                    randomization.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q5_id_study_design" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Students
                in a large statistics class were randomly divided into two groups. The first group
                took the midterm exam with soft music playing in the background, and the second
                group took the exam with no music playing. After the exam was completed, a
                researcher compared deidentified exam scores of the two groups.</p>
            <p>Which of the following is the reason this experiment was <em style="bold">not</em>
                blind?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">The sample sizes in both groups was large.</choice>
            <choice value="B">Researchers looked at exam scores for the two groups.</choice>
            <choice value="C">The students knew whether or not music was playing while they were
                taking the exam. </choice>
            <choice value="D">Some of the students may not have studied for the exam.</choice>
            <choice value="E">Students were randomized into the two groups.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Blinding in study design has nothing to do with the size of
                    the samples.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Since the researcher looked at scores without student names and
                    conditions after the exam was complete, she was “blind” to which students were in
                    each of the two conditions.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Blinding in study design is when the subjects don’t know which
                    treatment they’re getting. In this case, the treatments are background music or
                    no background music. The students would certainly be aware of whether music was
                    playing during the exam, so they would know which treatment they got.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Blinding in study design does not refer to whether the
                    students know the answers on the exam. It refers to whether the subjects are
                    aware of something else pertaining to the study.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="E" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Having two randomized groups isn’t what determines whether or
                    not a study is blind.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q6_id_study_design" select="multiple">
        <body>
            <p>To test an herbal treatment for depression, 100 volunteers who suffered from mild
                depression were randomly divided into two groups. Each person was given a month's
                supply of tea bags. For one group, the tea contained the herb mixed with spice tea,
                whereas for the other group, the bags contained only the spice tea. Participants
                were not told which type of tea they had, and were asked to drink one cup of tea per
                day for a month. At the end of the month, a psychologist evaluated them to determine
                if their mood had improved. The psychologist did not know which of the subjects had
                the tea with the herbal ingredient added. </p>
            <p>Which of the following statements is true regarding this study? Check all that
                apply.</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="false">
            <choice value="A">This study is an observational study. </choice>
            <choice value="B">This study is double-blind. </choice>
            <choice value="C">The "only spice tea" group serves as the control group.
            </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. A study is observational when the researcher doesn’t play any
                    role in determining what treatment each subject might get. But in the study
                    described, the researchers assigned each subject which tea to use, so the study
                    wasn’t observational. Also, there is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study is double-blind, because the
                    subjects didn’t know which tea they got (which protects against the placebo
                    effect), and the psychologist also didn’t know (which helps guard against
                    researcher bias). However, there is at least one other true
                    statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the "only spice tea" group serves as the
                    control group, because they didn’t get any active herbal ingredient. However,
                    there is at least one other true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study is double-blind, because the
                    subjects didn’t know which tea they got (which protects against the placebo
                    effect), and the psychologist also didn’t know (which helps guard against
                    researcher bias). However, a study is observational when the researcher doesn’t
                    play any role in determining what treatment each subject might get. But in the
                    study described, the researchers assigned each subject which tea to use, so the
                    study wasn’t observational.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,C" score="3">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the "only spice tea" group serves as the
                    control group, because they didn’t get any active herbal ingredient. However, a
                    study is observational when the researcher doesn’t play any role in determining
                    what treatment each subject might get. But in the study described, the
                    researchers assigned each subject which tea to use, so the study wasn’t
                    observational.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B,C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. The study is double-blind, because the subjects didn’t know which
                    tea they got (which protects against the placebo effect), and the psychologist
                    also didn’t know (which helps guard against researcher bias). Also, the "only
                    spice tea" group serves as the control group, because they didn’t get any active
                    herbal ingredient. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="A,B,C" score="7">
                <feedback>Incorrect. You are correct that the study is double-blind, because the
                    subjects didn’t know which tea they got (which protects against the placebo
                    effect), and the psychologist also didn’t know (which helps guard against
                    researcher bias). Also, you are correct that the "only spice tea" group serves
                    as the control group, because they didn’t get any active herbal ingredient.
                    However, there is at least one other true statement. However, a study is
                    observational when the researcher doesn’t play any role in determining what
                    treatment each subject might get. But in the study described, the researchers
                    assigned each subject which tea to use, so the study wasn’t
                    observational.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="*" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There is at least one true statement.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
