<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="study_design_def_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_study_design_def" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>In a 2003 study by Bertrand and Mullainathan to measure racial discrimination in the
                labor market, experimenters sent fictitious resumes to help-wanted ads in Boston and
                Chicago newspapers. To manipulate perception of race each resume was assigned either
                a very African American–sounding name or a very White sounding name. They then
                measured the response to the resumes. Which of the following is a correct statement
                about this study? </p>
            <p>Bertrand, M., and Mullainathan, S. “Are Emily and Greg More Employable than Lakisha
                and Jamal?” Working Paper 9873, <em style="italic">National Bureau of Economic
                    Research</em>, 2003. http://www.nber.org/papers/w9873.pdf</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">It was a blind study because those who received the resumes did not
                know the treatment they received. </choice>
            <choice value="B">It was not a blind study because there was no placebo. </choice>
            <choice value="C">It was not a blind study because the experimenters knew where they
                were sending the resumes. </choice>
            <choice value="D">It was problematic because the subjects didn’t even know they were in
                an experiment.</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Blind studies are those in which the subjects (in this case, the
                    people who reviewed the resumes) do not know which treatment they receive.
                </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While you are correct that there is no placebo, for an
                    experiment or study to be considered blind, the subjects don’t know which
                    treatment they are receiving. A placebo is not required. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While the experimenters may or may not have known whom they
                    were studying, for an experiment or study to be considered blind the <em style="italic">subjects</em> don’t know which treatment they are receiving.
                    A <em style="italic">double-blind</em> experiment is one in which the subjects
                    don’t know which treatment they are receiving and neither do the people who are
                    administering the treatment. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. The fact that subjects did not know they were in an experiment
                    in fact may help add realism to the study. Blind studies are those in which the
                    subjects (in this case the people who reviewed the resumes) do not know which
                    treatment they receive. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_study_design_def" select="single">
        <!-- LO:  -->
        <body>
            <p>In a recent study to establish the effectiveness of a new cancer drug, subjects were
                randomly divided into three groups. Group A got a known and effective cancer drug,
                group B got the new experimental compound, and group C got a combination of the two
                drugs. None of the individuals nor the nurses knew group assignments, and nurses
                administering the drugs did not know what drug was being administered to their
                patients.</p><p> Which of the following is a correct statement about this study?</p>
        </body>
        <input shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">It was a blind study because subjects did not know the treatment they
                were receiving. </choice>
            <choice value="B">It was not a blind study because there was no placebo. </choice>
            <choice value="C">It was a double-blind study because neither the subject nor the
                experimenter knew what the treatment for a patient was. </choice>
            <choice value="D">It was not a blind study because patients knew they were participating
                in a study. </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. While it is true that subjects did not know which treatment
                    they were receiving, there is a better answer. Note that the experimenters did
                    not know what treatment was being administered either which makes this a
                    double-blind study. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. In fact knowingly treating a cancer patient with an ineffective
                    drug such as a placebo would be considered unethical. Placebos are not necessary
                    for blind or double-blind studies, only that the subject (and for double-blind
                    the experimenters) do not know which treatment is being received. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Neither the subjects nor the experimenters knew what treatment
                    was being administered. </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Whether or not the subjects know they are in an experiment does
                    not necessarily affect whether or not it is blind or double-blind experiment. In
                    this study neither the subjects nor the experimenters knew what treatment was
                    being administered. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
