<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pool PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment Pool MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><pool xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="survey_design_pool">
    <title>pool</title>
    <multiple_choice id="q1_survey_design" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>Which of the following best describes the method of randomized response?</p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">A sampling method</choice>
            <choice value="B">A method in which subjects answer the questions in a
                survey in a random order</choice>
            <choice value="C">A technique used to minimize the bias in the responses
                of subjects to sensitive questions</choice>
            <choice value="D">A method in which subjects answer each of the questions
                in a survey with a random guess</choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Randomized response isn’t a sampling method, because it doesn’t
                    involve how the subjects are chosen to be interviewed.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. In randomized response, the word <em style="italic">randomized</em> does not refer to the order of the survey
                    questions.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Randomized response is a technique designed to disguise
                    individual responses (thus putting the people more at ease about revealing
                    embarrassing information) while retaining the overall proportional results (thus
                    still making the study useful). </feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. There <em style="italic">is</em> something about the subject’s
                    answer that gets randomized in the andomized response technique, but it’s not
                    their answers to all the survey questions.</feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
    <multiple_choice id="q2_survey_design" select="single">
        <body>
            <p>When surveying subjects about sensitive or self-incriminating topics, what technique
                might be used to help ensure that individuals answer sensitive or self-incriminating
                questions honestly? </p>
        </body>
        <input labels="false" shuffle="true">
            <choice value="A">Using simple, direct questions</choice>
            <choice value="B">Asking questions in random order</choice>
            <choice value="C">Asking technically complex questions </choice>
            <choice value="D">Using randomized response </choice>
        </input>
        <part>
            <response match="A" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Simple, direct questions are a good way to make sure the
                    respondents are answering the question that you are asking, but it does not help
                    make them more likely to answer honestly if the topic is sensitive or even
                    self-incriminating.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="B" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Putting the questions in random order may help eliminate a bias
                    created when earlier questions inform later ones, but it does not help make respondents
                    more likely to answer honestly if the topic is sensitive or even
                    self-incriminating.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="C" score="0">
                <feedback>Incorrect. Technically complex questions often confuse respondents and
                    will not help make them more likely to answer honestly if the topic is sensitive
                    or self-incriminating.</feedback>
            </response>
            <response match="D" score="10">
                <feedback>Correct. Randomized responses allow respondents to be anonymous when
                    answering a question and make it more likely that they will answer a sensitive
                    or self-incriminating question. </feedback>
            </response>
        </part>
    </multiple_choice>
</pool>
