<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_27">
	<head>
		<title>Aging and the Circulatory System</title>
		<objref idref="describe_changes_circulatory_system_aging_OBJ"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Arterial walls change with age. Arteries that undergo significant changes include the
			large elastic vessels such as the aorta, the coronary arteries, and the carotid
			arteries. <term>Arteriosclerosis</term> refers to conditions that make arteries less
			elastic (commonly referred to as hardening of the arteries). This commonly occurs as we
			age because of calcium deposition in the walls of vessels (calcific arteriosclerosis),
			or degenerative loss of elastic fibers with age (senile arteriosclerosis).</p>
		<p><term>Atherosclerosis</term> is a specific type of arteriosclerosis that involves the
			formation of plaques on arterial walls that make them stiffer. Plaques are made of fatty material containing
			cholesterol. This fatty substance may eventually be replaced with connective tissue and
			deposits of calcium. Plaques can rupture, initiating a blood clot at the site. Both
			arteriosclerosis and atherosclerosis increase resistance to blood flow. Atherosclerosis
			in blood vessels that supply the brain can reduce blood flow to the brain, causing brain
			cells to malfunction or die if the reduction in flow is severe enough. Arteriosclerosis
			and atherosclerosis can also lead to poor wound healing. These conditions are usually
			firmly diagnosed with vascular imaging methods.</p>
		
		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_27.jpg" width="500" alt="">
			<title>Figure 24</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>
		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_28.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 25</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>
		
		<p>A main contributor to the development of atherosclerosis is high levels of low density
			lipoprotein (LDL or “bad” cholesterol) in the bloodstream. LDL typically rises with
			increased dietary saturated fat and decreased exercise. Because atherosclerosis is the
			main culprit of coronary artery disease, which is a leading cause of heart disease and
			death in the elderly, it is recommended that cholesterol levels be monitored with lipid
			profiles conducted every five years beginning at the age of 20.</p>
		<p>Another condition that is more common in older adults is congestive heart failure, which
			is caused by impaired pumping efficiency in the heart. Congestive heart failure can
			cause shortness of breath and leg swelling and is typically diagnosed by blood and
			imaging tests. Treatment focuses on preventing further progression and easing symptoms
			with methods such as oxygen delivery, medications, and palliative care.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_changes_circulatory_system_aging_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_changes_circulatory_system_aging_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
