<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_04"><head><title>Red Blood Cells</title><objref idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="f5545b4280b247cdae654e02cc5e5a8d"><term>Red blood cells (RBCs)</term>, also called <term>erythrocytes</term> (<em style="italic">erythro</em>- red and <em style="italic">cytes</em> –cells), are disc like cells that are the most abundant cell types in blood. Red blood cells transport the oxygen from our lungs to all of our body’s cells that carry out aerobic respiration. RBCs also pick up carbon dioxide (the gaseous waste product of cells) from metabolically active cells, bringing it back to the lungs. Red blood cells contain a special protein that contains iron, called <term>hemoglobin (Hbg)</term>, to which both oxygen and carbon dioxide are able to bind. Red blood cells do not have nuclei or many other organelles, which leaves more room in cytoplasm for hemoglobin needed for the cell&apos;s job to transport these molecules.</p><image id="bfa9f6cb4f1e42e5a4c8787849ba5e69" src="../webcontent/C_M1_05a.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="300" width="200"><title>Figure 5</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ffef41675faf4f448a58b21694d05548">Hemoglobin consists of four <term>heme</term> groups (non-protein) and four globin (protein) molecules. Each heme group is composed of an iron structure surrounded by carbon rings containing nitrogen. Heme, in combination with oxygen, is responsible for the red pigment of blood. Each hemoglobin molecule can transport up to four oxygen atoms, one bound to each heme group, when the hemoglobin is said to be fully saturated. In fetuses and infants, hemoglobin is mainly composed of two alpha and two gamma globin chains (there are very few beta chains). As an infant develops, the gamma chains are replaced by beta globin chains. In an adult, hemoglobin consists of two alpha and two beta globin chains. A single erythrocyte has about a quarter of a billion hemoglobin molecules, which demonstrates the amazing capacity of red blood cells to transport oxygen.</p><materials id="e55d9fd6945d4f9dacf3de7be5fefe0c"><material><image id="ff2505f47e46405aa3f5ba0e38ab63d8" src="../webcontent/C_M1_05b.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><title>Figure 6</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><image id="f7a8ed0b0453408da5fec1dd31b7b2c1" src="../webcontent/C_M1_05c.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><title>Figure 7</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material></materials><section id="d5598cd4aa6747ee8a4f179659e92d1a" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_identify_structure_function_hemoglobin_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_01" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><p id="ecf490d6fd8049a6997ea2970659f580">Blood passing through the lungs is exposed to high oxygen levels, and when red blood cells pick up this oxygen the hemoglobin is called <term>oxyhemoglobin (HbO</term><sub><term>2</term></sub><term>)</term>. As blood passes through other tissues, oxygen-carrying RBCs drop off a fraction of this oxygen (typically 25%). The hemoglobins that are no longer carrying oxygen are called <term>deoxyhemoglobin (Hb)</term>. </p><p id="dfc16278beab462dac879b5578b3fb4d">If hemoglobin has lost a fraction of its bound oxygen, then a small amount of carbon dioxide can bind to the protein sections of Hb (versus oxygen that binds to the heme), and can be transported from tissues to the lungs. This hemoglobin is referred to as <term>carbaminohemoglobin (HbCO</term><sub><term>2</term></sub><term>)</term>, which accounts for 25 percent of the carbon dioxide transported in in the blood. However, the bulk of carbon dioxide collected from tissues throughout the body is transported in the form of <term>bicarbonate (HCO</term><sub><term>3</term></sub><sup><term>-</term></sup><term>)</term> in the plasma. The enzyme <term>carbonic anhydrase</term>, found in high concentration in erythrocytes, catalyzes the conversion of carbon dioxide and water into bicarbonate. This bicarbonate then moves into the plasma in an exchange with chloride across the RBC membrane.</p><section id="a99ad2e1b7474f049001b110447b72a8" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_identify_function_red_blood_cells_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="_u9_identify_function_red_blood_cells_LBD_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="d5f84ace3c384f57857fbc1399c43640" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="b0e3faa5fc074290a4ddad26e5087a9a"><title>Life cycle of Red Blood Cells</title><body><p id="a2a97a1f1f2941c5b2def7a106de0a3a"><term>Erythropoiesis</term> is the process by which bone marrow stem cells develop into erythroblasts that differentiate further into reticulocytes, and then mature before being released into the circulation (Figure 8). This process of making RBCs occurs continuously and at a high rate, with approximately 2.5 million RBCs produced every second. This matches the breakdown rate of RBCs, as old ones are removed and destroyed by the liver and spleen. Erythropoietin is the hormone from the liver and kidney that regulates the rate of RBC production.</p><p id="b79c45a36a184700b7a2354c1fff15b9">Mature red blood cells are disc-shaped structures with a flattened center. They do not possess a nucleus or other organelles, but instead use the space for hemoglobin. The depressed center also maximizes the surface area of red blood cells, which facilitates the exchange of O<sub>2 </sub>and CO<sub>2</sub>. The flattened shape of RBCs allows them to navigate through narrow capillaries, which are often of similar (or smaller) diameter than the RBCs. The lack of a nucleus also means that RBCs lack the genetic material (DNA) necessary to reproduce, grow, and carry out functions of maintenance and repair. This limits the lifespan of these cells.</p><image id="f57283f44e124b30a6b62a6b77436989" src="../webcontent/C_M1_06a.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><title>Figure 8</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c78d1c7d405d496cb86b7bfd5010c237">Red blood cells have a typical lifespan of 120 days. Over time, red blood cells accumulate cellular damage. Once they get to a point where they cannot deform appropriately when moving through narrow channels, they are removed from the circulation by specialized cells, called macrophages, in the spleen or liver. Macrophages <term>phagocytose</term> (engulf) the old RBCs, separating the protein (globin) and non-protein (heme) portions of hemoglobin. The protein chains are further degraded into amino acids and dispersed within the blood plasma. Iron is extracted from heme and is either stored or enters the bloodstream. Stored iron is attached to proteins <term>ferritin</term> and <term>hemosiderin</term>, preventing the buildup of toxic free iron. Iron entering the bloodstream is also attached to a molecule called a <term>transferrin</term>; which can be picked up for use by various tissue types such as muscle cells, or even bone marrow, where it is used to generate new erythrocytes.</p><image id="c6d57c24a19e460d9965c6b69fe05fec" src="../webcontent/C_M1_06b.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><title>Figure 9</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="c82e8625fdb04e76ab3bcc3c883a4ea9" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_describe_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_01" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="_u9_describe_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_03" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="b3c2418b688f4920bfe9b9a1c531efde" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_describe_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_digt_03" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="f9c8152ff5c1411d8d2990fcf15645fd"><title>Blood Groups</title><body><p id="d487cab49a7e41c2b3bc1e62d9bb3e5d">You are probably aware that if an individual is transfused with non-compatible blood that negative consequence, such as the clumping together (agglutination) or destruction (hemolysis), of the donated red cells might result. Compatibility is determined by the lack of interaction between antigens on the donor red blood cells and antibodies in the plasma of the recipient. People of different blood groups (types) vary in the red blood cell antigens and plasma antibodies they have.</p><p id="ca66e019b382443390c63f968bd6926f">Although there are many blood groups, the ones that are the most important when it comes to transfusions are the ABO and Rh groups. These groups are genetically determined, with a single gene coding for protein synthesis being responsible for each. The alleles inherited determine which if any protein antigen(s) (sometimes called agglutinogens) are expressed and embedded in the RBC membrane. In the case of the ABO blood group, the two alleles of the gene can each be one of 3 different variants, O (i), A (I<sup>A</sup>), or B (I<sup>B</sup>). The A and B alleles are dominant to the O allele, while the A and B alleles (AB or IAIB genotype) are codominant, creating the AB blood group when inherited together. The O or null allele results in no antigen being created (so A blood group could be either AA or AO genotype). For the Rh group the dominant D allele determines if a person is Rh+ with possible genotypes of either DD, Dd, or dd. </p><p id="e83f538490f440d49c7d1ec344587fc4">Note that these two blood groups are distinct from one another such that they are used in combination, and not one or the other. For example, those with blood type O- express neither antigen A or B or D, while those with type A+ blood express the A antigen and the D antigen on their red cells. </p><p id="b64cc12f4ea04fba85fe3faba89b2275">Besides the antigens, the ABO blood group also determines the antibodies (sometimes called agglutinins) that are present in the person’s plasma. These antibodies start forming soon after birth, likely in response to bacteria with similar membrane antigens that start inhabiting the gut. Those with type O blood will make both anti-A and anti-B antibodies, those with type AB blood will not produce either antibody, while those with either type A or type B blood will make antibodies against the antigen not found on their red cells. In contrast, those that are Rh-, do not make anti-D antibodies unless exposed to a significant amount of blood containing the D antigen.</p><p id="b278bb4ecdac446c81905e09cc1c7936">As mentioned, in order for a blood transfusion to be compatible, the donor blood cannot contain antigens that will cross react with recipient plasma antibodies. The most obvious way to prevent transfusion reactions is to infuse donor red blood cells (which is more common than using whole blood) that are of the same type as the recipients. But in some cases other red blood cells can be used as well. For example, because those individuals who are blood type AB do not have any anti-A or anti-B antibodies in their plasma, they can accept blood from any other ABO blood type (as long as the RH factor matches as well), making them the universal acceptor.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_06" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_LBD_06_layout.xml</param></wb:inline><wb:inline idref="identify_function_life_cycle_red_blood_cells_DIGT_05" purpose="didigetthis" /></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
