<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_01"><head><title>The Molecular Composition of Plasma</title><objref idref="describe_composition_plasma_OBJ" /></head><body><section id="aa94eb9e47934f3e924739d7d47bfcc1"><title>Overview of Blood</title><body><p id="a13946f3411e4fd58e074ee1543b38d4">The adult human body contains approximately 5 liters of blood (8 percent of the body’s weight), which courses through the heart, arteries, veins, and capillaries. As blood courses through blood vessels it carries out essential functions in the body, such as transporting nutrients, gases, hormones, and heat toward the body’s tissues and carrying waste material, carbon dioxide and excess heat away from these same tissues. The blood also plays an important role in protecting the body against microbial infection and forming clots to protect against blood loss. It takes about 60 seconds for blood to travel completely through the body and return back to the heart.</p></body></section><section id="f6f253a93681450b8ec4275989f2e813"><title>Blood Properties: color, pH, specific gravity and viscosity</title><body><p id="cb10a27aa9e54e3481835e88ef4cec66">Arterial blood that flows into the aorta from the left ventricle is fully oxygenated so that it can deliver the oxygen necessary for the tissues to make adequate ATP. The combination of oxygen bound to the heme groups in the red blood cells gives this blood a red pigment. Venous blood, which returns to the right side of the heart after having exchanged nutrients in the tissues, appears darker in color because it contains a larger fraction of hemoglobin that is no longer combined with oxygen. In the pulmonary circulation, it is the pulmonary artery blood that is less oxygenated, and therefore darker in color in compared to the brighter red blood in the pulmonary veins.</p><p id="ad91c7c48ba64219abf9e6da32d2adb7">The heme groups in the red blood cells are part of larger hemoglobin molecules, which are found in high concentration within red blood cells (RBCs). These oxygen carrying cells typically make up 35-45% of blood volume. Together with a small fraction of white blood cells (WBCs) and platelets, they collectively make up the formed elements of the blood. The rest of the blood is composed of a fluid fraction called <term>plasma</term>. Plasma is composed of water and other substances such as proteins, salts, and gases. The pH of blood plasma ranges from 7.35 to 7.45. It has a specific gravity between 1.050 and 1.060 in adults. Specific gravity is a measure of blood density related to pure water (water has a specific gravity of 1.000), so blood is about 5-6% more dense than water. The specific gravity of blood may vary and can be affected by certain diseases that change the concentration of cells within the plasma.</p><p id="a3d7793e8e144bc99f7baaf176058e0b">Besides specific gravity, <term>viscosity</term> is another fluid property that may be of importance in blood. Viscosity is the internal friction liquid exhibits when it tries to flow. For example, honey and syrup have a much higher viscosity than water, and they flow slower under similar conditions than water would. The viscosity of pure water is 1.00, whereas the viscosity of blood can be roughly three to five times that because it contains cells and proteins.</p><p id="e2ace833fb30420c91a8f315b7d4affd">Blood helps in the regulation of body temperature. The blood entering the body’s core (the area in which thoracic and abdominal organs are located) is immediately warmed to a temperature of approximately 38°C (100.4°F). Depending on body temperature, this blood may end up traveling to the skin where it can transfer some of this heat to the external environment.</p></body></section><section id="ba44b87226684683b1373cbbe10b8cfa" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="describe_composition_plasma_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="_u9_describe_composition_plasma_DIGT_01" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="_u9_describe_composition_plasma_DIGT_02" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="ff748270c0144b4c9622efeb81cff46e"><title>Overview of Plasma</title><body><p id="b3261aabc68b4522ad630c1f394ba23c"><term>Plasma</term> is the fluid portion of blood with no cells. <term>Serum</term> is the portion of plasma that does not contain any blood-clotting proteins. Plasma consists of mainly water (90 percent). Other substances found in plasma include proteins, respiratory gases (O<sub>2 </sub>and CO<sub>2</sub>), electrolytes (sodium, chloride, calcium, and bicarbonate), nutrients, and waste products (e.g., urea and uric acid). The most abundant of the proteins is albumin, which helps retain water in the vascular compartment. The function of plasma is to transport dissolved nutrients and gases, regulate pH, and contribute to fluid and electrolyte balance.</p></body></section><section id="a24af74464af42e788f0a8c4032f5eeb"><title>Plasma Proteins</title><body><p id="b0752a47f58344628532f8c29c470144"><term>Plasma proteins</term>, which make up approximately 7 to 9 percent of plasma, consist of albumin, globulins, and fibrinogen. These molecules carry out several important functions within the body. <term>Albumin</term> is the smallest, yet it accounts for the majority of these plasma proteins (60 percent). Albumin is synthesized by the liver and functions to maintain colloid osmotic pressure in the blood compartment. This helps prevent the leakage of fluid into the surrounding interstitial spaces, and helps prevent <term>edema</term> (swelling). Three types of <term>globulins</term> make up about 36 percent of the plasma proteins: alpha, beta, and gamma. The alpha and beta globulins transport lipids and metals in blood. Gamma globulins are the antibodies released by immune cells that attack microorganisms and other foreign molecules. <term>Fibrinogen</term> makes up about 4 percent of plasma proteins and is important in the formation of blood clots.</p><p id="ce99aedf766a43f1964a97e707f8b618"><em style="bold">Plasma Proteins and their Functions</em></p><table id="fd96739aa26b42ceba52f8893d3e8506" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i7e12643924024ff98fe5c299f8fb42d1" /><caption><p id="aed68aca664284ddab3ed43f5122c2b01"></p></caption><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b18f08987f844fdab2987b4ad8f00f82"><em style="bold">Protein</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="a53b4986f17d48b78ce58aa2555efc08"><em style="bold">Site of Origin</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f29ee2c4d41a4141ab5e9b914c56c484"><em style="bold">Function</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa06333b8e604f869c7885188bc6079d"><em style="bold">Percentage of Plasma</em></p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad2111f0ca0fe44f39a3d64e155f2749d">Albumin</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="add9fcdc58edb4bfab5de0cb210f3b055">Liver</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad5adcb38cac84535bc03b93b057e8e4f">Maintains colloid osmotic pressure and contributes to the viscosity of blood</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="af26b107b666c4740b8fc0c9b130b0ef0">60</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af28bb310425548318288c248d4d7a319">Fibrinogen</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac661c61c96cd4f519a389ec1bfcd7d9a">Liver</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab52fe4e17c634892ac3c12a308a82819">Contributes to blood clotting</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="afb1e09e0ea014ecc8e5504907059e8e3">4</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aac8acc275df440dcab018bd59f6cfa1f">Globulins (Alpha, Beta, Gamma)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="aaf3ef200d68c4f34a08c35a08e1c5876">36</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afca7598478e84a2f9c357935278129a3">Alpha</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aca6d8496a9c5473fbd1ab1d0cdfd4490">Liver</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae6717dce68984e40aaa49cf80d65b665">Transport lipids and fat-soluble vitamins</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af477ddc34efe46ebb8ea17e2e96140aa"></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ade13cb2663874627a4b41bb5230d02f1">Beta</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af16bbd2430794bcfabaed7fa6f562f92">Liver</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adb622a047c474d7db6d4442689d93799">Transport lipids and other molecules</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="d0545da9a5034272b311ba3aa91bd98b"></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab820ed377cf8400389f73a024dacf707">Gamma</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adf42c89bee6d4e54873fee9d0619caaa">Lymphocytes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adf913ecb8b5c47b3a62dc2ce8d7da7d4">Immunity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b3e75327cc5b436ca9f975992a113562"></p></td></tr></table></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u9_identify_plasma_proteins_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="b2eb77ec351440bbb9147902b9ae526a" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_define_plasma_serum_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="describe_composition_plasma_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="ccef0e7dd714439abf8d93f91896fa68" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_define_plasma_serum_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="describe_composition_plasma_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="a9fffa43f3034c348f2d38e3392df2e9"><title>Disorders of Blood Plasma: Hypoalbuminemia</title><body><p id="eb9ec5d478f34240a090e70e335909d1">Albumin is a transport protein that carries various small molecules, such as bilirubin, metals, hormones, and medications, through blood. Another important function of albumin is to prevent plasma from leaking into tissues. If albumin levels are low, fluid will leak into the tissues, resulting in edema (swelling). Serum albumin levels typically decrease secondary to liver disease (including hepatitis and cirrhosis), loss of albumin in the urine, poor nutrition, or gastrointestinal disorders (celiac, Crohn’s and Whipple’s disease) that interrupt normal nutrient absorption. Levels may be increased with increased concentration of hormones such as steroids, growth hormone or insulin. The levels of albumin can be measured with a serum albumin test; with normal levels between 3.4 and 5.4 g/dL.</p><p id="b186db34abde45d6afb4acf6cb50104e">A consequence associated with hypoalbuminemia is that medications that are carried by albumin may have an increased concentration of unbound drug in the plasma. It is the unbound fraction that is active, such that even normal doses may seem like an “overdose”. Hypoalbuminemia occurs in acute and chronic inflammatory responses. As a result, a serum albumin plays an important prognostic role among hospitalized patients; as it is correlated with an increase risk of morbidity and mortality. Hypoalbuminemia commonly occurs among older adults who live in long-term care facilities, hospitalized patients with chronic illnesses, and malnourished children.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="describe_composition_plasma_digt_03" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
