<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_37">
	<head>
		<title>Veins of the Upper Limbs</title>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_upper_limbs_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The deep veins of the upper limbs have similar courses and names as their companion arteries. However, most of these veins are paired and run alongside their accompanying artery. The large superficial veins in the upper limbs are clearly visible just below the skin.</p>
		<p><term>Major Veins of the Upper Limbs*</term></p>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<td><term>Location/Vein</term></td>
				<td><term>Area Drained</term></td>
				<td><term>Description</term></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Deep</td>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Radial veins</td>
				<td>Lateral side of forearms</td>
				<td>
						Paired <term>radial veins </term>begin at the deep <term>palmar venous arches </term>that drain the palmar metacarpal veins in the palms
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Ulnar veins</td>
				<td>Medial side of forearms</td>
				<td>
						Paired <term>ulnar veins </term>begin at the superficial palmar venous arches, which drain the <term>common palmar digital veins </term>and <term>proper palmar digital veins </term>in the fingers
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Brachial veins</td>
				<td>Forearms, elbow joints, upper limbs, humerus</td>
				<td>
						Paired <term>brachial veins </term>merge with the <term>basilic veins </term>to form the <term>axillary veins</term>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Axillary veins</td>
				<td>Upper limbs, axillae, superolateral chest wall</td>
				<td>
						Continue as the subclavian veins
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Subclavian veins</td>
				<td>Upper limbs, neck, thoracic wall</td>
				<td>
						Continuations of the axillary veins; Merge with the internal jugular veins to form the brachiocephalic veins
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Superficial</td>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Cephalic veins</td>
				<td>Lateral side of upper limbs</td>
				<td>
						The <term>cephalic veins </term>begin on the lateral side of the <term>dorsal venous arch</term>, a plexus of veins formed by the <term>dorsal metacarpal veins </term>that drain the <term>dorsal digital veins </term>of the fingers
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Basilic veins</td>
				<td>Medial aspects of upper limbs</td>
				<td>
						At the crook of the elbow, the basilic veins are connected to the cephalic veins by the <term>median cubital vein </term>that drains the forearm; The median cubital vein is often used to draw blood or inject intravenous medications; In the axilla, the basilic veins merge with the brachial veins to form the axillary veins
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Median antebrachial vein</td>
				<td>Palms, forearms</td>
				<td>
						The <term>median antebrachial vein </term>runs between the radial and ulnar veins in the forearm; Ends at the elbow by entering either the basilic or cephalic vein
				</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
		<p>*Some veins of the upper limbs also drain structures of the thorax.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
