<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_13">
	<head>
		<title>Vascular Tissue</title>
		<objref idref="define_properties_vessel_wall_layers_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="define_functions_tinuca_interna_media_externa_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="identify_cells_extracellular_matrix_tinuca_interna_media_externa_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The structural variations between the five major vessel types are due to the relative
			thickness and composition of three vessel wall layers called <term>tunics</term>. The
			specific function of each vessel type is dependent on the presence or absence of the
			three tunics, as well as the extent of the tunic structures. The three tunics, from
			inside to outside, are the <term>tunica interna</term>, <term>tunica media</term>, and
				<term>tunica externa</term>.</p>
		<section>
			<title>Tunica Interna</title>
			<body>
				<p>The tunica interna forms the interior lining of blood vessels and is in direct
					contact with the blood. This layer consists of <term>endothelium</term>, which
					forms a continuous sheet of cells that lines the lumen of vessels. The
					endothelial cells are involved in many vessel-related activities. The
					endothelium is physically supported by the underlying basement membrane. The
						<term>basement membrane</term> is composed largely of collagen fibers that
					provide both strength and flexibility. The basement membrane anchors the
					endothelium to the outermost component of the tunica interna, the <term>internal elastic lamina</term>. The internal elastic lamina is a sheet of
					elastic fibers with numerous openings that allow movement of solutes between the
					layers. The internal elastic lamina adheres the tunica interna to the tunica
					media.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Tunica Media</title>
			<body>
				<p>The tunica media shows the greatest variation among the five vessel types. This
					layer is composed of smooth muscle and connective tissue layers. In most vessel
					types this is the thickest tunic. The smooth muscle cells of the tunica media
					are oriented such that they encircle the <term>lumen</term> of the vessel. These
					cells regulate the size of the vessel lumen by contracting or relaxing upon
					stimulus of associated neurons, circulating hormones or local signaling
					molecules. The flow and distribution of blood, as well as blood pressure, are
					controlled by the dilation and contraction of blood vessels. The connective
					tissue of the tunica media is composed of elastic fibers that are interspersed
					within the muscle cell layers and that also form a separate sheet-like layer,
					the <term>external elastic lamina</term>, between the tunica media and tunica externa. The
					elastic fibers allow vessels to expand and recoil without loss of tension.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Tunica Externa</title>
			<body>
				<p>This tunic forms the outermost layer, merging with the surrounding tissues and
					anchoring the blood vessel in place. The tunica externa is composed of mostly
					collagen fibers. There are many nerves in the tunica externa and, in larger
					vessels, a system of vessels that supply the vessel tissues called the
						<term>vasa vasorum</term>.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<image src="../webcontent/C_M2_14.jpg" width="450"
			alt=""><title>Figure 12</title><caption></caption></image>
		
		<wb:inline idref="define_properties_vessel_wall_layers_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="define_properties_vessel_wall_layers_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="define_properties_vessel_wall_layers_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
