<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_30"><head><title>Veins that Return Blood to the Heart</title><objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="c18e96fe6deb4cf282b383e7886404d4">Venous blood from the systemic circuit is returned to the right atrium by way of the venae cavae and the coronary sinus. The superior vena cava receives veins that drain the head, neck, chest, and upper limbs. The inferior vena cava receives veins that drain the abdomen, pelvis, and lower limbs. The coronary sinus drains the myocardium.</p><p id="adff5ebe73f04a53af62446284485ce9">The majority of blood that returns to the heart flows through the superior and inferior venae cavae. The names of these veins are derived from the location of their tributaries. The <term>superior vena cava</term> collects blood from veins located superior to (above) the diaphragm, with the exception of the wall of the heart and the alveoli of the lungs. The superior vena cava, which delivers blood to the right atrium, is formed by the merger of the right and left <term>brachiocephalic veins</term>. Each of these veins, in turn, is formed by the union of the <term>internal jugular vein</term> and <term>subclavian vein</term> on the right or left side of the body. The <term>inferior vena cava</term>, which is the largest-diameter blood vessel in the body, collects blood from veins located inferior to (below) the diaphragm and delivers it to the right atrium. This vein is located directly to the right of the abdominal aorta. Its distal end is created by the merger of the paired <term>common iliac veins</term>. Blood that drains from the myocardium of the heart empties into cardiac veins and returns to the right atrium via the <term>coronary sinus</term>.</p><table id="e101503c0d114ce4af5ffeea4beb4e6b" summary="" rowstyle="alternating"><cite id="ib276c7e3210c4983a031fe77257866e0" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="a06218cef7d74c6694ac9fd1e67ca5f5"><em style="bold">Vein</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="d62ec6de38fc408683abfe63428d24e5"><em style="bold">Area Drained</em></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f2879c3f26e545e08589fa19f0ebe12b"><em style="bold">Description</em></p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae878149008424ac096d3486218acffb7">Superior vena cava</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af4036a0abca7495c9606455b3884c138">Head, neck, chest, upper limbs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afb679c41c0114bbea1d50f6baccc6a8a">7.5 cm (3 in.) long, with a diameter of 2 cm (1 in.)</p><p id="ad60c0242ea434e7f9cb01164bc474030">Returns blood to the superior portion of the right atrium</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="abae6563452d742328441deac80ac03af">Inferior vena cava</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac8146eb5977f4ecfa7725cd701e9efe2">Abdomen, pelvis, lower limbs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afdeaaee16fb545c3984e1c03dd68366d">~3.5 cm (1.4 in.) in diameter, the widest vein in the body</p><p id="ae2a6c3641020490d9d4e42fa5b55e6db">Returns blood to the inferior portion of the right atrium</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="addeca6e4d71747cc85d853e9439ca3e2">Coronary sinus</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae81425ea7e054c9e934ab664ef7e20b5">Myocardium</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af1808d2f01314e6088517bb84ae2afac">Receives the great, middle, and small cardiac veins</p><p id="ab700aaa92e5b4730a0ae2f5eec6f7adf">Returns blood to the right atrium; A few anterior cardiac veins drain directly into the right atrium </p></td></tr></table><wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_veins_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_veins_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
