<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_09">
	<head>
		<title>Hematopoiesis and Stem Cells</title>
		<objref idref="describe_process_hematopoiesis_OBJ"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p><term>Hematopoiesis</term>, or the formation of blood cells, occurs in the red bone
			marrow of the body. Recall that seven different cell types (including platelets)
			circulate in the blood, yet their lineage can all be traced to stem cells in the bone
			marrow. As these stem cells produce new cells via mitosis, the daughter cells may follow
			different maturational paths, depending on the needs of the body. Two common paths are
			the myeloid cell line and the lymphoid cell line. The myeloid line gives rise to red
			blood cells, granular leukocytes, platelets, and monocytes. The lymphoid cell line
			produces T and B lymphocytes. Although most myeloid cells mature in the myeloid tissues
			of the red bone marrow of the skull, vertebrae and rib cage (as well as long bones in
			children), lymphoid derived cells typically mature in lymphoid tissues throughout the
			body, such as the spleen, tonsils and lymph nodes.</p>
		
		<image src="../webcontent/C_M2_09.jpg" width="550"
			alt=""><title>Figure 11</title><caption></caption></image>
		
		<p>During embryonic development the formation of blood cells occurs in the liver, spleen,
			and yolk sac. However, after birth, the infant’s liver and spleen become the locations
			for destroying blood cells. All blood cells, whether they end up in the myeloid or
			lymphoid family, begin as hemocytoblasts, stem cells that develop from embryonic
			mesenchyme.</p>
		<p><em style="bold">Formation of the Seven Cell Types in the Blood</em></p>
		<table rowstyle="alternating">
			<tr>
				<th><em style="bold">Progenitor Cell</em></th>
				<th><em style="bold">Formed Element</em></th>
				<th><em style="bold">Function</em></th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Proerythroblasts</td>
				<td>Red blood cells</td>
				<td>Transport oxygen and carbon dioxide</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Myeloblasts</td>
				<td>Neutrophils</td>
				<td>Phagocytic</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td/>
				<td>Basophils</td>
				<td>Release heparin (anticoagulant)</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td/>
				<td>Eosinophils</td>
				<td>Phagocytic</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Lymphoblasts</td>
				<td>Lymphocytes</td>
				<td>Provide specific immune response</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Monoblasts</td>
				<td>Monocytes</td>
				<td>Phagocytic</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Megakaryoblasts</td>
				<td>Platelets (thrombocytes)</td>
				<td>Hemostasis</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_process_hematopoiesis_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_process_hematopoiesis_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
