<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_03"><head><title>Main Types of Blood Cells</title><objref idref="identify_erythrocytes_leukocytes_thrombocytes_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="f53be8a2f85a4933b6d08ff0bb9b5d26">There are three main types of blood cells that flow through the blood stream, with each type serving specialized functions. Red blood cells primarily carry oxygen and remove carbon dioxide, white blood cells are immune cells that patrol the blood and body tissues for pathogens and platelets, which are involved in hemostasis, as described previously.</p><image id="d0ad82ac47524077b69946ff62f16ab9" src="../webcontent/C_M1_03.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><title>Figure 3</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="ca76af6372604eb6b7a21b474582b5ba" src="../webcontent/C_M1_04.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><title>Figure 4</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b6e8f8f15b534e63b2c7f7397c304853"><term>Red blood cells (RBCs)</term> are one of the most abundant formed elements in blood. Also called <term>erythrocytes</term>, red blood cells are specialized for oxygen transport and function primarily in gas exchange. Red blood cells bring oxygen to tissues and pick up carbon dioxide (the gaseous waste product of cells), bringing it back to the lungs. Red blood cells contain hemoglobin, a protein that contains iron, to which both oxygen and carbon dioxide are able to bind. In the lungs, red blood cells pick up the oxygen that they transport.</p><p id="aa1afcc5d5d7441a827cef08aceaa89f">The various types of <term>white blood cells (WBCs)</term>, or <term>leukocytes</term>, are readily distinguished by whether or not they possess granules within their cytoplasm. Granulocytes, as their name suggests, possess numerous granules in their cytoplasm, whereas agranulocytes do not. The shapes of the nuclei of granulocytes and agranulocytes also differ. Leukocytes mainly function to protect the body from microbial invasion and toxins. WBCs readily travel through the bloodstream. However, most leukocytes can also travel from the bloodstream into the interstitial tissues in order to attack foreign agents in those spaces.</p><p id="fb11cfbc4e5f488fa071cb03cc9d2621"><term>Platelets</term> are smaller fragments of larger cells called <term>megakaryocytes</term>, and they are sometimes not even classified as cells. Megakaryocytes are large nucleated cells off of which numerous platelets bud. Platelets lack a nucleus but do have a plasma membrane surrounding a cytoplasm and a few organelles. As described previously, platelets play a role in hemostasis.</p><section id="fd12e14de8d64a4d80b7b85e5ef816df" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="identify_erythrocytes_leukocytes_thrombocytes_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="af97ef5c6ee640ae93fb5d2b8a55e133" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="identify_erythrocytes_leukocytes_thrombocytes_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="identify_erythrocytes_leukocytes_thrombocytes_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
