<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_16"><head><title>Valves of the Heart</title><objref idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="cc3976562cee499ca803bab6c552fb69">As mentioned earlier, blood flows through the heart in one direction. What prevents blood from flowing in the opposite direction? The answer is the heart’s valves. These valves maintain unidirectional flow by preventing backward (retrograde) flow when the pressure gradients change during the heart cycle. These valves are found in matched pairs in two locations of the heart. The first set, the <term>atrioventricular (AV) valves</term>, separate the atria from the ventricles. The second, the <term>semilunar valves</term>, are located between the ventricles and the arteries they feed.</p><p id="bf36f78a13bd43f2a80527bc0e125d68">Following the path of blood flow through heart, the first valve is the <term>tricuspid valve</term> found separating the right atrium from the right ventricle. This AV valve is so named because it has three flaps: the <term>anterior cusp</term>, the <term>medial cusp</term>, and the <term>posterior cusp</term>. On the ventricle side of the valve are long muscular cords, called chordate tendinae, that extend from the inferior side of each cusp. The chordate tendinae attach to each cusp on one end and to the <term>papillary muscle</term>, which is connected to the inner wall of the ventricle, on the other end. These muscles prevent the valves from inverting back into the atria during ventricular contraction.</p><image id="fd28f0b2dcd7423580a31b6334e56bc9" src="../webcontent/C_M2_16.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><title>Figure 14</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="e11449581d3644999287307631aac9d9">Most of the blood flows passively into the atria, through the tricuspid valve, and into the right ventricle. Atrial contractions then push most of the remaining atrial blood into the ventricle. As the right ventricle fills, the pressure inside it increases. This increased pressure, coupled with the right atria moving into its relaxation phase, causes the ventricular pressures to be greater than atrial pressures. This causes the tricuspid AV valves to close. In this closed position, the chordae tendinae that are attached to the ventricular side of the valves are fully extended and taut, like a stretched bungee cord. The chordae tendinae prevent the higher pressure in the ventricle from forcing the valve to open back into the atria, thus preventing the backflow of blood through the tricuspid valve.</p><p id="a08bb20b06c4491991912dc24c633ef2">As the blood flows from the right ventricle into the pulmonary artery, it passes through the <term>pulmonary semilunar valve</term> (pulmonary valve). Opposite to the tricuspid, the pulmonary semilunar valve remains closed when the ventricle is filling and opens during ventricular contraction.Again, this is because the valves work by opening when the pressure is higher on their proximal side and close when the pressure is higher on their distal side.</p><p id="a31e970058944f949ce83f0bb92a35db">On its return from the lungs, blood enters the left atrium. As the blood passes from the left atrium into the left ventricle, it passes through the <term>bicuspid valve</term>, often referred to as the <term>mitral valve</term>. This valve is similar in structure and function to the tricuspid, but only contains two cusps, the anterior and posterior cusps. It, too, is open when the pressure in the atria exceeds the ventricle and it, too, has chordae tendinae and papillary muscles that prevent its inversion upon ventricular contraction. The release of blood from the left ventricle into the aorta is regulated by the <term>aortic semilunar valve</term>, which is most commonly referred to as the <term>aortic valve</term>. It is similar in structure and function to the pulmonary semilunar valve. Because they regulate the flow of blood through the heart and prevent its backflow, these valves are indispensable for the proper function of the heart.</p><wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_04" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="b1c9c20431f7410ca424363e2f2def7d"><title>Diseases of the Heart: Ruptured Chordae Tendinae</title><body><p id="f745ab9ff3394a4683531dc6112516b1">The chordae tendinae perform an important function by keeping the cusps of the atrioventricular valves tethered to the interior wall of the ventricles. Without these tendons, and their associated papillary muscles, the valves could become inverted when the pressure in the ventricle increases, causing the blood to rush back into the atria.</p><p id="d6ae30fdfe8545bc9ceef0174686667c">Although this happens infrequently, the chordae tendinae can rip or rupture. When this happens, the cusps of the tricuspid or mitral valves are no longer properly tethered to the wall of the ventricle. As the blood presses back against the valves during ventricular contraction, the valves may not remain closed. If many of these connections are ruptured or if the thicker ones are affected, the valves can open in the reverse direction, and blood can backflow into the atria. This results in increased pressure in the atria and, if the backflow is significant enough, congestive heart failure could develop.</p><p id="dc558a289d614ed2b167bdb33737cab6">Rupture of the chordae tendinae occurs when a patient suffers from a myocardial infarction (heart attack), heart valve infection, or from trauma to the chest. Damage can range from minor to major depending on the number of chordae affected. It is diagnosed by hearing a murmur, or a characteristic whooshing noise, upon auscultation (listening to heart sounds with a stethoscope or other device) of the heart. Ruptured chordate tendinae, and their associated conditions, commonly lead to heart failure.</p><p id="d4f01b85fa4c418ebf0facf598c52417">Rupture of the chordae tendinae attached to the mitral valve is most common, although rupture of those bound to the tricuspid valve can also occur. Rupture of the mitral valve chordae tendinae can result in a rapid increase in left atrial pressure. This can subsequently increase the pressure in the pulmonary circulation, ultimately producing pulmonary edema; which is retention of fluid in the lungs. An echocardiogram can provide a more detailed look into the condition of the heart and the degree of damage to the chordae tendinae.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_10" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
