<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_02"><head><title>Hemostasis and Blood Clotting</title><objref idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_OBJ" /></head><body><section id="f5e573f502de4d429d082281927a2dd7"><title>Hemostasis</title><body><p id="acff72db4ac8404795e6d072ea77e68a"><term>Hemostasis</term> (<em style="italic">hemo</em>- blood and <em style="italic">stasis</em> – standing still) is a protective process in which the body undergoes a cascade of steps in order to stop the bleeding from a damaged blood vessel. The process of hemostasis is incredibly complex so that blood clots form where and when we need them to. We have all seen that small cuts on our skin begin the healing process with a clot. However, clots are not always beneficial. The formation of blood clots within an intact blood vessel can lead to heart attacks and strokes. Thus, this process has to be well regulated. Hemostasis is a multi-step process, characterized by three major activities: vasoconstriction, platelet aggregation, and formation of a fibrin clot.</p><p id="f8d212598b8d47c38d1ddd549a3bd6f2">When a blood vessel is torn, the first response is a vascular (vascular refers to blood vessels) spasm, which is the constriction of the blood vessel at its site of injury. This vascular constriction is initiated by activation of pain receptors that reflexively cause constriction of local smooth muscle cells.</p><p id="c95f227d8451450195a6924a975f1353">Second, platelets (a type of cell fragment) stick to the collagen fibers that become exposed when the endothelial cell lining of the blood vessels is damaged during injury. In doing so, they begin to plug up the hole. These bound platelets also become activated and release secretory granules that contain <term>adenosine diphosphate (ADP)</term>, serotonin, prostaglandins, and phospholipids. These signaling molecules lead to binding of more platelets at the site of injury. This process continues until enough platelets have aggregated to form a platelet plug. <term>Serotonin</term>, a neurotransmitter, and <term>thromboxane A2</term>, a prostaglandin produced by activated platelets, both facilitate vasoconstriction at the site. The released phospholipids activate the clotting factors. In the end, the platelets at the site of injury form of loose meshwork of interconnected platelets.</p><p id="ba602dffcf4e4c968472e81668fdb200">Third, a more stable plug called a clot, or <term>thrombus</term>, forms via <term>coagulation</term> (blood clotting). Coagulation occurs as a series of reactions that result in the formation of the fibrin protein. This fibrin protein can cross-link to other fibrin proteins, as well as to platelets, providing strength to the thrombus. The end product of coagulation is a clot, or thrombus, consisting of a fibrinous gel that encloses trapped blood cells. During the coagulation process the clotting cascade amplifies itself, making this a classic example of a homeostatic feedback loop that uses positive feedback (although in a limited manner).</p><image id="aab10c64881e4eaaada2e78519ca4c8c" src="../webcontent/C_M1_02.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><title>Figure 1</title><caption><p id="acca002d78cb34c3abbab0e074e25f8b6"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="eae94210008649a48d0435adf811bd03"><term>Fibrin</term> is formed from the plasma protein fibrinogen. This conversion occurs only after a cascade of enzymatic reactions involving various plasma proteins called <term>clotting factors</term>. The 13 clotting factors are named in the order of their discovery as I through XIII. Two separate pathways exist in the clotting pathway: an extrinsic and intrinsic pathway. The majority of the reactions that occur in both the extrinsic and intrinsic pathways require calcium in order for the steps to occur. Coagulation can be inhibited by adding a <term>chelating agent</term>, such as citrate, that binds to calcium making it unavailable to facilitate blood clotting. This is a way to prevent freshly drawn blood from clotting.</p></body></section><section id="d5f02322592740948bc0fc92c065ce34" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="_u9_distinguish_hemostasis_coagulation_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><section id="ed5b93ffc26f468b9ffe24ae7829c27a" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="_u9_distinguish_hemostasis_coagulation_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="de60b179218c49099e197db86e9d1d9b"><title>Intrinsic Pathway</title><body><p id="d8b528c929c2496992a0d3e6c27d53dd">The <term>intrinsic pathway</term> is activated when plasma is exposed to collagen after endothelial cell injury, or when blood is exposed to negatively charged surfaces such as glass. For example, if blood is added to a test tube that doesn’t contain any clot inhibiting chemicals, the intrinsic pathway will be activated, causing clots to form. The intrinsic pathway starts with the activation of factor XII (a protein-digesting enzyme), which removes the inactive part of factor XI in order to activate it. Activated factor XI, in turn, activates factor IX. Phospholipids (provided by platelets) and calcium are utilized in the remainder of the steps in the cascade. A complex is formed with phospholipids, calcium, factor IX and factor VIII. This new complex activates factor X, and they all combine to convert prothrombin into thrombin followed by the conversion of fibrinogen into fibrin. Fibrin polymerizes to form long fibers that interconnect and form the meshwork of the clot. Platelets are interweaved into the fibrin mesh and further fill the clot.</p></body></section><section id="c4fd1af01d7544e2991aefa5e302af62"><title>Extrinsic Pathway</title><body><p id="fef5df83bb9c42a5b36ddfb451246e3c">The <term>extrinsic pathway</term> is triggered by chemicals released by the damaged cells of the blood vessel wall. In this pathway, clot formation occurs rapidly with the release of tissue thromboplastin (factor III), by the damaged tissue cells. Factor III activates another clotting factor called factor VII. Phospholipids and calcium are added to factor VII in order to form a complex (VII complex) that in turn activates factor X. Factor X, factor V, phospholipids, and Ca<sup>++ </sup>all contribute to the formation of the V complex that converts prothrombin (inactive factor II) into thrombin. Thrombin then converts fibrinogen (factor I) to fibrin. Fibrin is acted on by factor XIII to form an impenetrable fibrin clot.</p></body></section><image id="c58cc591d8544cecb29b509b88eaef5c" src="../webcontent/C_M1_01.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><title>Figure 2</title><caption><p id="aae520ae6ab4c40e2b7a91d4c2fd04dbc"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="c88e10f160584b6e83479353f00d6150" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="diff_intrinsic_extrinsic_clotting_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></section><wb:inline idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_digt_03" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="dcc6caa9ae9140db817254ee2e82bdb1"><title>Fibrinolysis</title><body><p id="ce8ec893bcaf499a93debc19a887f7f4">After the clot has performed its function of stopping blood loss, the constituents of the clot have to be removed. <term>Clot retraction</term> is the gradual removal of the fibrin threads that make up the blood clot, and <term>fibrinolysis</term> is the process by which a blood clot is broken down. Once a damaged blood vessel wall is undergoing repair, factor XII will convert inactive prekallikrein into active kallikrein. <term>Kallikrein</term> is responsible for the conversion of an inactive plasma protein called <term>plasminogen</term> into plasmin. <term>Plasmin</term> is an enzymatically active molecule that splits the fibrin polymers that make up the clot. Kallikrein also plays a role in the production of <term>bradykinin</term>, which stimulates vasodilation to help counter the vasoconstrictive effects of serotonin and prostaglandins that were released by platelets during clot formation.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="describe_process_fibrinolysis_LBD" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/describe_process_fibrinolysis_layout.xml</param></wb:inline><wb:inline idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_digt_05" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="f796005a2ba84167b3cda710320ed86c"><title>Problems in Blood Clotting</title><body><p id="fd28c6fed3b24c82b8c6c0ae7704073c">Normal hemostasis can be reduced by a number of conditions, including decreased platelet levels, genetic defects leading to insufficient or abnormal clotting factors (hemophilias), or lack of production of clotting factors in the liver (where many are formed). Certain clotting factors require <term>vitamin K</term>, a fat-soluble nutrient that is synthesized by bacteria in the large intestine. Conditions that result in the malabsorption of fat lead to the deficiency of vitamin K and correspondingly increased bleeding times.</p><p id="ad3c5a0fd6404ed9a9e37270cc4ef5a7">Blood clots can break free from sites of injury. These <term>thromboemboli</term> then get trapped within small blood vessels, blocking flow through the vessels. Thromboemboli that originate in the venous circulation travel until they reach the small blood vessels in the lungs where they lodge as pulmonary emboli. If these thromboemboli are large enough, the person will have abnormal breathing or may die.</p><p id="aedc8f2c28874f5bb8a4253715ae4fe7">Sometimes it is beneficial to inhibit the clotting cascade to lower the risk of thromboemboli. During surgery this is usually done with the injectable drug heparin, which rapidly inactivates the enzyme thrombin. Heparin is used because it can be rapidly reversed. For those that need a longer term reduction in clotting ability, the oral drug Warfarin is commonly used. This drug is a vitamin K antagonist and reduces the levels of several clotting factors.</p></body></section><section id="d33c0b9279c0411ba2b29d035551597f" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="explain_calcium_vitamin_k_clotting_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="describe_phases_hemostasis_digt_04" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
