<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_17">
	<head>
		<title>Blood Flow Through the Heart</title>
		<objref idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_classify_major_blod_vessels_heart_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Blood circulates in a closed system. It flows from the heart, through the lungs, back to
			the heart, and then to the rest of the body. The blood always returns to the heart. The
			amount of blood that circulates and the rate blood circulates is controlled by the
			pumping of the heart. The system is similar to having a rubber ball filled with water
			and a tube connected on both sides of it. When the ball is squeezed, the water enters
			the tube on one side. When the ball is relaxed, water is drawn into it through the other
			side. Squeeze again, and more water is ejected into the tube. Relax again, and water is
			drawn into the ball. The valves between the opening of the tube and the ball, which only
			open one way, control the entry of water into the tube and prevent its tendency to move
			backwards.</p>
		<p>Blood continuously flows in a circle. Oxygen-poor blood enters the lungs where carbon
			dioxide, a waste product of the organs’ cells, is exchanged for oxygen. This oxygen-rich
			blood returns to the heart by way of the pulmonary veins. When it arrives from the
			lungs, it enters the left atrium. Some of the blood flows passively through the bicuspid
			(or mitral) valve into the left ventricle. When the left atrium contracts, the remaining
			blood in the left atrium is pushed through the bicuspid valve into the powerful left
			ventricle.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="blood_flow" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<p>After the left ventricle contracts, the blood exits through the aortic valve into the
			aorta to be circulated throughout the body. The first section of the aorta is the
			ascending aorta, which runs only a short way before becoming the aortic arch at the apex
			of an inverted U, from which vessels branch to supply the head, neck and arms. After the
			aortic arch turns downward it becomes the descending aorta. The thoracic aorta supplies
			blood to the thorax above the diaphragm and the abdominal aorta supplies blood to the
			region below the diaphragm. Arteries that branch off of the aorta continue to branch
			into smaller and smaller arterioles and eventually form the capillaries within the
			organ. It is within the capillaries that the gas exchange occurs. In the organs, oxygen
			is provided and carbon dioxide is removed. This is the opposite of gas exchange in the
			lungs where carbon dioxide is removed and oxygen is provided.</p>
		<p>Once exchange has occurred, oxygen-poor blood exits the capillaries, flowing into
			venules, or small veins. These venules combine to form veins, which eventually return
			the blood to the right atrium. The blood from the head, neck and arms returns to the
			right atrium through the <term>superior vena cava</term>, while the blood from the lower
			body returns through the <term>inferior vena cava</term>. The right atrium contracts and
			blood passes through the tricuspid valve into the right ventricle. From the right
			ventricle, the blood is ejected through the pulmonary semilunar valve into the pulmonary
			artery to travel to the lung arterioles and capillaries. Oxygen-rich blood flows into
			the venules and back to the heart through the pulmonary vein and is ready to enter the
			left atrium again and circulate around the body again.</p>
		<image src="../webcontent/C_M2_17.jpg" width="550" alt="">
			<title>Figure 15</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_03"
					purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_05"
					purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_11" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>The Fetal Circulation</title>
			<body>
				<p>The path that blood takes through the fetal circulatory system and heart differs
					somewhat from that in the postpartum state. In particular, a majority of the
					blood passes through three shunts, bypassing the liver and lungs that do not
					require as much blood in the fetus as they do after birth. These shunts include
					the ductus venosus, which bypasses the liver, and two shunts that bypass the
					lungs; the foramen ovale and the ductus arteriosus.</p>
				<p>As highly oxygenated blood travels along the placental vein into the fetus, some
					of the blood perfuses the liver, while a majority bypasses the liver through the
					ductus venosus and directly enters the inferior vena cava. The fetal liver
					matures late in development, when it prepares to take over functions such as
					processing chemicals and nutrients absorbed by the GI tract. Because it is not
					carrying out such functions in the fetus, there is not a need to send
					significant blood flow there.</p>
				<p>The lungs are also not functional in the fetus, as the placenta carries out the
					functions of gas exchange. In fact, the lungs are deflated, with the alveoli
					collapsed. This condition also narrows the vessels of the pulmonary vasculature,
					creating high resistance to blood flow. To keep the workload on the right heart
					from becoming too high in the fetus, most of the blood bypasses the lungs. This
					occurs via two shunts. The first is an opening between the right and left atria
					called the foramen ovale. Because the pressures are higher in the right heart
					than the left heart in the fetus (due to the high pulmonary resistance), blood
					moves from the right atrium to the left atrium through this shunt. The remaining
					blood moves into the right ventricle where it is pumped into the pulmonary
					artery. But even from here most blood will not go through the remainder of the
					pulmonary circulation. Instead, it travels from the pulmonary artery to the
					aorta through the ductus arteriosus. </p>
				<p>Soon after birth the lungs inflate, greatly reducing the resistance through
					pulmonary circulation and lowering the pressures on the right side of the heart.
					This briefly reverses flow through the foramen ovale, pushing two flaps of
					tissue over the opening, closing it. These flaps grow into the atrial septum,
					leaving a slight depression called the fossa ovalis. The decreased pressure in
					the pulmonary artery also triggers the ductus arteriosus to collapse, converting
					it into the connective ligamentum arteriosum over the next three months or so.
					The ductus venosus become a connective tissue remnant, called the ligamentum
					venosum, found on the inferior surface of the liver.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_lbd_12" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		

		<section>
			<title>Aging and the Heart: Valvular Stenosis</title>
			<body>
				<p>If any of the four valves within the heart become stiff, the valves are unlikely
					to open to the fullest extent. Blood flow is impeded and the pressure in at
					least one of the heart chambers increases.</p>
				<p>Mitral valve stenosis increases the stiffness of the mitral valve that separates
					the left atrium from the left ventricle. This results in increased pressure in
					the left atrium, which backs up into the pulmonary circulation, causing edema
					there. If the atria can’t compensate enough to maintain flow through the
					narrowed mitral valve, heart failure will develop. People with untreated mitral
					stenosis typically develop atrial hypertrophy in an effort to generate enough
					atrial pressure to maintain this flow. Similar results and compensatory
					mechanisms occur in tricuspid valve stenosis.</p>
				<p>Aortic valve stenosis occurs when the aorta valve stiffens. This increases the
					pressure in the left ventricle and increases the stress developed in the wall of
					the left ventricle during ejection. The stroke volume is reduced as the left
					ventricle has to contract more forcefully to eject the blood into the aorta.
					This causes left ventricular hypertrophy, although this is not always enough to
					maintain flow.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		
				<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_12" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
