<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_28"><head><title>Arterioles, Metarterioles, Capillaries, and Venules</title><objref idref="describe_structure_function_arterioles_metarterioles_capillaries_venules_OBJ" /></head><body><section id="c04d022af9b94ef387f655ec56b19725"><title>Arterioles</title><body><p id="bfffdbae8de84317b87e4b889549bdd1">The smallest of the vessels that carry blood away from the heart, the<term>arterioles</term>, direct blood into the capillary networks. Both thetunica interna and tunica externa of arterioles are thin and the tunica media
consists of only one or two layers of muscle cells that encircle the vessel.
However, these arterioles are particularly important in regulating the amount of
flow delivered to the tissues that they feed. These arterioles have a rich
supply of sympathetic nerve fibers. When they receive a high number of signals
from the sympathetic nervous system (i.e. a high degree of sympathetic tone),
the arterioles constrict, increasing resistance to blood flow. If the signals
from the sympathetic nervous system decrease (i.e. decreased sympathetic tone),
the arterioles dilate, reducing the resistance to flow. Arterioles can also
adjust their diameters in response to hormonal signals (such as angiotensin II)
and local signaling molecules (such as prostaglandins). Fine adjustments to the
diameter of the arteriole lumen have a direct effect on the flow of blood into
the capillary network supplied by that particular arteriole. Arterioles are
numerous and do not have individual names as the elastic and muscular arteries
do.</p></body></section><image id="fbcd05db5e8f4b729750f8337ed9b4ec" src="../webcontent/C_M3_29.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><title>Figure 26</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="d855527f7a3b449f92a010810129fa69" src="../webcontent/C_M3_35.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="550"><title>Figure 31</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="d691e1c19e104c56b277b19006d0b4a2"><title>Metarterioles</title><body><p id="bc51ece1af574280a9b5e3b6bdeb0a99"><term>Metarterioles </term>are short vessels that connect arterioles to thecapillary networks. Metarterioles do not have a true tunica media. Instead, at
the metarteriole-capillary junctions a single smooth muscle cell forms a ring
around the metarteriole. Each encircling muscle cell acts as a
<term>precapillary sphincter</term>, regulating the flow of blood into thecapillaries that branch from the metarteriole. In response to stimuli, the
muscle cell encircling the metarteriole contracts, reducing the size of the
lumen. This prevents the flow of blood into the capillaries fed by that
metarteriole. If most or all of the precapillary sphincters associated with a
capillary network contract simultaneously, blood is moved directly from the
arterial to the venous system through the metarteriole. In this situation, the
metarteriole is acting as a thoroughfare channel, and the entire capillary
network is bypassed. Because each metarteriole regulates blood flow into a
specific number of capillaries, blood flow through any tissue is finely
controlled. Blood delivery to a particular tissue can be quickly increased,
decreased, or even temporarily halted in order to respond to the current
metabolic activity of the tissues they supply.</p></body></section><image id="a441cdfde73b48eb838d55c607fe6424" src="../webcontent/C_M3_30.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><title>Figure 27</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="e7a8fda22fac4ed6a71df979177d5b41"><title>Capillaries</title><body><p id="a1d439a903824b84b80b8930f80cc599">The smallest of all the vessels, the <term>capillaries</term> form extensivenetworks throughout the entire body. Capillary networks form the connections
between the arterial and venous systems. The complexity of each capillary
network varies in response to the metabolic needs of the tissues served. Tissues
with high oxygen requirements, such as skeletal muscle, have 8 or 10 capillaries
branching from each metarteriole. Tissues with lower needs, such as the
intestinal tract have 2 or 3 capillaries from each metarteriole. There are even
some tissues, such as nail beds, with metabolic needs so low that the ratio of
metarteriole to capillary is one to one.</p><p id="a083d442445c4fe797c8bf8a52d41979">In addition to capillary network design, capillary wall construction furtherfacilitates the rapid exchange of gases and solutes. Capillary walls consist of
only a tunica interna. Decreasing the distance that substances must travel
increases the diffusion rate. The artery and arteriole wall thickness prevents
diffusion of gases and solutes from the blood until it arrives at the target
tissue. In some tissues the demand for oxygen and nutrients is so high that even
the thin barrier of the tunica interna prevents adequate diffusion rates. To
accommodate the specific needs of each tissue and organ, there are three
different types of capillaries, based on wall structure. Following the exchange
of gases and solute, capillary networks drain into postcapillary venules.</p><p id="c3f0063c4af1424f80d2d5ce9e33eba8"><em style="emphasis">Types of Capillaries</em></p><p id="c8db3206f3da40dbbe299f53f121afb7">Capillaries are classified by the structure and arrangement of their endothelialcells and the underlying basement membrane. The three types, <term>continuouscapillary</term>, <term>fenestrated capillary</term>, and <term>sinusoidcapillary</term>, each have a characteristic structure that dictates thelevel of permeability. Continuous capillaries form smooth tubes with only narrow
intercellular clefts between the adjacent endothelial cells. The basement
membrane is whole and without pores. Small molecules such as glucose and oxygen
can readily pass across and between the cells, but larger molecules such as
plasma proteins and platelets, cannot pass across the membrane. Continuous
capillaries have the lowest permeability rate of the three types and are common
in muscle, nervous, and connective tissues. The endothelial cells of fenestrated
capillaries have numerous <term>fenestrae</term> (“windows”). These are areas ofthe cells where the plasma membranes from opposite sides of the cell adhere and
exclude the cytoplasm. Often the membrane of the fenestrations is constructed of
a material even more porous than a typical phospholipid bilayer. The basement
membrane of fenestrated capillaries has openings or pores that also increase the
permeability of the vessels. Fenestrated capillaries allow for faster solute
exchange but still exclude larger molecules from passing through. They are
common in areas that require rapid absorption or filtration such as the small
intestines, the kidneys and the choroid plexuses of the brain. Sinusoid
capillaries are limited to areas where blood cells move in and out of the
bloodstream. The endothelial cells are widely separated and contain large pores
without membrane coverings. The basement membrane of sinusoid capillaries is
sparse or missing. This structure allows large plasma proteins and even blood
cells to enter and leave the capillaries. Sinusoid capillaries are found where
blood cells are formed, such as red bone marrow, and where large proteins enter
the bloodstream, such as the liver.</p></body></section><image id="ce46d6db460e449faa56d1c9c888dd99" src="../webcontent/C_M3_32.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="500"><title>Figure 28</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><section id="b63f5e606b7942b2b09346dafe9a9ddf"><title>Venules</title><body><p id="f254320407f246c1a56201aad998e720">At the venous end of a capillary network, the capillaries that branch from asingle metarteriole reunite and empty into a <term>venule</term>. As blood movesinto the venules, and thus the venous system, the return trip to the heart
begins. The walls of venules and veins are much thinner than those of arteries
and arterioles. Without blood within, arteries retain their shape but veins
collapse. The postcapillary venules collect blood from the capillary networks.
These smallest and most porous of the venules are involved in solute and gas
exchange in the tissues along with the capillary networks. Postcapillary venules
are also the site of white blood cell exit from the bloodstream in response to
inflammation or infection. In a reversal of the branching of arteries into
smaller and smaller vessels, venules coalesce to form larger and larger vessels,
gaining vessel wall components and thickness as they enlarge.</p></body></section><image id="dce3620539bc478086ee7d5eb9a1afe6" src="../webcontent/C_M3_33.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><title>Figure 29</title><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_arterioles_metarterioles_capillaries_venules_lbd_01" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/describe_structure_function_arterioles_metarterioles_capillaries_venules_lbd_01_layout.xml</param></wb:inline><wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_arterioles_metarterioles_capillaries_venules_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
