<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_19">
	<head>
		<title>Vessels of the Heart</title>
		<objref idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_coronary_arteries_branches_veins_sinus_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Force generating cells of the heart require energy to beat constantly and the conductive
			cells require energy to maintain electrical potentials. So the heart, itself, requires a
			large supply of blood. It is the role of the <term>coronary circulation</term> to
			deliver this blood to the heart. In this circulation, the coronary arteries deliver the
			oxygen-rich blood to the myocardium while the cardiac veins are responsible for
			returning the blood back to the right atrium.</p>
		<p>Coronary arteries on the surface of the heart are called epicardial coronary arteries.
			These arteries are commonly affected by atherosclerosis and can become blocked, causing
			angina or heart attack. The branches of the coronary arteries penetrate the myocardium
			and work their way inward, ending up as subendocardial arteries.</p>
		<p>The right and left <term>coronary arteries</term> originate from the aortic sinuses,
			which exit from the aorta right after it leaves it heart. The <term>posterior
				interventricular branch</term> of the right coronary artery supplies the right and
			left ventricles. The right ventricle also receives blood from the second branch of the
			right coronary artery, the <term>marginal branch</term>. The left coronary artery has
			two branches: the <term>anterior interventricular branch</term> (<term>left anterior
				descending branch</term>), which supplies both ventricles, and the <term>circumflex
				branch</term>, which supplies the left ventricle and left atrium.</p>
<!--SHOULD HAVE AN IMAGE HERE (8B) arteries and veins of the heart-->
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_07" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
