<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_15">
	<head>
		<title>Chambers of the Heart</title>
		<objref idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_heart_double_pump_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="identfiy_location_four_chambers_blod_flow_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>In many ways, the heart is the center of the circulatory system. It is the pump that
			controls the movement of blood. The arteries carry blood away from the heart; veins
			carry it back to the heart. Blood circulates around the body, providing nutrients to
			organs, while removing metabolic waste. What route does blood take? Blood enters the
			right side of the heart by streaming into the <term>right atrium</term>, the chamber of
			the heart that receives blood from the superior vena cava, inferior vena cava, and the
			coronary sinus.</p>
		<p>From the right atrium, it flows into the <term>right ventricle</term>. Blood then exits
			the heart and enters <term>pulmonary circulation</term>, traveling through the
				<term>pulmonary artery</term> (artery that carries blood from the heart to the
			lungs) to the lungs where gases are exchanged. Freshly re-oxygenated blood returns to
			the <term>left atrium</term> traveling through the <term>pulmonary vein</term> (vein
			that carries blood from the lungs to the heart). From the left atrium, it flows into the
				<term>left ventricle</term> before exiting the heart into the <term>aorta</term> to
			enter the systemic circulation to be transported throughout the body. This oxygen-rich
			blood flows through the arteries to the organs where oxygen is delivered and metabolic
			waste is removed. From the organs, oxygen-poor (more specifically, less oxygenated)
			blood returns to the heart, carried by the veins, and enters the right atrium again.</p>
		<image src="../webcontent/C_M2_15.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 13</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>
		<p>While these muscular pumps work together in the heart, they are not equal in the size of
			their musculature. The left side contains thicker muscles than the right side. Why? The
			right side has to generate less pressure in order to pump the blood through the short
			circulatory pathway of the lungs. This does not require as much pressure as pumping to
			the systemic circulation, like the left ventricle has to do.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section>
			<title>Diseases of the Heart: Atrial Septal Defects</title>
			<body>
				<p>Have you ever heard of having a hole in the heart? A small percentage of people
					have just that, a hole in the wall (septum) that separates the right and left
					atria. Medically, this is known as an <term>atrial septal defect</term>. This
					defect is a congenital disease, meaning it is present at birth. When a fetus is
					still developing, the septum between the right and left atrium is not fully
					formed. The atria are connected together by a hole, called the foramen ovale,
					between the two chambers. This opening allows blood in the fetal heart to be
					shunted from the right atrium into the left atrium. This shunted blood does not
					get pumped into the pulmonary artery, as this is not necessary in the fetus.
					Instead, the fetus receives oxygen (and nutrients) from the placenta via the
					umbilical cord. When delivery occurs and the newborn takes his or her first
					breath, the lungs inflate. This changes the pressure distribution in the heart
					and causes a flap of tissue to close the foramen ovale, which then grows into a
					completed septum. When the foramen ovale does not close properly, or if there
					are similar congenital defects, the child is left with an atrial septal defect
					or, in other words, a hole in his or her heart.</p>
				<p>Whether or not this problem needs to be corrected is mainly dependent on the size
					of the hole. This is because some blood from the left atrium will move through
					the atrial septal defect into the right atrium, causing it to recirculate
					through the pulmonarycirculation. If too much blood is shunted back through the
					lungs it can cause pulmonary hypertension and ultimately heart failure.</p>
				<p>Most of the time, symptoms are very mild or not even noticed. Sometimes, symptoms
					do not develop until much later in life. Atrial septal defects can be treated
					with surgical closure of the defect.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_09" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
