<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_36">
	<head>
		<title>Veins of the Abdomen</title>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_abdomen_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Blood from the abdominal walls and abdominal (and pelvic) organs returns to the heart via the inferior vena cava. Blood from the digestive organs empties into veins that drain into the <term>hepatic portal vein</term>. This common vessel carries the venous blood into the liver. The <term>hepatic veins </term>then carry the blood into the major systemic circulation. This hepatic portal system includes two sets of capillary beds located between the arterial supply and the ultimate venous drainage. Capillary beds in the stomach and intestines empty into tributaries of the hepatic portal vein, which carries the blood to the capillary bed in the liver. The hepatic portal system also includes a variety of tributary vessels from the stomach and pancreas, including the superior and inferior mesenteric veins and the splenic vein. The <term>superior mesenteric vein </term>collects blood from all of the small intestine, the ascending and transverse colons of the large intestine, and the stomach. The <term>splenic vein </term>drains the spleen and portions of the pancreas and stomach. This vein unites with the superior mesenteric vein to create the hepatic portal vein. Blood from the distal parts of the large intestine and rectum drains into the <term>inferior mesenteric vein</term>, which unites with the splenic vein immediately prior to its merger with the superior mesenteric vein to form the hepatic portal vein.</p>
		<p><term>Major Veins of the Abdomen</term></p>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<td><term>Vein</term></td>
				<td><term>Area Drained</term></td>
				<td><term>Description</term></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Inferior vena cava</td>
				<td>Abdomen, lower limbs, pelvis</td>
				<td>
						Formed by the merger of the two common iliac veins
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>External iliac veins</td>
				<td>Abdominal wall, lower limbs, cremaster muscle in males</td>
				<td>
						Companions of the internal iliac arteries; Continuations of the femoral veins; End by merging with the internal iliac veins to form the common iliac veins
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Lumbar veins</td>
				<td>Posterior abdominal wall (both sides), vertebral canal, spinal cord, meninges</td>
				<td>
						Usually four <term>lumbar veins </term>on each side; Some drain directly into the inferior vena cava and others into the ascending lumbar veins of the thoracic azygos system
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Gonadal veins</td>
				<td>Testes in males; ovaries in females</td>
				<td>
						<term>Gonadal veins </term>are called <term>testicular veins </term>in males and <term>ovarian veins </term>in females; Left testicular and left ovarian veins drain into the left renal veins; Right testicular and right ovarian veins empty into the inferior vena cava
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Renal veins</td>
				<td>Kidneys</td>
				<td>
						The right <term>renal vein </term>is shorter than the left; The left renal vein collects blood from the left ovarian/testicular, left inferior phrenic, and left suprarenal veins; The right renal vein drains into the inferior vena cava
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Suprarenal veins</td>
				<td>Adrenal glands</td>
				<td>
						The left <term>suprarenal vein </term>drains into the left renal vein; The right suprarenal vein drains into the inferior vena cava
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Inferior phrenic veins</td>
				<td>Diaphragm</td>
				<td>
						Typically, the left inferior phrenic vein has tributaries to the left suprarenal vein (which drains into the left renal vein) and to the inferior vena cava; The right inferior phrenic vein drains into the inferior vena cava
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Hepatic veins</td>
				<td>Liver</td>
				<td>
						Right and left hepatic veins empty into the inferior vena cava
				</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
