<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_22">
	<head>
		<title>Arteries</title>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_function_main_types_arteries_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Arteries are vessels that carry blood away from the heart. The tunica media is the
			thickest tunic in arteries, although all three layers are present. The smooth muscle
			cells in the tunica media of arteries are innervated by fibers of the autonomic nervous
			system. When stimulated, the muscle cells contract and cause
				<term>vasoconstriction</term>, a decrease in the diameter of the blood vessel lumen.
			Relaxation of the muscle cells causes <term>vasodilation</term>, an increase in diameter
			of the lumen. Damage to an artery also triggers vasoconstriction to help prevent blood
			loss. As arteries move blood away from the heart, they branch into smaller and smaller
			vessels.</p>
		<section>
			<title>Artery Types</title>
			<body>
				<p>Arteries are typically classified by location, but they can also be described by
					their function.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Elastic Arteries</em></p>
				<p>As the name indicates, <term>elastic arteries</term> have vast capacity for
					expansion and retraction. These properties are due to the internal and external
					elastic laminae and extensive elastic fiber sheets interspersed within the
					muscle cells. The arteries with the largest diameters in the body are elastic
					arteries. The elastic arteries that receive blood from the heart, such as the
					aorta, the common carotids, and the pulmonary trunk, play a critical role in
					regulating the pulsing blood that is ejected from the heart. These vessels
					temporarily store blood by expanding and then slowly recoiling. This action
					propels the blood forward at a more consistent rate than is delivered during
					systole and also helps to maintain blood pressure during diastole. The elastic
					arteries are also called <term>conducting arteries</term> because they direct
					blood to the next smallest diameter vessels, the muscular arteries.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Muscular Arteries</em></p>
				<p>Compared to elastic arteries, <term>muscular arteries</term> have a smaller
					diameter and a higher percent of muscle cells to elastic fibers in the tunica
					media. Muscular arteries are typically medium-sized vessels with a very thick
					tunica media. The extensive smooth muscle cells in muscular arteries allow for
					greater vasoconstriction and vasodilation. This property of muscular arteries
					contributes to the regulation of blood flow. Muscular arteries are also called
						<term>distributing arteries</term> because they direct blood into the
					various organs, continuing to branch into smaller and smaller diameter vessels.
					Some examples of muscular arteries are the brachial, radial, ulnar, and coronary
					arteries.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
