<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_20">
	<head>
		<title>Gross Anatomy and Physiology: Blood Vessels</title>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_aorta_and_branches_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_arterioles_metarterioles_capillaries_venules_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="compare_structure_arteries_veins_arterioles_venules_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The human cardiovascular system consists of two separate circulatory routes, the
				<term>pulmonary circuit</term> and the <term>systemic circuit</term>. In each
			circuit, several levels of blood vessels work in sequence to receive blood from the
			heart, deliver it to the appropriate tissues and cells, and then return blood to the
			heart. In general, the <term>arteries</term> and <term>arterioles</term> of the systemic
			circuit deliver blood, rich with oxygen and nutrients, to <term>capillary</term>
			networks interspersed within the organs and tissues. The systemic <term>venules</term>
			and <term>veins</term> drain the capillary networks and return the blood, high in carbon
			dioxide and waste products, to the right side of the heart. In contrast, the arteries
			and arterioles of the pulmonary circuit deliver oxygen-poor blood to the capillaries
			surrounding the <term>alveoli</term> (singular: alveolus) of the lungs. After carbon dioxide is
			exchanged for oxygen, the pulmonary venules and veins return oxygen-rich blood to the
			left side of the heart. The arteries, arterioles, capillaries, venules, and veins are
			categorized by wall structure, location in the circuit, and function.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_21.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 18</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<p>Blood from the left ventricle is pumped into the aorta. This is the beginning of the
			systemic circulation. The aorta and its branches deliver blood to all body tissues
			except for those in the lungs. Venous blood from the systemic circuit is returned to the
			right atrium by way of the venae cavae and the coronary sinus. The superior vena cava
			receives blood from veins that drain the head, neck, chest, and upper limbs. The
			inferior vena cava receives blood from veins that drain the abdomen, pelvis, and lower
			limbs. The coronary sinus drains the myocardium.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow__LBD_03" purpose="learnbydoing"
			src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf">
			<param name="interfaceDescription"
				>../webcontent/describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow__LBD_03_layout.xml</param>
		</wb:inline>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_08" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_22.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 19</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<p>The aorta is divided into the ascending aorta, the arch of the aorta, the thoracic aorta,
			and the abdominal aorta. Branches off of the ascending aorta supply the atria and ventricles of
			the heart. The aortic arch has three major branches: the brachiocephalic trunk, left
			common carotid artery, and left subclavian artery. These arteries and their branches
			supply the head, neck, brain, and upper limbs. Branches of the thoracic aorta and
			abdominal aorta supply structures of the thorax and abdomen, respectively. Branches of
			the abdominal aorta also supply the lower limbs.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_23.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 20</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<p>The arterial supply of the brain includes an arrangement of arteries called the arterial
			circle (circle of Willis). These vessels provide collateral pathways that ensure
			uninterrupted blood supply to the brain if some arteries are blocked. The venous
			drainage of the brain is unique in that blood drains first into large chambers called
			dural sinuses instead of veins.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_24.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 21</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<p>The arterial supply of the thorax and abdomen includes both visceral and parietal
			branches. The visceral branches perfuse the organs, and the parietal branches perfuse
			the wall structures. Venous drainage of the digestive organs includes the hepatic portal
			circulation, which sends blood to the liver for nutrient processing and toxin removal
			before it is returned to the systemic circulation.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_25.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 22</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<p>The arterial supply of the upper limbs is primarily a continuing sequence of vessels
			rather than branches of other vessels. The subclavian artery continues as the axillary
			artery, which continues as the brachial artery.</p>
		<p>The pelvis and lower limbs are supplied by the internal and external iliac arteries,
			respectively. These arteries are branches of the right and left common iliac arteries,
			which are the terminal branches of the abdominal aorta.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_26.jpg" width="450" alt="">
			<title>Figure 23</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
