<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_12"><head><title>Skeletal Versus Cardiac Muscle</title><objref idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_OBJ" /></head><body><section id="eac3d25e20654f11a0762b0b854e1df0"><title>Skeletal and Cardiac Muscle Similarities</title><body><p id="f0b821f562f7431595229e619a38ba16">Heart muscle, or cardiac muscle, is similar to the skeletal muscle you already learned about. Both types of muscle contain sarcomeres and T tubules and depend on calcium for contraction. Both muscles produce action potentials and contract. Both contain mitochondria and require oxygen.</p><p id="b95ef1f676cf4fa2bf431560ca82e231">While similarities are evident between skeletal muscle cells and cardiac cells, several important differences exist as well. These differences are what make the heart a uniquely functioning organ. Cardiac muscle generally has a higher concentration of mitochondria, which increases its requirement for oxygen. One large advantage for having such a high concentration of mitochondria per cell is that it does not fatigue. For a heart muscle that beats an average of 70 beats per minute during every minute of every day, the need for energy is essential. The disadvantage of a high mitochondrial content is that the amount of oxygen required is quite high, which puts these cells at risk if blood flow to them is ever limited, which is what occurs during heart attacks.</p></body></section><section id="f1c589f4b98247028dbf0123fe93be99"><title>Skeletal and Cardiac Muscle Differences</title><body><p id="b7de37d477cd491eb8a7917d0440abd3">These cells also differ in how they increase their cytosolic calcium for contraction. Cardiac cells employ two sources of calcium for contraction. During a cardiac action potential L-type calcium channels open, allowing calcium to enter from the extracellular space. The entry of this calcium then stimulates the release of calcium from internal calcium stores located in the sacroplasmic reticulum. This is called <term>calcium-induced calcium release</term>. The calcium then binds to the troponin, just like in skeletal muscle cells to initiate contraction. In contrast, the cytosolic calcium in skeletal muscles comes only from its intracellular stores and is released after an action potential passes into the T-tubules.</p><p id="d9d7dc8260c74ee3b293b3649389d1a9">There are other important differences between cardiac and skeletal muscle. The fibers of the cardiac muscle are short, while skeletal muscle cells are long. Cardiac cells are branched, while skeletal muscle cells are stacked side by side. Cardiac muscle cells contain only one or two nuclei, whereas skeletal muscle cells are multi-nucleated. Most importantly, cardiac muscle cells are interconnected, while skeletal muscle cells are not.</p><p id="d319b954f67145bdb791910dd86a8fe0">Cardiac muscle cells are connected together by <term>intercalated discs</term>. These disks physically connect adjacent cells, and include a set of specialized proteins called gap junctions, that can directly pass electrical signals. Because of this, depolarization of one cell can ultimately cause depolarization of all the cells within the heart. This means that cardiac cells act together as a single unit, allowing the heart to function as a whole to contract properly and pump the blood efficiently. In the heart, gap junctions allow ions such as calcium to flow quickly and unimpeded from one cardiac cell to the next. The presence of intercalated disks and gap junctions increase the electrical conductivity of the heart, allowing the action potential to rapidly spread throughout all the cells of the heart. If these differences between cardiac and skeletal muscle cells did not exist, then the heart would probably not be able to pump as efficiently.</p></body></section><section id="e069e716e9584df3803257a091ef17e5" purpose="learnbydoing"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing" /><wb:inline idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_lbd_03" src="/superactivity/assessment2/InlineAssessmentClient4.swf" purpose="learnbydoing"><param name="interfaceDescription">../webcontent/identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_lbd_03_layout.xml</param></wb:inline></body></section><section id="facf62bfb285417885e2203ac9b0deb0" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_digt_03" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body></workbook_page>
