<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_29">
	<head>
		<title>Veins</title>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_characteristics_function_veins_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Although all three tunics are present in veins, the tunica interna and tunica media are
			quite thin, and both the internal and external elastic laminae are absent, or very thin.
			These features render the veins capable of great expansion to hold the variable volume
			of blood passing through them. At any given time, there is three times as much blood
			volume in the venous system than there is in the arterial system. However, veins are not
			designed to handle the high blood pressure commonly found in arteries. Due to the
			relatively large lumen and thin walls, veins will appear flattened in a micrograph since
			the vessel collapses when it is not filled with blood.</p>
		<p>Blood pressure in the venous system is much lower than blood pressure in the arterial
			system (10 mm Hg compared to 90–100 mm Hg). Therefore, the flow of blood back to the
			heart from the capillary networks, called venous return, cannot depend on pressure
			alone. One feature of veins that augments venous return is the presence of <term>venous
				valves</term> within the vessels, most commonly in the limbs. The valves of veins
			are formed by extensions of the tunica interna that form flaps into the vessel lumen.
			These valves close when blood in a vein tries to move backward, away from the heart. The
			closed valve forms a barrier to the backward flow of blood.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M3_34.jpg" width="350" alt="">
			<title>Figure 30</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<p>Along with the differences in wall structure, the venous system has some unique features.
			One of these is the presence of <term>venous sinuses</term>, large-diameter veins with
			extremely thin walls that contain no smooth muscle. Support is instead provided by the
			dense connective tissue surrounding the vessel. Venous sinuses are collection points for
			oxygen-poor blood that is headed back to the heart. Examples are the coronary sinus of
			the cardiac venous system and the dural sinuses in the brain. In addition, veins are
			more numerous than arteries. Often two veins will accompany a single artery. Between the
			veins are connecting channels, called <term>anastomoses</term>. Anastomoses are most
			commonly found in the limbs, and the veins that form them are not always associated with
			arteries. In the upper and lower limbs, superficial veins are present where arteries are
			not. Anastomoses connect the superficial veins to the deeper veins which are accompanied
			by arteries. Also unique to the venous system are <term>portal veins</term>. Portal
			veins drain one capillary network, travel to another organ or tissue, and empty into
			another capillary network. The hepatic portal vein carries nutrient-rich blood from the
			gastrointestinal tract and spleen to the liver.</p>

		

		<wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_veins_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
