<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_10">
	<head>
		<title>Cells of the Vessels</title>
		<objref idref="identify_types_cells_blood_vessels_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="describe_blood_features_connective_tissue_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_cells_blood_vessels_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="describe_function_endothelial_cells_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Within a blood vessel there are three main layers, which we will consider in vascular
			tissue, described later. Endothelial cells are on the inside (lumen) of a blood vessel.
			In some vessels, they are wrapped by smooth muscle cells. Fibroblasts secrete
			extracellular matrix in the large vessels, creating a connective tissue outer
			layer.</p>

		<image src="../webcontent/C_M2_13.jpg" width="400" alt="">
			<title>Figure 12</title>
			<caption/>
		</image>

		<section>
			<title>Endothelial Cells</title>
			<body>
				<p>Any surface that comes in contact with blood, including the inside of the heart
					and every blood vessel, is lined with a special cell called an
						<term>endothelial</term> (endo-inside) <term>cell</term>. Vascular
					endothelium line the blood vessels, and there are special endothelial cells of
					the lymph system. Endothelium of the interior surfaces of the heart chambers are
					called endocardium.</p>
				<p>The layer of endothelium is only one layer thick, and these cells have several
					important functions.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Mechanical-chemical Stimulation</em></p>
				<p>Endothelial cells sense changes in local chemical and mechanical environment, and
					signal to the underlying muscle cells. For example, under certain conditions,
					increased force on the vessels cause endothelial cells to release vasodilator
					chemicals (such as nitric oxide) which cause the smooth muscle cells to relax,
					leading to a dilated (expanded) vessel.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Immune Response</em></p>
				<p>When tissues have been compromised by damage or invasion of pathogens, the immune
					system releases chemical signals (cytokines) into the region. These cytokines
					activate the endothelial cells to promote association with circulating immune
					cells. Also, pores open up between endothelial cells to allow immune cells from
					the circulation to leave the lumen of the vessel and invade the tissue.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Forming New Blood Vessels</em></p>
				<p>As we grow or repair damaged tissue, we need new blood vessels to carry nutrients
					and oxygen into new tissue. The process of blood vessel formation is called
					angiogenesis, and involves stimulation of endothelial cells. <term>Vascular
						endothelial growth factor (VEGF)</term> stimulates the normally quiescent
					(non-dividing) endothelial cells to begin to divide. The cells then break down
					the extracellular matrix and form new blood vessels. Without angiogenesis, we
					could not repair any damaged tissue or adapt to changes. However, cancer cells
					will often secrete VEGF or other angiogenic factors to cause the ingrowth of
					vessels into the tumor, supporting its rapid growth.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Preventing Clot Formation</em></p>
				<p>One important function of endothelial cells is only really observable as a
					dysfunction: thrombus prevention. A thrombus, or a blood clot inside the vessel,
					can occur because of the easily activated coagulation proteins that flow through
					the blood stream<!-- to repair any damage [link to coagulation cascade]-->.
					Endothelial cell dysfunction, such as loss or inflammation, can cause clots to
					form on the inner surface of the blood vessel. Large thrombi can occlude (or
					completely block) blood vessels, so material cannot pass through. Just as
					dangerous, these thrombi can dislodge from the vessel wall and may travel to the
					vessels of the heart or brain and cause heart attacks or strokes,
					respectively.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="identify_types_cells_blood_vessels_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="identify_types_cells_blood_vessels_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section>
			<title>Smooth Muscle Cells</title>
			<body>
				<p>Smooth muscle tissue is found throughout the body, including around organs in the
					digestive, respiratory, and reproductive tracts and around blood vessels. In the
					cardiovascular system, smooth muscle cells form a layer outside of the
					endothelial cells. Here they provide strength to blood vessels and provide a
					mechanism for vessel adaptation.</p>
				<!--<p><em style="highlight">[NOTE: link to smooth muscle cell anatomy and physiology in
						muscular unit]</em></p>-->
				<p>Smooth muscle cells contract via the actin-myosin contraction mechanism described
					in the muscular unit. Smooth muscle cells adjust their contraction based on
					sensed stretch or the concentration of various chemical factors. For example,
					hormones related to exercise or anxiety can cause vessel constriction and nitric
					oxide can cause vasodilation.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="identify_types_cells_blood_vessels_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section>
			<title>Extra-Cellular Matrix of the Vessels</title>
			<body>
				<p>Besides the endothelial lining found in all blood vessels, and the smooth muscle
					cell layer found in most vessels, all vessels except capillaries also have one
					or more layers of connective tissue associated with them. These vessels have an
					outer connective tissue layer (tunica externa, or adventitia), while some also
					have a thin layer of connective tissue, called the internal elastic lamina that
					is found between the endothelial layer and smooth muscle layer. The types and
					concentrations of molecules in these connective tissue layers provide structure,
					support, and determine how easily the vessels will passively (without relaxation
					of muscle cells) expand.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Elastin</em></p>
				<p>Even without active changes in smooth muscle tension, blood vessels need an
					ability to deform and return to form when internal or external pressures are
					applied. The elastin molecule in the connective tissue layers of blood vessels
					gives them this property. <term>Elastin</term>, when combined with other
					extracellular components, helps blood vessels and other tissues, including skin,
					to return to their original shapes after expansion or deformation. Elastin
					molecules are disorganized, entangled and crosslinked. When stretched, these
					fibers straighten out, but will recoil back to normal when force is released on
					the tissues.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Collagen</em></p>
				<p><term>Collagen </term>is a stiff, filamentous extracellular protein found in most
					connective tissues. Collagen filaments are composed of twisted protofilaments,
					and protofilaments themselves are also twisted. Thus, collagen has ropelike
					qualities that provide stiffness. In blood vessels, collagen is found in the
					tunicia externa and provides stiffness to the blood vessel to prevent rupture.
					Arteries contain blood at higher pressure than veins so they have a thicker
					layer of collagen than veins.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="identify_types_cells_blood_vessels_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="identify_types_cells_blood_vessels_digt_03" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<section>
			<title>Blood as a Connective Tissue</title>
			<body>
				<p><term>Blood</term> is a liquid connective tissue. Connective tissues are defined
					as tissues with multiple cell types and a large extracellular matrix component.
					The blood cells, described before, serve different functions and the plasma acts
					as the extracellular matrix. Blood is a unique, complex fluid with various
					physical characteristics and functions needed to maintain a stable internal
					environment in the body. <term>Blood volume</term> is the combination of
					hematocrit (45 percent) and <term>plasma volume</term> (55 percent).
						<term>Hematocrit (hct)</term> is the fraction of blood that is composed of
					red blood cells (RBCs). Besides RBC, leukocytes (white cells) and platelets make
					up the rest of the formed elements. The process of producing blood cells is
					called <term>hematopoiesis</term>. <term>Stem cells</term> are nascent cells in
					the bone marrow that differentiate into various types of formed elements in
					blood.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_blood_features_connective_tissue_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_blood_features_connective_tissue_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				<wb:inline idref="describe_blood_features_connective_tissue_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
