<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_14">
	<head>
		<title>Gross Anatomy and Physiology: The Heart</title>
		<objref idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_location_heart_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The heart resides just left of the midline of the body in the chest cavity (thorax), and
			is protected by the rib cage. It is made of two pumps that are connected by a series of tube-like blood vessels that create the
				<term>circulatory system</term>; the system of arteries, capillaries, and veins that
			transport the blood to and from the heart. These
			pumps are separated by a thick wall called the <term>septum</term>. The circulatory
			system can be divided into two parts, the <term>pulmonary circulation</term>, which connects the
			heart to the lungs; and the <term>systemic circulation</term>, which connects the heart
			to the rest of the body.</p>
		<section>
			<title>The Heart</title>
			<body>
				<p>The heart is made of two pumps, each containing an atrium and a ventricle that is
					separated by a thick wall called a septum. The heart pumps blood in one
					direction through the circulatory system to provide oxygen to organs and to
					remove metabolic waste from the tissues. Each heart beat forces blood through
					the circulatory system and back to the heart. The blood enters the right atrium
					and passes into the right ventricle. It is then ejected from the right ventricle
					into the pulmonary artery, which carries blood from the heart to the lungs. Gas
					exchange, which involves releasing carbon dioxide and acquiring oxygen, occurs
					within capillaries of the lungs. Freshly re-oxygenated blood returns through the
					pulmonary vein back to the left atrium. The blood passes from the left atrium
					into the left ventricle. From there, it is ejected into the aorta and then into
					systemic circulation.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_anatomy_heart_and_blood_flow_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
