<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_23">
	<head>
		<title>Arteries of the Head and Neck</title>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_head_neck_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The head and neck are supplied by the paired common carotid arteries and three paired
			branches of the right and left subclavian arteries: the vertebral arteries,
			thyrocervical trunks, and costocervical trunks.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/abfdiagrams2.png" width="650"></image>
		<section>
			<title>Common Carotid Arteries</title>
			<body>
				<p>Branches of the common carotid arteries supply blood to the head and brain. The
					right common carotid originates from the brachiocephalic trunk. The left common
					carotid is the second branch of the aortic arch. At the "Adam's apple," the
					common carotids divide into the external and internal carotid arteries.</p>
				<p>The external carotid artery supplies most external head structures, except the
					orbits. It gives rise to the <term>superior thyroid artery</term>, which
					supplies the thyroid gland and larynx; the <term>lingual artery</term>, which
					supplies the tongue; the <term>facial artery</term>, which supplies the skin and
					muscles of face; the <term>occipital artery</term>, which supplies the posterior
					scalp; the <term>maxillary artery</term>, which supplies the teeth, maxilla,
					buccal cavity, external ear; and the <term>superficial temporal artery</term>,
					which supplies the chewing muscles, nasal cavity, lateral aspect of face, most
					of the scalp, and the dura mater around brain. A branch of the maxillary artery,
					the <term>middle meningeal artery</term>, supplies the dura mater and cranial
					cavity. Injury to the head that ruptures the middle meningeal artery causes
					epidural hematoma, which can be fatal.</p>
				<p>The internal carotid artery supplies the orbits and more than 80 percent of the
					cerebrum. It gives rise to the <term>ophthalmic artery</term>, which supplies
					the orbits, nose, and forehead; the anterior cerebral artery, which supplies the
					medial aspect of the cerebral hemisphere, and the <term>middle cerebral
						artery</term>, which supplies the lateral aspect of temporal and parietal
					lobes. The internal carotid arteries have a carotid sinus with baroreceptors
					that help regulate BP. Pressure on the neck near the carotid sinuses can cause
					unconsciousness, because it simulates high blood pressure, eliciting a reflex
					vasodilation and interfering with blood flow to the brain.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Vertebral Arteries</title>
			<body>
				<p>Branches of the vertebral arteries supply blood to the neck structures and the
					spinal cord. They originate from the subclavian arteries at the base of the neck
					and unite in the brain stem to form the basilar artery. The basilar artery
					branches supply the cerebellum, pons, and inner ear. At the junction of the pons
					and midbrain, the basilar artery flows into the arterial circle where it divides
					into two posterior cerebral arteries that supply the occipital lobes and
					inferior portions of temporal lobes.</p>
				<p>The <term>thyrocervical trunks</term> supply the thyroid gland and some scapular
					muscles. They are small vessels that originate from the subclavian arteries.
						<term>Costocervical trunks</term> arise from the subclavian arteries and
					supply blood to the deep neck muscles and some intercostal muscles of superior
					rib cage.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Arterial Circle</title>
			<body>
				<p>The arterial circle, also called the circle of Willis, is an arrangement of
					arteries surrounding the pituitary gland and optic chiasm. It creates
					redundancies to ensure blood supply to the brain if one artery feeding the
					circle—or a part of the circle—is damaged. The arterial circle is fed anteriorly
					by the left and right carotid arteries and posteriorly by the basilar artery.
					The circle itself is composed of two posterior communicating arteries, and one
					anterior communicating artery. Branches off of the circle include two posterior
					cerebral arteries, two middle cerebral arteries, and two anterior cerebral
					arteries.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Arteries of the Thorax</title>
			<body>
				<p>The wall of the thorax is supplied by a collection of arteries, some of which
					originate directly from the thoracic aorta and others from branches of the
					subclavian artery. Two bronchial arteries on the left and one on the right
					deliver systemic blood to the lung structures, including the visceral pleura,
					esophagus, and bronchi of lungs. Blood is also delivered to the esophagus by the
					four or five esophageal arteries. Numerous small mediastinal arteries deliver
					blood to the posterior mediastinal structures.</p>
				<p>Nine pairs of posterior intercostal arteries wrap around the rib cage before
					anastomosing anteriorly with the anterior intercostal arteries. The first pair
					arises from the costocervical trunk and the rest from the thoracic aorta. They
					supply blood to the skin and subcutaneous tissue, breasts, spinal cord and
					meninges, and pectoralis, intercostal, and some abdominal muscles. The
					distribution of the subcostal arteries is similar to that of the posterior
					intercostal arteries. They supply blood to the posterior intercostal tissues,
					vertebrae, spinal cord, and deep muscles of the back. One or more pairs of the
					small superior phrenic arteries supply blood to the posterosuperior surface of
					diaphragm.</p>
				<p>Internal thoracic arteries, also called the <term>mammary arteries</term>,
					originate from the subclavian artery and supply the breast tissue. Their
					branches, the <term>anterior intercostal arteries</term>, supply the intercostal
					spaces anteriorly.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_arteries_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
