<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_06">
	<head>
		<title>White Blood Cells</title>
		<objref idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_ObJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p><term>White blood cells</term>, or <term>leukocytes</term>, are immune cells that are
			present in the blood. The detailed mechanisms of immune function are covered in the
			immunity unit, but we will discuss the classes here. There are five common types of
			leukocytes (and some of those types have subgroups). One way of categorizing these five
			is by whether or not they contain granules in their cytoplasm when the cells are
			stained. If they do, they are a type of granulocyte. If not, they fall into the category
			of agranulocytes. Another way of distinguishing leukocytes from one another is by the
			morphology (shape and patten) of their nuclei. Granulocytes have multilobulated nuclei
			and agranulocytes have a spherical (nonlobulated) nucleus. The lifespan of a granulocyte
			ranges from about 12 hours to 4 days, but the agranulocyte survives for approximately
			100 to 300 days.</p>
		<p>Leukocytes mainly function to protect the body from microbial invasion and toxins. WBCs
			readily travel through the bloodstream. However, certain leukocytes have the ability to
			move into the interstitial spaces of the body’s tissues in order to attack foreign
			agents to protect the body from infection. They leave the capillalry by squeezing
			through the pores in the capillary walls via a process called <term>diapedesis</term>.
			This is due to the ability of these leukocytes to rearrange cytoskeletal matrix in a
			manner that changes their shape.</p>
		<section>
			<title>Granulocytes</title>
			<body>
				<p>Granulocytes contain many granules within the cytoplasm, and they have a
					multilobular, irregularly shaped nucleus. There are three types of granulocytes:
					neutrophils, eosinophils, and basophils. Each granulocyte is identified by
					specific stains used to reveal the granules in their cytoplasm. Granulocytes are
					responders of the nonspecific immune system, which means that the cells respond
					to injury and build up an inflammatory response against microbes or toxins
					regardless of whether the body has been previously invaded by the foreign agent.
					That is to say, granulocytes do not possess memory when mounting an immune
					response.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Nonspecific Immune Response Leukocytes</em></p>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Neutrophil</em></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07a.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07b.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Eosinophil</em></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07c.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07d.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Basophil</em></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07e.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07f.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Monocyte</em></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07g.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
						<td><image src="../webcontent/C_M1_07h.jpg" width="200" height="200" alt=""
							/></td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<p><em style="bold">Neutrophils</em></p>
				<p><term>Neutrophils</term> are the most abundant type of granulocyte (50 to 70
					percent of circulating WBCs). The S- or C-shaped nucleus of these cells has
					three to six lobules that are connected via strands of chromatin. The
					multi-lobular shape of the nucleus often classifies neutrophils as
						<term>polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMNs)</term>.</p>
				<p>During a bacterial infection, neutrophils are the first responders. The PMNs
					arrive at the site of infection through a process known as
						<term>chemotaxis</term> in which chemicals released by damaged cells draw
					neutrophils. The neutrophils attack bacteria by engulfing them via the process
					of phagocytosis. Once the bacteria are contained within the neutrophils, the
					granules release antimicrobial compounds called <term>defensins</term> and
						<term>lysozymes</term> to destroy the microbes. Pus is the culmination of
					destroyed neutrophils, bacteria, and dead tissue.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Eosinophils</em></p>
				<p><term>Eosinophils</term> only possess a bilobed nucleus linked by a thin strand
					of chromatin. Unlike neutrophils, eosinophils stain red with an eosin dye; the
					dye is acidic and is picked up by the cytoplasmic granules that contain
					digestive enzymes. Eosinophils also engulf foreign molecules attacking the body,
					particularly in parasitic infection and allergic reactions. They also play a
					role in modulating the activity of basophils.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Basophils</em></p>
				<p>The nucleus of <term>basophils</term> can contain two to five U- or S-shaped
					lobules. These leukocytes pick up basic dyes that cause their granules to have a
					blue-purple appearance. The granules of basophils contain histamine, serotonin,
					and heparin. The cells release histamine during an inflammatory response to
					tissue damage and microbial invasion. Basophils are similar in appearance and
					function with mast cells, which are strictly localized in connective tissue.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Agranulocytes</title>
			<body>
				<p>Unlike granulocytes, <term>agranulocytes</term> do not have granules within their
					cytoplasm and lack a lobulated nucleus. Under a microscope agranulocytes are
					observed to have a nucleus that composes the bulk of its cellular volume.
					Agranulocytes include lymphocytes, which are responsible for the specific immune
					response, meaning that they have memory and build up a vigorous response against
					toxins or microorganisms that the body has encountered before. The other
					agranulocyte is the monocyte, which is an immature form of the non-specific
					macrophage.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Lymphocytes</em></p>
				<p><term>Lymphocytes</term> can be categorized by their size (small, medium, and
					large). These cells have a round nucleus that virtually fills up the cell
					leaving very little blue-staining cytoplasm surrounding it (when stained in a
					standard manner). Lymphocytes are the only WBCs that reenter the bloodstream
					after moving into tissue to attack foreign agents.</p>
				<p>There are two types of lymphocytes: <term>T lymphocytes (T cells)</term> and
						<term>B lymphocytes (B cells)</term>.</p>
				<p>They both originate in the bone marrow, but T cells grow and mature within the
					thymus gland while B cells typically mature in bone marrow then move to lymph
					nodes and similar tissue. T cells attack abnormal cells in the body, such as
					virally infected cells, tumor cells, and donor transplant cells. B cells sense
					and attack invading antigens (foreign substance in the body) such as toxins,
					viruses, or bacteria. In response to antigens, B cells divide into plasma cells
					that make antibodies aimed at neutralizing and destroying these antigens.</p>
				<p><em style="bold">Monocytes</em></p>
				<p>The nuclei of <term>monocytes</term> are also large, but have a kidney shape. The
					cytoplasm of monocytes is greater in quantity compared to lymphocytes, and it
					stains in a bluish-gray color. Monocytes have the capacity to leave the
					bloodstream and enter tissue, where they mature into cells called
					<term>macrophages</term>. Macrophages phagocytose (phagocytize) microbes and tissue debris.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
