<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_31">
	<head>
		<title>Veins of the Head and Neck</title>
		<objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="describe_structure_function_veins_head_neck_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The three major vein pairs that drain blood from the head and neck are the <term>internal and external jugular veins</term> and the <term>vertebral veins</term>. The courses
			and interconnections of these veins are significantly different than the arterial system that supplies the head. Most of the veins that
			drain the brain empty into the dural sinuses. These large, interconnected chambers lie
			between the dura mater layers.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/abfdiagrams6.png" width="600"></image>
		<section>
			<title>Dural Sinuses</title>
			<body>
				<p>The superior and inferior sagittal sinuses drain blood from the brain. The
						<term>superior sagittal sinus</term> drains the cerebral hemispheres,
					meninges, and cranial bones. The much smaller <term>inferior sagittal sinus
					</term>receives blood from the <term>great cerebral vein</term>, which drains
					deeper parts of the brain. The <term>straight sinus</term> is formed by the
					merger of the inferior sagittal sinus and great cerebral vein. It drains the
					cerebellum. The <term>transverse sinuses</term> drain the cerebrum, cerebellum,
					and cranial bones. Near the temporal bone, the transverse sinuses become the
						<term>sigmoid sinuses</term>, which terminate in the internal jugular veins.
					The <term>cavernous sinuses</term> collect blood from the <term>ophthalmic veins
					</term>that drain the orbits, the <term>cerebral veins</term> that drain the
					cerebral hemispheres, and the <term>facial veins</term> that drain the nose and
					upper lip. Cranial nerves III, IV, and V (ophthalmic and maxillary branches) and
					the internal carotid arteries pass through the cavernous sinuses.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Jugular Veins</title>
			<body>
				<p>The <term>internal jugular veins</term> originate from the dural venous sinuses and drain most
					blood from the brain. They collect blood from deep face and neck vein branches
					of the facial and <term>superficial temporal veins</term>. The right and left
					internal jugular veins merge with the subclavian veins to form the right and
					left brachiocephalic veins.</p>
				<p>The <term>external jugular veins</term> are superficial veins (right and left) that empty into
					the subclavian veins. When venous pressure increases (e.g., during coughing or
					conditions such as congestive heart failure), these veins bulge conspicuously at
					the side of the neck. They drain the scalp, as well as superficial and deep
					regions of the face. Deep structures of the neck are also drained by the
					vertebral veins. Right and left vertebral veins run through transverse foramina
					of the first six cervical vertebrae before exiting at the sixth cervical
					vertebrae and entering the brachiocephalic veins at the base of the neck.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_veins_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_structure_function_veins_digt_03" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
