<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_11">
	<head>
		<title>Muscle Cells of the Heart</title>
		<objref idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="contrast_action_potentions_cardiac_skeletal_cells_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<!--<p><em style="highlight">[NOTE: Link to muscular system cardio muscle.]</em></p>-->
		<section>
			<title>Conducting Heart Cells</title>
			<body>
				<p>There are three types of cells that comprise the myocardium: the pacemaker, the
					conducting, and the myocardial cells. The <term>pacemaker cells</term>, also
					called the nodal cells, are the cells found within the sinoatrial (SA) and the
					atrioventricular (AV) nodes. These cells spontaneously depolarize, creating the
					action potentials (or electrical impulses) that start the signal for atrial and
					ventricular contraction. Specialized <term>conducting cells</term> carry the
					action potentials at a high rate from the SA to the AV node, and then from the
					AV node to the rest of the ventricular cells. Some of these specialized
					conducting cells have been named after the people who described them. For
					example, once action potentials move through the septum in the proximal part of
					the AV node, they enter the <term>Bundle of His</term> and then move rapidly
					through the <term>Purkinje fibers</term> that terminate in the ventricles.
					Conducting cells are necessary to coordinate contraction by disseminating the
					electrical signal through the ventricles.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Pacemaker Depolarization</title>
			<body>
				<p>The pacemaker cells in the nodes have the ability to spontaneously depolarize
					until they reach their threshold value. In this way, they can produce action
					potentials without the aid of nerves, neurotransmitters or neighboring cells.
					Each of the action potentials they generate spreads through the heart and
					results in a contraction. Because the SA node spontaneously depolarizes at a
					faster rate than the AV node it typically paces the heart, a process called
					overdrive suppression.</p>
				<p>These pacemaker action potentials have significant differences from the action
					potentials produced by skeletal muscle cells. Skeletal muscle cells have a
					baseline or resting membrane potential that remains relatively constant and
					highly negative (typically about -90 mV). The more negative potential of
					skeletal muscle cells is due to their sustained permeability to potassium in the
					resting state. Pacemaker cells have a much more positive resting potential (-55
					mV), as they are a little less permeable to potassium in their resting state.
					Their resting potential also slowly changes as the cells depolarize toward
					threshold. This spontaneous depolarization, which occurs in the prepotential
					period is due to the slow closure of their potassium channels (K+ channels) and
					the slow opening of <term>T-type calcium channels</term> (Ca++ channels).
					Remember that K+ channels allow for the efflux of potassium out of the cell,
					which increases the negative charges along the inside of the cell membrane,
					opposing depolarization. As these channels close, fewer positively charged ions
					are leaving the cell. At the same time, other positive ions are entering the
					cell (such as Calcium), allowing the cell to slowly become more positive.</p>
				<p>The calcium channels allow for the influx of calcium from the extracellular
					space. As these positive ions accumulate, it contributes to the rising membrane
					potential. This sets the stage for threshold potential to be reached and an
					action potential to fire.</p>
				<p>When the threshold voltage is achieved, the action potential is initiated. In
					skeletal muscle cells and neurons, the rapid depolarization at the beginning of
					the action potential is due to the opening of voltage-gated sodium channels;
					however, in cardiac pacemaker cells, these channels do not open. Instead,
						<term>L-type calcium channels</term> open, allowing calcium to rapidly flow
					into the cells to generate the upstroke. This dependence on external calcium to
					generate an action potential instead of sodium is an important distinction
					between cardiac and skeletal or neuronal cells.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Repolarization</title>
			<body>
				<p>After the rapid depolarization, the L-type calcium channels start closing, which
					begins the process of <term>repolarization</term>, in which the membrane
					potential becomes negative again. Along with the closing calcium channels,
					potassium channels also open during the phase of repolarization. Cardiac
					pacemaker cells do not hyperpolarize as do skeletal muscle cells or neurons. The
					cycle is then repeated in which the potassium channels slowly close and the
					calcium channels slowly open until an action potential is initiated. And so the
					cycle goes; prepotential period, action potential, and repeat for our entire
					lives.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Myocardial Cells</title>
			<body>
				<p>The third type of cell in the heart is the <term>myocardial cell</term>.
					Comprising 99% of the mass of the heart, these cells are the <term>cardiac
						muscle</term> cells that contract and carry out the flow generating function
					of the heart. Without these cells, there would be no contraction.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_lbd_01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="identify_three_kinds_cells_myocardium_digt_01" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
