<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u9_m3_levels_org_module_review"><head><title>Levels of Organization Review and Assessment unused</title></head><body><p id="ae4bff4ff214426eb2ff51fd583da9af">Before taking the quiz below, consider again the learning objectives for this module. Could you demonstrate each of these objectives? If so, you will be ready for the assessment below. If not, consider reviewing content related to these objectives before attempting the assessment.</p><ul id="e5bccbf48ed04478a2d71f23c634a665"><li><p id="aef7eff194d30417d98fbcd97f01afaac">Describe the overall composition of plasma, including the major types of plasma proteins, their functions, and where in the body they are produced.</p></li><li><p id="ae62c7d5efd5f4c38a6cdc5397ebde778">Describe the phases of hemostasis.</p></li><li><p id="ae74baf2393c04250bb7f27432013a470">Identify the microscopic features of erythrocytes (red blood cells), the five types of leukocytes (white blood cells), and thrombocytes (platelets).</p></li><li><p id="aaef08621c0b743e6bbaec425369759d9">Identify the function of red blood cells and describe the life cycle of red blood cells, including how and where iron and heme are recycled, as well as the resulting breakdown products.</p></li><li><p id="afe91c53ae8c7415f89a64a85e01a5e8e">Describe the functions for each of the five major types of leukocytes as well as the two major subtypes of lymphocytes (T and B).</p></li><li><p id="ac9d0476ed7534dcdb5d47b583c518f20">Describe the structure and function of platelets.</p></li><li><p id="ae329f0a089444e76a8216293aec5da1a">Describe the basic process of hematopoiesis, where it occurs, and the significance of the pluripotent stem cell (hemocytoblast) in the process.</p></li><li><p id="abc95e3dc9d2748aa9c05d14c9348c618">Identify the types of cells associated with blood vessels and relate them to the different properties of blood vessels.</p></li><li><p id="af367df8cd6254abea44ade3fa1b12395">Identify the three kinds of cells that make up the myocardium and describe the role of each in the physiology of muscle contraction.</p></li><li><p id="adf1b68d67a354ce88b14d61a02c56d1f">Describe the features of blood that give it the characteristics of a connective tissue.</p></li><li><p id="ad602f76b99bd4444a65cdb16c1749094">Describe the properties of the vessel wall layers (tunica interna, media, externa) and associate each with the function of different vessel types.</p></li><li><p id="adc5bc24bf7ae43c79c77235687f195fe">Describe the anatomical structures of the heart and major blood vessels entering and leaving the heart. Relate the features of these structures to blood flow into, out of, and through the heart.</p></li><li><p id="aaf1a28ef779f419da39d3cc796197b78">Describe the anatomy of the aorta and its major branches and relate it with their functions.</p></li><li><p id="ae27f08ca44834cd99c9fb4335072ef15">Describe the anatomical structure of the arteries in the body and relate it with their function.</p></li><li><p id="aed03f64aea8e423ebeb242a1ba93751a">Describe common changes of the circulatory system related to aging.</p></li><li><p id="af41eb235b02f4b6dbc13299ec424e08c">Describe the structure and function of arterioles, metarterioles, capillaries, and venules.</p></li><li><p id="ade6c2175b1dc47379effb49465e82a74">Describe the anatomical structure of the veins in the body and relate it with their function.</p></li></ul><activity idref="_u9_cardio_levels_of_org_quiz" purpose="quiz" /><activity idref="_u9_m3_levels_org_feedback" purpose="myresponse" /></body></workbook_page>
