<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u9_m3_CardioLevelOrg_07">
	<head>
		<title>White Blood Cell Disorders</title>
		<objref idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_OBJ"/>
		<!--<objref idref="identify_leukocytosis_leukopenia_leukemia_OBJ"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>There are three types of disorders that affect WBCs: leukocytosis, leukopenia, and
			leukemia. <term>Leukocytosis</term> is a condition characterized by an abnormally high
			number of mature WBCs. A common type of leukocytic illness is
			<term>mononucleosis</term>, in which monocyte numbers greatly increase as a result of a
			viral infection. Signs of this condition include enlarged spleen and lymph nodes.
				<term>Leukopenia</term> is an abnormally low level of WBCs and commonly occurs with
			the use of steroids such as cortisone. Like leukocytosis, <term>leukemia</term> is also
			characterized by a high number of WBCs; however, this high number is a result of
			cancerous proliferation of immature, nonfunctional WBCs.</p>
		<p><term>Neutropenia</term> is a condition in which neutrophils are abnormally low in the
			body. Because these granulocytes play an important role in fighting infection,
			individuals with neutropenia are more susceptible to infections. These infections are
			also more likely to develop into life-threatening conditions. Neutropenia often occurs
			in people undergoing chemotherapy or radiation therapy. Physicians may suspect
			neutropenia in patients who frequently develop infections.</p>
		<p>In order to test for neutropenia, a sample of blood is drawn. If the neutrophil count
			falls below 500 cells per microliter, then the risk of infection increases, and the
			ability of the body to fight infection decreases. There are various reasons why the
			number of neutrophils decreases in the body. For instance, bacterial infections and
			certain drugs can destroy neutrophils at a faster rate than they are produced by the
			bone marrow. In the case of an autoimmune disease, people can produce antibodies that
			target neutrophils, resulting in a neutrophil deficiency. Disorders in which the spleen
			becomes enlarged may result in neutropenia because the spleen traps and destroys
			neutrophils. There are also certain conditions that affect the bone marrow producing
			neutrophils in the body, such as cancer, viral infections (influenza), bacterial
			infections (tuberculosis), or vitamin deficiencies. Certain drugs and toxins can also
			decrease the red bone marrows’ ability to produce neutrophils.</p>
		<p>There are two types of neutropenia: acute and chronic. Neutropenia does not present any
			specific symptoms; it is usually diagnosed when a patient has frequently occurring and
			unusual infections. A physician will confirm his or her suspicions by ordering a
			complete blood cell count to identify the problem. While neutropenia is expected in
			patients undergoing chemotherapy or radiation therapy, if the etiology of neutropenia is
			unclear, doctors will obtain a bone marrow sample using a needle. The bone marrow sample
			is viewed under a microscope to determine the problem. Once the problem has been
			diagnosed, treatment depends on the origin or cause (etiology) and severity. If the
			problem is drug induced, then cessation of the drug is an option. Viral infections that
			cause neutropenia (e.g., influenza) are a transient problem, and neutropenia will be
			resolved once the infection has abated. When neutropenia occurs because of an underlying
			disorder such as leukemia, the patient’s neutropenic condition may improve after cancer
			treatments. However, a bone marrow transplant may be used to treat more serious forms of
			cancer, aplastic anemia, and leukemia.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_lbd_02" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="describe_functions_leukocytes_lymphocytes_digt_02" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
