<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_spirometry_airflow_lungs"><title>Tutor</title><question id="age_fev1fvc_ratio"><body><p>As a person ages the FEV1/FVC ratio <input_ref input="A" />. This would lead to <input_ref input="B" /> efficient movement of air into the lungs. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">increases</choice><choice value="two">decreases</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">more</choice><choice value="two">less</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="apply_FEV1_FVC_ratio" /><response name="increases" input="A" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The FEV1/FVC ratio is an important indicator of the efficiency of gas exchange. As a person ages there are changes in the respiratory muscles and anatomical composition of the lungs. This results in a decrease in the FEV1/FVC ratio. </feedback></response><response name="decreases" input="A" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The normal ratio should be between 75%-80%, but in elderly people it can be as low as 65% as a result of physiological changes that occur as the body ages. </feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="apply_FEV1_FVC_ratio" /><response name="more" input="B" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The FEV1/FVC ratio is an important indicator of the efficiency of gas exchange. As the ratio decreases so does the efficiency. </feedback></response><response name="less" input="B" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Ventilation is an important part of respiration. The lower the FEV1/FVC ratio the less efficiently the air is being exchanged. This low efficiency can result in the misdiagnosis of an obstructive pulmonary disease. </feedback></response></part></question><question id="disease_fev1fvc_ratio"><body><p>A person suffering from emphysema, and obstructive disease, would see a <input_ref input="C" /> in their FEV1 because of an <input_ref input="D" /> of airway resistance to the expiratory flow.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">increase</choice><choice value="two">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="D" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">increase</choice><choice value="two">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="apply_FEV1_FVC_ratio" /><response name="increase" input="C" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In an obstructive disease like emphysema or COPD, the rate of airflow exiting the lungs is decreased as a result of an obstruction in the airway. A bronchodilator may be prescribed to help relieve these symptoms. </feedback></response><response name="decrease" input="C" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. In an obstructive disease like emphysema or COPD, occurs when something makes it difficult for a person to exhale. This will decrease the FEV1 which will result in a lower FEV1/FVC ratio. </feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="apply_FEV1_FVC_ratio" /><response name="increase" input="D" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. An obstructive disease is one that occurs when a person has a hard time exhaling because of increased resistance in the airways. This can be the result of airway narrowing or damage.</feedback></response><response name="decrease" input="D" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An obstructive disease occurs when there is an “obstruction” either a narrowing of the airways or damage to the airways. This obstruction results in an increase resistance to airflow. </feedback></response></part></question><question id="resp_distress"><body><p>A baby suffering from infant respiratory distress syndrome or an adult suffering from tuberculosis ,both restrictive diseases ,would see a <input_ref input="E" />in their FEV1/FVC ratio because the amount of air exiting the lungs decreases <input_ref input="F" /> than the speed of the air moving out of the lungs. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="E" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">increases</choice><choice value="two">decreases</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="F" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">more</choice><choice value="two">less</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="apply_FEV1_FVC_ratio" /><response name="increases" input="E" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The ratio can stay the same but in some cases increase because in a restrictive disease the lungs are less compliant and can hold a lower volume of air. </feedback></response><response name="decreases" input="E" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The ratio will stay the same or increase because the rate of airflow may decrease but will not decrease as much as the forced expiratory capacity. In a restrictive disease the lungs are less compliant which decrease the volume more than the rate of exhalation.</feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="apply_FEV1_FVC_ratio" /><response name="more" input="F" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Although both the rate and volume will decrease, the volume of air decreases faster which can actually result in a higher ratio. In a restrictive disease the lung is prevented (restricted) from fully expanding and filling. This reduced a patients total lung capacity. </feedback></response><response name="less" input="F" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The amount of air leaving the lungs may be slightly impaired but, is not as reduced as the volume of the lungs. In a restrictive disease the lung is prevented (restricted) from fully expanding and filling. This reduced a patients total lung capacity. </feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
