<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_affects_on_pulmonary_ventilation"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="smooth_muscle_constricted"><body>Why do the accessory muscles of respiration seem to be straining during an asthma attack?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Because the smooth muscle of the bronchioles has dilated increasing the resistance of airflow into the lungs.</choice><choice value="B">Because the smooth muscle of the bronchioles has constricted increasing the resistance of airflow into the lungs.</choice><choice value="C">Because there is an increase in resistance of the respiratory zone during an asthma attack.</choice><choice value="D">Because there is a decrease in resistance of the conducting zone during an asthma attack.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="smooth_muscle_constricted_p1"><skillref idref="predict_affects_increased_resistance" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. During an asthma attack the smooth muscle of the bronchioles has constricted which will increase the resistance of airflow into the lungs. Bronchodilators are used to treat this condition.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. During an asthma attack the smooth muscle of the bronchioles has constricted which will increase the resistance of airflow into the lungs. When this happens a person now needs to generate much larger changes in intrapulmonary pressure to maintain a normal flow rate of air during breathing which will require the muscles of respiration to work harder.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. During an asthma attack the increase in resistance occurs in the conducting zone of the bronchial tree.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. During an asthma attack there is an increase of resistance in the conducting zone as the bronchial tubes constrict.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="elasticity_surface_tension"><body>Compliance of the lungs is dependant on what two properties of lung tissue?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The dilation of the smooth muscle tissue and the resistance in the conducting zone.</choice><choice value="B">The constriction of smooth muscle tissue and the accumulation of mucus in the airways.</choice><choice value="C">The constriction of smooth muscle tissue and elasticity of the connective tissue.</choice><choice value="D">Elasticity of the connective tissue and alveolar surface tension.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="elasticity_surface_tension_p1"><skillref idref="describe_compliance_lungs" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The property of resistance is dependent on the dilation and constriction of the smooth muscle tissue of the bronchial tubes.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The constriction of smooth muscle tissue and accumulation of mucus will both increase the resistance of the airway.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The constriction of the smooth muscle tissue will increase the the resistance of the air ways not the compliance. The elasticity of the lung tissue will affect the compliance.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Compliance is going to determine how much effort is required to breathe. Both the elasticity of the connective tissue and the alveolar surface tension are going to play a role in this.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
