<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_inhalation"><title>Tutor</title><page><question id="respiratory_inhalation_q1"><body><p>Normal inspiration is a <input_ref input="A" /> process that primarily relies on the <input_ref input="B" /> of the <input_ref input="C" />. By <input_ref input="D" /> the volume of the thoracic cavity, the pressure <input_ref input="E" /> allowing air to <input_ref input="F" /> the lungs.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">passive</choice><choice value="two">active</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">contraction</choice><choice value="two">relaxation</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">diaphragm</choice><choice value="two">external intercostals</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="D" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">increasing</choice><choice value="two">decreasing</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="E" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">increase</choice><choice value="two">decrease</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="F" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">enter</choice><choice value="two">exit</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="describe_process_inspiration" /><response name="passive" input="A" match="one"><feedback>Incorrect. Passive means that the muscles are relaxing which does not require energy.</feedback></response><response name="active" input="A" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Active means that the muscles are contracting which requires energy.</feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture and that volume and pressure are inversely related. </hint></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="describe_process_inspiration" /><response name="contraction" input="B" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. When muscles such as the diaphragm and external intercostals contract they become shorter which increases the volume of the thoracic cavity. </feedback></response><response name="relaxation" input="B" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. When muscles such as the diaphragm and the external intercostals relax they return to their original length which decreases the volume of the thoracic cavity.</feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture and that volume and pressure are inversely related. </hint></part><part id="p3"><skillref idref="describe_process_inspiration" /><response name="diaphragm" input="C" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The diaphragm is the muscle that is primarily responsible for inspiration. The diaphragm will contract to increase the volume of the thoracic cavity.</feedback></response><response name="external_intercostals" input="C" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. Although the external intercostals play an important role in increasing the volume of the thoracic cavity during inspiration, they are not the primary muscle.</feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture and that volume and pressure are inversely related. </hint></part><part id="p4"><skillref idref="describe_process_inspiration" /><response name="increasing" input="D" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. As the diaphragm and external intercostals contract they shorten and increase the volume of the thoracic cavity.</feedback></response><response name="decreasing" input="D" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. As the diaphragm and external intercostals contract they shorten which actually increases the volume of the thoracic cavity because the external intercostals pull the chest walls out and the diaphragm flattens also increasing the volume of the thorax.</feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture and that volume and pressure are inversely related. </hint></part><part id="p5"><skillref idref="describe_process_inspiration" /><response name="increase" input="E" match="one"><feedback>Incorrect. Pressure and volume have an inverse relationship. As the volume increases the pressure will decrease. </feedback></response><response name="decrease" input="E" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Pressure and volume have an inverse relationship. As the volume increases the pressure will decrease.</feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture and that volume and pressure are inversely related. </hint></part><part id="p6"><skillref idref="describe_process_inspiration" /><response name="enter" input="F" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Air will flow from an area of high pressure to an area of low pressure. By lowering the pressure of the thoracic cavity below the atmospheric pressure air can enter the lungs.</feedback></response><response name="exit" input="F" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. Air will flow from an area of high pressure to an area of low pressure. By lowering the pressure of the thoracic cavity below the atmospheric pressure air can enter the lungs not exit.</feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture and that volume and pressure are inversely related. </hint></part></question></page><page><content><p>Based on what you know about the physiology of normal inspiration predict whether the following situation would inhibit normal inspiration or allow for forced inspiration (the process of inhaling more than normal). </p></content><question id="inspiration_pregnancy"><body><p>Pregnancy- <input_ref input="H" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="H" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">inhibit normal inspiration</choice><choice value="two">forced inspiration</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="inspiration_pregnancy_p1"><skillref idref="apply_process_inspiration" /><response name="inhibit_normal_inspiration" input="H" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. During pregnancy the organs are forced upward and can inhibit the ability of the diaphragm to contract and flatten. This reduces the ability of the thoracic cavity to increase in volume.</feedback></response><response name="forced_inspiration" input="H" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. Forced inspiration will allow the body to take increase the volume of the thoracic cavity more than it is during normal inspiration. During pregnancy the organs are forced upward and decrease the volume of the thoracic cavity. </feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture. Inspiration can be inhibited by situations that prevents the chest cavity from expanding. Inspiration can be increased by situations that increase the volume of the chest cavity. </hint></part></question><question id="inspiration_mucscle"><body><p>Contraction of the sternocleidomastoid muscle.<input_ref input="I" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="I" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">inhibit normal inspiration</choice><choice value="two">forced inspiration</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="inspiration_mucscle_p1"><skillref idref="apply_process_inspiration" /><response name="inhibit_normal_inspiration" input="I" match="one"><feedback>Incorrect. Contraction of the sternocleidomastoid muscle will elevate the sternum, also known as the “breastbone”. Which will result in an increase of volume in the thoracic cavity. This will allow more air to flow into the lungs not less.</feedback></response><response name="forced_inspiration" input="I" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Contraction of the sternocleidomastoid muscle will elevate the sternum, also known as the “breastbone”. Which will result in an increase of volume in the thoracic cavity as the volume increases above the normal volume, the pressure will decrease even further allowing more air to flow into the lungs. </feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture. Inspiration can be inhibited by situations that prevents the chest cavity from expanding. Inspiration can be increased by situations that increase the volume of the chest cavity. </hint></part></question><question id="inspiration_obesity"><body><p>Obesity-<input_ref input="J" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="J" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">inhibit normal inspiration</choice><choice value="two">forced inspiration</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="inspiration_obesity_p1"><skillref idref="apply_process_inspiration" /><response name="inhibit_normal_inspiration" input="J" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Obesity results in the abdominal organs being forced upward and can inhibit the ability of the diaphragm to contract and flatten. This reduces the ability of the thoracic cavity to increase in volume.</feedback></response><response name="forced_inspiration" input="J" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. Forced inspiration will allow the body to take increase the volume of the thoracic cavity more than it is during normal inspiration. Obesity results in the abdominal organs being forced upward and decrease the volume of the thoracic cavity. </feedback></response><hint>Remember to refer to the picture. Inspiration can be inhibited by situations that prevents the chest cavity from expanding. Inspiration can be increased by situations that increase the volume of the chest cavity. </hint></part></question></page></assessment>
