<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_smokers"><title>Tutor</title><question id="smokers_cough"><body><p>Consider what occurs to cause &quot;Smoker’s cough&quot;. Based on this description, the function of the cilia is to move <input_ref input="A" /> up and out of the lungs. If the cilia are paralyzed or destroyed by chemicals in cigarettes the body must <input_ref input="B" />to remove mucus from the lungs. If mucus is not removed from the lungs, microorganisms can grow in it and lead to <input_ref input="C" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">mucus</choice><choice value="two">air</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">cough</choice><choice value="two">sneeze</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">COPD</choice><choice value="two">pneumonia</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="describe_function_cilia" /><response name="mucus" input="A" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The function of the cilia is to create an escalator that moves mucus from the lungs up into the trachea. </feedback></response><response name="air" input="A" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Air moves in and out of the lungs because of the differences in pressures between inside of the lungs and outside the lungs. </feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="identify_function_coughing" /><response name="cough" input="B" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. If the cilia are paralyzed or destroyed the body still needs to remove the mucus from the lungs. The reflex of coughing will provide the physical force to remove the mucus.</feedback></response><response name="sneeze" input="B" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. A sneeze is usually caused by an irritation of the nasal mucosa and is not used as a mechanism to remove mucus from deep in the lungs. </feedback></response></part><part id="p3"><skillref idref="differentiate_respiratory_disorders" /><response name="copd" input="C" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. COPD, is Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease is a broad category for diseases such as emphysema, and chronic bronchitis. These disease are characterized by obstruction of the airways and limitation to airflow. </feedback></response><response name="pneumonia" input="C" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The accumulation of mucus in the lungs can lead increased microbial growth. If the mucus cannot be moved out of the lungs then the bacteria can grow and cause disease such as pneumonia. </feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
