<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_conducting_respiratory_zone"><title>Tutor</title><question id="conducting_respiratory_zone"><body><p><input_ref input="A" />respiration includes ventilation which is the movement of air into the body and the movement of air back out of the body. The channel for moving air into the lungs and back out is referred to as the <input_ref input="B" />.The location where gas exchange occurs is called the <input_ref input="C" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">External</choice><choice value="two">Internal</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">conducting zone</choice><choice value="two">respiratory zone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">conducting zone</choice><choice value="two">respiratory zone</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="p1"><skillref idref="define_external_respiration" /><response name="external" input="A" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. External respiration is the movement of atmosphere to the lungs and from the lungs back to the atmosphere. External indicates exchange between the body and the external environment. </feedback></response><response name="internal" input="A" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. Internal respiration is the exchange of gas between the blood and tissues of the body. Internal indicates that it is occurring on the inside of the body.</feedback></response></part><part id="p2"><skillref idref="identify_conducting_respiratory_zones" /><response name="conducting_zone" input="B" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The conducting zone provides a passageway or a conduit for air to move into the alveoli of the lungs. The conducting zone begins with the nose and the mouth and continues through the larger divisions of the bronchial tree. </feedback></response><response name="respiratory_zone" input="B" match="two"><feedback>Incorrect. The respiratory zone is where the exchange of gas can occur between the lungs and the blood. </feedback></response></part><part id="p3"><skillref idref="identify_conducting_respiratory_zones" /><response name="conducting_zone" input="C" match="one"><feedback>Incorrect. The conducting zone provides a passageway or a conduit for air to move into the alveoli of the lungs. It is known as the conducting zone because there is no exchange of gas here, only transportation.</feedback></response><response name="respiratory_zone" input="C" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The respiratory zone is where the exchange of gas can occur between the lungs and the blood. This includes some of the terminal bronchioles but primarily the alveoli. </feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
