<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_tonsils"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="pharyngeal_tonsils"><body>Which of the three pairs of tonsils shown above are commonly referred to as the “adenoids” ?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Pharyngeal Tonsils</choice><choice value="B">Lingual Tonsils</choice><choice value="C">Palatine Tonsils</choice></multiple_choice><part id="pharyngeal_tonsils_p1"><skillref idref="identify_adenoids" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The pharyngeal tonsils located in the nasopharynx are commonly called the adenoids.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The lingual tonsils are located on the base of the tongue and are named “lingual” in reference to their location on the tongue.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The palatine tonsils are located in the oropharynx and are visible when someone opens their mouth wide.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="palatine_tonsils"><body>Which of the three pairs of tonsils shown above are commonly removed in during a tonsillectomy?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Pharyngeal Tonsils</choice><choice value="B">Lingual Tonsils</choice><choice value="C">Palatine Tonsils</choice></multiple_choice><part id="palatine_tonsils_p1"><skillref idref="identify_palatine_tonsils" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The pharyngeal tonsils can be removed in an adenoid removal surgery that may take place at the same time as the palatine tonsils which are removed in a tonsillectomy. </feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The lingual tonsils are located on the base of the tongue and are very rarely infected to the point that they need to be removed. </feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The palatine tonsils are located in the oropharynx and are visible when someone opens their mouth wide. These tonsils can become chronically inflamed and need to be removed. </feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
