<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="explain_wrinkles"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>One cosmetic treatment for wrinkles is Botox. This neurotoxin helps temporarily remove wrinkles caused by repetitive motion, such as crow&apos;s feet. Which of the following explains why this treatment is only temporary and why it cannot fix other types of wrinkles?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Botox can decrease the tension of underlying muscles but not repair the damaged extracellular matrix proteins.</choice><choice value="B">Botox can signal the fibroblast to secrete more extracellular matrix, replacing the damaged fibers.</choice><choice value="C">Botox can signal to the muscles to stretch the epidermis back out.</choice><choice value="D">Botox can reduce the damage by increasing production of collagen.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="d614fb9087ab4b059d0419ff006a253d"><skillref idref="explain_wrinkles_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The toxin will cause paralysis of the facial muscles and reduce wrinkles, but it does not fix the damage, so it is only temporary.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Botox does not affect the fibroblast cells, it inhibits the neural impulses. Fixing the damaged extracellular proteins would fix the problem permanently.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Botox can induce paralysis of the muscles, which does not stretch the epidermis out.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Botox is a toxin that paralyzes the muscles. The fibroblasts are responsible for making more extracellular proteins.</feedback></response><hint>Botox only temporarily immobilizes underlying muscles.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
