<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="melanocyte_function_digt"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Some people see freckles appear on their nose and cheeks during the summertime and fade during the winter. What would cause this?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Uneven distribution of melanocytes reacting to UV radiation</choice><choice value="B">Uneven production of melanin in response to temperature</choice><choice value="C">A lower amount of melanin being transferred to the keratinocytes in response to UV radiation</choice><choice value="D">Freckles cannot just appear during the summer and fade during the winter</choice></multiple_choice><part id="fe31abe93cae4746a76c1e4fa7266294"><skillref idref="melanocyte_function_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. With sun exposure, all melanocytes will produce more melanin in response to UV radiation from the sun, but because melanocytes can be clustered in certain areas of the skin, this distribution becomes more noticeable, producing more melanin in areas with more melanocytes than in the surrounding areas that have fewer melanocytes.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Even though these melanocytes may produce more melanin, they are not producing it in response to temperature.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In the local area of the freckle, more melanin is being transferred to the keratinocytes.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Although some people genetically inherit the trait for freckles that are present all the time, some freckles can appear in the summer because of the radiation and disappear in the winter.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
