<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="nail_structure"><title>tutor</title><page id="f1690a90884f47ceb44bcc25b7b9bfaa"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><question id="q1"><body><p id="ae2ed66b2aeb2438ebba93fb546c0cce0">Onychocryptosis is more commonly known as an ingrown toenail. The &quot;onycho&quot; prefix means &quot;nail&quot; and &quot;cryptosis&quot; means&quot;hidden.&quot; This uncomfortable condition can occur if people incorrectly cut their nails. Nails consist of several layers of dead keratinized cells that continually need to be trimmed because:</p></body><multiple_choice id="e26cc97983284edc884458e863bc9595" labels="false" select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The matrix continues to produce new cells for the nail folds.</choice><choice value="B">The matrix continues to produce new cells for the nail root.</choice><choice value="C">The nail root produces new cells for the cuticle.</choice><choice value="D">The lunula contains live reproducing cells.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i5a943a305f6b4993a6d1db80bf3f9ff2"><skillref idref="nail_structure_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback><p id="aae4b49b185b9468fa29b13424822e78c">Incorrect. The matrix produces new cells for the nail bed; the nail folds are part of the surrounding epidermis.</p></feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback><p id="af25075b1371247ef8b75f2062924f009">Correct. The matrix continues to produce new cells as part of the nail root and this results in nail length continuing to grow.</p></feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback><p id="aa67fc8d8f28b49e48028ecc9a8b8021b">Incorrect. The nail root&apos;s matrix produces new cells for the nail bed; the cuticle is part of the surrounding epidermis.</p></feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback><p id="adf6d1db4272e4a13af985cff5ef53d54">Incorrect. The lunula is near the matrix and is composed of recently divided cells that have not flattened and are producing keratin, making it less transparent.</p></feedback></response><hint><p id="aac26fdce779645d4a803dcecac5c37dd">The nail body itself is composed of dead cells, but what is in the nail root and matrix?</p></hint></part></question></page></assessment>
