<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="sweat_glands"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="q1"><body>Sweat produced by apocrine sweat glands contains water, salt, and other solutes. When most people think about sweating, they think about smelling bad. Sweat itself, however, does not smell, so why do people smell bad after they have been sweating?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Sweat contains a microbe-killing compound that creates this odor.</choice><choice value="B">Microbes on your skin break down fats and create this odor.</choice><choice value="C">The salt interacts with chemicals on your skin and creates this odor.</choice><choice value="D">Merocrine glands secrete other things besides sweat that creates this odor.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="i728cd5f5ea0a48bbbac71e902b7c2a5d"><skillref idref="sweat_glands_SKILL" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Eccrine glands secrete a microbe-killing compound, but it is the sweat from apocrine glands that is typically associated with odor.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Microbes live on your skin and when they break down the fats in the apocrine secretions that mix with sweat, waste is created, and it has an odor.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect.The salt does not interact to produce any odor; in fact, it may be antibacterial and help reduce the odor.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Eccrine glands secrete sweat for regulating body temperature; apocrine glands secrete the fatty acids that bacteria metabolize.</feedback></response><hint>Apocrine glands become active during puberty and secrete a sweat with more fatty acids.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
