<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_hemoglobin_oxygen_dis"><title>Tutor</title><content><p>Based on the situation described in each question below, decide whether the oxygen-hemoglobin dissociation curve will shift to the left or to the right.</p></content><question id="increase_temp"><body><p>There is an increase in temperature. Is this a <input_ref input="A" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">left shift</choice><choice value="two">right shift</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="increase_temp_p1"><skillref idref="predict_shift_oxygen-hemoglobin_dissociation" /><response name="left_shift" input="A" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. An increase in temperature can be caused by cells that are actively using energy, which means they need more oxygen to replace the energy they just used. So, the hemoglobin’s affinity would decrease and hemoglobin would not bind the oxygen tighter. </feedback></response><response name="right_shift" input="A" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Cells that are using energy or are metabolically active produce heat while they are converting nutrients to energy. This raises the temperature of the area around these cell which require more oxygen to keep making energy. So, the hemoglobin’s affinity will decrease so the oxygen can diffuse into the cells. </feedback></response><hint>A left shift means there is an increased affinity for oxygen and the hemoglobin will bind to it tighter. A right shift means there is a reduced affinity and the hemoglobin will release the oxygen more readily.</hint></part></question><question id="decrease_ph"><body><p>There is a decrease in pH. Is this a <input_ref input="B" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">left shift</choice><choice value="two">right shift</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="decrease_ph_p1"><skillref idref="predict_shift_oxygen-hemoglobin_dissociation" /><response name="left_shift" input="B" match="one"><feedback>Incorrect. A decrease in pH can occur because cells that are using energy or are metabolically active produce carbon dioxide while they are converting nutrients to energy. The more active a cell is the more carbon dioxide it produces the lower the pH drops. So, the hemoglobin’s affinity would decrease and hemoglobin would not bind the oxygen tighter.</feedback></response><response name="right_shift" input="B" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Cells that are using energy or are metabolically active produce carbon dioxide while they are converting nutrients to energy. This lowers the pH of the area around these cell which require more oxygen to keep making energy. So, the hemoglobin’s affinity will decrease so the oxygen can diffuse into the cells. </feedback></response><hint>A left shift means there is an increased affinity for oxygen and the hemoglobin will bind to it tighter. A right shift means there is a reduced affinity and the hemoglobin will release the oxygen more readily.</hint></part></question><question id="decrease_carbon_dioxide"><body><p>There is a decrease in carbon dioxide. <input_ref input="C" />. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">left shift</choice><choice value="two">right shift</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="decrease_carbon_dioxide_p1"><skillref idref="predict_shift_oxygen-hemoglobin_dissociation" /><response name="left_shift" input="C" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Cells that are using energy or are metabolically active produce carbon dioxide while they are converting nutrients to energy. A decrease in carbon dioxide production would indicate that the cell is not as metabolically active so does not require as much oxygen. A lower amount of carbon dioxide will also increase the pH which will increase hemoglobin’s affinity for oxygen. </feedback></response><response name="right_shift" input="C" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Cells that are using energy or are metabolically active produce carbon dioxide while they are converting nutrients to energy. A decrease in carbon dioxide production would indicate that the cell is not as metabolically active so does not require as much oxygen. A lower amount of carbon dioxide will also increase the pH which will increase hemoglobin’s affinity for oxygen. </feedback></response><hint>A left shift means there is an increased affinity for oxygen and the hemoglobin will bind to it tighter. A right shift means there is a reduced affinity and the hemoglobin will release the oxygen more readily.</hint></part></question></assessment>
