<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_chemical_equation_oxygen"><title>Tutor</title><page><question id="lungs_tissue"><body>HHb + O<sub>2</sub> → HbO Would this process take place in the lungs or in the tissues?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">Lungs</choice><choice value="B">Tissue</choice></multiple_choice><part id="lungs_tissue_p1"><skillref idref="predict_location_process" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. In the lungs, hemoglobin binds to oxygen and becomes oxyhemoglobin in order to transport oxygen to the body tissues.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In the tissues, the oxyhemoglobin release the oxygen into the tissues and becomes hemoglobin.</feedback></response><hint>Consider where oxygen enters the body and where it is used.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="def_arrow_equation"><body><p>HHb + O<sub>2</sub>⇄ HbO<sub>2</sub><input_ref input="A" />.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false"><choice value="one">reversible</choice><choice value="two">irreversible</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="def_arrow_equation_p1"><skillref idref="predict_location_process" /><response name="reversible" input="A" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The arrows pointing in both directions means that under certain conditions this reaction will proceed to the left and under different conditions the reaction will proceed to the right.</feedback></response><response name="irreversible" input="A" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If this chemical reaction was irreversible there would be only a single arrow indicating the direction of the reaction.</feedback></response><hint>Consider where oxygen enters the body and where it is used. </hint></part></question></page><page><question id="restricts_hemoglobin_function"><body><p>Carbon monoxide is a poison that binds to hemoglobin in the following chemical reaction:</p><p>CO + HHb ⇄ COHb</p><p>How would this affect the ability of hemoglobin to do its function?</p></body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">It will prevent the HbO<sub>2</sub> from delivering oxygen to the tissues</choice><choice value="B">It will prevent the HHb from picking up enough oxygen from the lungs</choice><choice value="C">It will permanently bind to the HHb</choice><choice value="D">It will have no effect on the ability of HHb to perform its function.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="restricts_hemoglobin_function_p1"><skillref idref="predict_location_process" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If HbO<sub>2</sub> can be formed then it can deliver oxygen to the tissues.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>HHb binds to CO more readily than it binds to O<sub>2</sub>. So, if CO levels are high enough, HHb will bind the CO molecules and not O<sub>2</sub>.Correct.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. This chemical reaction is reversible if the patient is provided with a high enough concentration of oxygen to displace the CO. Usually 100% oxygen will be administered.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. HHb binds to CO more readily than it binds to O<sub>2</sub>. However, COHb is not able to deliver any oxygen to the tissues.</feedback></response><hint>Review what ⇄ and the abbreviations mean.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
