<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_gas_exchange"><title>Tutor</title><page><question id="air_lungs_partial_pressure"><body><p>Air that enters the lungs from the atmosphere has a <input_ref input="A" /> partial pressure than the air in the alveoli of the lungs. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">higher</choice><choice value="two">lower</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="air_lungs_partial_pressure_p1"><skillref idref="predict_airflow_based_partial_pressure" /><response name="higher" input="A" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. The air entering our lungs at sea level has a partial pressure of 160mmHg which is higher than the partial pressure of air in our lungs which is about 105mmHg.</feedback></response><response name="lower" input="A" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the air entering our lungs had a lower partial pressure of oxygen than the air in the alveoli than oxygen would not diffuse into our lungs from the atmosphere. </feedback></response><hint>Oxygen will move from areas of high concentration or high partial pressure to lower partial pressure.</hint></part></question></page><page><question id="blood_tissues_partial_pressure"><body><p>The air in alveoli of the lungs has a slightly lower partial pressure because gas exchange is occurring with the blood and tissues <input_ref input="B" /> even between breaths.</p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">constantly</choice><choice value="two">intermittently</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="blood_tissues_partial_pressure_p1"><skillref idref="describe_air_pressure_alveoli" /><response name="constantly" input="B" match="one" score="10"><feedback>Correct. We need a continual supply of oxygen to make energy for our cells.</feedback></response><response name="intermittently" input="B" match="two" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Even between breaths the oxygen remaining in our lungs is used as much as possible for cellular respiration. Think about CPR, if there was no oxygen left in the air we breathe out normally we would not be able to perform CPR. </feedback></response><hint>Oxygen is used by our body to convert the energy found in food into ATP which is the form of energy our cells need to function. </hint></part></question></page><page><question id="higher_altitudes_partial_pressure"><body><p>At higher altitudes the partial pressure of oxygen <input_ref input="C" /> which makes it more difficult for enough oxygen to diffuse into the alveoli of the lungs. </p></body><fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="true"><choice value="one">increases</choice><choice value="two">decreases</choice></fill_in_the_blank><part id="higher_altitudes_partial_pressure_p1"><skillref idref="predict_airflow_based_partial_pressure" /><response name="increases" input="C" match="one" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. If the partial pressure of oxygen in the atmosphere increased then it would be easier for more oxygen to diffuse into the alveoli of the lungs because the diffusion gradient would be steeper. </feedback></response><response name="decreases" input="C" match="two" score="10"><feedback>Correct. If the partial pressure of oxygen in the atmosphere decreases then the diffusion gradient between the air in the atmosphere and the air in the alveoli of the lungs becomes shallower and less oxygen will enter the body. </feedback></response><hint>Think of rolling a ball down a hill. The oxygen is the ball, the hill is the difference in partial pressures. The steeper the hill the faster the ball rolls. The steeper the diffusion gradient the faster diffusion occurs.</hint></part></question></page></assessment>
