<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_internal_respiration"><title>tutor</title><page><question id="describe_internal_respiration"><body>Which of the following <em style="bold">does not</em> accurately describe internal respiration?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="true"><choice value="A">The partial pressure of oxygen is lower in the tissues because cells are constantly using it to make energy so oxygen will diffuse from the capillaries into the body tissues.</choice><choice value="B">The partial pressure of oxygen is lower in the capillaries because body tissues are using oxygen to make energy so oxygen will diffuse from the alveoli into the capillaries.</choice><choice value="C">The partial pressure of carbon dioxide is higher in the body tissues and will diffuse into the capillaries.</choice><choice value="D">The partial pressure of carbon dioxide is lower in the capillaries than in the body tissues so it diffuses into the capillaries.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="describe_internal_respiration_p1"><skillref idref="describe_internal_respiration" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Internal respiration relies on the partial pressure of oxygen being lower in the tissues so that oxygen can diffuse from the capillaries into the the tissues.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Internal respiration occurs between the capillaries and the tissues of the body. This statement describes external respiration.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Internal respiration allows carbon dioxide that was created as a waste product of cellular respiration to diffuse into the capillaries and be carried to the lungs. The higher partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the tissues is what allows this direction of diffusion.</feedback></response><response match="D" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Internal respiration allows carbon dioxide that was created as a waste product of cellular respiration to diffuse into the capillaries and be carried to the lungs. The higher partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the tissues is what allows this direction of diffusion. Hint: Internal respiration involves the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide between the blood and tissues of the body.</feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
