<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="respiratory_internal_external_respiration"><title>tutor</title><question id="partial_pressure_oxygen"><body>The partial pressure of oxygen is higher in the alveoli then the partial pressure of oxygen in the blood plasma. What is this called?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>External Respiration</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Internal Respiration</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>Neither</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="partial_pressure_oxygen_p1"><skillref idref="differentiate_between_internal_external_respiration" /><response match="A" score="10"><feedback>Correct. In external respiration the partial pressure difference between the alveoli and the blood plasma allows oxygen to diffuse from the area of higher pressure in the alveoli into the blood plasma.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Internal respiration occurs between the capillaries and the tissues of the body.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. The partial pressure of oxygen needs to be higher in the alveoli to allow for it to diffuse into the blood capillaries.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="partial_pressure_carbon_dioxide"><body>What is it called when partial pressure of carbon dioxide is higher in the alveoli then the partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the blood plasma?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>External Respiration</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Internal Respiration</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>Neither</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="partial_pressure_carbon_dioxide_p1"><skillref idref="differentiate_between_internal_external_respiration" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In external respiration the partial pressure of carbon dioxide is higher in the blood plasma than in the alveoli. This allows the carbon dioxide to diffuse down its partial pressure gradient and exit the body.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. In internal respiration the partial pressure of carbon dioxide is higher in the body tissues than in the blood plasma. This allows carbon dioxide to leave the body tissues and diffuse into the capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="10"><feedback>Correct. If the partial pressure of carbon dioxide remained higher in the alveoli than the partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the blood plasma carbon dioxide would diffuse into the bloodstream. One of the main functions of respiration is to remove excess carbon dioxide from the body.</feedback></response></part></question><question id="partial_pressure_blood_plasma"><body>What is it when the partial pressure of oxygen is lower in metabolically active cells than in the blood plasma?</body><multiple_choice select="single" shuffle="false"><choice value="A"><p>External Respiration</p></choice><choice value="B"><p>Internal Respiration</p></choice><choice value="C"><p>Neither</p></choice></multiple_choice><part id="partial_pressure_blood_plasma_p1"><skillref idref="differentiate_between_internal_external_respiration" /><response match="A" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. External respiration occurs between the alveoli of the lungs and the blood capillaries.</feedback></response><response match="B" score="10"><feedback>Correct. Internal respiration relies on the partial pressure of oxygen being lower in metabolically active cells so it can diffuse from the blood into the tissues.</feedback></response><response match="C" score="0"><feedback>Incorrect. Internal respiration involves the diffusion of oxygen from the higher partial pressure in the blood plasma into the lower partial pressure region of the tissues.</feedback></response></part></question></assessment>
