<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.6//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_6.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" id="eda_summary">
<head>
<title>Summary (EDA)</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>This summary provides a quick recap of the material you've learned in the Exploratory Data
   Analysis unit. Please note that this summary <em>does not provide complete coverage</em> of the
   material, but just lists the main points. We therefore recommend that you use this summary only
   as a checklist or a review before going on to the next unit, or before an exam.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The purpose of exploratory data analysis (EDA) is to convert the available <em>data</em> from their raw form to an informative one, in which the main features of the data are illuminated.
 </p>
</li>
<li> When performing EDA, we should always:
<ul>
<li>use <em>visual displays</em> (graphs or tables) plus <em>numerical summaries</em>. </li>
<li>describe the <em>overall pattern</em> and mention any <em>striking deviations </em>from that pattern.
 </li>
<li>
<em>interpret </em>the results we got <em>in context</em>.
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>When examining the <em>distribution</em> of a single variable, we distinguish between
 a <em>categorical </em>variable and a <em>quantitative</em> variable.</p>

</li>
<li><p>The distribution of a <em>categorical</em> variable is summarized using:</p>
 <ul>
<li>Display: pie-chart or bar-chart (variation: pictogram → can be misleading&#8212;beware!) </li>
<li>Numerical summaries: category (group) percentages. </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The distribution of a <em>quantitative</em> variable is summarized using:</p>
 <ul>
<li>Display: histogram (or stemplot, mainly for small data sets). When describing the distribution
      as displayed by the histogram, we should describe the: <ul>
       <li>Overall pattern → shape, center, spread. </li>
       <li>Deviations from the pattern → outliers.</li>
      </ul>
     </li>
<li>Numerical summaries: descriptive statistics (measure of center plus measure of spread): <ul>
       <li>If distribution is symmetric with no outliers, use mean and standard deviation. </li>
       <li>Otherwise, use the five-number summary, in particular, median and IQR (inter-quartile
        range). </li>
      </ul>
     </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The five-number summary and the 1.5(IQR) Criterion for detecting outliers are the ingredients we
     need to build the <em>boxplot</em>. Boxplots are most effective when used side-by-side for
     comparing distributions (see also case C→Q in examining relationships).</p>


</li>
<li><p>In the special case of a distribution having the normal shape, the <term>Standard Deviation Rule</term>
     applies. This rule tells us approximately what percent of the observations fall within 1,2, or
     3 standard deviations away from the mean. In particular, when a distribution is approximately
     normal, almost all the observations (99.7%) fall within 3 standard deviations of the mean.</p>

</li>
<li><p>When examining the relationship between two variables, the first step is to classify the two relevant variables according
 to their role and type:</p>

 <image style="block" src="../webcontent/eda_summary1.gif" alt="There are explanatory categorical variables, explanatory
 quantitative variables, response categorical variables, and response quantitative variables. It is possible
 for any type of explanatory variable to be paired with any type of response variable. The possible pairings are:
 Categorical Explanatory → Categorical Response (C→C),
 Categorical Explanatory → Quantitative Response (C→Q),
 Quantitative Explanatory → Categorical Response (Q→C), and
 Quantitative Explanatory → Quantitative Response (Q→Q)"/>
 and only then to determine the appropriate tools for summarizing the data. (We don't deal with case Q→C in this course).
</li>
<li><p>Case C→Q:</p> <p>Exploring the relationship amounts to <em>comparing the distributions</em> of the quantitative
     response variable for each category of the explanatory variable. To do this, we use: </p>
<ul>
<li>Display: side-by-side boxplots. </li>
<li>Numerical summaries: descriptive statistics of the response variable, for each value (category)
      of the explanatory variable separately. </li>
</ul>

</li>
<li>Case C→C: <p>Exploring the relationship amounts to <em>comparing the distributions</em> of the
     categorical response variable, for each category of the explanatory variable. To do this, we
     use: </p>
    <ul>
     <li>Display: two-way table. </li>
     <li>Numerical summaries: conditional percentages (of the response variable for each value
      (category) of the explanatory variable separately). </li>
    </ul>
   </li>
<li>Case Q→Q: <p>We examine the relationship using: </p>
    <ul>
     <li>Display: scatterplot. When describing the relationship as displayed by the scatterplot, be
      sure to consider: <!--:ERROR: Lists cannot be used within a paragraph.--><ul>
       <li>Overall pattern → direction, form, strength.</li>
       <li>Deviations from the pattern → outliers. </li>
      </ul> Labeling the scatterplot (including a relevant third categorical variable in our
      analysis), might add some insight into the nature of the relationship. </li>
    </ul>
    <p>In the <em>special case</em> that the scatterplot displays a <em>linear</em> relationship
     (and only then), we supplement the scatterplot with:</p>
    <ul>
     <li>Numerical summaries: the correlation coefficient (r) <em>measures</em> the direction and,
      more importantly, the <em>strength of the linear relationship</em>. The closer r is to 1 (or
      -1), the stronger the positive (or negative) linear relationship. r is unitless, influenced by
      outliers, and should be used only as a supplement to the scatterplot. </li>
     <li>When the relationship is linear (as displayed by the scatterplot, and supported by the
      correlation r), we can summarize the linear pattern using the <em>least squares regression
       line</em>. Remember that: <ul>
       <li>The slope of the regression line tells us the average change in the response variable
        that results from a 1-unit increase in the explanatory variable. </li>
       <li>When using the regression line for predictions, you should beware of extrapolation. </li>
      </ul>
     </li>
    </ul>
   </li>
<li>When examining the relationship between two variables (regardless of the case), any <em>observed
     relationship</em> (association) <em>does not imply causation</em>, due to the possible presence
    of lurking variables.</li>
<li><p>When we include a lurking variable in our analysis, we might need to rethink the direction of the relationship → <em>Simpson's paradox</em>.</p></li>
</ul>
</body>
</workbook_page>
