<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="u2_m2_review"><head><title>The Cell Review and Assessment </title></head><body><p id="bfc9098d78094233aa274eefff1757ea">Cells are the basic structural unit of living things. The cell is the first level of complexity able to maintain homeostasis, and it is the unique structure of the cell that enables this critical function.</p><p id="a4c7c6e2b1914b24b106b18b65ee079b">Cells have cell membranes which surround and protect the cell. The cell membrane is a dynamic structure composed of lipids, proteins, and carbohydrates. It protects the cell by preventing materials from leaking out, controls what can enter or leave through the membrane, provides a binding site for hormones and other chemicals, and serves as an identification card for the immune system to distinguish between “self” and “non-self” cells. The phospholipid bilayer is the main fabric of the membrane. The cell membrane is a dynamic, or fluid, structure that allows the movement of phospholipids and proteins. Molecules may pass through the cell membrane in a variety of ways, namely simple diffusion, facilitated diffusion, or active transport.</p><p id="f79e0754016d490196b774a6f9527ab9">The cytoplasm is the watery interior of the cell which contains ions, proteins, and organelles. Organelles carry out all activities necessary for the cell to live, grow, and reproduce. Each cell process is carried out in a specific location in the cell, often located in or around an organelle. Organelles carry out specialized tasks within the cell, localizing functions such as replication, energy production, protein synthesis, and processing of food and waste. The various cells differ in the arrangement and number of organelles, as well as structurally, giving rise to the hundreds of cell types found in the body.</p><activity idref="_u2_cells_quiz" purpose="quiz" /></body></workbook_page>
