<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="u2_m1_review">
    
    <head>
        <title>Chemistry Review and Assessment </title>
    </head>
    
    <body>
        
        <p>Chemistry is fundamental as a building block for the hierarchy of organization within the body. 
            The movement of subatomic particles called electrons can cause atomic charge. Ions are atoms that 
            carry either a positive or negative charge from altered numbers of electrons, and many atoms and 
            molecules exist in the body as ions. Ionic chemistry is important in human medicine and health. 
            Ions play an essential role in physiological processes, particularly as they move across cell membranes.</p>
       
        <p>The key biologically relevant elements are hydrogen (H), carbon (C), nitrogen (N), oxygen (O), phosphorous (P)
            and sulfur (S), which represent more than 95 percent of the mass of a cell. Chemical bonds result when atoms
            of the same element (e.g., C-C) or different elements (e.g., C-O, C-N, O-H) combine into relatively strong, 
            commonly neutral, structures. There are two major types of chemical bonds: ionic and covalent.</p>
        
        <p>Water accounts for up to 75 percent of the weight of the human body, providing a relatively stable medium 
            in which chemical reactions can take place. Water’s unique chemical properties (as a solvent with a high
            boiling point and high heat capacity) make it essential for homeostasis.</p>
        
        <p>A macromolecule is a single molecule that consists of many covalently linked subunit molecules. A polymer 
            is a single molecule composed of similar monomers. In physiology, the four major macromolecules are nucleic acids,
            proteins, lipids and carbohydrates. Proteins are structurally the most complex macromolecules, and are composed 
            of amino acids. </p>
        
        <!--  Quiz  --> 
        <activity idref="_u2_chemistry_quiz" purpose="quiz"/>
    </body>
    
</workbook_page>

