<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m1_intro_c">
	<head>
		<title>Overview of the Digestive System</title>
		

	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Here is a preview of each of the modules to come:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><em style="emphasis">Structures and Functions</em>, will explore how the major organs of the digestive system are able to accomplish the major system level functions:
			<ul>
				<li>movement through the length of the digestive system</li>
				<li>complementary mechanisms for digestion in different segments</li>
				<li>structural components enhancing efficient absorption</li>
			</ul>
				<p><em>Pay attention to</em> not only what structures are similar and what are unique in the different sections, but how this contributes to the overall function of the system as a whole. </p>
			</li>
			
			<li><em style="emphasis">Levels of Organization</em>, will examine this structure and function in more detail, progressing through the major levels of organization in the human organism from the chemical and cellular levels to the tissues, organs and organ systems:
			<ul>
				<li>nutritive and digestive molecules</li>
				<li>cells of the stomach, small and large intestine, liver, and pancreas</li>
				<li>tissue layers and organs that make up the GI tract, from mouth to anus</li>
				<li>accessory organs that contribute secretions to the GI tract</li>				
			</ul>
				
				<p><em>Pay attention to</em> the function of cells for both secretion and absorption of specific substances in the different parts of the digestive tract and accessory organs.  What these specific cells produce and how they move materials across cell membranes is critical to understanding the function of the system as a whole.</p>
			</li>
			
			<li><em style="emphasis">Homeostasis</em>, will delve into how this system contributes to the body’s natural tendency to maintain a stable internal environment:
				<ul>
					<li>how hormones and nerves control and coordinate the digestive system</li>
					<li>what happens when digestive system malfunctions</li>					
				</ul>
				<p><em>Pay attention to</em> how not only is the rate of movement from one section to another controlled, but what is released into the lumen is controlled based on monitoring of content of food eaten.  Don’t get the endocrine secretion of hormones into the blood for control and regulation confused with the exocrine secretion of substances into the lumen for the digestion and absorption processes – both are happening.</p>
			</li>
			
			<li><em style="emphasis">Integration of Systems</em>, will investigate which systems are subsets of larger systems, and how they function together in harmony and conflict:
				<ul>
					<li>how digestive system interacts with the other body systems</li>
					<li>how other systems affect the digestive system functions</li>
				</ul>
				<p><em>Pay attention to</em> the relationship between proper movement and secretion for digestion and the subsequent absorption and transport of materials for metabolism.  This links the digestive tract and accessory digestive organs to the other systems.</p>				
			</li>
		</ul>
		
		
		<wb:inline idref="digest_intro_c_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	
	</body>	
</workbook_page>
