<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m1_intro_a"><head><title>Introduction to the Digestive System </title><objref idref="_u1_list_OBJ" /><objref idref="_u1_identifyExplain_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="ead9e5f4666346759a621401dc12d206">The digestive system is basically a tube within our body, from mouth to anus. It includes the stomach and intestines, as well as accessory organs such as the liver, gall bladder and pancreas. The space within any tubular body structure, such as blood vessels or this digestive tract, is known as a lumen. During embryological development, embryonic cells (endoderm) forming the primitive yolk sac, turn outside-in (invaginates) forming the anal opening to the outside. This endoderm layer becomes the epithelial tissue lining of the future gastrointestinal (GI) tract and many associated organs. Later in the development process, the mouth opening breaks through the outer layer of embryonic cells (ectoderm) from the opposite side, meeting the endoderm. This ectoderm lines the mouth and forms the salivary glands. As a result, anything inside the space or lumen of the GI tract can technically be described as still being “external” to the body tissues. So, the caustic process of digestion is occurring in an “external” tube, without destroying the “internal” body tissues themselves. Then the products of digestion are absorbed from this “external environment” into the body cells and tissue fluids.</p><p id="cea6f055ae554521b340160dcfebf807">As early as the 2nd century, early anatomists understood the basic structure and important function of the digestive system. Many of the terms we still use for anatomy were developed then and during the medieval period, when they described the importance of the stomach and intestines for proper nutrition and digestion to maintain health. They also recognized the association of the liver and gall bladder to produce and store bile, although they didn’t correctly understand its physiology. It was identified as one of the four body fluids (blood, phlegm, yellow bile and black bile) that Hippocrates proposed were the physiological foundation for different human emotions and behaviors; thus they were called “humors”. The imbalance of these four humors was thought to be the cause of physical and mental illnesses. This and many of the early physiological theories have since been discarded. However, their idea that the stomach was an animate organ with ability to think or feel doesn’t seem totally ridiculous as you learn about how modern science is discovering the physiological importance of a specific part of the nervous system that resides entirely in our gut. By the renaissance period, physiologists were focusing their research on the chemical basis of digestion occurring inside the GI tract.</p><wb:inline idref="digest_intro_lbd1" purpose="learnbydoing" /><materials id="e59af92f4df64d639c38c7d35f3a8c47"><material><image id="d13f0aa5b7e7431b88821035c6783b56" src="../../webcontent/D_M2_12.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="455" width="250"><caption><p id="ac410e13f91b34f338668c9f5a8c2f25b"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><wb:inline idref="_u1_list_digest_intro" purpose="didigetthis" /></material></materials></body></workbook_page>
