<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m1_intro_b">
	<head>
		<title>Digestive System in the Big Picture of A&amp;P</title>
		<!--<objref idref="_u1_list_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="_u1_identifyExplain_OBJ"/>-->
		<objref idref="digest_bp_LO"/>
		<objref idref="_u01_m01_self_assess_OBJ"/>

	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Several of the core ideas in A&amp;P are clearly demonstrated as you investigate the
			digestive system in this module:</p>

		<ol>
			<li><p>Living organisms are causal mechanisms whose functions are to be understood by
				the applications of the laws of <term>physics</term> and <term>chemistry</term>.</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>Both mechanical and chemical digestion are necessary to convert the food we eat
					into a form that can be absorbed.</p></li>

			<li><p>The <term>cell</term> is the basic unit of life and cell plasma membranes control transport
					and signaling necessary for life. </p>
				<p></p>
				<p>Specialized cells are able to secrete
				substances into the digestive system space (lumen), to protect the body from
				this mixture because some of these substances would otherwise digest the body,
				and then to absorb specific substances from the mixture into the body.</p></li>
			
			<li><p>Life requires <term>information flow</term> within and between cells and between the environment and the organism.</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>Receptors monitor the composition of the mixture as it moves through the digestive system lumen, stimulating secretion of hormones and nerve impulses that coordinate the release of substances and control the movement from one segment to another by circular muscles called sphincters.</p></li>
			
			<li><p>Living organisms must obtain matter and energy from the external world.  This matter and <term>energy must be transformed and transferred</term> in varied ways to build the organism and to perform work.</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>Food in the diet must be broken down into its basic units for absorption and then these are used to fuel ATP production, build and repair cells and tissues, and participate in other metabolic activities of the body.</p>
			</li>
			
			<li><p><term>Homeostasis</term> (and “stability” in a more general sense) maintains the internal environment in a more or less constant state compatible with life.</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>In addition to nutrients, the absorption of vitamins, electrolytes and water are critical to maintaining body homeostasis, with disorders and diseases occurring when malabsorption occurs.</p>
			</li>
			<li><p>Understanding the behavior of the organism requires understanding the relationship between <term>structure and function</term> (at each and every level of organization).</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>This is best illustrated by the concept of increased surface area for efficient absorption in the digestive system.</p>
			</li>
			<li><p>Living organisms carry out functions at many different <term>levels of organization</term> simultaneously.</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>Cell level function is supported by all the tissue structures that make up the different segments and organs of the digestive system.</p>
			</li>
			<li><p>All life depends upon the proper <term>interactions and supporting functions</term> among interrelated organ systems.</p>
				<p></p>
				<p>In addition to obtaining necessary metabolic substances needed by all other body systems, the digestive system has several mechanisms to protect other systems against pathogens that can enter with things we ingest.</p>
			</li>
		</ol>
		
		
		<!--Interactive activity goes here-->
		<wb:inline idref="digest_bp_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
