<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_36"><head><title>Absorption and Excretion Functions of Large Intestine</title><objref idref="deficate_reflex_LO" /></head><body><p id="c38e8acdf4274e3f807f608e5521a445">After chyme has been in the large intestine for three to 10 hours, water absorption changes it into the solid or semisolid substance called <em style="emphasis">feces</em> (&quot;stool&quot;). Feces is composed of undigested food residues (dietary fiber), unabsorbed digested substances, millions of bacteria, sloughed-off epithelial cells from the GI mucosa, inorganic salts, mucus, fat and just enough water to let it pass smoothly out of the body. Of every 500 mL (17 ounces) of food residue that enters the cecum each day, about 150 mL (5 ounces) becomes feces. </p><p id="a7a59fa6a318429d8f4fdc0f2b54a776">Although the small intestine absorbs around 90 percent of the water that enters the GI tract, the water absorbed in the large intestine is important in maintaining the body&apos;s water balance. For every 0.5 to 1.0 liter (16 to 32 ounces) of water that goes into the large intestine, only around 100 to 200 mL (3 to 7 ounces) escapes being absorbed by osmosis.</p><p id="b42d7c7dda694ef4ad6415dc585c31db">The process of defecation begins when mass movements force feces from the sigmoid colon into the rectum, stretching the rectal wall and provoking the <em style="emphasis">defecation reflex</em> , which eliminates feces from the rectum. This parasympathetic reflex is mediated by the spinal cord. It contracts the sigmoid colon and rectum, relaxes the internal anal sphincter, and initially contracts the external anal sphincter. The presence of feces in the anal canal sends a signal to the brain, which gives us the choice of voluntarily opening the external anal sphincter (defecating) or keeping it temporarily closed. When we decide to delay defecation, it takes a few seconds for the reflex contractions to stop and the rectal walls to relax. The next mass movement will trigger another defecation reflex and another until we defecate. </p><p id="a2c124d1ac7c42a59daf03d3eff91741">Feces is eliminated during defecation through contraction of the rectal muscles. We help this process by a voluntary procedure called the <em style="emphasis">Valsalva maneuver</em> , in which we increase intra-abdominal pressure by contracting our diaphragm and abdominal wall muscles and closing our glottis. Along with learned control of the external anal sphincter, these actions must be learned, which is why infants and young children wear diapers. </p><p id="a3641121511149ea888bc6f94f0a08f5">Diet, health, exercise and stress determine the frequency of bowel movements. The number of bowel movements varies greatly between individuals, ranging from two or three per day to three or four per week.</p><section id="bdbbc69b02a64439abdd2d0982e903fe" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="deficate_reflex_sc" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="defecate_reflex_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
