<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_05">
	<head>
		<title>Mucosal Barrier</title>
		<!--<objref idref="PLACEHOLDER!!"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>The mucosa of the stomach is exposed to the highly corrosive acidity of gastric juice.
			Gastric enzymes and acid that can digest and denature protein can also digest the cells
			and tissues of the stomach itself. The stomach is protected from self-digestion by the
				<term>mucosal barrier</term>. This barrier has several components. First,
			the stomach wall is covered by a thick coating of bicarbonate-rich mucus. This mucus
			provides a protective coating since bicarbonate ions neutralize acid. Second, the
			epithelial cells of the stomach's mucosa are joined by tight junctions, which block
			gastric juice from penetrating between cells into the underlying tissue layers. Finally,
			stem cells in the region quickly replace damaged epithelial mucosal cells when the
			epithelial cells are shed. In fact, the surface epithelium of the stomach is completely
			replaced every three to six days.</p>
		<example>
			
			<title>Ulcers: When the Mucosal Barrier Breaks Down</title>
		<p>As effective as the mucosal barrier is, it is not a "fail-safe" mechanism. Sometimes
			gastric juice eats away at the superficial lining of the stomach mucosa, creating
			erosions, which usually heal without treatment. Deeper mucosal barrier breakdowns,
			involving the muscularis, for example, result in ulcers.</p>
		<p>Why does the mucosal barrier break down? A number of things interfere with its ability to
			protect the stomach lining, including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), <em
				style="italic">Helicobacter pylori </em>infection, alcohol, smoking, and caffeine.
			As the population ages and people rely more on NSAIDs to treat a variety of aches and
			pains, there has been an increase in the incidence of ulcers. Antacids, which are
			typically bicarbonate buffers, help relieve symptoms of ulcers such as "burning" pain;
			antacids buffer the low pH of the stomach interior. When ulcers are caused by infection,
			antibiotics are given to kill the bacteria and anti-inflammatory drugs are often
			effective in reducing inflammation and side effects. Perforated ulcers create a hole in
			the stomach wall, resulting in peritonitis (inflammation of the peritoneum). These
			ulcers need to be fixed surgically.</p>
		</example>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
