<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_38"><head><title>Liver</title><objref idref="liver_structures_LO" /></head><body><p id="a9cd2932ceff426fb056b5a89222145a">The <term>liver</term> is the largest gland in the body, as well as one of the most important organs. It plays a number of major roles in metabolism and regulation. In an adult, the reddish-brown liver weighs about 3 pounds (1.4 kg) This wedge-shaped organ lies inferior to the diaphragm in the right upper quadrant of the abdominal cavity. The liver is almost completely surrounded by the rib cage, which offers it some protection.</p><section id="b23f4cf967074907859985d9d600adb4"><title>The Liver’s Anatomical Structures</title><body><p id="d6abde01d64341c29472df82fa03afa9">The liver has different levels of structure and function, and different models have been used to describe the organizational and functional relationships between hepatocytes, bile canaliculi, and hepatic sinusoids. The <term>hepatic lobule</term> was considered the functional unit of the liver in years past. In this model, each hexagonal (six-sided) hepatic lobule has a central vein. Radiating from this vein are rows of hepatocytes and hepatic sinusoids.</p><materials id="b661b3b75a5a4a29b76ac9d3093cf418"><material><image id="d0ba85089d0e4380b1c77bd64bdb77b6" src="../../webcontent/D_M4_31.jpg" alt="Microscopic structure of the liver showing sinusoids, veins, arteries, and cells." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="fa2af9da0bb247668354710e973a2906">Microscopic structure of the liver. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><image id="c8757b444c804180a1916291a32d9e0b" src="../../webcontent/D_M4_31b.jpg" alt="Microscopic structure of the hepatic acinus." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption><p id="df8716f9854543d1bcd92c7fc668b895">Microscopic structure of the hepatic acinus. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material></materials><p id="c3ef353995b14feca39f6fafc749e51e">The <term>hepatic acinus</term> has become the preferred model of the metabolic functional unit of the liver in recent years. Each primarily oval hepatic acinus includes parts of two adjacent hepatic lobules. Branches of the portal triad that run along the hepatic lobule border delineate the short axis of the hepatic acinus. The long axis is created by two imaginary curved lines that connect the two central veins nearest the short axis. In the hepatic acinus, hepatocytes are organized in three zones around the short axis. Zone 1 cells, which are nearest the portal triad branches, are the first to receive oxygen, nutrients, and toxic substances from incoming blood. After a meal, zone 1 cells are the first to absorb glucose and store it as glycogen; during fasting, they are the first to break down glycogen to glucose. If circulation is disrupted, zone 1 cells are the last to die and the first to regenerate. Zone 3 cells, which are farthest away from the portal triad branches, die first if circulation is disrupted and are the last to regenerate. They are also the first to demonstrate the accumulation of fat. Predictably, the structural and functional qualities of zone 2 cells lie between those of zone 1 and 3 cells.</p><p id="ff18c9b2c5184acba5131d5d7291b76c">The popularity of the hepatic acinus model is based on its reasonable description of glycogen storage and release patterns, as well as the degeneration, regeneration, and toxic effects in the three zones according to their proximity to portal triad branches.</p></body></section><section id="fb81bd7de5b342f6b7ed8d2566592946"><title>Liver Gross Anatomy</title><body><p id="ec7958bf6d1d4d60a1883f7c57191911">The liver is divided into two primary lobes, a large right lobe and a smaller left lobe. Separating the right and left lobes anteriorly is a mesentery called the falciform ligament, which also helps suspend the liver in the abdominal cavity. A number of anatomists believe that the right lobe also includes an inferior quadrate lobe and a posterior caudate lobe, which are defined by internal features. Ligaments connect the liver to other visceral organs, and the visceral peritoneum enshrouds almost the entire liver, except for the part that abuts the diaphragm. The lesser omentum tethers the liver to the lesser curvature of the stomach. The <term>porta hepatis</term> (&quot;gateway to the liver&quot;) is where the <term>hepatic artery</term> and <term>hepatic portal vein</term> enter the liver on its inferior surface. These two vessels, along with the common hepatic duct, run through the lesser omentum on the way to their destinations.</p><image id="c952618baa5a45edaee4355243f2ddfc" src="../../webcontent/D_M4_33.jpg" alt="Gross anatomy of the liver showing veins, arteries, and ducts." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="400"><caption><p id="cdba5c77dd424cc18375370120f6781a">Gross anatomy of the liver. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="fd51e9c881284ac4a3bde8d5054bdd20">The hepatic artery delivers oxygenated blood from the heart to the liver. The portal system in general has a direct cconnection between two organs bypassing the systemic circulation. The hepatic portal vein delivers deoxygenated blood containing newly absorbed nutrients, drugs, and possible bacteria from the alimentary canal. Branches of both vessels bring blood into liver sinusoids, where hepatocytes take up most nutrients and some of the toxins. The hepatocytes secrete substances, including nutrients needed by other cells, back into the blood, which drains into the central vein and then the hepatic vein. In this hepatic portal circulation, blood from the GI tract passes through the liver before entering the systemic circulation. This is why the liver is a common site for the metastasis of cancer that originates in the alimentary canal.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="id_hepatic_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="b6e2159ff4ba4a958418991fd07f2f95" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="liver_lobes_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="liver_lobes_digt2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section><section id="eb0d04c2106441b5a52598d532ea444f"><title>Liver Ducts</title><body><p id="ef123f5307b645868bc15e20995e2c8d">The liver has three main components: hepatocytes, bile canaliculi, and hepatic sinusoids. Between adjacent hepatocytes, grooves in the cell membranes provide room for <term>bile canaliculi</term> (&quot;small canals&quot;). These small ducts accumulate the bile produced by hepatocytes. From here, bile flows first into bile ductules and then into bile ducts. The bile ducts unite and form the larger <term>right</term> and <term>left hepatic ducts</term>, which themselves merge and exit the liver as the <term>common hepatic duct</term>. This duct then joins with the cystic duct from the gall bladder, forming the <term>common bile duct</term> through which bile flows into the small intestine. Bile production increases when fat-rich chyme stimulates the release of secretin from intestinal cells. Between meals, when most absorption is complete, the hepatopancreatic sphincter prevents bile flow into the duodenum, and bile backs up into the gall bladder, where it is stored until needed.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="bile_ducts_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="eb0a9419a3664ce182acf3c6cca465f8"><title>Liver Circulation</title><body><p id="bfac39a132a843b39e4f8335d72aeb5c"><term>Hepatic sinusoids</term> are specialized blood vessels, more like dilated channels, located between rows of hepatocytes. Branches of the hepatic artery deliver oxygenated blood to hepatic sinusoids; while branches of the hepatic portal vein deliver nutrient-laden blood. The hepatic sinusoids combine and send blood into a <term>central vein</term>. Blood then flows into the <term>hepatic veins</term>, which drain into the inferior vena cava. This means that blood and bile flow in opposite directions. The hepatic sinusoids also contain the immune cells called <term>Kupffer cells</term>. A distinctive arrangement in the liver called the <term>portal triad </term>includes three basic structures: a bile duct, a hepatic artery branch, and a hepatic portal vein branch.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="id_hepatic_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="bcd14cdb1cb6471abf96770a399a49ef"><title>Liver Ligaments</title><body><p id="f2403feeea0748a39948e95bda44bf46">The liver is covered with a visceral peritoneum. These ligaments are useful anatomic positions but serve little physiological purpose aside from attaching the liver to the body wall and other structures. The <term>ligamentum teres (round ligament)</term> runs along the inferior border of the <term>falciform</term> ligament. Tapered extensions of the parietal peritoneum, called the right and left <term>coronary ligaments</term>, hang the liver from the diaphragm.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="id_ligaments_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
