<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_35">
	<head>
		<title>Mechanical and Chemical Digestion</title>
		<objref idref="id_lgintestine_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<section>
			<title>Mechanical Digestion</title>
			<body>
				<p>Mechanical digestion in the large intestine begins when chyme moves from the
					ileum into the cecum, an activity regulated by the ileocecal valve. This
					sphincter is usually partially closed, allowing slow movement of chyme into the
					large intestine. Right after we eat, peristalsis in the ileum is escalated by
					the gastroileal reflex, which forces whatever chyme is in the ileum into the
					cecum. The activity of the hormone gastrin also relaxes the ileocecal valve.
					When the cecum is distended with chyme, contractions of the ileocecal sphincter
					strengthen. Once chyme enters the cecum, colon movements begin. As food residues
					pass the ileocecal valve, they fill the cecum and gather in the ascending
					colon.</p>
				<p>The presence of food residue in the colon stimulates slow-moving <em style="bold"
						>haustral contractions (haustral churning)</em>. These sluggish
					segmentations, primarily in the transverse and descending colons, occur about
					every 30 minutes and last about one minute. When a haustra is distended with
					chyme, its muscle contracts, pushing the residue into the next haustra. The
					movements also mix the food residue, which helps the large intestine absorb
					water.</p>
				<p>The large intestine also has peristaltic movements, but they are slower than in
					more proximal portions of the alimentary canal, at a rate of from three to 12
					contractions per minute. The third type of movement in the large intestine is
					called <em style="bold">mass movements (mass peristalsis)</em>. These drawn-out,
					slow-moving, but strong peristaltic waves start around the middle of the
					transverse colon and quickly force the contents of the colon into the rectum.
					Mass movements usually occur three or four times per day, either while we eat or
					immediately afterward. Distension in the stomach and the breakdown products of
					digestion in the small intestine provoke the <em style="bold">gastrocolic or
						duogenocolic reflex</em>, which increases motility, including mass
					movements, in the colon. Fiber in the diet both softens the stool and increases
					the power of colonic contractions, optimizing the activities of the colon.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Chemical Digestion</title>
			<body>
				<p>The glands of the large intestine secrete only mucus; they do not secrete
					digestive enzymes. So chemical digestion in the large intestine occurs only
					through the activity of the bacteria in the lumen of the colon. Bacteria ferment
					residual carbohydrates in the chyme and discharge the hydrogen sulfide, carbon
					dioxide, and methane gases that help create <em style="bold">flatus </em>(gas)
					in the colon. (<em style="bold">Flatulence </em>refers to excessive flatus.)
					Some of these gases, including dimethyl sulfide, have foul odors. Each day,
					about 500 mL of flatus is produced in the colon. Much more is produced when we
					eat some fiber-rich foods such as beans.</p>
				<!--<wb:inline idref="digest_lgint_digestion_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>-->
				<p><em style="highlight">Placeholder for activity</em></p>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
