<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_14">
	<head>
		<title>Tissue Layers of the Gastrointestinal Tract</title>
		<objref idref="wall_layers_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>


		<p>Throughout the gastrointestinal (GI) tract, walls are comprised of the same four
			fundamental tissue layers. From the lumen of the GI tract, these layers are the mucosa,
			submucosa, muscularis, and serosa.</p>


		<section>
			<title/>
			<body>
				<materials orient="horizontal">
					<material>
						<image src="../../webcontent/D_M2_16.jpg" width="300"
							alt="Histology image of the lining of the small intestine labeling the 4 tissue layers">
							<caption>The lining of the small intestine. Image courtesy of Dr. Allan
								Wiechmann, University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center </caption>
						</image>
					</material>
					<material>
						<image src="../../webcontent/D_M2_17.jpg" width="350"
							alt="4 layers of the GI tract.">
							<caption>Tissue layers of the GI tract. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
								Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
									href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
									>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
						</image>
					</material>
				</materials>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>The Mucosa</title>
			<body>
				<p>The mucosa is a mucous membrane that makes up the inner lining of the GI tract.
					It has three layers: (1) the epithelium, made of closely packed cells without a
					blood supply or nerves in direct contact with the foodstuffs that enter the GI
					tract; (2) the lamina propria, a layer of connective tissue that supports the
					epithelial cells; and (3) a thin smooth muscle layer called the muscularis
					mucosae. In the mouth, pharynx, esophagus, and distal portion of the anal canal,
					the <term>epithelium</term> is primarily nonkeratinized stratified squamous
					epithelium. In the stomach and intestines, it is simple columnar epithelium,
					whose cells participate in secretion and absorption. Every five to seven days,
					the harsh chemical and mechanical environment of the GI tract causes epithelial
					cells to be sloughed off and replaced by new ones. Epithelial cells are
					interspersed with exocrine cells that secrete mucus and digestive fluid into the
						<term>lumen</term> (interior space) of the alimentary canal and with
					enteroendocrine cells that secrete hormones and paracrines. In addition to
					connective tissue, the <term>lamina propria </term>of the mucosa contains
					numerous blood and lymphatic vessels, which transport nutrients absorbed into
					the GI tract to the liver. The lamina propria also contains most of the immune
					cells that make up the <term>mucosa-associated lymphatic tissue
					(MALT)</term>.</p>
				<p>The <term>muscularis mucosae </term>layer is not responsible for movement of
					material through the GI tract, but it controls the exposed surface area. Small
					alterations in the many small folds in the mucous membrane of the stomach and
					small intestine increases the surface area available for digestion and
					absorption. Of these folds, the rugae in the stomach are temporary structures
					while the plicae circulares of the small intestine are permanent. When this
					muscle layer contracts, rugae and plicae circulars are pushed together exposing
					less SA to the lumen. When it relaxes more of the mucosal surface is revealed
					and in contact with the digestive products in the lumen.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>The Submucosa</title>
			<body>
				<p>The <term>submucosa</term> binds the mucosa to the muscularis externa. It is
					composed of areolar connective tissue and includes blood and lymphatic vessels
					(which transport absorbed food molecules) and the submucosal plexus (which is
					part of nervous system control).</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>The Muscularis</title>
			<body>
				<p>In the mouth, pharynx, and superior and middle esophagus, the <term>muscularis
						externa</term> contains skeletal muscle that we use for voluntary
					swallowing. The external anal sphincter is also made of skeletal muscle, giving
					us voluntary control of defecation. In the rest of the GI tract, the muscularis
					externa is smooth muscle, which contracts involuntarily to break down food, mix
					it with digestive juices, and move it along the GI tract. Complementary muscles
					in longitudinal (along the length of the tract) and circular layers creates
					peristalsis – the wave-like muscular movements to move good from the esophagus
					to the anus.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>The Serosa</title>
			<body>
				<p>The <term>serosa</term> is the superficial layer of the intestine that covers the
					parts of the GI tract that is exposed to the abdominal cavity. This serous
					membrane is made up of areolar connective tissue and simple squamous epithelium
						(<term>mesothelium</term>). The esophagus has a single layer of tough
					connective tissue called the <term>adventitia</term>; it does not have a
					serosa.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<wb:inline idref="GI_layers1_la" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_GI_layers_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
