<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_02">
	<head>
		<title>Chemical Digestion</title>
		<objref idref="digest_mols2_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="digest_mols_LO"/>-->
		
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The digestive system breaks down ingested material into absorbable components (nutrients)
			that the rest of the body can use to maintain adequate function. We require a diverse
			set of nutrients to support energy production, carry out metabolism and maintain
			structure.</p>

		<p>Chemical digestion generally, breaks down large food molecules into their respective
			chemical building blocks, called <term>monomers</term>, that can be absorbed. The enzymes responsible
			for chemical digestion are released by both intrinsic glands found in the
			gastrointestinal tract and the accessory glands which secrete molecules into the
			gastrointestinal tract. </p>
		
		<p><term>Hydrolysis</term> refers to the breakdown of a chemical where water breaks a covalent bond.
			Hydrolysis can happen spontaneously, but the breakdown of food into macromolecules and
			monomers occurs by enzymatic hydrolysis - where the hydrolysis reaction catalyzed by an
			enzyme. Hydro- is part of the name because a water molecule is added to each molecular
			bond that is broken, or -lysed. More specifically, hydrolysis is a method of degradation
			which splits a molecule of water to help break chemical bonds in a larger molecule.
			Usually an H+ is attached to one of the components and an OH- group to the other.
			Hydrolysis reactions are important for many other physiologic processes in the body in
			addition to the breakdown of food molecules.</p>
		
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/Hydrolysis.png" width="600" alt="Molecular image showing the hydrolysis breakdown of Sucrose into Glucose and Fructose"><caption>Hydrolysis of a Sucrose molecule into Glucose and Fructose. </caption></image>

		<p>For a review of nutritive molecules, including chemical structure and bonds, revisit the
				<activity_link idref="bonding_wbk" target="new">Chemical Bonding and
				Molecules</activity_link> page and the rest of the Levels of Organization unit.</p>
		
		<!--<wb:inline idref="digest_mols_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>-->
		<wb:inline idref="digest_mols_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>

		

	</body>
</workbook_page>
