<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_03">
	<head>
		<title>Saliva</title>
		<objref idref="digest_secretions_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="digest_saliva_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>Some <term>salivary glands</term> are always secreting <term>saliva</term>. Intrinsic salivary glands of the mouth
			secrete small amounts of saliva, usually just enough to moisten the mucous membranes and
			clean the mouth and teeth. The accessory salivary glands are exocrine organs under
			autonomic nervous system control with ducts leading into the mouth. Secretion increases
			when there is food in the mouth, as well as through a reflex when food is smelled, seen
			or thought about (you have probably heard about Pavlov’s experiment with the salivating
			dog and bell). Saliva is needed to moisten and lubricate the food and begin its chemical
			breakdown. </p>
			
			<p>Saliva is mainly water, which dissolves chemicals in the food. Only dissolved
			chemicals can activate the different kinds of taste receptor cells on the tongue, palate
			and other parts of the mouth and pharynx. Mixed in with the water, saliva also contains
			mucus, various electrolytes typically found in blood plasma, as well as some digestive
			molecules, metabolic waste products and immune molecules. Each of these contributes to
			the various functions of saliva. </p>
			
			<p><term>Bicarbonate</term> and <term>phosphate ions</term> help maintain the pH of
			saliva as neutral or slightly basic (average 7.4 pH). This not only helps protect the
			teeth from acidic substances eaten and plaque bacteria that grow best in an acidic
			environment, but also maintains the optimal pH for the enzyme amylase. <term>Salivary amylase</term>
				starts breaking complex carbohydrates eaten, like starch, into sugars. This enzymatic
			activity will stop once the mixture of food and saliva, called a bolus, is swallowed and
			reaches the acidic environment of the stomach. <term>Salivary lipase</term> is another enzyme in
			saliva that breaks down dietary lipids, but it is activated when it reaches the acidic
			gastric juice with its optimal pH being much more acidic than the salivary pH.</p> 
			
			<p>In addition to the water of saliva, mucus in the saliva is composed of glycoproteins and
			helps moisten the food, so it can be manipulated into a mass for swallowing. It also
			helps lubricate the movement of food through the pharynx and esophagus by peristalsis.
			<term>Lysozyme</term> antimicrobial enzymes and antibodies (<term>Immunoglobulin A</term>) in the saliva help
			combat pathogens that might enter the body with food or drink. Like the sweat glands,
			salivary glands play a role in some metabolic waste excretion, so <term>urea</term> and ammonia are
			also found in saliva.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="digest_saliva_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_saliva_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
