<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_01"><head><title>Digestive Levels of Organization</title><objref idref="digest_loo_LO" /></head><body><p id="de61ab26afb74583ad6a092ccf448dae">In order to get the various materials needed for energy production and anabolic metabolism in all body cells, our body has to exchange nutrients, water and electrolytes from the environment. However, the substance taken into the space of the GI tract is not always in the form that can be absorbed, so it must first be broken down. Various secreted chemicals are critical to accomplishing this digestion. These ingested macromolecules are digested in different regions of the GI tract, requiring that the mixture of material be moved through the digestive system in a controlled way. Once it has been digested to a basic chemical structure, the material can be absorbed into the blood or lymph. At that point, the other body systems integrate to distribute these absorbed nutrients, fluids and electrolytes through the body as needed. Any material remaining in the GI tract as waste will then be removed from the body by defecation.</p><p id="f70f29ed396d44eaa8cd8205e5ae61f7">To understand these system-level functions, you will be further exploring structures and processes occurring at all levels of organization. Some examples of major digestive structures assigned to their structural level of organization of the digestive system include:</p><ol id="d07f5f4e16174ed6af2db1958203a23c"><li><p id="e58d49e8be234528a70e6515969bc63c"><em style="italic">Chemical level</em> - sodium, potassium, chloride, bicarbonate, and phosphate ions and hydrochloric acid</p></li><li><p id="d164f79aeeba45c689415ec78279919d"><em style="italic">Macromolecular level</em> - enzymes of digestion, bile, and the nutritive molecules such as carbohydrates, protein, lipids and nucleic acids</p></li><li><p id="f18c39d85e6242d5ac71b538ef1cf78e"><em style="italic">Cellular level</em> – mucosa cells, secretory cells, and immune cells </p></li><li><p id="a48f45a376fd494db3332c7afd9ca1c6"><em style="italic">Tissue level</em> – epithelial, connective, and smooth muscle tissues</p></li><li><p id="fe9f194df2f54757a43ec62db47ac4e0"><em style="italic">Organ level</em> - gastrointestinal tract and accessory organs </p></li><li><p id="e94b8cf8f2844a9f875c69ac4fdb8138"><em style="italic">Organ System level</em> - integration of organs for nutrient and waste movement, digestion and absorption </p></li></ol><wb:inline idref="digest_loo_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
