<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_07"><head><title>Intestinal Juice and Accessory Secretions</title><objref idref="digest_secretions_LO" /></head><body><section id="d7e66543c8d944e3a5fa1f1ccbda6643"><title>Pancreatic Juice In Digestion</title><body><p id="f8679d10d434460095c3d1a94e9d6959">The pancreas produces about 1.2 to 1.5 quarts (1.1 – 1.4 liters) of <term>pancreatic juice</term> each day. This clear, colorless liquid is mostly water, along with some salts, sodium bicarbonate, and several digestive enzymes. Sodium bicarbonate is responsible for the slight alkalinity of pancreatic juice (pH 7.1 to 8.2). The sodium bicarbonate buffers the acidic gastric juice which has arrived in the small intestine from the stomach, inactivates pepsin from the stomach, and creates an optimal pH for the activity of the digestive enzymes in the small intestine.</p><p id="e7e9bcb279b54d5d855c30b40d1faac9">Just as the stomach produces pepsin in its inactive form (as pepsinogen), the pancreas creates and produces its protein-digesting enzymes as zymogens. These zymogens (trypsinogen, procarboxypeptidase, and chymotrypsinogen) are activated in the duodenum. If produced in their active forms, they would digest the pancreas itself. The intestinal enzyme <term>enteropeptidase</term> converts trypsinogen to the active <term>trypsin</term>. Trypsin also converts pancreatic enzymes procarboxypeptidase and chymotrypsinogen to their active forms, <term>carboxypeptidase</term> and <term>chymotrypsin</term>. Some pancreatic enzymes, including <term>amylase</term>, <term>lipase</term>, and <term>nuclease</term>, are secreted in their active form, but their optimal activity requires interactions with ions or bile in the intestinal lumen.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="digest_pancreatic_juice_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="bcc9262539fd4a0981b39c168a672d7d"><title>Bile</title><body><p id="c15b73d569aa43c68cf9017d410fcbd7"><term>Bile</term> is another accessory organ contribution to the GI tract lumen. Bile is made by the hepatocytes of the liver, but stored in, concentrated, and released from the gall bladder. Unlike pancreatic juice that is produced and released as needed, bile is produced in small quantities by the liver continuously. The gall bladder stores it for release into the small intestine as needed. </p><p id="a3e74e691f9e41688b88f23692eee4eb">Like saliva, bile is a mixture of mainly water with many substances, including electrolytes, bile pigments, <term>bile salts</term> and lipids (including the phospholipid <term>lecithin</term> and cholesterol). The bile pigments include bilirubin and biliverden, which are waste by-products from the destruction of the hemoglobin in aged or damaged red blood cells destroyed in the liver. These wastes are then eliminated from the body with the feces and contribute to its color. In addition, cells lining the bile duct secrete bicarbonate ions into the bile. However, it is the lecithin and bile salts produced from cholesterol that have a digestive function related to dietary lipids. </p><image id="bdd69023308e4420a7985e412a794580" src="../../webcontent/D_M1_10.jpg" alt="A fat globule being emulsified by bile salts into fat droplets." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="cfdcbe9b82794c919fd1c928401fb5d4">Emulsification of a fat globule by bile salts. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="d7ed100e27a04ae4a2034bbe08e59b7e">Recall that <activity_link idref="levels_m1_lipids" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">phospholipids</activity_link> in the cell membrane have a hydrophilic and hydrophobic portion. Bile salts are also amphiphilic. When they are released into the small intestine as part of the bile, the hydrophobic/lipophilic portion of the molecule is attracted to fat globules in the lumen, while the hydrophilic/lipophobic portion is attracted to the water in the digestive juice mixture. This chemical attraction and mechanical mixing breaks large fat globules into smaller droplets suspended in the fluid. The bile salts prevent the droplets from rejoining and thus increase the surface area of the lipid exposed to lipase enzymes; but the bile salts don’t actually digest the lipid into fatty acids and monoglycerides. This process is called <term>emulsification</term>. </p><example id="bbe54d399fbc43cf818b61e477a9fa07"><title>Emulsification</title><p id="a1098dee04fb4b738aed0ce2d6a3d934">Think of what happens when you mix oil and vinegar for a salad dressing. You can mechanically shake it up to produce smaller fat droplets suspended in the vinegar, but if left to sit, the two layers separate again. Lecithin from egg yolks is the emulsifier added to mayonnaise, which is a mixture of oil in vinegar or lemon juice that has been emulsified.</p></example><p id="f985e3ff775c4d309bf5fde93c7c5e80">Once the lipids have been digested, the bile salts are still attracted to the lipid and form small micelles. These micells come in contact with the small intestine cell membranes, releasing and facilitating absorption of its fatty acids, monoglycerides and lipid-soluble vitamins. The bile salts are later reabsorbed themselves in the large intestine and recycled through the hepatic portal vein back to the hepatocytes, in what is called the enterohepatic circulation. Soluble fiber in the diet, such as psyllium, interferes with the reabsorption of these bile salts. As a result, the hepatocytes metabolize new bile salts using cholesterol from the blood, helping to lower LDL cholesterol. </p><p id="ee14e8abf37e4e31b3c538c8692812a1">There are also other mechanisms by which both soluble and insoluble fiber affect the body’s cholesterol metabolism and balance. The liver also excretes excess cholesterol in the bile. When the bile becomes supersaturated with such excess cholesterol, one of the three kinds of bile stones may form and obstruct the bile ducts. Not surprisingly, this type of gallstone is often associated with obesity. The absence of bile salts in bile results in a condition called steattorhea, where fats remain mainly undigested in the feces and can lead to diarrhea and fat malabsorption. This condition can result from liver damage or be a side-effect after the gallbladder is removed (cholecystectomy).</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="digest_bile_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><section id="ce0cbe1d5f654dcd826228a7ed214a17"><title>Intestinal Juice</title><body><p id="f8d1d6399d184500b57ebb1038e0ecf6">The intestinal glands at the base of villi produce intestinal juice, a mixture of water and mucus. Each day, about one to two quarts (1-2 liters) are secreted. The mucus in intestinal juice is produced by both the duodenal glands and the goblet cells of the mucosa. The difference is that the mucus produced by the duodenal glands is alkaline, while goblet cell mucus is typically neutral. Progressing along the jejunum and into the ileum, goblet cells become more abundant. Secretion of intestinal juice is primarily stimulated by distension of the small intestine or the irritating effects of hypertonic or acidic chyme on the intestinal mucosa. The mucus also protects the surface cells from abrasion as the food moves through the lumen. Although the intestinal juice mucus secreted doesn’t have a direct digestive function, it does play an important role as a substrate for digestion. Extending into the mucus, but embedded in the cell membrane of intestinal villi cells, are various enzymes. These cell membrane surface enzymes are very important for the final digestion of organic substances before absorption. </p></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
