<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_29">
	<head>
		<title>Digestive Functions of the Stomach</title>
		<objref idref="stomach_muscles_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>The stomach participates in virtually all digestive activities with the exception of
			ingestion and defecation. In addition to mechanical and chemical digestion, the stomach
			absorbs some fat-soluble substances, including alcohol and aspirin.</p>
		<!--<table>
			<tr>
				<td><em style="bold">Structure</em></td>
				<td><em style="bold">Action</em></td>
				<td><em style="bold">Outcome</em></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Muscularis Externa</td>
				<td>Mixing wavesPeristalsis</td>
				<td>Forms chyme by liquefying food and mixing it with gastric juicePropels chyme
					through pyloric sphincter</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Pyloric sphincter</td>
				<td>Controls passage of chyme from the stomach to the duodenum</td>
				<td>Delivers chyme to the intestine at a rate optimal for digestion and absorption;
					prevents chyme from flowing back to stomach from duodenum</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Chief cells</td>
				<td>Secrete pepsinogenSecrete gastric lipase</td>
				<td>Pepsin (activated form) breaks proteins down into peptidesBreaks down
					triglycerides into fatty acids and monoglycerides</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>G cells</td>
				<td>Secrete gastrin</td>
				<td>Activates secretion of HCl by parietal cells and pepsinogen by chief cells;
					contracts lower esophageal sphincter, enhances stomach motility, and relaxes
					pyloric sphincter</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Parietal cells</td>
				<td>Secrete HClSecrete intrinsic factor</td>
				<td>Kills food microbes; denatures proteins, transforms pepsinogen into
					pepsinEnables vitamin B12 absorption for red blood cell formation</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Surface mucous cells and mucous neck cells</td>
				<td>Secrete mucusAbsorption</td>
				<td>Protects stomach wall from digestive processesAllows limited amount of water,
					ions, short-chain fatty acids, and certain drugs to enter bloodstream</td>
			</tr>
		</table>-->
		<section>
			<title>Mechanical Digestion</title>
			<body>
				<p>A few minutes after food enters the stomach, mixing waves begin at intervals of
					about 15 to 25 seconds. <term>Mixing waves</term> are a gentle type of
					peristalsis that soften and moisten food. They also combine food with gastric
					juice and create chyme. Initial gentle mixing waves are followed by more intense
					waves that break down food into smaller pieces and further mix with digestive
					juice, starting at the body of the stomach and increasing in force as they reach
					the pylorus.</p>
				<p>The pylorus, which holds around 30 mL (1 ounce) of chyme, acts as a filter,
					permitting only liquids and small food particles to pass through the mostly, but
					not fully, closed pyloric sphincter. When food enters the pylorus, periodic
					mixing waves force about 3 mL of chyme through the pyloric sphincter and into
					the duodenum, a process called <term>gastric emptying</term>. The rest
					of the chyme is pushed back into the body of the stomach, where it continues
					mixing. This process is repeated when the next mixing waves force more chyme
					into the duodenum. These forward and backward movements accomplish most of the
					mixing in the stomach.</p>
				<p>Gastric emptying is regulated by both the stomach and the duodenum. The presence
					of chyme in the duodenum activates receptors that inhibit gastric emptying. This
					prevents additional chyme from being released by the stomach before the duodenum
					is ready to process it.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Chemical Digestion</title>
			<body>
				<p>Some foods sit in the fundus of the stomach for an hour or so before they are
					mixed with gastric juice. During this time, the digestive activity of salivary
					amylase continues. Mixing waves soon take over however, combining chyme with
					acidic gastric juice, which inactivates salivary amylase and activates lingual
					and gastric lipase. Lingual lipase then starts breaking down triglycerides into
					fatty acids and diglycerides.</p>
				<p>The digestion of protein begins in the stomach, primarily by pepsin. During
					infancy, gastric glands also produce <term>rennin</term>, an enzyme
					that helps digest milk protein. Lingual lipase secreted by the salivary glands
					may also participate in triglyceride digestion in the stomach. Parietal cells
					secrete hydrogen ions and chloride ions into the stomach lumen, effectively
					forming HCl, which denatures dietary proteins.</p>
				<p>The contents of the stomach are completely emptied into the duodenum within two
					to four hours after you eat a meal. Carbohydrate-rich foods are the quickest to
					leave the stomach. High-protein foods exit a little more slowly. Fatty meals
					with high triglyceride content remain in the stomach the longest. Enzymes in the
					small intestine digest fats slowly. So when the duodenum is processing fatty
					chyme, food can stay in the stomach for six hours or longer.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<wb:inline idref="stomach_muscles_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
