<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_23">
	<head>
		<title>Pharynx</title>
		<objref idref="food_structures_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="food_structures_mouth"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>The <term>pharynx</term> (throat) is a funnel-shaped tube that runs from the
			choanae (internal nostrils) to the esophagus posteriorly and to the larynx anteriorly.
			The pharynx has three subdivisions: the nasopharynx, the oropharynx, and the
			laryngopharynx. The <term>nasopharynx</term> acts as a passageway for air
			during ventilation, while the other two subdivisions participate in both ventilation and
			digestion. Superiorly, the oropharynx is connected with the nasopharynx, inferiorly with
			the larynx and laryngopharynx, and anteriorly with the mouth.</p>
		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M3_23.jpg" width="400" alt="Areas of the pharynx - nasopharynx, oropharynx, and laryngopharynx."><caption>The Pharynx. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
			Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
				href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
				>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption></image>
		<p>Histologically, the wall of the pharynx is similar to that of the oral cavity. The mucosa
			includes a epithelium with mucous-producing glands. The nasopharynx is lined with
			pseudostratified columnar epithelium; the oropharynx and laryngopharynx are lined with
			stratified squamous. There are two skeletal muscle layers in the external muscle layer
			of the pharyngeal wall. Cells in the inner layer extend longitudinally. In the outer
			layer, the <term>superior</term>, <term>middle</term>, and <term>inferior pharyngeal constrictor muscles</term> are stacked, one inside
			the other, like flowerpots. Contraction of these muscles propels food toward the
			esophagus.</p>
		<p>When swallowed food enters the <term>oropharynx</term> and <term>laryngopharynx</term>, it provokes contractions of the pharyngeal constrictor muscles
			that help push food into the esophagus. Usually during swallowing, the soft palate moves
			back to close off the nasopharynx, while the trachea ("windpipe") moves up under the
			epiglottis to cover the glottis (the opening to the larynx or voice box); this
			effectively blocks off air passages. But we all know what it feels like to have food "go
			down the wrong tube," which means it either goes into the nasal cavities or the trachea.
			When food enters the trachea, our reaction is to cough, which usually forces the food up
			and out of the trachea and back into the pharynx.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
