<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_33">
	<head>
		<title>Bacterial Flora in the Large Intestine</title>
		<objref idref="lgintest_bacteria_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>There are many species of bacteria that populate the large intestines. They
			digest food products for which we do not have enzymes (such as plant materials)
			and we absorb some of the nutrient products. They can also produce some vitamins
			like vitamin K and B vitamins. A byproduct of bacterial fermentation (digestion)
			is gas (flatus).</p>
		<p>Although the bacteria provide additional nutrients from the food we ingest, they
			can also infect us. Because of the large and diverse bacterial population that
			resides in the large intestine, the large intestine also contains plentiful
			lymphatic tissue to protect us from potentially harmful effects of resident
			bacteria.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="digest_large_intestine_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
		<p>Most bacteria that migrate to the cecum from the small intestine have already been killed
			by lysozyme and other antibacterial molecules, HCl, and protein-digesting enzymes. Those
			that are still living, along with bacteria that come into the alimentary canal through
			the anus, are referred to as the large intestine's (enteric) <term>bacterial
				flora</term>. The more than 700 species of bacterial flora in the colon participate in
			chemical digestion and absorption. The large intestine is also home to a number of
			viruses and protozoans, at least 20 of which are known pathogens.</p>
		<p>Most enteric bacteria are nonpathogenic <term>commensals</term> (also called
			symbiotic, wityh benefit to both organisms) that cause no harm as long as they stay in
			the gut lumen. A refined system prevents these bacteria from crossing the mucosal
			barrier. First, certain bacterial components activate the release of chemicals by the
			mucosa's epithelial cells, which recruit immune cells, especially dendritic cells, into
			the mucosa. Dendritic cells open the tight junctions between epithelial cells and extend
			probes into the lumen to evaluate the microbial antigens. The dendritic cells then
			travel to neighboring lymphoid follicles in the mucosa and hand over the antigens to T
			cells. This triggers an IgA antibody-mediated response in the lumen that blocks the
			commensals from infiltrating the mucosa and setting off a far greater, widespread
			systematic reaction.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="lgestest_bacteria_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
