<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_04"><head><title>Gastric Juice</title><objref idref="digest_secretions_LO" /></head><body><section id="fec51da095e84063ac517fabb0dfaff4"><title>Enzymes and Acids of the Stomach</title><body><p id="d03587a38fbc49348fdf5fdc33a61696">Gastric glands produce <term>hydrochloric acid (HCl)</term>, enzymes, and <term>intrinsic factor</term>. HCl is responsible for the high acidity (<activity_link idref="ph_wbk_mod_ml" target="new" purpose="checkpoint">pH</activity_link> 1.5 to 3.5) of the stomach contents. The acidity directly kills a lot of the bacteria we ingest with food and helps <extra id="baeddc1aa4dd435cbaa55a4b489e1153"><anchor>denature</anchor><p id="c860ec100c2745c4bcf922c39143bbd7">disruption of protein structure, usually making it more amenable to enzymatic digestion.</p></extra> proteins and substances found in plants. In the presence of gastric juice’s low pH, the inactive enzyme, <term>pepsinogen</term>, is modified to become the active protein enzyme, <term>pepsin</term>. Protein enzymes of the digestive system are produced and secreted in an inactive form, to be activated only in the lumen, thus preventing digestion of the cells themselves. The glycoprotein <term>intrinsic</term> factor is necessary for the absorption of vitamin B<sub>12</sub> later in the small intestine.</p><p id="a0973ead2ecb4013a631d80b26c9381f">It is amazing that cells of the body can produce acids that normally would destroy the cell itself. Strong acids are also produced in cells in the immune system (to break down foreign organisms) and the skeletal system (to break down mineralized bone). High levels of acidity in the wrong places can be very destructive to living cells. Our body has several mechanisms to control pH.</p><p id="d6e91d04300e4cf398122614da4f9dde">In the stomach cell, the enzyme carbonic anhydrase converts one molecule of carbon dioxide and one molecule of water indirectly into a bicarbonate ion (HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>) and a hydrogen ion (H<sup>+</sup>). In the stomach ion exchange is used to move H<sup>+ </sup>ions out the cells and into the lumen of the stomach.</p></body></section><image id="ac6b539de4e84a4da339e0857d11294d" src="../../webcontent/D_M1_9.jpg" alt="Enzymes, ions, and channels inloved in the production of HCl in a parietal cell of the stomach lumen." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="450"><caption><p id="bcc06d68ea154cac80bf91b6c0a24a8c">Production of Hydrochloric Acid (HCl). This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><wb:inline idref="define_enzymes_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><p id="c01581b7393245bdab2d51f89d760752">The bicarbonate ion (HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>) is then exchanged for a chloride ion (Cl<sup>-</sup>) on the basal side (away from the lumen) of the cell. Potassium (K<sup>+</sup>) and chloride (Cl<sup>-</sup>) ions diffuse into the secretory region of the cell called the <term>canaliculi</term>. Then the potassium is exchanged in this region for hydrogen ions via a H+/K+ ATPase. The hydrogen ions, which are millions of times more concentrated in this region of the cell than any other, are then pumped from the canaliculi into the lumen of the stomach. The following video illustrates this process.</p><youtube id="b7c8f6813aab4125b09509d654e92e7c" src="CSXxu5NRevk" height="300" width="500" controls="true"><title>Production of Hydrochloric Acid in the Stomach</title><cite id="i853b793cd4384c0ab6b69f57cc981793" /><caption><p id="adafbb121696b40aea6d767311beaebeb">Explanation of how the stomach produces hydrochloric acid without the lumen&apos;s cells being harmed in the process.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube><section id="cbb8099114214b908f3876d776e6ef33"><title>Mucosal Barrier</title><body><p id="a518123b666d46909adb682776ce50b7">Once the hydrochloric acid is produced in the stomach lumen, this creates a low (acidic) pH that could potentially destroy the cells in the mucosal layer of the stomach. However, there are several structural and functional components that are part of an effective mucosal barrier that protects the stomach cells and prevents the stomach from digesting itself. The thick mucus layer produced by gastric mucus cells has lots of bicarbonate ions that will buffer the effect of the acid in the lumen. This stable, pH neutral mucus layer also provides a barrier to the now activated pepsin enzymes in the lumen as well. The surface gastric epithelial cells under the mucus layer have tight cell-to-cell junctions that would prevent transcellular reabsorption of hydrochloric acid from the lumen. Like epithelial tissue elsewhere in the body, these gastric surface cells are replaced continually by gastric stem cells that are stimulated to divide more rapidly if there is tissue damage from the gastric juice. Prostaglandins are chemical messages involved in cell inflammation response to injury. Prostaglandins produced in the stomach stimulate production of gastric mucus and bicarbonate and promote tissue healing. When the mucosal barrier breaks down and tissue destruction reaches into the deeper connective and muscular layers of the stomach, this is called a peptic or gastric ulcer.</p></body></section><example id="d57bcc9158c1417b82466498bf59d571"><title>Ulcers: When the Mucosal Barrier Breaks Down</title><p id="c83cb6d4b96a4d53a7ce5a633ce5c5f2">Aspirin and other non-steroid anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are known to increase the risk of gastric ulcers. NSAIDs break down the mucosal layer and reduce secretion of bicarbonate ion, but even when they are enteric coated to protect the cells from contact, they increase the risk of gastric ulcers.</p><wb:inline idref="digest_mucous_barrier_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="a92dfd9cfb1840799f6c125574d407f3">The acidity of gastric juice destroys many, but not all bacteria. There is one bacterium, <em style="italic">Helicobacter pylori</em>, adapted to live in the stomach mucus layer. Most people have this bacterium in their stomach with no symptoms, but in some people the bacterium is linked to increased incidence of gastric ulcers. There is still uncertainty about why only some people are affected this way. The bacterium uses the enzyme urease to convert urea to ammonia that helps neutralize acid in the mucus layer locally. If the mucus becomes too acidic for the bacterium, it can also induce an inflammatory response that lowers the gastric juice acidity. This immune response and associate release of free radicals may stimulate the formation of the ulcers in affected individuals. Once the causal link between ulcers and <em style="italic">H. pylori</em> was discovered, a new treatment for ulcers was implemented and the number of gastric ulcers in developed countries fell sharply.</p><wb:inline idref="digest_mucous_barrier_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="bb9450224f54404aaa41642a4e007b80">There is evidence to suggest that the H. pylori should be considered to be colonizing the stomach, like other GI tract microbiota, rather than infecting the stomach because it does have some protective effects. As the incidence of gastric ulcers fell in developed countries due to the use of antibiotics, the incidence of esophageal reflux and cancer increased. Research has shown that the presence of H. pylori is inversely related to the incidence of not only GERD and esophageal cancer, but also childhood diarrhea, IBS, asthma and even tuberculosis. So there are interesting interactions between this bacterium and its human host that need further study.</p></example><wb:inline idref="protein_enzy_sc" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="a016bd25c6f64f7db58da409ed14a2b0" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="digest_mucous_barrier_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="define_gastric_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
