<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_48"><head><title>Absorption Function of the Small Intestine - 2</title><objref idref="nutrient_absorption_LO" /></head><body><section id="bf9bba384aad40799cfcf9600dd35a82"><title>Electrolyte Absorption</title><body><p id="c34b400d89f748e5ac492fd2cbe9b863">The electrolytes absorbed by the small intestine are from both GI secretions and ingested foods and liquids. Recall that electrolytes are compounds that separate into ions in water. Most ions are absorbed throughout the entire small intestine. Exceptions are iron and calcium, which are primarily absorbed in the duodenum.</p><p id="f83673f2aeb64a7bb10f3004fd701821">In the small intestine, sodium ion absorption is linked via co-transport mechanisms to the absorption of glucose and amino acids. A sodium-potassium pump moves sodium ions from the basolateral side of small intestine epithelial cells into the bloodstream they enter. Chloride ions are also absorbed via active transport. Changing osmotic gradients passively move potassium ions across the intestinal mucosa via facilitated diffusion (or via leaky tight junctions).</p><p id="ade4f268acdc42ce940ed43bc1c221aa">In general, all nutrients that enter the intestine are absorbed, whether we need them or not. Iron and calcium are exceptions; they are absorbed in amounts that fulfill the needs of our body. The iron ion needed for the production of hemoglobin is absorbed into mucosal cells via active transport. Once inside mucosal cells, ionic iron binds to the protein ferritin, creating iron-ferritin complexes that act as intracellular storage facilities for iron. When the body has enough iron, most of the stored iron is lost when worn-out epithelial cells slough off. When the body needs iron because, for example, it is lost during acute or chronic bleeding, there is increased uptake of iron from the intestine and accelerated release of iron into the blood. Because women experience significant iron loss during menstruation, they have around four times as many iron transport proteins in their intestinal epithelial cells as men.</p><p id="a951649b2a6344ea8aa2eb9d2da3435d">Blood levels of ionic calcium (Ca2+) determine the absorption of calcium. The active form of vitamin D, under the control of parathyroid hormone, provides local regulation of this process in the intestines. When blood levels of ionic calcium drop, parathyroid hormone (PTH) secreted by the parathyroid glands stimulates the release of calcium ions from bone matrix and increases the reabsorption of calcium by the kidneys. PTH also provokes the activation of vitamin D by the kidneys, which triggers greater calcium ion absorption in the small intestine.</p></body></section><section id="bc700d4ad53f41689d5dbb770f3f91e3"><title>Vitamin Absorption</title><body><p id="db46dd29caaf42108afc4e96e1691165">Vitamins in our food are absorbed in the small intestine. Some of the vitamin K and B vitamins created by enteric bacteria are absorbed in the large intestine. Fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, and K) are absorbed along with dietary lipids in micelles via simple diffusion. In fact, you need some fat in your diet in order to be able to absorb fat-soluble vitamins. Some of the B vitamins are not actually found in our food but are made by gut bacteria. Most water-soluble vitamins are absorbed by simple diffusion , including most B vitamins and vitamin C. An exception is vitamin B12, which is a very large molecule. Intrinsic factor secreted in the stomach binds to vitamin B12, creating a combination that can bind to mucosal receptors in the terminal ileum, launching its active uptake by endocytosis.</p></body></section><section id="cd59b436a5ec437984afaa5837694110"><title>Water Absorption</title><body><p id="c513ba8d48974537a2ecdfedc99fc4ad">Each day, about nine liters (9.8 quarts) of fluid enter the small intestine; about 2.3 liters are ingested, and the rest is from GI secretions. About 95 percent of water is absorbed in the small intestine. The absorption of water in the alimentary canal occurs via osmosis. Around 300 to 400 mL of water is absorbed per hour. Water can move easily in both directions across the intestinal mucosa. The active transport of solutes into mucosal cells establishes a concentration gradient that results in water moving into the cells via the process of osmosis. As water enters the cells, it concentrates the solutes left in the lumen, enhancing the absorption of those molecules absorbed by passive diffusion. This means that the absorption of water is essentially linked to the absorption of solutes, which, in turn, determines the absorptive rate of those salts and sugars that are absorbed via diffusion. The water that moves into the mucosal cells is followed by these substances along their concentration gradients.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u8_digestion_absorption_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /></body></workbook_page>
