<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_21">
	<head>
		<title>Teeth</title>
		<objref idref="food_structures_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="id_teeth_LO"/>-->
	</head>


	<body>

		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M3_22.jpg" width="400"
			alt="identifying the specific teeth within the mouth."><caption>Specific teeth and structures of the mouth. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption></image>
		<p>The teeth, or <term>dentes</term>, are secured in sockets of the alveolar processes of
			the maxillae and mandible. <term>Gingivae</term> (gums; singular gingiva) cover the
			alveolar processes. Lining the sockets is the <term>periodontal ligament</term>, a dense
			fibrous connective tissue that secures the teeth in place. The teeth are covered by
				<term>enamel</term>, which is the hardest substance in the body. Enamel helps
			prevent teeth from being worn down when we chew, and it helps keep out acids that could
			easily dissolve the interior of a tooth.</p>
		<p>Humans have two sets of teeth (<term>dentitions</term>). The 20 <term>deciduous teeth</term>, or baby teeth, first appear at about 6 months of age. Between
			ages 6 and 12 years, these teeth are replaced by the 32 <term>permanent teeth</term>.
			Closest to the midline are the two <term>incisors</term>, chisel-shaped teeth we use for
			cutting into food. The <term>cuspids</term> (<term>canines</term>) are next to
			the incisors. A cuspid’s pointed edge (<term>cusp</term>) tears and shreds
			food. Posteriorly, the next teeth are the two premolars (bicuspids) followed by up to
			three molars. Premolars and molars have broader, flatter surfaces, which we use to crush
			and grind food.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="id_teeth_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
