<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_09">
	<head>
		<title>Cells of the Stomach</title>
		<!--<objref idref="HCI_cells_LO"/>
		<objref idref="digestive_cells_LO"/>
		<objref idref="digest_cell_function"/>-->
		<objref idref="GIcell_specialization_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>A single layer of epithelial cells forms the inner most later of the stomach, called the
			mucosa. The mucosa is marked by depressions called gastric pits (these are lined with
			epithelial cells). The gastric gland is at the bottom of the pit, which contain multiple
			cell types: mucous cells, stem cells, parietal cells, chief cells, and G cells
			(enteroendocrine cells).</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M2_11.jpg" width="450"
			alt="Gastric pits in the mucosa and the epithelial cells lining it.">
			<caption>Cells of the gastric pit in the mucosa. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>

		<section>
			<title>Exocrine Function</title>
			<body>

				<p>Digestion in the stomach requires a combination of acid and pepsin. In the glands
					of the stomach, <term>chief cells</term> secrete pepsinogen, which is converted
					to pepsin, as well as gastric lipase, which is used for digestion of fats.
						<term>Parietal cells</term> secrete hydrochloric acid (HCl) as well as
					intrinsic factor.The gastric mucous cells associated with the surface and neck
					of the gastric pit secrete a thick mucus that is more alkaline than the mucus
					produced by goblet cells found elsewhere in epithelial tissue. This helps
					provide a protective mucosal barrier from the acid and protein enzymes in the
					gastric juice.</p>
			</body>
		</section>



		<section>
			<title>Endocrine Function</title>

			<body>
				<p>Regulation within the digestive system is tightly controlled by
						<term>enteroendocrine cells</term>. Collectively, these cells are found in
					the organs of the digestive system (entero- inside) and release hormones and
					paracrine signals which regulate production of digestive chemicals and also
					influence the nervous system for global regulation of digestion. Within the
					stomach, the enteroendocrine cells are called <term>G-cells</term>.</p>
				<p>G-cells secrete the signaling molecules including <term>gastrin</term>. Gastrin
					signals parietal cells (HCl producing) and chief cells (enzyme producing) to
					regulate production and alters stomach motility by altering the sphincter
					function on either side of the stomach. G cells also secrete other paracrines –
					serotonin, histamine, somatostatin, and other hormones which regulate
					digestion.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="HCI_cells_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>

		<section>
			<title>Overview of Stomach Cells</title>
			<body>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<th><em style="bold">Structure</em></th>
						<th><em style="bold">Action</em></th>
						<th><em style="bold">Outcome</em></th>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Gastric epithelial cells</em></td>
						<td>Structure of the stomach lumen</td>
						<td>Maintains structure of the mucosa</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Chief cells</em></td>
						<td>Secrete pepsinogenSecrete gastric lipase</td>
						<td>Pepsin (activated form) breaks proteins down into peptidesBreaks down
							triglycerides into fatty acids and monoglycerides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>G cells</em></td>
						<td>Secrete gastrin</td>
						<td>Activates secretion of HCl by parietal cells and pepsinogen by chief
							cells; contracts lower esophageal sphincter, enhances stomach motility,
							and relaxes pyloric sphincter</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Parietal cells</em></td>
						<td>Secrete HClSecrete intrinsic factor</td>
						<td>Kills microbes; denatures proteins, transforms pepsinogen into
							pepsinEnables vitamin B12 absorption, which is necessary for red blood
							cell formation</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<wb:inline idref="HCI_cells_LBD1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				<wb:inline idref="HCI_cells_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>

			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
