<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_08">
	<head>
		<title>Overview of Chemical Digestion</title>
		<objref idref="digest_secretions_LO"/>
		
	</head>
	<body>
		
		
		<section>
			<title>Carbohydrates in Digestion</title>
			<body>
				<p>The mouth is where the chemical digestion of starch and possibly glycogen begins.
					Salivary amylase acts to break down the polysaccharide starch into the
					disaccharide maltose, the trisaccharide maltotriose, and short chains of glucose
					called α-dextrins.</p>
				<p><term>Pancreatic amylase</term> in the small intestine continues the chemical
					digestion of starch and other digestible carbohydrates that have not been broken
					down into maltose, maltotriose, and α-dextrins by salivary amylase. After starch
					has been broken down into smaller fragments by salivary or pancreatic amylase,
					the brush-border enzyme <term>α-dextrinase</term> starts working on the
					resulting <term>α-dextrins</term>, breaking off one glucose unit at a time. The
					disaccharides sucrose, lactose, and maltose are not digested until they enter
					the small intestine. Here, three brush-border enzymes hydrolyze them into
					monosaccharides. <term>Sucrase</term> splits sucrose into one molecule of
					fructose and one molecule of glucose; <term>lactase</term> breaks down lactose
					into one molecule of glucose and one molecule of galactose; and
						<term>maltase</term> breaks down maltose and maltotriose into two and three
					glucose molecules, respectively. The digestive system can then absorb
					monosaccharides.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Proteins</title>
			<body>
				<p>The digestion of protein starts in the stomach, where pepsin breaks down proteins
					into peptides. In the small intestine, trypsin and chymotrypsin hydrolyze
					polypeptides into smaller peptides, and <term>elastase</term> fragments whole
					proteins into peptides. The small peptides are then broken down into monomers.
					Carboxypeptidase cleaves a single <term>amino acid</term> from the carboxy
					terminus of a small peptide, whereas <term>aminopeptidase</term> cleave an amino
					acid from the amino terminus. <term>Dipeptidase</term> splits dipeptides in the
					middle, liberating two amino acids.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Lipids</title>
			<body>
				<p>Triglycerides and their breakdown products do not dissolve in water. Before they
					can be digested in the watery environment of the small intestine, large lipid
					globules must be separated into smaller lipid globules, a process called
					emulsification, which is aided by the presence of bile salts. Recall that bile
					salts facilitate emulsification of large lipid globules.intosmall lipid globules
					of about 1 µm in diameter.[link to bile salts] This emulsification greatly
					increases the surface area to volume ratio of fat globules, which allows
					pancreatic lipase to access more lipid molecules.</p>
				<p>The three lipases involved in the digestion of triglycerides and phospholipidsare lingual
					lipase (in the saliva), <term>gastric lipase</term>, and <term>pancreatic
						lipase</term>. Pancreatic lipase in the small intestine does most of the
					lipid digestion. Pancreatic lipase breaks down triglycerides into fatty acids
					and monoglycerides. The fatty acids include both short-chain (less than 10 to 12
					carbons) and long-chain fatty acids.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Nucleic Acids</title>
			<body>
				<p>Nucleic acids, including DNA and RNA, are in the cells of all once-living things
					which we may ingest. There are two nucleases in pancreatic juice –
						<term>deoxyribonuclease</term>, which digests DNA, and
						<term>ribonuclease</term>, which digests RNA. The nucleotides that are the
					products of this digestion are further broken down by intestinal brush-border
					enzymes (<term>nucleosidases</term> and <term>phosphatases</term>) into
					pentosesugars, phosphates, and nitrogenous bases, which can be absorbed through
					the GI tract wall.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="enzy_secretions1_la" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
		
		<section>
			<title>The Digestive Enzymes</title>
			<body>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<th>Enzyme</th>
						<th>Source</th>
						<th>Food</th>
						<th>Product</th>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td colspan="4" align="center"><em>Saliva</em></td>
						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Lingual Lipase</em></td>
						<td>Lingual glands</td>
						<td>Triglycerides (fats and oils), other lipids</td>
						<td>Fatty acids and diglycerides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Salivary Amylase</em></td>
						<td>Salivary glands</td>
						<td>Polysaccharides (starches)</td>
						<td>α-Dextrins, disaccharide (maltose), trisaccharide (maltotriose)</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td colspan="4" align="center"><em>Gastric juice</em></td>
						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Gastric lipase</em></td>
						<td>Stomach chief cells</td>
						<td>Triglycerides (fats and oils)</td>
						<td>Fatty acids and monoglycerides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Pepsin*</em></td>
						<td>Stomach chief cells</td>
						<td>Proteins</td>
						<td>Peptides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td colspan="4" align="center"><em>Brush-border</em></td>
						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>α-Dextrinase</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>α-Dextrins</td>
						<td>Glucose</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Enteropeptidase</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>Trypsinogen</td>
						<td>Trypsin</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Lactase</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>Lactose</td>
						<td>Glucose and galactose</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Maltase</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>Maltose</td>
						<td>Glucose</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Nucleosidases and phosphatases</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>Nucleotides</td>
						<td>Phosphates, nitrogenous bases, and pentoses</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Peptidases</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>Aminopeptidase: amino acid at amino end of peptides Dipeptidase:
							dipeptides</td>
						<td>Aminopeptidase: amino acids and peptides Dipeptidase: amino acids</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Sucrase</em></td>
						<td>Small intestine</td>
						<td>Sucrose</td>
						<td>Glucose and fructose</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td colspan="4" align="center"><em>Pancreatic juice</em></td>
						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Carboxy-peptidase*</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Amino acid at carboxyl end of peptides</td>
						<td>Amino acids and peptides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Chymotrypsin*</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Proteins</td>
						<td>Peptides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Elastase*</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Proteins</td>
						<td>Peptides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Nucleases</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Ribonuclease: ribonucleic acidDeoxyribonuclease: deoxyribonucleic
							acid</td>
						<td>Nucleotides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Pancreatic amylase</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Polysaccharides (starches)</td>
						<td>α-Dextrins, disaccharide (maltose), trisaccharide (maltotriose)</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Pancreatic lipase</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Triglycerides that have been emulsified by bile salts</td>
						<td>Fatty acids and monoglycerides</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em>Trypsin*</em></td>
						<td>Pancreatic acinar cells</td>
						<td>Proteins</td>
						<td>Peptides</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<p>*These enzymes have been activated by other substances.</p>
				
			</body>
		</section>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_enzymes_LBD" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
