<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_32">
	<head>
		<title>Large Intestine Gross Anatomy</title>
		<objref idref="id_rectum_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>The first part of the large intestine is the <term>cecum</term>, a small
			sac-like region that is suspended inferior to the ileocecal valve. This cecum is about
			2.4 inches long. The <term>appendix</term> or <term>vermiform
				appendix</term> (<em style="italic">vermiform</em> = “worm-shaped”, and <em
				style="italic">appendix</em> = “appendage”) is a winding, coiled tube that attaches
			to the cecum. This 2-7 cm (~3 inch) long appendix contains lymphoid tissue and plays an
			important role in immunity. Nevertheless, its twisted anatomy provides a haven for the
			accumulation and multiplication of enteric bacteria. The <term>mesoappendix</term>,
			the mesentery of the appendix, tethers it to the inferior part of the mesentery of
			the ileum.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M4_30.jpg" width="400"></image>
		<p>The end of the cecum joins with the <term>colon</term>, a long tube with several
			distinct areas. The <term>ascending colon</term> runs up the right side of the
			abdomen. At the inferior surface of the liver, it takes a right-angle turn, forming the
				<term>right colic</term> (hepatic) flexure and becoming the <em
				style="bold">transverse colon</em>. The transverse colon runs across to the left
			side of the abdomen. It then bends sharply at a point immediately anterior to the
			spleen, forming the <term>left colic (splenic) flexure</term>. As the <em
				style="bold">descending colon</em>, it runs down the left side of the posterior
			abdominal wall. After entering the pelvis inferiorly, it becomes the s-shaped <term>sigmoid colon</term>, which extends medially to the midline (Figure
			24.19). Most of the colon is between the peritoneal membrane and the body wall, except
			for the intraperitoneal transverse and sigmoid colons, which are tethered to the
			posterior abdominal wall by mesocolons.</p>
		<p>The sigmoid colon joins the rectum in the pelvis, near the third sacral vertebra. The <term>rectum</term> is the final 8 inches (20 cm) of the alimentary canal. It
			extends anterior to the sacrum and coccyx. Even though <term>rectum</term> is
			Latin for "straight," this structure has three lateral bends that create a trio of
			internal transverse folds called the <term>rectal valves</term>. These valves
			allow passing of gas (flatus) while preventing the simultaneous passage of feces.</p>
		<p>The last part of the large intestine is the <term>anal canal</term>, which is
			located in the perineum, completely outside the abdominopelvic cavity. This 1 inch (3
			cm) long structure opens to the exterior of the body at the anus. The anal canal
			includes two sphincters. The involuntary <term>internal anal sphincter</term>
			is made of smooth muscle; the voluntary <em style="bold">external anal sphincter
			</em>is skeletal muscle. Except when defecating, these two sphincters are usually
			closed.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="id_rectum_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		
	</body>
</workbook_page>
