<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_30">
	<head>
		<title>Small Intestine</title>
		<objref idref="smintest_regions_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The small intestine is a convoluted tube that begins just distal to the pyloric sphincter
			of the stomach and then loops through the central and inferior region of the abdomen
			before ending at the ileocecal valve, where it merges with the large intestine. The
			small intestine is the primary digestive organ in the body. Not only is it the part of
			the GI tract where digestion is completed, it is also where the majority of absorption
			occurs.</p>
		<p>Although the small intestine is the longest part of the GI tract, its diameter is about
			half that of the large intestine, averaging a little over one inch (2.5 cm). When we are
			alive, the small intestine is more than 3 meters (10 feet) long – the size of a
			one-story building. Its length provides expansive surface area necessary for digestion
			and absorption. However, circular folds, villi, and microvilli add even more surface
			area. With loss of muscle tone after death, the folds of the small intestine relax,
			extending it to about 20 feet in length.</p>
		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M4_29a.jpg" width="150"
			alt="Regions of the small intestine - duodenum, jujunum, and ileum.">
			<caption>This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United
				States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		<section>
			<title>Small Intestine Anatomy</title>
			<body>
				<p>The <term>duodenum</term> precedes the jejunum and ileum and is the shortest part
					of the small intestine; it is less than 1 foot of the 10 foot intestine (30 cm
					of the 3 m). The duodenum receives the stomach contents, pancreatic juice and
					bile. Chemical digestion continues in the duodenum. The <term>jejunum</term> is
					the next portion (3.5 - 5.5 ft or 110-170 cm) of the small intestine and is
					responsible for the absorption of a majority of nutrients. In the last section
					of the small intestine, the <term>ileum</term>, vitamin B12 and bile salts are
					absorbed as well as materials not absorbed by the jejunum.</p>
				
				<wb:inline idref="smintest_regions" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
				
				<p>The term <term>mucosa</term> or mucous membrane always refers to the combination
					of the epithelium plus the lamina propria. The lamina propria layer of the small
					intestinal mucosa is composed of areolar connective tissue and quite a bit of
					mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue. Most solitary lymphatic nodules are located
					in the distal portion of the ileum. The blood supply which runs through the
					lamina propria and drains the villus is part of the the hepatic portal systems
					and not general systemic circulaions</p>
				<p>In the ileum, the lamina propria also has <term>aggregated lymphatic
						follicles</term> (groups of lymphatic nodules) called <term>Peyer's
						patches</term>. There are more Peyer's patches toward the end of the small
					intestine, possibly because of the high amounts of bacteria in that area must be
					prevented from entering the bloodstream. The submucosa of the duodenum is the
					only site of the complex mucus-secreting <term>duodenal (Brunner's)
						glands</term>, which produce a bicarbonate-rich alkaline mucus that helps
					buffer the acidic chyme coming in from the stomach.</p>
				<p>Like in the rest of the GI tract, the muscularis externa layer is made of two
					layers of smooth muscle – an outer, thinner layer of longitudinal fibers and an
					inner, thicker layer of circular fibers. The serosa completely enshrouds the
					small intestine, with the exception of a large region of the duodenum.</p>
			
				<wb:inline idref="smintest_regions_sc" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>
				<wb:inline idref="smintest_regions_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
