<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_26"><head><title>Stomach</title><objref idref="stomach_structures_LO" /></head><body><p id="a80a4d42abcd4e2cb204d089f69c1435">The stomach is an expansion of the GI tract that lies below the esophagus. It is a very mobile structure between its relatively fixed upper and lower ends. The stomach is found between the esophagus to the first part of the small intestine (the duodenum). The stomach&apos;s position and size are always changing. It is about as big as a large sausage when empty, and stretches to hold 1 liter of food when full; the stomach has a final capacity of 2-3 liters. One of the digestive functions of the stomach is to serve as a temporary &quot;holding chamber&quot;. This is an important step in digestion, because we can eat a meal far more quickly than it can be digested and absorbed in the small intestine. So the stomach pushes only a small amount of food into the small intestine at a time.</p><p id="b80f345b4fdc450d81c09043ae91ae16">The stomach plays several important roles in chemical digestion, including the continued digestion of starch and the initial digestion of proteins and triglycerides. The stomach is also where the semisolid bolus is converted to a liquid (chyme) and where some ingested substances are absorbed.</p><section id="a043bf5e326d404890b29c936a4f9a62"><title>Stomach Anatomy</title><body><p id="d4746e8a5ffe4525849bb730b48296e2">There are four main regions in the stomach: the cardiac, fundus, body, and pylorus. The <term>cardiac</term> (<term>cardia region</term>) is a small area surrounding the cardiac orifice through which food from the esophagus enters the stomach. Lying beneath the diaphragm, superior and to the left of the cardiac, is the dome-shaped <term>fundus</term>, which functions as a temporary storage center for food. Inferior to the fundus is the <term>body</term>, the large central part of the stomach. The funnel-shaped <term>pylorus</term> connects the stomach to the duodenum. The <term>pyloric antrum</term> is the wider, more superior portion of the pylorus that connects to the body of the stomach. The pyloric antrum narrows into a region called the <term>pyloric canal</term>, which leads into the duodenum. The pylorus communicates with the duodenum via the smooth muscle <term>pyloric sphincter</term>. This sphincter controls stomach emptying. In the absence of food, the stomach deflates inward and its mucosa and submucosa fall into large folds called rugae.</p><materials id="e01fab068ce44543b84cbca70c11cd64"><material><image id="a8454554bd4b474f842dcb0c3c07bfff" src="../../webcontent/D_M3_26b.jpg" alt="Stomach regions - Cardia, Fundus, Body, pylorus." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption><p id="cf6afcab10e54a2ea23f1e70982856e2">Stomach anatomy. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><image id="f4bb655fb2e44f459baa7d2aa17024ba" src="../../webcontent/D_M3_26a.jpg" alt="Structures and curvatures of the stomach." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><caption /><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material></materials><p id="ca466131f9fc4a25a0cbd059c349aced">The convex lateral surface of the stomach is called the <term>greater curvature</term>; the concave medial border is the <term>lesser curvature</term>. Two fatty mesenteries (peritoneal folds) called omenta hold the stomach in place. The lesser omentum extends from the liver to the lesser curvature. The greater omentum runs from the greater curvature to the posterior abdominal wall.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="stomach_regions_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="a5abacd0a0a74a62a8b5721dceaf0e4a"><title>Adaptations of Stomach Wall</title><body><p id="cdf1c7c834914ecc85d118c23506f22a">The wall of the stomach is made of the same four tissue layers as most of the rest of the GI tract, but with adaptations to the mucosa and muscularis externa for the unique functions of this organ. In addition to the typical circular and longitudinal smooth muscle layers, the muscularis externa has an inner oblique smooth muscle layer that runs diagonally around the organ. As a result, in addition to moving food through the GI tract, the stomach can more vigorously churn and mix food, mechanically breaking it down into smaller particles.</p><materials id="ffb9b758e7584a26bcc60334595846f3"><material><image id="a7ca70357f3e4fbcafefc0c77d5f08d4" src="../../webcontent/D_M3_27.jpg" alt="Gatric pit in the lining of the stomach wall and the glands beneath them." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="300"><caption><p id="fbb8080b1b7b4bd3a0e369b2d7f46eb9">Gatric pit. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/" target="new" internal="false">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><image id="cec3128c22a44a70bb00a32e233e9c2f" src="../../webcontent/D_M3_28.jpg" alt="Histology section of a gastric pit with pits and glands labeled." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="350"><caption><p id="adf646ae38ca5477da15a409deb19ae3c">Histology section of a gastric pit. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 License© copyright 2010 Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material></materials><p id="e5e18522116240cf99fad2f6e87eca77">Millions of deep <term>gastric pits</term> in the epithelium lead into <term>gastric glands</term>, which secrete <term>gastric juice</term>. The walls of the gastric pits are made up primarily of epithelial cells. The gastric glands are made up of different types of cells. Glands of the cardia and pylorus are composed primarily of mucus-secreting cells. Cells that make up the pyloric antrum secrete mucus and a number of hormones, including gastrin. The much larger glands of the fundus and body of the stomach, the site of most chemical digestion, produce most of the gastric secretions. These glands are made up of a variety of secretory cells, including mucous neck, parietal, chief, and enteroendocrine cells (G-cells).</p><wb:inline idref="gastric_gland_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><table id="ee1e0cc309f3490397d3e58f29f91066" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i830df79acefa45c996f180ea8ad7d61f" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab4391c75e13b443f81bdf08065cd9571">Structure</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afa72f80c50da47ebb9b89a6a7f05d33a">Action</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac309c628442c4190a14dca7472cee317">Outcome</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="cbbd812bfc38459691181a7bc95cb271"><em style="italic">Muscularis Externa</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad55955208e784200a2b356a7e030cfea">Mixing waves</p><p id="ab868c204369a4fb093997e82410a9b63">Peristalsis</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae60eccb315b64bedab9a3a9c8f173263">Forms chyme by liquefying food and mixing it with gastric juice</p><p id="acc45df3a3579433d8bb3a7760ead4fc7">Propels chyme through pyloric sphincter</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ecb65cf067c34a85bdc483c7285b0efa"><em style="italic">Pyloric sphincter</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aabc1a6ae1ef743cd990d39b33ad2cca7">Controls passage of chyme from the stomach to the duodenum</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae2c8fc9124774e378f6d255375efff93">Delivers chyme to the intestine at a rate optimal for digestion and absorption</p><p id="ad59506b54de5412da89b5668d5c5376a">Prevents chyme from flowing back to stomach from duodenum</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="dc0afcd480174c01af8500c44699862f"><em style="italic">Chief cells</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af3b49acaba774c9788e0faa6c0c4e657">Secrete pepsinogen</p><p id="af1f96e81babd4c7fbe184020fda5b916">Secrete gastric lipase</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="acb3a14c0645447be8666a1414b7de035">Pepsin (activated form) breaks proteins down into peptides</p><p id="aa99d9605168a42ed96b4593a3f58d9dd">Breaks down triglycerides into fatty acids and monoglycerides</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b27d2fbef919483dbb782684dd6a8bd1"><em style="italic">G cells</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ab26f274eaf944966a75ccb79520daad0">Secrete gastrin</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac1259b5887be463a8248ccb09226a8cd">Activates secretion of HCl by parietal cells and pepsinogen by chief cells; contracts lower esophageal sphincter, enhances stomach motility, and relaxes pyloric sphincter</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="bcbf0fa692504b05a523034896c5e602"><em style="italic">Parietal cells</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af0b75e8f5cfa4679b803d4847988d0f0">Secrete HCl</p><p id="ad08fb28688054146bc33f215b9f9b6cd">Secrete intrinsic factor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="afde445b4b1cc4597b502a0ca7538cbcf">Kills food microbes; denatures proteins, transforms pepsinogen into pepsin</p><p id="abb5a3174ea324fa69e93f6ad089eb2f3">Enables vitamin B12 absorption for red blood cell formation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af3ac26c6f834a6a855016db82789667"><em style="italic">Surface mucous cells and mucous neck cells</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ac18d5d4b83964b10ade36bac0cabe3b1">Secrete mucus</p><p id="ab4456c8ac5604fb68f8a506ec2662b05">Absorption</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ae0dfaef463a14ce389dfe40af8acb5c9">Protects stomach wall from digestive processes</p><p id="aa6b47696cf604afbbd858ffc7d669093">Allows limited amount of water, ions, short-chain fatty acids, and certain drugs to enter bloodstream</p></td></tr></table></body></section></body></workbook_page>
