<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_06">
	<head>
		<title>Bile</title>
		<objref idref="digest_bile_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p><term>Bile</term> is a yellow-brown or yellow-green alkaline solution (pH 7.6 to 8.6)
			that contains mainly water, bile salts, bile pigments, phospholipids (such as lecithin),
			electrolytes, cholesterol, and triglycerides. The only components involved in digestion
			are bile salts and phospholipids. Bile salts and phospholipids are both amphipathic
			molecules with both a hydrophilic region and a hydrophobic region. Bile salts are
			produced from cholesterol and contain many of the same ring structures.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M1_10.jpg" width="450"></image>
		
		<p><term>Bile salts</term> and the phospholipid <term>lecithin</term> convert large lipid
			globules into small lipid globules in a process called <term>emulsification</term>
			[definition: emulsification - the breakdown of large globules of hydrocarbons, fats or
			lipids into smaller, uniformly distributed particles]. The non polar regions of bile
			salts and lecithin are attracted to the lipids via the hydrophobic effect and polar
			regions are left exposed to the digestive juices. The mechanical mixing in the
			intestines causes the large fat droplets to break into smaller fat droplets. Without the
			bile salts and lecithin, the small droplets would re-form big fat droplets, but the
			hydrophilic coating keeps the droplets broken up. We can observe the process of
			emulsificationby mixing dish detergent with fat reside, the detergent breaks down large
			droplets of oil and solubilizes the oil inwater.</p>
		<p>The smaller lipid globules then present a large surface area for the actions of
			pancreatic lipase, which digest triglycerides. Bile salts are also involved in the
			absorption of digested lipids. In contrast to the many constituents of bile that are
			eliminated in feces, bile salts are reclaimed by a recycling mechanism. The liver then
			secretes them again in newly created bile.</p>
		<p>Refresh yourself on <activity_link idref="levels_m1_lipids">lipids</activity_link> in
		chemistry section.</p>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_bile_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
