<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u8_m2_organization_47"><head><title>Absorption Function of the Small Intestine - 1</title><objref idref="nutrient_absorption_LO" /></head><body><p id="de1ee3b0d76842ccb3adc3508a975d14">Each day, the alimentary canal processes up to 10 liters of food, liquids, and GI secretions; of which, only about one liter enters the large intestine. Almost all ingested food and drink, 80 percent of electrolytes, and most of the water are absorbed in the small intestine. The entire small intestine is involved in absorption, but most absorption occurs before chyme reaches the <em style="emphasis">ileum</em> . Absorption in the ileum primarily involves the recycling of <em style="emphasis">bile salts</em> . The absorptive capacity of the alimentary canal is amazing. By the time chyme passes from the ileum into the large intestine, it is essentially indigestible food residue (mainly plant fibers like cellulose) some water, and millions of bacteria. </p><p id="a5753780406647df9d171715f66eb2d7">The absorption of most nutrients through the mucosa of the <em style="emphasis">intestinal villi</em> occurs via active transport mechanisms that are driven directly or indirectly by metabolic energy. These nutrients enter the capillary blood in the villus and travel to the liver via the <em style="emphasis">hepatic portal vein</em> . An exception is certain lipids, which undergo passive absorption via diffusion and then enter the modified lymph duct in the villus (called a <em style="emphasis">lacteal</em> ), to be transported to the blood in lymphatic fluid. Substances cannot be absorbed between the <em style="emphasis">epithelial cells</em> of the intestinal mucosa, because these cells connect with tight junctions. This is why substances can only enter blood capillaries by passing through the epithelial cells and into the interstitial fluid. </p><section id="ff61617b34d44a1b9a304b0ab3c4dc64"><title>Carbohydrate Absorption</title><body><p id="b9cf9322a9f9475a88280a27a3a5b196">All carbohydrates are absorbed in the form of monosaccharides. The small intestine is highly efficient at this, absorbing monosaccharides at an estimated rate of 120 grams per hour. All normally digested dietary carbohydrates are absorbed. However, indigestible fibers including cellulose, glucose polymers made by plants which is not broken down in humans, are eliminated in feces. The monosaccharides glucose and galactose – the products of the breakdown of starch and disaccharides – are transported into the epithelial cells by common protein carriers via secondary active transport, which requires ATP). They leave these cells via facilitated diffusion and enter the capillaries through intercellular clefts. The monosaccharide fructose (which is in fruit) is absorbed and transported by facilitated diffusion alone. Monosaccharides combine with the transport proteins, which lie very near the disaccharide splitting enzymes on the microvilli, immediately after disaccharides are broken down.</p></body></section><section id="d694ae6f4ff74a73bdc1041df84214fd"><title>Protein Absorption</title><body><p id="a22a0cd4bc974e78adc509044acbef97">Active transport mechanisms, primarily in the duodenum and jejunum, absorb most proteins as their breakdown products, amino acids. Almost all (95 to 98 percent) protein is digested and absorbed in the small intestine. The type of carrier that transports an amino acid varies. Most carriers are linked to the active transport of sodium. Short chains of two amino acids (dipeptides) or three amino acids (tripeptides) are also transported actively. But after they enter the absorptive epithelial cells, they are broken down to their amino acids before leaving the cell and entering the capillary blood via diffusion.</p></body></section><section id="e38a34d009ad4486b40729064c49ce17"><title>Lipid Absorption</title><body><p id="ae651a26173f4debb2317d1b41f76769">Despite being hydrophobic, the small size of short-chain fatty acids enables them to be absorbed in intestinal chyme, enter absorptive cells via simple diffusion, and then take the same path as monosaccharides and amino acids into the blood capillary of a villus. The large and hydrophobic long-chain fatty acids and monoglycerides are not so easily suspended in the watery intestinal chyme. However, bile salts and the phospholipid lecithin (also found in bile) help make them more soluble by surrounding them and creating tiny spheres called micelles. <em style="emphasis">Micelles</em> are macromolecular structures made up of aggregates of fatty elements and bile salts that create a polar (hydrophilic) end that faces the water and a nonpolar (hydrophobic) core. The core also includes cholesterol molecules and fat-soluble vitamins. Micelles can easily squeeze between microvilli and get very near the luminal cell surface. At this point, lipid substances exit the micelle and are absorbed via simple diffusion. Without their &quot;vehicles&quot; (i.e., the micelles), lipids would sit on the surface of chyme, like oil on water, and would never come in contact with the absorptive surfaces of the epithelial cells. About 95 percent of lipids are absorbed in the small intestine. Bile salts not only speed up lipid digestion, they are also essential to the absorption of the end products of lipid digestion. </p><p id="d30a03e6fb95461ba03cb21d283ad7aa">The free fatty acids and monoglycerides that enter the epithelial cells are reincorporated into triglycerides, which are then mixed with phospholipids and cholesterol and surrounded with a protein coat, creating chylomicrons. <em style="emphasis">Chylomicrons</em> are milky-white droplets of water-soluble lipoprotein that are processed by the Golgi apparatus for release from the cell. Chylomicrons are too big to pass through the basement membranes of blood capillaries. Instead, they enter the much larger pores of lacteals. This means that most fats are first transported in the lymphatic vessels and do not enter the venous blood until they reach the thoracic duct in the neck region. In the bloodstream, the enzyme <em style="emphasis">lipoprotein lipase</em> breaks down the triglycerides of the chylomicrons into free fatty acids and glycerol. These two breakdown products can then pass through capillary walls to become energy used by our cells or to be stored in adipose tissue as fats. Liver cells combine the remaining chylomicron material with proteins, forming &quot;new&quot; lipoproteins that transport cholesterol in the blood. </p></body></section><section id="cbc66af6ee41472895fd96fc36fdcfc7"><title>Nucleic Acid Absorption</title><body><p id="b5dc4e91463a48728ac2c82d53e99ebf">The products of nucleic acid digestion – pentose sugars, nitrogenous bases, and phosphate ions –are transported across the epithelium by special carriers in the villus epithelium via active transport.</p></body></section><wb:inline idref="nutrient_absorption_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing" /><table id="ca9e4257fcb7416490a0b4fb6cd3f3cf" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i3c6808720f8d44349a4dd155b524ac85" /><caption /><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="af6d31105daf84c448c459fc4249b9e25">Food/Breakdown Products</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aa8f3c7884e79411892fde99fb067fd9b">Absorption Mechanism</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="adfe47e69735d48b0a0d06e92ba88df90">Entry to Bloodstream</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ad36fa9e9af4d4715bff0eee964c3274a">Destination</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="f525a0b12c314a56a3d0a4e16b27db2b"><em style="italic">Carbohydrates</em></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="bbb98163f4444a7da3d87da043b6b5f2"><em style="italic">Glucose</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="bed85f22aaa346f09d80072e94bc2730">Co-transport with sodium ions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="a486bc04763448a993bab0f3d32d023f">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f21e1cd32c704c8e85663be182f0b11d">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f6c350bfb83e4b719b6aa18a657dce84"><em style="italic">Galactose</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ef6a3e31094e41feab3edf7c6e8a5ac6">Co-transport with sodium ions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b01cb6f8b86a4856ae7303af2bbe30ad">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b708d3561a864a628cf182d9df215367">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ea02412900d545658d8ba09b1f25bd69"><em style="italic">Fructose</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e8b4851c46364cba921f253aa9346a75">Facilitated diffusion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="c7e4d9b586c64fd1a16249bfabb0d038">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f5ea3fa2b70844058fdd9a2a018af2c2">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="a4de1572ff00419bb2d2cfff6522b92a"><em style="italic">Protein</em></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b7ff93e492a04556a3769060ded84512"><em style="italic">Amino acids</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="c64b6b3ae1294cdcb0ce17e635b89173">Co-transport with sodium ions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="fd28c5ab3ac04a768ec53ad541bdb275">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b1a7eb022b9745d099d6a85ee3911783">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1" align="center"><p id="ac6a7b7295a0409fb5972353fb1028ba"><em style="italic">Lipids</em></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="c7a4ac7ae6e94c8bb57c873d0ff797c7"><em style="italic">Long-chainfatty acids</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="a41b087fa0f24acb8acb3353062a9ad0">Diffusion into intestinal cells, where they are combined with proteins to create chylomicrons</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b31a6cb49f934257bf504be5657cc8a0">Lacteals of villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ef7db9fb68da4e9bacd2ade3874589b0">Systemic circulation via lymph in thoracic duct</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ec8ef787fd404857a1707743ce1b82bd"><em style="italic">Monoglycerides</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="dd30859675f54b3cab13a77a0d670465">Diffusion into intestinal cells, where they are combined with proteins to create chylomicrons</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="be1f1ff70a86466fad86ed52cbc09e8d">Lacteals of villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="a8076b4a944c48d8a18d28acd4a077c8">Systemic circulation via lymph in thoracic duct</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="bf9dc07a8c2b4e02b2678b74c38b2e0b"><em style="italic">Short-chainfatty acids</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e5a28efde40e4ad99bc40dcdffcd52c1">Simple diffusion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="d1b1b52d21d14cfdbdd1befcebda9c1d">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e7ff18b2981a447e812538b7d7cc066f">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="aaed01c2756e4e0885ea7d2269ed95c8"><em style="italic">Glycerol</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="baaf86cb13b84d62abf9f283af671679">Simple diffusion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e28bd49e20974f0fa7aa88ef69e0b354">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="c747814a24784809887acaeafeb8b458">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b5e42bd10e7546a897c6946572e0a8d9"><em style="italic">Nucleic acids</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b1a954540fc946f5999ea763018d7051">Active transport via membrane carriers</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ed78fe6646b64cdfa1b3691a00b925d9">Capillary blood in villi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f6f99fe1e04444b083590df07f89479e">Liver via hepatic portal vein</p></td></tr></table><section id="c7c0228ac3194d8083045c35cbe0a532" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><wb:inline idref="nutrient_absorption_digt" purpose="didigetthis" /><wb:inline idref="nutrient_absorption_digt2" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
