<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_02a">
	<head>
		<title>Nutritive Molecules </title>
		<objref idref="digest_mols2_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="digest_carbo_LO"/>
		<objref idref="digest_protein_LO"/>
		<objref idref="digest_lipids_LO"/>
		<objref idref="digest_nucleic_acids_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>The nutritive organic compounds in our food includes carbohydrates, proteins and lipids.
			These molecules are digested, then absorbed, and reassembled into macromolecules or used
			as fuel for metabolism in the body. The process of breaking down these macromolecules
			involves splitting into smaller molecules using water molecule, thus the name hydrolysis
			(“hydro” = water; “lysis” = splitting). The reverse reaction, called dehydration
			synthesis, can build macromolecules from the absorbed building blocks. Enzymes can speed
			up the rate of these reactions.</p>
		<section>
			<title>Carbohydrates</title>
			<body>
				<p>Our daily food intake usually includes from 200 to 600 grams of carbohydrates.
					Carbohydrates are primarily used for quick energy, but some are also used to
					create important signaling and structural molecules. The monomers of
					carbohydrates, <term>monosaccharides</term> (simple sugars), are absorbed easily
					and can therefore be a source of quick energy for the body when we consume them
					in this form. <term>Glucose</term>, <term>galactose</term>, and
						<term>frutose</term> are the three common monosaccharides in our diet. </p>


				<image src="../../webcontent/carb_digestion.png" width="450" alt="Molecular image showing the hydrolysis breakdown of a carbohydrate (Sucrose) into 2 monosachharides (Glucose and Fructose).">
					<caption>Hydrolysis: carbohydrate digestion </caption>
				</image>

				<p>Disaccharides are two monosaccharides bound together and include
						<term>sucrose</term> (table sugar), <term>lactose</term>, and
						<term>maltose</term>. <term>Polysaccharides</term> are long chains of
					monomers and include polymerized glucose in different forms including
						<term>glycogen</term>, which is the stored form of glucose in our bodies,
					and <term>starch</term>, a polysaccharide of glucose molecules that comes from
					plant sources.</p>

				<p>In many places around the world, starch accounts for the largest portion of
					digestible carbohydrates in the diet, with the addition of some glycogen,
					disaccharides and monosaccharides. There are other polysaccharides in our diet,
					like cellulose, but our bodies do not produce enzymes that can break them down,
					so they are indigestible. While indigestible polysaccharides do not give us any
					nutrients, they do provide bulk (fiber) that helps propel food through the
					digestive system.</p>

			</body>
		</section>


		<example>
			<title>Lactose Intolerance</title>
			<p>Individuals with lactose intolerance are unable to metabolize lactose, a sugar found
				in milk. The problem is usually caused by a lack of the enzyme lactase, which is
				required to break down lactose in the lining of the small intestine. Without
				breakdown in the small intestine, lactose flows into the large intestine where
				bacteria metabolize lactose in a process called fermentation. In fermentation,
				gasses are produced that cause abdominal bloating. Sugars and fermentation products
				also cause large amounts of water to enter the large intestine, leading to loose
				stool. Most infants are born the enzyme lactase, and as adults lose the ability to
				produce this enzyme.</p>
		</example>

		<wb:inline idref="digest_carbo_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		<!--<wb:inline idref="digest_carbo_digt2" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>-->
		<section>
			<title>Proteins</title>
			<body>
				<p>We get protein when we eat meat, seafood, eggs, beans, nuts and soy products.
					USDA recommends 5 to 6 ounces of protein in diet per day, although children need
					less. This dietary protein is usually in the form of polypeptides and must be
					digested into its <activity_link idref="amino_acids" target="new">amino
						acid</activity_link> building blocks for absorption. There are numerous
					enzymes that break large proteins into smaller peptides and then into amino
					acids. Amino acids are then absorbed from the digestive system into the
					circulatory system where they are delivered throughout the body. Once amino
					acids have entered cells throughout the body, they are bonded together to make
					proteins needed for cell function. As a last resort, proteins and amino acids
					can also be used as energy; they are metabolically converted to glucose before
					they are used as energy sources.</p>
				<image src="../../webcontent/protein_digestion.png" width="350" alt="Molecular image showing the hydrolysis breakdown of a dipeptide protien into 2 amino acids.">
					<caption>Hydrolysis: protein digestion </caption>
				</image>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_protein_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Lipids and Fats</title>
			<body>
				<p>Dietary lipids include fats and oils. While not considered a USDA food group,
					oils contain some essential nutrients and are recommended as part of a healthy
					diet, although only in small amounts. Solid fats have more saturated and
					trans-fatty acids and are considered empty calories when included in a diet
					because they add calories but not needed nutrients. Most dietary lipids are in
					the form of triglycerides, with one glycerol molecule and three fatty acids
					bound together. <activity_link idref="levels_m1_lipids" target="new"
						>Lipids</activity_link> are processed by enzymes secreted from the pancreas
					(with some enzymes from the stomach and saliva) and are then solubilized for
					absorption by salts secreted in bile (from the liver). These steps prepare them
					for absorption in the small intestine. Like proteins, ingested lipids are broken
					down into smaller parts for absorption and then are either metabolized to make
					energy or are use to make cellular structures including cell membranes. Lipid
					absorption is also required for absorption of some fat-soluble vitamins.</p>
				<image src="../../webcontent/lipid_digestion.png" width="500" alt="Molecular image showing the hydrolysis breakdown of a triglyceride into 1 monoglyceride and 2 fatty acids.">
					<caption>Hydrolysis: lipid digestion </caption>
				</image>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_lipids_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Nucleic Acids</title>

			<body>
				<p>When we eat any plant or animal foods, we are able to digest the DNA or RNA
					nucleic acid that was in their cells. The fundamental unit of nucleic acids is
					the nucleotide, with a phosphate group, a pentose sugar, and one of 5 nucleic
					bases. The pancreas produces and releases into the small intestine two enzymes
					to break down either DNA (deoxyribonuclease) or RNA (ribonuclease) into
					individual nucleotides. Brush border enzymes of the cells lining the small
					intestine further digest the nucleotide into its molecular components for
					absorption.</p>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_nucleic_acids_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis"/>



			</body>
		</section>
		<section purpose="learnbydoing">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_mols_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
				<wb:inline idref="_u8_digestion_macromolecules_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
