<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_16">
	<head>
		<title>Peritoneum and Peritoneal Folds</title>
		<objref idref="wall_layers_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		<p>The <term>peritoneum</term>, is the largest serous membrane in the body and
			lines the abdominal cavity. The tissue has several components including the the
			mesothelium and an underlying supporting areolar connective tissue layer. The connective
			tissue in turn has two layers: the <term>parietal peritoneum</term>, which
			lines the abdominal wall, and the <term>visceral peritoneum</term>, which
			covers some organs and serves as their serosae. The <term>peritoneal cavity</term>
			is the small space between the parietal and visceral peritoneum that contains the
			lubricating serous fluid.</p>
		<p>The peritoneum includes large folds that bind organs to each other and to the abdominal
			walls. This keeps the organs in the proper place and suspends them when we are upright.
			Within these folds are blood vessels, lymphatic vessels, and nerves that innervate the
			abdominal organs.</p>
		<section>
			<title>The Five Major Peritoneal Folds</title>
			<body>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<th><em style="bold">Fold</em></th>
						<th><em style="bold">Description</em></th>
						<th><em style="bold">Comment</em></th>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Greater omentum</em></td>
						<td>Drapes over the transverse colon and small intestine</td>
						<td>High adipose tissue content vastly expands with weight gain, creating
							the characteristic "beer belly"</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Falciform ligament</em></td>
						<td>Attaches the liver to the anterior abdominal wall and diaphragm</td>
						<td>The liver is the only digestive organ attached to the anterior abdominal
							wall</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Lesser omentum</em></td>
						<td>Suspends the stomach and duodenum from the liver</td>
						<td>Provides a pathway for the blood supply of liver; contains the common
							bile duct</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Mesentery</em></td>
						<td>Attaches the jejunum and ileum of the small intestine to the posterior
							abdominal wall</td>
						<td>Includes blood and lymphatic vessels, and lymph nodes</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><em style="bold">Mesocolon</em></td>
						<td>Attaches the transverse colon and sigmoid colon of the large intestine
							to the posterior abdominal wall</td>
						<td>Along with mesentery, it holds intestines loosely in place, enabling
							movement with muscle contractions</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</body>
		</section>
		<example>
			<title>Homeostatic Imbalances of the Peritoneum: Peritonitis</title>
					<p>Inflammation of the peritoneum is called peritonitis. It can be caused by an
						injury that penetrates into the abdomen or from an ulcer that perforates the
						stomach wall, allowing gastric fluids into the peritoneal cavity. The most
						common cause of peritonitis is a ruptured appendix. The appendix is a
						terminal part of the cecum (a peritoneal pouch at the beginning of the large
						intestine), and the function (if any) is still debated. When the appendix
						bursts open, bacteria-laden feces spurt into the peritoneum. Usually, the
						peritoneal layers will bind together around the site of inflammation,
						keeping the infection from spreading, while macrophages move in to dispose
						of infected tissue. Peritonitis that spreads out into the peritoneal cavity
						can be life-threatening. The condition is treated by surgically removing the
						infected tissue and administering high doses of antibiotics. Generally,
						peritonitis is a concern with any kind of puncture wound to the abdomen.</p>	
		</example>
				
				<wb:inline idref="digest_peritoneum_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
				
			
	
	</body>
</workbook_page>
