<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_28">
	<head>
		<title>Control of Gastric Secretion</title>
		<objref idref="digest_gastric_secretion_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The secretion of gastric juice is controlled by nerves, hormones, and the presence of
			products of digestion. Stimuli from smell, sight and taste as well as food in the oral
			cavity, stomach, and small intestine activate or inhibit gastric juice production. This
			is why the three phases of gastric secretion are called the cephalic, gastric, and
			intestinal phases. However, once gastric secretion begins, all three phases can occur
			simultaneously.</p>
		<p>The <term>cephalic</term> (<term>reflex</term>) <term>phase</term> of gastric secretion,
			which lasts just a few minutes, takes place before food enters the stomach. The smell,
			taste, sight, or thought of food triggers this phase. For example, impulses from
			receptors in taste buds or the nose are relayed to the brain, which returns signals that
			increase gastric secretion to prepare the stomach for digestion. This enhanced secretion
			is a <em style="italic">conditioned reflex</em>, meaning it occurs only if we like or
			want a particular food. Depression and loss of appetite can suppress the cephalic
			reflex.</p>
		<p>The <term>gastric phase</term> of secretion lasts three to four hours and is set in
			motion by local neural and hormonal mechanisms triggered by the entry of food into the
			stomach. For example, stomach distension activates stretch receptors that stimulate
			parasympathetic neurons to release acetylcholine, which then provokes increased
			secretion of gastric juice. Partially digested proteins, caffeine, and rising pH
			stimulate the release of gastrin from enteroendocrine <term>G cells</term>, which in
			turn provokes parietal cells to increase their production of HCl and increase motility
			through the stomach by altering sphincter function. The presence of proteins in the
			stomach raises pH, which stimulates the increased gastrin and HCl release needed to
			create an acidic environment for protein digestion.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="digest_gastric_secretion_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<example>
			<title>GERD</title>
			<p>If this control of gastric juice secretion is not working properly and too much
				hydrochloric acid is produced, conditions such as Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease
				(GERD) can occur. The acidic pH irritates the lining of the esophagus near the
				cardiac or lower esophageal sphincter and can lead to esophageal cancer. Antacids
				provide only temporary relief. Some drugs known as histamine-2 antagonists
				(H2-blockers) or proton-pump inhibitors (PPIs) may be needed to control the amount
				of stomach acid produced. However, the two drugs act on different parts of the
				parietal cell metabolism. </p>

			<p>Review the process of <activity_link idref="_u8_m2_organization_04" target="new">hydrochloric acid secretion by parietal cell</activity_link> <!--[link to the
				walkthrough on page Gastric Juice page]--> to analyze the physiology behind these two
				drugs.</p>
		</example>
		<wb:inline idref="digest_gastric_secretion_sc" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
