<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_24">
	<head>
		<title>Esophagus</title>
		<objref idref="food_structures_LO"/>
		<!--<objref idref="esoph_muscles_LO"/>-->
	</head>
	<body>

		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M3_24.jpg" width="450"
			alt="The digestive system, pointing out the trachea, esophagus, diaphram, and stomach."><caption>The Esophagus. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption></image>
		<p>The <term>esophagus</term> is a collapsible tube located posterior to the trachea. This
			muscular tube is about 10 inches long. The esophagus runs a mainly straight route
			through the mediastinum of the thorax. To enter the abdomen, the esophagus penetrates
			the diaphragm through an opening called the <term>esophageal hiatus</term>. At the
				<term>cardiac orifice</term>, the esophagus joins with the stomach. Surrounding this
			orifice is the <term>lower esophageal sphincter</term> (also called the
				<term>gastroesophageal</term> or <term>cardiac sphincter</term>). Remember that
			sphincters are circular muscles that surround tubes and serve as valves, closing the
			tube when the sphincters contract and opening it when they relax. The lower esophageal
			sphincter relaxes to let food pass into the stomach, then contracts to prevent stomach
			contents from backing up into the esophagus. Surrounding this sphincter is the muscular
			diaphragm, which helps close off the sphincter when no food is being swallowed. When the
			lower esophageal sphincter does not completely close, some of the stomach contents can
			reflux (i.e., back up into the esophagus), causing heartburn or gastroesophageal reflux
			disease (GERD).</p>
		<p>The esophageal mucosa is made up of nonkeratinized stratified squamous epithelium, lamina
			propria, and a muscularis mucosa. The mucosa near the stomach also includes mucous
			glands. The stratified squamous epithelium protects against abrasion and erosion from
			food particles. In the superior third of the esophagus, the muscularis is skeletal
			muscle, in the middle third it is both skeletal and smooth muscle, and in the inferior
			third it is smooth muscle. A slight prominence at either end of the esophagus creates
			two sphincters: the <term>upper esophageal sphincter</term>, made of skeletal muscle,
			and the lower esophageal sphincter, made of smooth muscle. As we have already learned,
			the superficial layer of the esophagus is called the adventitia, not the serosa. In
			contrast to the stomach and intestines, the areolar connective tissue of the adventitia
			is not covered by mesothelium.</p>

		<wb:inline idref="esoph_muscles_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>

		<p>The esophagus secretes mucus that lubricates food, and it propels food into the stomach.
			Chemical digestion that began in the mouth continues in the esophagus, but there aren’t
			any new digestive enzymes secreted. The upper esophageal sphincter controls the movement
			of food from the pharynx into the esophagus. The lower esophageal sphincter controls the
			movement of food from the esophagus into the stomach. Rhythmic waves of peristalsis
			begin in the esophagus and then continue in the rest of the digestive tract organs. The
			feeling of having a lump in your throat when you are nervous is caused by peristalsis
			that occurs when there is no food in the esophagus.</p>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<th>Action</th>
				<th>Outcome</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Upper esophageal sphincter relaxation</td>
				<td>Allows bolus to move from the laryngopharynx to the esophagus</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Peristalsis</td>
				<td>Propels bolus down the esophagus</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Lower esophageal sphincter relaxation</td>
				<td>Allows bolus from the esophagus to enter the stomach</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Mucus secretion</td>
				<td>Lubricates the esophagus, allowing easy passage of bolus</td>
			</tr>
		</table>

		<wb:inline idref="esoph_muscles_digt2" purpose="didigetthis"/>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
