<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_25">
	<head>
		<title>Deglutition</title>
		<objref idref="digest_deglutition_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		
		
		<p><term>Deglutition</term> is another word for swallowing – the movement of food
			from the mouth and into the stomach. The entire process takes about four to eight
			seconds for solid or semisolid food and about one second for very soft food and liquids.
			Deglutition involves the mouth, pharynx, and esophagus. It is facilitated by the
			secretion of mucus and saliva. There are three stages in deglutition: the voluntary
			phase, the pharyngeal phase, and the esophageal phase.</p>
		
		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M3_25.jpg" width="500" alt="The structures and positions of the mouth and throat when swallowing."><caption>Bolus position during deglutition. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
			Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
				href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
				>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption> </image>
		<p>The <term>voluntary phase</term> of deglutition is also called the <term>oral phase</term> or <term>buccal phase</term>. In this phase,
			swallowing is set in motion when the tongue moves upward and backward against the
			palate, pushing the bolus to the back of the oral cavity and into the oropharynx. At
			this point, the two involuntary phases of swallowing begin.</p>
		<p>In the <term>pharyngeal phase</term>, stimulation of receptors in the oropharynx
			sends impulses to the <term>deglutition center</term> (a collection of neurons
			that controls swallowing) in the medulla oblongata. Impulses are then sent back to the
			uvula and soft palate, provoking them to move upward to close off the nasopharynx.
			Sequential contractions of the pharyngeal constrictor muscles move the bolus through the
			oropharynx and laryngopharynx. Relaxation of the upper esophageal sphincter then allows
			food to enter the esophagus. <!--[video]--></p>
		<p>The entry of food into the esophagus marks the beginning of the <term>esophageal phase</term> of deglutition. Peristalsis propels the bolus through the
			esophagus and toward the stomach. The circular muscle layer of the muscularis
			immediately superior to the bolus contracts, pinching the esophageal wall, forcing the
			bolus forward. At the same time, the longitudinal muscle layer of the muscularis
			inferior to the bolus also contracts, shortening this inferior area and pushing out its
			walls to receive the bolus. Waves of contractions keep moving the food toward the
			stomach. When the bolus nears the stomach, relaxation of the lower esophageal sphincter
			allows the bolus to pass into the stomach. During the esophageal phase, esophageal
			glands secrete mucus that lubricates the bolus and minimizes friction. Peristalsis is
			completely involuntary even though there is skeletal muscle in the first 2/3 of the
			esophagus.</p>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
