<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u8_m2_organization_18">
	<head>
		<title>Mouth</title>
		<objref idref="food_structures_LO"/>
	</head>
	<body>

		<p>The cheeks, tongue, hard palate, and soft palate frame the mouth, also called the
				<term>oral cavity</term> or <term>buccal cavity</term>. The mouth is involved in
			both mechanical and chemical digestion. Mechanical digestion consists of
				<term>mastication</term> (chewing), in which the tongue manipulates food, the teeth
			grind it, and saliva mixes with it. Mastication turns food into an easy-to-swallow bolus
			and breaks the food into smaller pieces so that there is more contact area for digestive
			enzymes.</p>
		<p>The cheeks make up the oral cavity's lateral walls. The outer covering of the cheeks is
			the skin, and the inner covering is the mucous membrane. This membrane is made up of
			nonkeratinized stratified squamous epithelium; the multiple layers are resistant to
			abrasion. Between the skin and mucous membranes are connective tissue, fat tissue and
			buccinator muscles.</p>
		<image src="../../webcontent/Frenulum.jpg" width="350"
			alt="Oral cavity pointing out the Frenulum.">
			<caption>The bounds of the oral cavity. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
				Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
					href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
					>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption>
		</image>
		<p>The lips, also called labia ("fleshy borders"), encircle the opening of the mouth. Their
			outer covering is skin, and their inner lining is mucous membrane. Between these two
			layers is the orbicularis oris muscle. The <term>labial frenulum</term> is a midline
			fold of mucous membrane that attaches the inner surface of each lip to the gum. When we
			chew food, the buccinator muscles in the cheeks and the orbicularis oris muscle in the
			lips contract, which keeps food between the lower and upper teeth. These muscles also
			play a role in speech.</p>
		<p>The area between the lips (or cheeks) and teeth is called the <term>oral
			vestibule</term>. The <term>oral cavity </term>is the area than runs between the gums
			and teeth and the entrance to the throat (oropharynx), also called the
				<term>fauces</term> ("passages"). If you puff out your cheeks, you can increase the
			size of the oral vestibule but not the oral cavity.</p>
		<p>The <term>septum</term> that separates the oral cavity and nasal cavity is called the
			palate. Anatomically, a septum (plural, septa) is a wall within a single organ or cavity
			that separates the space into distinct sides. For example, the nasal septum divides the
			nostrils. This is separating two distinct cavities.</p>

		<image src="../../webcontent/D_M3_20B.jpg" width="450" alt="Structures of the oral cavity, particularly the hard and soft palates, pharynx, larynx, esophagus, and tracea."><caption>Structures of the oral cavity. This work by Cenveo is licensed under a Creative
			Commons Attribution 3.0 United States (<link
				href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/"
				>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/</link>).</caption></image>

		<p>The <term>palate</term>, which forms the roof of the mouth, is what allows us to breathe
			while chewing food. The anterior part of the roof of the mouth is called the <term>hard
				palate</term>. It is created by the maxillae and palatine bones and is covered by
			mucous membrane. The hard palate makes up the bony wall between the oral and nasal
			cavities. The posterior part of the roof of the mouth, the <term>soft palate</term>, is
			also lined with mucous membrane. This arch-shaped muscular structure forms a dividing
			wall between the oropharynx and nasopharynx.</p>
		<p>The <term>uvula</term> (Latin for ‘little grape’) is a cone-shaped muscular process that
			hangs from the end of the soft palate. It plays a role in speech and articulation of
			words. It also plays a small role in preventing foods and liquids from entering the
			nasal cavity. Two muscular folds on each side of the base of the uvula extend down the
			lateral sides of the soft palate. The anterior fold is called the <term>palatoglossal
				arch</term>, which terminates next to the base of the tongue. The posterior fold,
			the <term>palatopharyngeal arch</term>, lies at the interface with the pharynx. Between
			these two arches on the lateral wall are the <term>palatine tonsils</term>. The
				<term>lingual tonsils </term>are located at the base of the tongue.</p>

		<p>There are also many small, intrinsic salivary glands within the mucous membrane of the
			mouth and tongue. Their secretion is independent of the presence of food. These glands
			either open directly into the oral cavity or indirectly through short ducts. Small
			amounts of saliva are secreted by the <term>labial glands</term> in the lips, the
				<term>buccal glands</term> in the cheeks, the <term>palatal glands</term> in the
			palate, and the <term>lingual glands</term> in the tongue.</p>
		
		<wb:inline idref="food_structures_sc" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>
		
		<section purpose="didigetthis">
			<title/>
			<body>
				<wb:inline idref="digest_structures_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
		<wb:inline idref="oral_cavity_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>
			</body>
		</section>
	</body>
</workbook_page>
