<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u1_m2_roletype2_tutor3">
   <title>Tutor</title>
<page><question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>A study was conducted in order to explore the relationship between the number of beers a
               person drinks and his/her blood alcohol content (BAC, in %).</p>
         <p>This study is an example of which role-type classification?</p>
      </body>
      <multiple_choice shuffle="false">
         <choice value="Res1">Case C→Q</choice>
         <choice value="Res2">Case C→C</choice>
         <choice value="Res3">Case Q→Q</choice>
         <choice value="Res4">Case Q→C</choice>
      </multiple_choice>
      <part>
         <response match="Res1" score="0">
            <feedback>Not quite right. We are exploring how the number of beers affects BAC. You are correct that the response variable, BAC, is quantitative. Is the explanatory variable categorical or quantitative?</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res2" score="0">
            <feedback>Incorrect. We are exploring how the number of beers affects BAC. Decide which is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable. Then decide whether each is categorical or quantitative.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res3" score="10">
            <feedback>Correct. Both the explanatory (number of beers) and response (BAC) variables
                  are quantitative in this case, and therefore this is an example of case
                  Q→Q.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response match="Res4" score="0">
            <feedback>Not quite right. We are exploring how the number of beers affects BAC. You are correct that the explanatory variable, number of beers, is quantitative. Is the explanatory variable categorical or quantitative?<!-- We are exploring how the number of beers affects BAC.  Decide which is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable.  Then decide whether each is categorical or quantitative.  Please try again.--></feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>The two relevant variables here are number of beers and blood alcohol content (BAC).
               Determine the role-type classification for these two variables.</hint>
      </part>
   </question></page>
</assessment>
