<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u1_m2_scatterplot5_lbd_tutor2">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>Consider how taking gender into account adds to our understanding of the overall form of
            the relationship. Address any interesting differences between the clusters associated
            with the two genders. More specifically, address the following two questions:</p><p>(<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T164028-0400"?>A<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T164028-0400" content="i"?>)
            Where do the males and females fall on the scatterplot with respect to height and
            weight. Explain why you think this is so. </p><p>(<?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T164033-0400"?>B<?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T164030-0400" content="ii"?>)
            Does it look like the weight of females increases with an increase in height as quickly
            as the weight of males increases with a corresponding increase in height?</p>
      </body>
      <short_answer id="A"/>
      <part>
         <response input="A" match="*" score="1"/>
         <explanation>
            <p>We see that the overall form of the relationship can be thought of in terms of two
               clusters, one for each gender. Points corresponding to the females cluster in the
               lower left of the scatterplot, which means that females generally have a lower height
               and weight <?oxy_insert_start author="mmyers" timestamp="20101021T164113-0400"?>than
               males <?oxy_insert_end?>(due to obvious biological differences between males and
               females). The main difference between males and females is that the weight of females
               does not appear to increase as quickly with height as the weight of males does.</p>
         </explanation>
      </part>
   </question>
</assessment>
