<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_4.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u1_m2_scatterplot4_tutor1">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
      <body>
         <p>A study examined how the percentage of participants who completed a survey is related to
            the monetary incentive that researchers promised to participants. Consider the
            relationship between these two quantitative variables, displayed in the scatterplot
            below.</p>
         <image src="../../webcontent/flash/didigetthis_scatterplot4q1image1.gif" alt="scatterplot graph"/>
         <p>The direction of this relationship is <input_ref input="A"/>. In the context of this
            example, this means that when researchers promised higher payments, the percentage of
            participants who completed the survey <input_ref input="B"/>. The form of the
            relationship is <input_ref input="C"/>. Based on the form of the relationship as it is
            illustrated above, the relationship is quite <input_ref input="D"/>.</p>
      </body>
      <fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false">
         <choice value="one">positive</choice>
         <choice value="two">negative</choice>
         <choice value="three">neither positive nor negative</choice>
      </fill_in_the_blank>
      <fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false">
         <choice value="one">increased</choice>
         <choice value="two">remained the same</choice>
         <choice value="three">decreased</choice>
      </fill_in_the_blank>
      <fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="false">
         <choice value="one">linear</choice>
         <choice value="two">curvilinear</choice>
         <choice value="three">neither linear nor curvilinear</choice>
      </fill_in_the_blank>
      <fill_in_the_blank id="D" shuffle="false">
         <choice value="one">strong</choice>
         <choice value="two">weak</choice>
      </fill_in_the_blank>
      <part>
         <response input="A" name="positive" match="one" score="1">
            <feedback>Correct. As the incentive amount increases, the percentage of returned surveys also tends to increase, indicating a positive relationship.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="A" name="negative" match="two">
            <feedback>Incorrect. A negative relationship means that when the values of one variable increase, the values of the other variable <em style="italic">decrease</em>. That is not what is happening in this scatterplot.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="A" name="neither positive nor negative" match="three">
            <feedback>Incorrect. When no relationship exists (neither positive nor negative), there is no clear pattern in the scatterplot. There is a pattern in this scatterplot, so a relationship does exist.</feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>A positive relationship means that when the values of one variable increase, so do the values of the other variable.<!--Please click <link
               href="javascript:loadImage('../../webcontent/flash/didigetthis_scatterplot4q1image2.gif')"
               >here</link> for an illustration that will help you see the pattern on the scatterplot above.--></hint>
      </part>
      <part>
         <response input="B" name="increased" match="one" score="1">
            <feedback>Correct. Since a positive relationship exists, when the values of one variable increase, so do the values of the other variable.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="B" name="remained the same" match="two">
            <feedback>Incorrect. The percentage of participants who completed the survey would have decreased if <em style="italic">no</em> relationship exists. This scatterplot shows a positive relationship.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="B" name="decreased" match="three">
            <feedback>Incorrect. The percentage of participants who completed the survey would have decreased if a <em style="italic">negative</em> relationship exists. This scatterplot shows a positive relationship.</feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>A positive relationship means that when the values of one variable increase, so do
            the values of the other variable.</hint>
      </part>
      <part>
          <response input="C" name="linear" match="one">
            <feedback>Incorrect. Relationships with a linear form have points scattered about a straight line, but in this scatterplot, the points appear to curve at higher incentive amounts.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="C" name="curvilinear" match="two" score="1">
            <feedback>Correct. Relationships with a curvilinear form have points dispersed around a curved line, which appears to happen in this scatterplot at the higher incentive amounts.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="C" name="neither linear nor curvilinear" match="three">
            <feedback>Incorrect. When the scatterplot shows no clear pattern, the form of the relationship would be neither linear nor curvilinear. There is a clear pattern in the data in this scatterplot.</feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>Relationships with a linear form have points scattered about a straight line, while relationships with a curvilinear form have points dispersed around a curved line.<!--Please click <link
               href="javascript:loadImage('../../webcontent/flash/didigetthis_scatterplot4q1image2.gif')"
            >here</link> for an illustration that will help you see the pattern on the scatterplot above.--></hint>
      </part>
      <part>
         <response input="D" name="strong" match="one" score="1">
            <feedback>Correct. The data points fit tightly into a curvilinear form.</feedback>
         </response>
         <response input="D" name="weak" match="two">
            <feedback>Incorrect. Note how closely the data points follow the suggested form.</feedback>
         </response>
         <hint>Do the data points fall tightly into a pattern, or is there a lot of scatter in the
            data?</hint>
      </part>
   </question>
</assessment>
