<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE assessment
  PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment 1.0//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_1_0.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_inline_assessment_1_1.css"?>
<assessment id="u1_m2_roletype1_tutor1">
   <title>Tutor</title>
   <question id="q1">
<body>
   <p>In example 2, the number of calories is the <input_ref input="A"/> variable, and the type of
            hot dog is the <input_ref input="B"/> variable.</p>
   <p>In example 4, gender is the <input_ref input="C"/> variable, and smoking habit is the
               <input_ref input="D"/> variable.</p>
   <p>In example 6, age is the <input_ref input="E"/> variable, and legibility distance is the <input_ref input="F"/> variable.</p>
   <p>In example 8, favorite type of music is the <input_ref input="G"/> variable, and IQ level is the <input_ref input="H"/> variable.</p>
</body>
<fill_in_the_blank id="A" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="B" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="C" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="D" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="E" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="F" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="G" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<fill_in_the_blank id="H" shuffle="false">
   <choice value="one">explanatory</choice>
   <choice value="two">response</choice>
</fill_in_the_blank>
<part>
   <response input="A" name ="explanatory" match="one">
       <feedback>Incorrect. In this study, we are exploring whether the type of hot
               dog affects the number of calories it has. Thus, the number of calories is the
               response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="A" name ="response" match="two" score="1">
      <feedback>Correct. In this study we are exploring whether the type of hot dog affects the number of calories it has.  Thus, the number of calories is the response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
      <hint>Does the type of hot dog affect the number of calories or do the number of calories
            affect the type of hot dog?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="B" name ="explanatory" match="one" score="1">
      <feedback>Correct. In this study we are exploring whether the type of hot dog affects the number of calories it has. Thus, the type of hot dog is the explanatory variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="B" name ="response" match="two">
       <feedback>Incorrect. In this study we are exploring whether the type of hot dog affects the number of calories it has. Thus, type of hot dog is the explanatory variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other.  If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
   <hint>Does the type of hot dog affect the number of calories or does the number of calories
            affect the type of hot dog?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="C" name ="explanatory" match="one" score="1">
      <feedback>Correct. Note that in most studies involving gender, it will be the explanatory variable.  We are not trying to see how a person's smoking habits affect the person's gender, but rather explore whether gender is one of the factors that can explain whether the person is a smoker or not. </feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="C" name ="response" match="two">
       <feedback>Incorrect. Note that in most studies involving gender, it will be the explanatory variable. We are not trying to see how a person's smoking habits affect the person's gender, but rather explore whether gender is one of the factors that can explain whether the person is a smoker or not.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
   <hint>Does a person's gender affect that person's smoking habits, or does a person's smoking
            habits affect that person's gender?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="D" name ="explanatory" match="one">
      <feedback>Incorrect. If a person's gender is one of the factors that can explain whether the person is a smoker or not, then smoking habits is the response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="D" name ="response" match="two" score="1">
      <feedback>Correct. If a person's gender is one of the factors that can explain whether the person is a smoker or not, then smoking habits is the response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
   <hint>Does a person's gender affect that person's smoking habits or does a person's smoking habits affect that person's gender?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="E" name ="explanatory" match="one" score="1">
       <feedback>Correct. In this study we are examining how legibility distance changes with age.
               Thus, we can say that age affects legibility distance, making it the explanatory
               variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="E" name ="response" match="two">
      <feedback>Incorrect. In this study we are examining how legibility distance
               changes with age. Thus, we can say that age affects legibility distance, making it
               the explanatory variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
<hint>Does a driver's age affect that driver's sign legibility distance or does a driver's sign
            legibility distance affect that driver's age?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="F" name ="explanatory" match="one">
      <feedback>Incorrect. Since we are examining how age affects legibility distance, legibility distance is the response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="F" name ="response" match="two" score="1">
       <feedback>Correct. Since we are examining how age affects legibility distance, legibility distance is the response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
   <hint>Does a driver's age affect that driver's sign legibility distance or does a driver's sign
            legibility distance affect that driver's age?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="G" name ="explanatory" match="one">
       <feedback>Incorrect. Since the purpose of this study was to explore whether a person's IQ level can explain or help predict the person's favorite type of music, type of music is the response variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="G" name ="response" match="two" score="1">
       <feedback>Correct. Since the purpose of this study was to explore whether a person's IQ level can explain or help predict the person's favorite type of music, type of music is the response variable. </feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
<hint>Does a person's favorite type of music affect that person's IQ level or does a person's IQ
            level affect that person's favorite type of music?</hint>
</part>
<part>
   <response input="H" name ="explanatory" match="one" score="1">
       <feedback>Correct. Since the purpose of this study was to explore whether a person's IQ level can explain or help predict the person's favorite type of music, IQ level is the explanatory variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <response input="H" name ="response" match="two">
       <feedback>Incorrect. Since the purpose of this study was to explore whether a person's IQ level can explain or help predict the person's favorite type of music, IQ level is the explanatory variable.</feedback>
   </response>
   <hint>The key to deciding which variable is the explanatory variable and which is the response variable is to decide which variable affects (or explains) the other. If we can say that X affects (or explains) Y, then X is the explanatory variable.  </hint>
   <hint>Does a person's favorite type of music affect that person's IQ level or does a person's IQ
            level affect that person's favorite type of music?</hint>
</part>

   </question>
</assessment>
