<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>

<workbook_page id="_u1_m1_intro_01">
    <head>
        <title>Introduction to Anatomy and Physiology</title>
    </head>
    <body>

        <p><em style="bold">Welcome to the Open Learning Initiative Introduction to Anatomy and
                Physiology course!</em></p>

        <p> We are happy that you have decided to introduce yourself to this important field, and we
            hope that your learning experience will be an enriching and enjoyable one.</p>
        <p> The purpose of this introductory section is to prepare you conceptually and technically
            for this course. We will start with a short orientation to the course, including some
            learning strategies that will explain a little about how the course works and give you
            some pointers on how to use the material most efficiently. </p>

        <p>We will then discuss what Anatomy and Physiology is all about—the "Big Picture" of
            Anatomy and Physiology—and look at how the major themes discussed in the Big Picture tie
            in to the material presented in the course. </p>

        <section>
            <title>Orientation to Anatomy and Physiology</title>
            <body>
                <p>The Introduction to Anatomy and Physiology is a preparatory course that will
                    introduce you to basic terms and concepts and provide a foundation for your
                    future study in this discipline. </p>
                <p>This course is primarily intended for community college students who need Anatomy
                    and Physiology knowledge for their selected discipline, and for students who are
                    planning on entering an allied health program (such as nursing) that requires
                    prerequisites in Anatomy and Physiology. </p>
                <p>Prerequisite knowledge needed to succeed in this course:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Understanding of the Scientific Method.</li>
                    <li>Introductory, college-level Biology and Chemistry.</li>
                    <li>Basic math and language skills.</li>
                    <li> Study skills.</li>
                </ul>
                <p>The course is designed to be offered in a hybrid format to allow you the full
                    affordances of the online learning environment and the expertise and support of
                    your instructor. </p>
                <p>Your instructor is your first line of support. He or she will be available to you, in
                    the same way as in your traditional courses. Ask questions in class, or submit
                    questions and comments through the system. You can e-mail your professor
                    directly, or provide feedback within the My Response activities provided
                    throughout the course material.</p>

                <p> If you have technical difficulty, you can press the Help button at the top of
                    any page's browser window. This will open a web form where you can type your
                    questions or comments and send it to the OLI help desk. Asking for help this way
                    will send several pieces of contextual information with the message (such as the
                    course page, your browser, your computer platform) that will help our technical
                    team diagnose your issue quickly. </p>

                <p>If you do submit a question or report an error, please provide as much detail as
                    possible about the error.</p>

            </body>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Overall Course Structure </title>
            <body>
                <p> OLI Anatomy and Physiology is not your typical course.
                    Our goal is for you to work through the course materials online in the way that
                    is most efficient given your prior knowledge.</p> 
                    
                    
                    <p>While you may have more flexibility than you do in a traditional course, you will also have more
                    responsibility for your own learning. You will need to: </p>
                
                   <ul> <li>Plan how to work through each unit.</li> 
                       <li>Determine how to use the various features of the course to help you learn.</li> 
                       <li>Decide when you need to seek additional support.</li> </ul>
                
                
                <p>Each unit in this course has features designed to support you as an independent learner and consists of
                the following: </p>
                
                
                <p><em style="bold">Learning Objectives:</em> Found at the top of each page, these will
                help prepare you for what you are about to learn and help check your
                    understanding of the material on each page. </p>
                
                <p><em style="bold">Explanatory Content:</em> This is the
                    informational introduction of the basic structures learned in each chapter. It
                consists of short passages of text with information, examples, images, and
                    explanations. </p>
                
                <p><em style="bold">Activities:</em> Activities such as 'Learn By Doing', 'Walkthroughs'
                and 'Did I Get This?' These are the most important aspects of the course.
                Different types of activities are interspersed throughout the course that will
                    help you build or test your mastery of the learning objectives. </p>
                
               <p><em style="bold">End of Unit
                Quizzes:</em> Taking these quizzes at the end of every unit will assess your mastery
                of the learning objectives identified for that unit. </p>
                
                <p><em style="bold">Vocabulary/Terms:</em> There are
                    many important vocabulary terms throughout the course. Where appropropriate,
                    audio pronunciation is provided for the terms, as well as definitions in context
                    that will pop up if you hover over the word. </p>


            </body>


        </section>
    </body>
</workbook_page>
