<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_8.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page id="_u1_m1_intro_03">
	<head>
		<title>Organizing Anatomy and Physiology Concepts</title>
		<objref idref="_u1_identifyExplain_OBJ"/>
		<objref idref="_u1_identify_OBJ"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<p>Our intention is for you to begin to think and speak in the language of the domain while
			integrating the knowledge you gain about anatomy to support explanations of
			physiological phenomenon. The course focuses on a few themes derived from the Big Ideas,
			that when taken together, provide a full view of what the human body is capable of and
			the exciting processes going on inside of it. These organizational themes are:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><em style="italic"><em style="bold">Structure and function </em></em>of the body,
				and the connection between the two.</li>
			<li><em style="italic"><em style="bold">Homeostasis</em></em>, the body’s natural
				tendency to maintain a stable internal environment.</li>
			<li><em style="italic"><em style="bold">Levels of Organization</em></em>, the major
				levels of organization in the human organism from the chemical and cellular levels
				to the tissues, organs and organ systems.</li>
			<li><em style="italic"><em style="bold">Integration of Systems</em></em>, concerning
				which systems are subsets of larger systems, and how they function together in
				harmony and conflict.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>You can see how these themes directly relate to the Big Ideas. As these themes are used
			to describe the inner workings of each of the body’s organ systems, an integrated
			collection of organs that function together, those systems can be categorized based on
			their contribution to the specific vital functions for human life. The vital functions
			provide the context for the whole body, and how each organ system plays a role in
			keeping us alive. So, the information provided for each of the organ systems is
			organized according to those functions that are essential to the survival of the human
			body. The vital functions for human life are:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Exchange with the environment</li>
			<li>Transport within the body</li>
			<li>Structure, support, and movement</li>
			<li>Control and regulation</li>
		</ul>
		<p>All multicellular organisms need these vital functions to operate properly in order to
			survive. In addition to understanding the Themes and Vital Functions that help us
			organize our knowledge about the structure and function of the different body organ
			systems, knowing and using proper terminology related to body planes and directional
			terms will also help you in your quest for Anatomy and Physiology mastery.</p>

		<section>
			<title>Body Systems</title>
			<body>
				<p>You will be first introduced to all of the body systems in this introductory
					unit. In the Introduction to Systems unit, you’ll see that we have grouped the
					organ systems according to the Vital Functions they perform. For example, the
					Digestive and Respiratory Systems are concerned with Exchange of substances and
					information within the environment. In the units that follow, with the exception
					of Levels of Organization, and Homeostasis, you will learn and explore each body
					system in-depth. The order in which you learn each system will be determined by
					your instructor, but the aspects of each system will be similarly described
					according to the Big Picture themes.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Body Planes and Directional Terms</title>
			<body>
				<p>Another commonality across body types are the body planes and directional terms.
					Those in the health professions must speak the same language with regard to
					locating and identifying specific body parts and organs. Body planes and
					directional terms are part of this common language. The imaginary vertical and
					horizontal planes run through the body, essentially cutting it into parts. You
					will be introduced to this new “language” and given opportunities to practice
					using it in context so that you become comfortable locating and describing all
					organs and parts in the body and in relation to each other. Everything that you
					learn after body planes and directional terms will be referring to this
					terminology to help you visualize, identify, and locate anatomical
					structures.</p>
			</body>
		</section>

	</body>
</workbook_page>
