<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page 3.7//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_3_7.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/authoring/oxy-author/oli_workbook_page_3_7.css"?>
<workbook_page xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"
    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/"
    xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="_u1_m1_intro_00">
    <head>
        <title>Themes in Anatomy and Physiology </title>
        <objref idref="_u1_identifyExplain_OBJ"/>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>Everyone has a body and, by adulthood, a general understanding of how it works. But to
            truly understand the intricate functions of the human body—and the problems that occur
            when something goes wrong—you must approach the study of the body in an organized way.
            This course will help you understand the functions of the human body. The course will
            discuss the details of many complex functional systems, but will also look at how all of
            these systems work in harmony to keep you healthy. As you move through this course, you
            should keep four main themes in mind: structure and function, homeostasis, levels of
            organization, and integration of systems.</p>
        <section>
            <title>Structure and Function</title>
            <body>
                <p>The first theme is the connection between structure and function. You will be
                    studying both <extra>
                        <anchor><term>anatomy</term></anchor>
                        <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/anatomy.mp3"
                            type="audio/mp3"/>
                    </extra>, which focuses on the body’s structures, and <extra>
                        <anchor><term>physiology</term></anchor>
                        <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/physiology.mp3"
                            type="audio/mp3"/>
                    </extra>, which focuses on the body’s functions. In fact, it is virtually
                    impossible to study one without the other, because function relies so completely
                    upon structure. For example, the structure of the bones in the skeletal system
                    provides the support necessary for the function of walking upright. The vocal
                    cords would not be able to fulfill their function—the production of sound—if
                    their structure were disrupted. The large surface area of the small intestine
                    allows it to efficiently perform its primary function: absorbing nutrients from
                    food. And the list goes on.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Homeostasis</title>
            <body>
                <p>The second theme will be <extra>
                        <anchor><term>homeostasis</term></anchor>
                        <pronunciation src="../../../webcontent/terms_audio/homeostasis.mp3"
                            type="audio/mp3"/>

                    </extra>, or the body’s natural tendency to maintain a relatively stable
                    internal environment. Most of the body’s functions are driven by homeostasis.
                    Homeostasis occurs at all different levels. For example, body temperature is
                    regulated around 98.6, a temperature that is optimal for cell function and
                    organism function. To maintain this temperature, we sweat to cool down on a hot
                    day and we shiver to increase temperature when we are cold. Other variables,
                    like blood pressure, blood pH, blood calcium concentrations are similarly
                    maintained within a narrow range that is optimal for human health. Many diseases
                    occur because of disruptions in homeostasis. </p>

                <wb:inline idref="_u1_m1_homeostasis_examp_inline01" purpose="learnbydoing"/>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Levels of Organization</title>
            <body>
                <p>The third theme will be the hierarchical organization of the parts of the body.
                    You can think of the body's parts as being organized into a hierarchy of levels.
                    Your body, like all things in the physical world, is built from
                        <term>chemical</term> building blocks. The smallest of these building blocks
                    are atoms of elements, which combine to form bigger and more complicated
                    structures called <term>molecules</term>. These molecules, such as water,
                    proteins, carbohydrates (glucose), and lipids are used to build
                        <term>cells</term>, the smallest unit of structure capable of carrying out
                    all life processes. Groups of related cells that work together to perform
                    specific functions make up <extra>
                        <anchor><term>tissues</term></anchor>
                        <p>A tissue is a group of cells with similar shape and function.</p>
                    </extra>, and tissues that work together form <term>organs</term>. Organs do not
                    work independently; they are organized into <term>organ systems</term> that
                    complete more complex tasks. </p>
                <p>The digestive system, for example, includes the mouth, stomach, intestines, and
                    many other organs—all of which are integral to proper functioning of the system
                    as a whole. The organ systems work together to support life in the entire
                    organism—in this case, a human being.</p>
                <p>Understanding this hierarchy is important because disruptions might occur at any
                    level. For example, a depletion of calcium atoms from the body can lead to weak
                    bones. Or a single mutation in a DNA molecule can lead to organ dysfunction,
                    such as the disturbed lung function found in individuals with cystic
                    fibrosis.</p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Integration of Systems</title>
            <body>
                <p>Finally, each section of the course will discuss the integration of all the
                    body’s systems. In order to carry out its functions, every organ system relies
                    on the healthy functioning of other systems. When these systems all work
                    together, the organism thrives. A breakdown in one system can cause failures in
                    other systems as well.</p>
            </body>
        </section>

    </body>
</workbook_page>
