<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u1_m1_vital_function_02"><head><title>Vital Functions for Human Life</title><objref idref="_u1_identify_OBJ" /></head><body><p id="eb6cb3a2a7cf46cdb77f2f1bb7c2cb17">In this section, you will be introduced to the major organ systems of the body. To put these systems in context, we will first discuss vital functions of life.</p><p id="eabdc542eb464909b0956a6beb8aa099">Within any organism, there are a multitude of functions taking place at any given time. Humans, for example, can breathe, talk, digest food, process visual images, and move their bodies all at the same time. While all of these activities are important, some are
 essential to the survival of the human body itself. They are <term>vital functions</term> - processes or actions of the body on which life is directly dependent. You will examine four main vital functions in this course: exchange with the environment; transport within the body; structure, support, and movement; and control and
 regulation.</p><p id="da92ba25b86148cd9f28ace3e27c5590">For human life, there are several vital functions. </p><wb:inline idref="_u1_m1_vital_function_inline01" purpose="learnbydoing" /><p id="b81416addbcf41dead181916f8f9a797">So you now know that all multicellular organisms need to do the following in order to survive:</p><ul id="b5d06bafe1ba49ecb59c7cd46635409e"><li><p id="ac6e94e3834da4a36aaa69ee70a985307">Exchange with the environment </p></li><li><p id="aa16aef51e1f44037a0fd884bf8a9fbdd">Transport fluids and material throughout the body </p></li><li><p id="afad8e04adef84e86a41ed2bdac85229b">Provide structure, support, protection and movement </p></li><li><p id="ac230470ccce1403db53dfb40c3078bbd">Regulate and control processes</p></li></ul><p id="c4551847236441418eb3f5f8ac6bee9d">So what does this mean? What does this involve? How does the human body do these things? Try answering the questions below to begin broadly thinking about bodily function within these categories and how they are linked to one or more of the primary organ systems. </p><wb:inline idref="_u1_m1_vital_function_inline-Combined" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="fad162714d4f453cad23985b894dafca"><title>Exchange with the Environment</title><body><p id="f1d5b125cc20461391c2e80f32987b74">An organism constantly interacts with its environment. In order to survive, the human body must obtain food, water, and oxygen from the world around it. The human body must also rid itself of wastes before they build up to toxic levels.
 Two organ systems are primarily responsible for exchange of material with the
 environment. The <term>digestivesystem</term> brings food and water into the body and eliminates solid wastes. The <term>respiratorysystem</term> brings in oxygen and removes carbon dioxide. </p><p id="e9c1c5e93fa2492db535c4ad5bc4fc77"> The <term>urinarysystem</term> doesn’t take in anything from the environment, but does eliminate waste products of metabolism from the body fluid. However, this is just one of several roles that the urinary system plays in maintaining
 homeostasis of body fluids, so it will be explored more extensively in the next
 vital function category involving body fluids.</p></body></section><section id="fa68c3aad4e24c09b0f62902cf4e3613"><title>Fluid Transport within the Body</title><body><p id="eb489b85c5ee45718d95d9acde592d4d">Single-celled organisms can absorb nutrients and oxygen directly from the environment into the cells, where they are used to support basic cell functions. Waste products are excreted from these single cells in a similar fashion. In
 multi-celled organisms like humans, however, most cells are not exposed directly
 to the outside environment. Instead, body cells rely on organ systems to
 transport and regulate the composition of internal fluids throughout the body.
 Three main body systems, the <term>cardiovascularsystem</term>, the <term>lymphaticsystem</term>, and the urinary system take care of this vital bodily function. The cardiovascular and lymphatic systems also participate in the function of <term>immunity</term>, to help defend the body&apos;s cells from foreign organisms that may enter the body tissues or fluids. The lymphatic system returns interstitial fluid to blood and the urinary system filters blood to
 regulate body fluid homeostasis, including volume, pressure, and chemical
 composition.</p></body></section><section id="d23371862c7649bbbfbd0df481ea5241"><title>Structure, Support, Protection, and Movement</title><body><p id="c1c4206006584c7191886dfb1afda1e6">For the organs of the human body to function, they must be protected from potentially damaging substances in the environment. One level of defense is provided by the <term>integumentarysystem</term>, made up of the skin, hair, and nails. This system prevents many potentially harmful irritants from entering the body. Eyelashes, for example, help keep sand or other items out of the eyes, where they could
 potentially cause serious damage, and the skin prevents most pathogens
 (disease-causing microorganisms) from entering the body and destroying healthy
 body cells. Certain parts of the <term>skeletalsystem</term>, such as the skull and ribcage, also help to protect the internal organs, such as the brain, heart and lungs, from damage. The skeletal system and the <term>muscularsystem</term> also support the body and allow it to move away from danger, toward food sources, etc. The cardiovascular and lymphatic systems also help defend the body’s cells from foreign organisms that may enter the body tissues
 or fluids through the process of immunity. </p></body></section><section id="f81f057e60cb49f9a80a951539b98c43"><title>Control and Regulation</title><body><p id="c3986391759348e09264ea276c638776">To keep itself in a state of equilibrium, an organism must constantly gather information and react accordingly. In humans, the <term>nervoussystem</term>, made up of the brain, nerves, spinal cord and sensory organs, reacts to stimuli in the environment and signals other systems when actions are needed to bring the body back into balance. The <term>endocrinesystem</term>, which produces hormones and other regulatory substances, plays a key role in maintaining balance among chemical messengers within the body. Locally, most body cells can produce chemical messages that influence the
 metabolism of other cells. And there are some organs in other body systems that produce
 chemicals that can travel through the body to regulate metabolic processes in
 other organs.</p></body></section><p id="f4e7469d7deb4c2fb274e32952e9a56e">As you can see, several organ systems work together to accomplish these various vital functions throughout the body. Since the organ systems are distributed throughout large regions of the human body, it is necessary to define orientation within the body and communicate the proper terminology as you study these
 integrated structures and functions. </p><wb:inline idref="_u1_m1_vital_function_DIGT" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
