<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u1_m2_planes_00"><head><title>Body Planes</title><objref idref="_u1_orientation_OBJ" /></head><body><section id="ebd09443bfe5407780ce2e84c774d0c7"><title>Body Planes</title><body><p id="db80453caa5d4fdc948b56e44b725b4a">To better identify the locations of the organs that contribute to vital functions, you need some points of reference for description. To serve that function, we will now define different planes of the body. These imaginary flat surfaces run through the body in different directions. They are used by medical professionals to examine various internal body parts. Directional orientation is another anatomical tool used to describe how parts of the body are related to one another.</p><p id="dd5bee8a3031492895c34239f2ec6e64">Each organ system spans large regions of the human body. It is helpful, therefore, to establish reference planes and directions that can help us describe specific locations of structures as we discuss them. To make sure everyone is talking about the same thing, anatomists and physiologists often refer to anatomical position and the body planes that penetrate it. Anatomical position describes a person standing upright, with the arms at the sides and the palms facing forward (as demonstrated in the image below). Body planes (a plane is a flat, two-dimensional surface) are imaginary surfaces that run through the body and divide it into different sections. We can talk about a specific location using the planes as reference points within the anatomical position. </p><p id="c2394fa880134c9ba772348b430ce2c6">There are an infinite number of planes running through the human body in all directions. However, we will focus on the three planes that are traditionally used when discussing human anatomy. First is the<term>transverse plane</term>, (also called the horizontal plane), which divides the body into top and bottom. In anatomical position, transverse planes are parallel to the ground. The second is the <term>coronal plane</term>, which is a vertical plane that divides the body into the front and back sections. If you do a “belly flop” into the water, you sink into the water via the coronal planes. Finally, we will refer to the <term>sagittal plane</term>, which divides the body into left and right sections with a vertical plane that passes from the front to the rear. </p><image id="a7e6b116940a4ad7b78fa86ebee1f667" src="../webcontent/1024px-Human_anatomy_planes.png" alt="Graphic identifying each plane - Sagittal, Coronal, and Transverse - and their intersections." style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="360" width="400"><caption><p id="d0363fe3745f42ef93c56c15073ac07b">Sagittal, Coronal, and Transverse body planes and their intersections. By YassineMrabet (<link href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/archive/e/e1/20080607094342%21Human_anatomy_planes.svg" target="new" internal="false">Human Anatomy Planes</link>)/<link href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page" target="new" internal="false">Wikimedia Commons</link>/<link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="new" internal="false">CC-BY-SA</link>.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><example id="bc495558cb7d4fe99a32ff447d1c662c"><title>Body Planes in Medicine</title><p id="c298405870004c219cb5c606ba3a2d98">Many imaging modalities used in medicine (CT scans, MRI scans and ultrasounds) image the body in cross sections. The three main planes described above are used to orient and describe where the cross section is and how it passes through the body so that the viewer knows what they are viewing. For example, the image below from a CT (or CAT) scan shows a cross section of the body that runs along the sagittal plane .</p><image id="ba761cc17c5942f189df405f21b50e71" src="../webcontent/lateral_brain_mri.png" alt="MRI scan of head from sagittal view" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="191" width="170"><caption><p id="af8c9267606ab428ca28fe38d649a616c"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="dfd6a7ab6f2c48dab24f51c84e363f8c">These images can sometimes be reconstructed in a computer to show the same body in a different plane, making some features of the body easier to see. Below is a coronal reconstruction of a CT:</p><image id="d599f3c7a2fe47cab3ac92f78ee02e06" src="../webcontent/anterior_brain_mri.png" alt="MRI scan of head from coronal view" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="191" width="170"><caption><p id="af0c66f70e253497796b5a90b14f8f0c8"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></example></body></section><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_planes_inline01" purpose="learnbydoing" /><section id="ccf33adb014b499ca3278a4208c19b12" purpose="didigetthis"><title> </title><body><materials id="df280f29185e410f9859dc0c99c839ad"><material><image id="ff335a005db545d2889252a3591f8777" src="../../_u1_m2_intro_systems_00/webcontent/lateral_view.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="218" width="200"><caption><p id="ab2a9bffc8c8c4bafa39a8e8103f77f85"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_planes_inline_digt" purpose="learnbydoing" /></material></materials><materials id="ff458ee4e5e845e59a3288a9442a694d"><material><image id="d2a150efc4cb4a6b82cbe96690620ac3" src="../../_u1_m2_intro_systems_00/webcontent/transverse.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="218" width="200"><caption><p id="aaff0eeb75f6f42f2bfa262cbc3a03566"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_planes_inline_digt2" purpose="learnbydoing" /></material></materials><materials id="b6bfe2c456884ba7ab69bc8eeaec213e"><material><image id="b2914822dfe34e9d823ca0aa4ff3ede7" src="../../_u1_m2_intro_systems_00/webcontent/coronal_posterior.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="200" width="200"><caption><p id="ae04d3b9a0f604c9ab7ee8da1a588cfa3"></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></material><material><wb:inline idref="_u1_m2_planes_inline_digt3" purpose="learnbydoing" /></material></materials></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
