<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="_u1_m1_intro_02"><head><title>Anatomy and Physiology Big Picture</title><objref idref="ap_bp" /></head><body><section id="d4cecafc8575430cb19f8d45cf7e98ed"><title>What is a Big Picture?</title><body><p id="e70a49bd89b94517a2a9c64e8b5e3de1">One goal of all OLI courses is to promote coherence by teaching students how the discrete skills they are learning fit together in a meaningful big picture of the domain. The Big Picture gives students an organizational structure through which they learn the material.</p><p id="c69cffec38ab489dbf210b191e4996f2">The Big Picture explains why the material in a course is being covered, as well as how the material is related or organized. The Big Picture illustrates why one might want to invest time in learning this material, and what it can do, in a way that students entering the course will easily understand.</p></body></section><section id="f7a1772bc88a4e75aa6329d0fb6c6f5c"><title>Why Study Anatomy and Physiology?</title><body><p id="d868dfdde00c4acabab3ece460760af0">You probably have a general understanding of how your body works, but to truly understand the intricate functions of the human body and dispel many misconceptions that you have learned about your body over the years, you must approach the study of the body in an organized way.</p><p id="df72e0d768534893ae40ebbf3617f217">This course will help you understand those intricacies and attack misconceptions head-on. This course will expose you to the complex levels of organization taking place inside the body and provide you with the information you need to delve deeply into the specific aspects of the body systems. This will prepare you for the more complex topics you will encounter in your future courses.</p><p id="a63dba29c5644f22a93c2106f5cda780">There is some agreement among professionals about how to do this, and what information must be common across all Anatomy and Physiology courses. This is presented as the Big Picture in Anatomy and Physiology.</p></body></section><section id="c129816460dd41dc91edb6d9a42e327d"><title>Big Picture Ideas in Anatomy and Physiology</title><body><p id="f212ad9a95c14132bd6abd5c06972f2a">Big Picture, Big Ideas, core principles, are all ways to describe the necessary concepts that make up a discipline. For Anatomy and Physiology, research studies have been conducted by various groups to determine what are the Big Ideas in this discipline. In 2007, Joel Michael and his colleagues compiled a list of <em style="italic">Big Ideas in Anatomy and Physiology </em>and then went on to test these ideas with several comprehensive surveys of professionals and educators in the field.</p><p id="e5d85218f2e944f784717ffca1a48e21">They determined that the “Big Ideas in Physiology” are:</p><ol id="f3ae34f7b352411989678cbc3bf78266"><li><p id="cfe2dde3b7c94dc8a4a52aefe0cd519f">Living organisms are <em style="bold"><em style="italic">causal mechanisms </em></em>whose functions are to be understood by applications of the laws of physics and chemistry.</p></li><li><p id="e56577951ffb4ae6a24f9ae4dea6686f"><em style="bold"><em style="italic">The cell </em></em>is the basic unit of life.</p></li><li><p id="e0a392cfe2044af3a0347b55844fbc5c">Life requires <em style="bold"><em style="italic">information flow </em></em>within and between cells and between the environment and the organism.</p></li><li><p id="e5d6d1cc35664bd5984b7b168b8c34de">Living organisms must obtain matter and energy from the external world. This matter and <em style="bold"><em style="italic">energy must be transformed and transferred </em></em>in varied ways to build the organism and to perform work.</p></li><li><p id="cd2242ee11da4dc3a7a01b6874c456fc"><em style="bold"><em style="italic">Homeostasis </em></em>(and “stability” in a more general sense) maintains the internal environment in a more or less constant state compatible with life.</p></li><li><p id="ea414c8533744dbb94e9dd4c5d80684a">Understanding the behavior of the organism requires understanding the relationship between <em style="bold"><em style="italic">structure and function</em></em> (at each and every level of organization).</p></li><li><p id="f5301e61f8d847b3a81a88c6e470c46b">Living organisms carry out functions at many different <em style="bold"><em style="italic">levels of organization </em></em>simultaneously.</p></li><li><p id="f0f1ea209e054438a88c3f1727c3f0e2">All life exists within an <em style="bold"><em style="italic">ecosystem </em></em>made up of the physiochemical and biological worlds.</p></li><li><p id="f872d2eb1a324d68a17e21c76bac6f9f"><em style="bold"><em style="italic">Evolution </em></em>provides a scientific explanation for the history of life on Earth and the mechanisms by which changes to life have occurred.</p></li></ol><p id="d74390a99333497aa8755480d31ee50f">This course has taken these Big Ideas and used them to structure the material of the course. We will explain this further on the next page.</p></body></section></body><bib:file /></workbook_page>
